<?xml version="1.0"?>
TrialsTrialsTrials1745-6215BioMed CentralLondon44468282601258574710.1186/s13063-015-0747-5Study ProtocolA mother-child intervention program in adolescent mothers and their children to improve maternal sensitivity, child responsiveness and child development (the TeeMo study): study protocol for a randomized controlled trialFirkChristinecfirk@ukaachen.deDahmenBrigittebdahmen@ukaachen.deLehmannChristinclehmann@ukaachen.deNiessenAnkeankniessen@ukaachen.deKoslowskiJuliajkoslowski@ukaachen.deRauchGeraldinerauch@imbi.uni-heidelberg.deSchwarteReinhildrschwarte@ukaachen.deStichKerstinkstich@ukaachen.deKonradKerstinkkonrad@ukaachen.deHerpertz-DahlmannBeatebherpertz@ukaachen.deDepartment of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University Hospital RWTH Aachen, Neuenhofer Weg 21, 52074 Aachen, Germany Institute of Neuroscience and Medicine (INM-3), Forschungszentrum Jülich, Leo-Brandt-Straße, 52425 Jülich, Germany Institute of Medical Biometry and Informatics, University of Heidelberg, Im Neuenheimer Feld 305, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany 275201527520152015162301822015652015© Firk et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundChildren of adolescent mothers present a high-risk group for child neglect and maltreatment. Previous findings suggest that early interventions can reduce maltreatment by improving the quality of mother-child interaction, particularly maternal sensitivity. The aim of the current study is to evaluate the effects of a mother-child intervention program using home visits and video-feedback regarding mother-child interaction (STEEP-b) plus psychiatric treatment of the mother in cases where mental illness is present compared with TAU (treatment as usual, that is, standardized support by the child welfare system) on enhancing maternal sensitivity and child responsiveness in adolescent, high-risk mothers. The second aim of the current project is to investigate behavioral and neural differences between adolescent and adult mothers at baseline and postintervention.Methods/DesignThis is a randomized controlled trial (RCT) with 120 high-risk adolescent mothers (&lt;21 years old) and their 3- to 6-month-old children. Half of the participants will be randomized to receive STEEP-b in addition to their standard treatment for up to 12 to 18 sessions over 9 months. The other half will continue with treatment as usual. For further comparisons, 40 adult mothers with positive and negative rearing experiences (&gt;25 years) will additionally be recruited to investigate behavioral and neural differences between the adolescent and adult group. Blind assessments will take place at T1 (pre-intervention), at the end of the 9-month intervention (T2, postintervention) and 6 months postintervention (T3, follow-up). Moderators of treatment outcomes and sociodemographic data will be assessed at T1. The primary outcome hypothesis is that STEEP-b added to treatment as usual will improve maternal sensitivity and child responsiveness compared with treatment as usual alone in high-risk adolescent mothers. The primary hypothesis will be evaluated at the end of the 9-month follow-up assessment based on the intention-to-treat principle. The trial is funded by the German Ministry for Research and Education (BMBF). Data collection started in October 2012.DiscussionThis is a randomized controlled trial that evaluates the effects of an early intervention program (STEEP-b) on the quality of mother-child interaction and child development in adolescent, high-risk mothers.Trial registrationDRKS00004409 (27 September 2012)KeywordsMaternal sensitivityChild developmentMaltreatmentAdolescent mothersSTEEPVideo feedbackissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2015<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods/Design</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Trial design</title><p>The Teemo study is designed as a single-center, randomized controlled, investigator-blinded superiority trial with two parallel groups and a primary endpoint of maternal sensitivity and child responsiveness after 9 months of intervention. Randomization will be performed as block randomization with a 1:1 allocation. The trial is located at the Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University Hospital RWTH Aachen.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Participants</title><p>Caucasian mothers 21 years old or younger with children between 3 and 6 months old and who receive support from the local youth welfare system and agree to participate will be included in the study. To increase the number of eligible participants, the study is being advertised in a local newspaper, obstetric clinics, midwife practices and pediatrician practices. Considering drop-out rates of 30 % during the entire study, a minimum of 180 mothers will be included. For further comparisons 40 adult mothers with positive and negative rearing experiences who are at least 25 years old and matched for education will additionally be recruited to investigate behavioral and neuronal differences between the adolescent and adult group at baseline, postintervention and follow-up. Inclusion and exclusion criteria are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Inclusion criteria</th><th/><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td>Maternal criteria</td><td>21 years old or younger at the beginning of pregnancy</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Mother and child live together</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Sufficient verbal and intellectual abilities to participate in a verbal training program</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Caucasian</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Written informed consent of the mother and, if &lt;18 years old, of the caregiver of the mother</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Child criteria</td><td>Between 3 and 6 months old</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Written informed consent of the caregiver</td></tr><tr><td>Exclusion criteria</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>Maternal criteria</td><td>Current substance abuse</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Current suicidal ideation</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Psychotic disorders</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Separation from the child (&gt;3 months)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Child criteria</td><td>Preterm birth (&lt;36 weeks gestation)</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Serious medical problems</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Genetic syndromes</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Intervention: STEEP-b</title><p>The intervention (STEEP-b) is an adaptation of the STEEP program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], which aims to enhance sensitive care using video-feedback to guide parents to recognize their children’s signals, take their children’s perspective and understand their children’s needs. STEEP-b was designed to be relatively brief, completed in 12 to 18 sessions, and started when the children are between 3 and 6 months of age (as a detailed meta-analysis could demonstrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], interventions with a small to moderate number of sessions and those with an older infant are more effective than longer interventions and those with very young infants). Adolescent mothers are visited at home every 2 to 3 weeks by the same adviser for 9 months. Furthermore, an optional group meeting is offered every second month that mothers can attend. The exact number of sessions will depend on clinical appropriateness in the 9-month window. The original STEEP program is not manualized; however, as treatment manualization is considered an important factor in treatment integrity and effectiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], STEEP-b has been modularized with every session focusing on one of four obligatory modules. The four modules emphasize the following elements: child development, maternal sensitivity, frightening and intrusive behaviors and sensitive discipline. Every module should be worked on twice, with the order depending on clinical appropriateness. A promising tool to increase sensitive parenting is video-feedback [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. A study in adolescent mothers demonstrated positive maternal behaviors and improved affective scores after video feedback of mother-infant interaction, but not in a control group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Therefore, video-feedback of free interaction situations and structured interaction situations will be used to work on the intervention topics. In addition, if the baseline assessment reveals any psychiatric diseases in the mother (for example, depression or PTSD), arrangements will be made for individual psychiatric treatment to be offered by a qualified clinical psychologist or psychiatrist within 4 weeks after the diagnostic assessments. The intervention is discontinued at the participant’s request or if interventions are no longer possible due to the separation of the mother and child (&gt;3 months) or any other serious harm (severe illnesses of either mother or child, death of participants) preventing study participation. Whenever possible, study participants are retained in the trial to enable follow-up data collection and to prevent missing data. Participants who are assigned to the TAU arm are not allowed to receive any intervention using video-feedback.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Measurement time points</title><p>The flow of participants from recruitment through the end of the study is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Children and mothers will be systematically assessed at T1 (pre-intervention, child age 3 to 6 months), at the end of the 9-month intervention (T2, postintervention) and 6 months postintervention (T3, follow-up). Moderators of treatment outcomes and sociodemographic data will be assessed at T1. Concomitant care is documented at all measurement time points.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study flow chart</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13063_2015_747_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>Due to the nature of the intervention neither participants nor trainers can be blinded to allocation. Therefore, all follow-up assessments are done by research staff members that are blinded. If unblinding occurs, another assessor will be brought in to re-establish blindness. Participants will be paid 50€ for each assessment session, and travel expenses will be refunded.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Outcomes</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Primary outcome measures</title><p>The primary outcome variables are maternal sensitivity and child responsiveness as changed from baseline to postintervention. These variables will be assessed by the Emotional Availability (EA) Scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. EA is a method to assess the emotional quality of dyadic interactions between an adult and a child. EA has been conceptualized as a research construct derived from attachment theory. It is supported by the empirical literature demonstrating robust links between assessments of attachment and EA in parent- child interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The EA Scales consist of six dimensions. The adult dimensions are sensitivity, structuring, nonintrusiveness and nonhostility. The child dimensions are responsiveness to the adult and involvement with the adult. All scales range from 1 to 7.</p><p>For the assessment of emotional availability, a videotaped free play interaction session as well as a videotaped age-appropriate stress situation session will be evaluated. Maternal sensitivity and child responsiveness are selected as primary outcome variables because of their specific relevance to the development of secure attachment behaviors. Furthermore, they have been shown to be the most reliable EA Scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Maternal sensitivity refers to the mother’s ability to read and respond to the child’s signals, and child responsiveness reflects a child’s eagerness and willingness to respond to the mother [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p>Videotaped interactions will be rated by psychologists trained for reliability in EA. Raters will be blind with respect to intervention group. Inter-rater reliability of the raters is formally assessed within a subsample of randomly selected videotapes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Secondary outcome measures</title><p>Secondary outcome measures for the child are social-emotional, cognitive, motor and language development assessed with the Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development (BSID-III, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]), social-emotional development assessed with the Brief Infant Toddler Social Emotional Assessment (BITSEA, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]), child temperament (IBQ-R, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]; ECBQ, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]), and child attachment assessed with the Strange Situation Procedure (SSP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Secondary outcome measures for the mother are overall psychopathological symptoms (BSI-18, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]), depressive symptomatology (BDI-II, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]), parental stress (PSI, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]) and child abuse potential (CAPI, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]). Furthermore, the emotional quality of the mother-child dyad will be assessed with the following EA dimensions: structuring, nonintrusiveness, non-hostility and child involvement.</p><p>At baseline (T1), to examine additional moderators of the outcome measures, we will also ask mothers to complete assessments of intellectual functioning (CFT-20R, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], an explanation of all abbreviations is given at the end of the text), psychiatric health (MINI, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]; SKID-II, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]; STAI, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]; CAARS, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]), child abuse history (CECA-Q, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]), attachment history (VASQ, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]; ECR-RC, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]), perception of parental rearing behaviors (EMBU, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]), impulsivity (BIS, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]), emotion regulation skills (DERS, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]) and empathic concern (IRI, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]). Furthermore, sociodemographic data will be collected, including standard questions on age, marital status, household composition, educational level, employment status, characteristics of the child’s father and neonatal data concerning the child and childbirth.</p><p>Neurobiological measures will also be assessed to test for moderation effects and for exploratory analyses. To investigate the impact of the hormone oxytocin, plasma oxytocin levels from the mothers will be collected after a standardized period of mother-infant interaction. Furthermore, buccal swabs will be collected from all participants (mothers and children) to investigate the impact of polymorphisms within the glucocorticoid receptor gene (NR3C1), the serotonin transporter gene (SLC6A4), the oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) and dopamine-system-related genes (DRD4/DRD2/COMT), and epigenetic changes will be assessed by buccal cell samples. To investigate the impact of chronic stress, hair cortisol will be assessed at T1, T2 and T3. For the examination of acute stress, saliva cortisol will be assessed following the SSP in both mother and child. In a subpopulation (<italic>N</italic> = 40 adolescent mothers and <italic>N</italic> = 40 adult mothers), the neural correlates of maternal affect regulation and reward processing will be studied using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) at T1.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Sample size calculation and statistical analysis</title><p>Based on a large meta-analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], we expect at least moderate effect sizes for maternal sensitivity and child responsiveness (Cohen’s d = 0.5). Assuming a small correlation between baseline and follow-up T2 of 0.25, the standardized effect of d = 0.5 can be detected with a power of 80 % for a two-sided significance level of 5 % with a total sample size of 120 mother-child dyads. Based on Suess <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], we expect drop-out rates of approximately 30 % during the longitudinal study; therefore, 180 individuals will be randomized in total to obtain at least 120 evaluable mother-infant dyads. In addition, we expect that approximately 20 % of the screened mothers cannot be included in the study due to violation of the inclusion/exclusion criteria. Hence, 220 to 230 mothers will be assessed for eligibility. If the planned sample size cannot be achieved within the time frame of funding, the Trial Steering Committee and the responsible biometrician of the Data management Team can decide to terminate the trial before the intended sample size is achieved.</p><p>All main analyses will be carried out at the end of the last follow up assessment and will be based on the intention to treat principle. Two primary hypotheses, one on the maternal outcome and the other on the child’s outcome, will be tested:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>H<sub>0</sub>: The change from baseline to the 9-month follow-up T2 in maternal sensitivity/child’s responsiveness is equal in the intervention and the control group.</p></list-item><list-item><p>H<sub>1</sub>: The change from baseline to the 9-month follow-up T2 in maternal sensitivity/child’s responsiveness is different in the intervention and the control group.</p></list-item></list></p><p>An analysis of covariance will be used for primary analyses using the EAS Score at the follow-up T2 as the dependent variable and the baseline value and group allocation as covariates. All other analyses will be performed descriptively. Means and standard deviations or absolute and relative frequencies will be reported according to the underlying scale level. A detailed statistical analytical plan will be written by the trial statistician and signed off by the principle investigator.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Methods against bias</title><p>Eligibility assessment, obtaining informed consent, and enrolling the patient in the trials is performed at the trial site by one of the investigators.</p><p>Subjects are randomly assigned to either group using a web-based randomization system (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.randomizer.at">http://www.randomizer.at</ext-link>) in a ratio 1:1. Data entry for randomization is done by the STEEP-b trainer and takes place after all baseline measurements to ensure allocation concealment. The randomization tool is supervised by the Institute of Medical Biometry and Informatics of the University of Heidelberg, Germany. Block randomization using fixed block lengths is used, stratified for mother’s age (&lt;18 years or &gt;18 years).</p><p>To ensure that all trainers implement STEEP-b in a very comparable way, all therapists are trained before the beginning of the study, and application of the modularized sessions is strictly monitored. In addition, therapists are supervised by an experienced STEEP therapist (G.J. Suess, STEEP training director in Germany). For the assessments of adherence and competence, sessions will be audiotaped. We will obtain independent judgments on the quality of therapy using a random selection of therapy tapes. Patients will also be asked to assess the intervention and the therapist’s empathy post-intervention.</p><p>Data quality is continuously monitored by the Data Management Team (Institute of Medical Biometry and Informatics (IMBI), University of Heidelberg and the Coordination Centre for Clinical Trials Heidelberg (KKS)). Data will be entered electronically at the IMBI. Range checks for data values are done to promote data quality. The original study forms will be kept at the trial site. Participants’ files are stored in locked cabinets and access to the study data will be restricted. Data will be collected, processed and stored according to the data protection laws. The principal investigators will be given access to the cleaned data sets.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Safety and ethical issues</title><p>Research activities within the UBICA-TeeMo project will be carried out in compliance with the fundamental ethical principles as stated by the Declaration of Helsinki. The Coordination Centre for Clinical Trials (KKS) will monitor the study, adapted to ICH-GCP guidelines (E6), and has approved the standard operating procedures. The trial has received approval from the local Research Ethics Committee at the University Hospital RWTH Aachen (reference EK144/12, protocol version 2.0 to 7.0). Any modification to the protocol will require a formal amendment and approval by the local Research Ethics Committee. The protocol must be agreed on by the Trial Steering Committee (principle investigators at the Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University Hospital RWTH Aachen) and Data Management Team (KKS and IMBI) at the University of Heidelberg.</p><p>Participants will be enrolled only after they have received comprehensive information from the responsible investigator. Participants will also receive information sheets and will have the opportunity to discuss the trial with the investigator. Written informed consent for the study will be obtained by the investigator from all participants who are willing to participate in the trial. Additional consent is obtained from participants for collection of genetic and neuroimaging data. Infants will only be included if the adolescent or young adult mother and the guardian have both given informed consent. All participants will be informed that they can stop participating in the study at any time without giving any reasons. Furthermore, additional consent is obtained from all participants who are willing to be contacted by the trial investigator for their participation in ancillary studies.</p><p>Study participants are provided with the right to have their information removed from the database at any time. Trial results will be communicated to participants and healthcare professionals who were involved in the study. Results will be published regardless of the magnitude or direction of the effect.</p><p>An independent Data and Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB), including two independent clinical experts and one biometrician, is established to monitor the progress of the trial and ensure adherence to protocol. Safety parameters include that all serious adverse events (SAE) or adverse events reported by the subject or detected by the local investigator that occur during the trial and all noticeable problems must be documented in the case report form (CRF). In case of an SAE, the Ethics Committee and DSMB will be informed within 24 h after the SAE becomes known. In case of significant preponderance of SAEs that might causally be associated with the trial, the DSMC will terminate the trial. Patients that are enrolled in the study are covered by indemnity for negligent harm by study insurance policies. Substantive contributions to the design, conduct and interpretation of the trial are recognized through the granting of authorship on the final trial report.</p></sec></sec>Trial statusMother-child dyads began to enter the trial in October 2012. Recruitment is still open.AbbreviationsBIS-15Barratt Impulsiveness ScaleBITSEABrief Infant-Toddler Social and Emotional AssessmentBDI-IIBecks Depression Inventory, Second EditionBSI-18Brief Symptom InventoryBSID-IIIBayley Scales of Infant and Toddler DevelopmentCAARSConners Adult ADHD Rating ScaleCAPIChild Abuse Potential InventoryCECA-QChildhood Experiences of Care Abuse QuestionnaireCFT 20-RCulture Fair Intelligence Test - Scale 2, RevisionECBQEarly Childhood Behavior QuestionnaireECR-RExperiences in Close Relationships Scale-RevisedEMBUA questionnaire measuring perceptions of parental rearing behaviorsDERSDifficulties in Emotion Regulation ScaleIBQ-RInfant Behavior QuestionnaireIRIInterpersonal Reactivity IndexM.I.N.IMini-International Neuropsychiatric InterviewPSIParental Stress IndexSCID-IIStructured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV axis II personality disordersSSPStrange Situation ProcedureSTAIState-Trait Anxiety InventoryVASQVulnerable Attachment Style QuestionnaireCompeting interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsBHD and KK wrote the grant application and drafted the manuscript together with CF. BHD and KK designed the trial with the help of CF and BD. RS supervised the implementation of the study. GR contributed to calculating statistical power for the primary outcome variable and writing of the statistical and data analytical plan. CF, BD, CL, JK, KS and AN acquired the data. JK, KS and AN provided the training. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.AcknowledgementsThis study is being performed within the consortium of UBICA (Understanding and Breaking the Intergenerational Cycle of Abuse), a research association for investigating the influence of maternal early trauma, neglect and abuse on child development. We acknowledge the advice of our research partners and the support of Romuald Brunner, MD, Department of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, University of Heidelberg, Germany, who is the speaker of our consortium.This study is supported by a grant awarded to BHD and KK by the German Ministry for Research and Education (BMBF No. 01KR1207B). The study is sponsored by the Clinical Trials Center Aachen (CTC-A). The sponsor and funding source had no role in the design of the study and will not have any role during its execution analyses, interpretation of the data, or decision to submit results.References1.GilbertRWidomCSBrowneKFergussonDWebbEJansonSBurden and consequences of child maltreatment in high-income countriesLancet.2009373688110.1016/S0140-6736(08)61706-7190561142.CicchettiDLynchMToward an ecological/transactional model of community violence and child maltreatment: consequences for children’s developmentPsychiatry.1993569611884882173.CicchettiDTothSLChild maltreatmentAnnu Rev Clin Psychol.200514093810.1146/annurev.clinpsy.1.102803.144029177160944.Kendall-TackettKAEckenrodeJThe effects of neglect on academic achievement and disciplinary problems: a developmental perspectiveChild Abuse Negl.199620161910.1016/S0145-2134(95)00139-587345465.PerezCMWidomCSChildhood victimization and long-term intellectual and academic outcomesChild Abuse Negl.1994186173310.1016/0145-2134(94)90012-479539026.CyrCEuserEMBakermans-KranenburgMJVan IjzendoornMHAttachment security and disorganization in maltreating and high-risk families: a series of meta-analysesDev Psychopathol.2010228710810.1017/S0954579409990289201026497.WidomCSDuMontKCzajaSJA prospective investigation of major depressive disorder and comorbidity in abused and neglected children grown upArch Gen Psychiatry.200764495610.1001/archpsyc.64.1.49171990548.PillhoferMZiegenhainUNandiCFegertJMGoldbeckLPrävalenz von Kindesmisshandlung und -vernachlässigung in Deutschland: Annäherung an ein DunkelfeldKindheit und Entwicklung.201120647110.1026/0942-5403/a0000429.ReichlCKaessMReschFBrunner R [The role of genotype in the intergenerational transmission of experiences of childhood adversity]Z Kinder Jugendpsychiatr Psychother2014423495910.1024/1422-4917/a0003102516399710.WidomCSThe cycle of violenceScience.1989244160610.1126/science.2704995270499511.CrittendenPMMaltreated infants: vulnerability and resilienceJ Child Psychol Psychiatry.198526859610.1111/j.1469-7610.1985.tb01630.x397293412.CrittendenPMChildren’s strategies for coping with adverse home environments: an interpretation using attachment theoryChild Abuse Negl.1992163294310.1016/0145-2134(92)90043-Q161746813.CrittendenPMDiLallaDLCompulsive compliance: the development of an inhibitory coping strategy in infancyJ Abnorm Child Psychol.1988165859910.1007/BF00914268323574914.BowlbyJAttachment and loss1969LondonThe Hogarth Press15.ZhangTYLabonteBWenXLTureckiGMeaneyMJEpigenetic mechanisms for the early environmental regulation of hippocampal glucocorticoid receptor gene expression in rodents and humansNeuropsychopharmacology.2013381112310.1038/npp.2012.1492296881416.LupienSJMcEwenBSGunnarMRHeimCEffects of stress throughout the lifespan on the brain, behaviour and cognitionNat Rev Neurosci.2009104344510.1038/nrn26391940172317.DahmenBFirkCKonradKHerpertz-Dahlmann B [Adolescent parenting - developmental risks for the mother-child dyad]Z Kinder Jugendpsychiatr Psychother2013414071710.1024/1422-4917/a0002572424049718.HodgkinsonSBeersLSouthammakosaneCLewinAAddressing the mental health needs of pregnant and parenting adolescentsPediatrics.20141331142210.1542/peds.2013-09272429801019.Statistische Ämter des Bundes und der LänderGeburten: Lebendgeborene nach Geschlecht, Nationalität und Altersgruppen der Mutter2010MünchenStatistische Ämter des Bundes und der Länder20.ChristoffersenMNGrowing up with unemployment - A study of parental unemployment and children’s risk of abuse and neglect based on national longitudinal 1973 birth cohorts in DenmarkChildhood.200074213810.1177/090756820000700400321.KrpanKMCoombsRZingaDSteinerMFlemingASExperiential and hormonal correlates of maternal behavior in teen and adult mothersHorm Behav.2005471122210.1016/j.yhbeh.2004.08.0061557927222.LeeYEarly motherhood and harsh parenting: the role of human, social, and cultural capitalChild Abuse Negl2009336253710.1016/j.chiabu.2009.02.0071981850023.D’OnofrioBMGoodnightJAVan HulleCARodgersJLRathouzPJWaldmanIDMaternal age at childbirth and offspring disruptive behaviors: testing the causal hypothesisJ Child Psychol Psychiatry.20095010182810.1111/j.1469-7610.2009.02068.x1928160324.ThomasRZimmer-GembeckMJAccumulating evidence for parent–child interaction therapy in the prevention of child maltreatmentChild Dev.2011821779210.1111/j.1467-8624.2010.01548.x2129143625.Bakermans-KranenburgMJvan IJzendoornMHJufferFLess is more: meta-analyses of sensitivity and attachment interventions in early childhoodPsychol Bull200312919521510.1037/0033-2909.129.2.1951269683926.ChablaniASpinneyEREngaging high-risk young mothers into effective programming: the importance of relationships and relentlessnessJ Fam Soc Work.2011143698310.1080/10522158.2011.58854427.SroufeLAEgelandBCarlsonEACollinsAThe development of the person. The Minnesota study of risk and adaptation from birth to adulthood2005New YorkGuilford28.SuessGJBohlenUMaliAMaierMF[Preliminary results concerning the effectiveness of early intervention from the STEEP practice research project “WiEge”]Bundesgesundheitsblatt Gesundheitsforschung Gesundheitsschutz2010531143910.1007/s00103-010-1145-52097643329.van IjzendoornMHSchuengelCBakermans-KranenburgMJDisorganized attachment in early childhood: meta-analysis of precursors, concomitants, and sequelaeDev Psychopathol.1999112254910.1017/S09545794990020351650653230.SchuengelCBakermans-KranenburgMJVanIMHFrightening maternal behavior linking unresolved loss and disorganized infant attachmentJ Consult Clin Psychol.199967546310.1037/0022-006X.67.1.541002820931.CarlsonEAA prospective longitudinal study of attachment disorganization/disorientationChild Dev.19986911072810.1111/j.1467-8624.1998.tb06163.x976848932.Lyons-RuthKEasterbrooksMACibelliCDInfant attachment strategies, infant mental lag, and maternal depressive symptoms: predictors of internalizing and externalizing problems at age 7Dev Psychol.1997336819210.1037/0012-1649.33.4.681923238333.BayerJKUkoumunneOCLucasNWakeMScalzoKNicholsonJMRisk factors for childhood mental health symptoms: national longitudinal study of Australian childrenPediatrics.2011128e8657910.1542/peds.2011-04912189082434.ChemtobCMGudinoOGLaraqueDMaternal posttraumatic stress disorder and depression in pediatric primary care: association with child maltreatment and frequency of child exposure to traumatic eventsJAMA Pediatr.20131671011810.1001/jamapediatrics.2013.22182399961235.EricksonMFEgelandBStärkung der Eltern-Kind-Bindung. Frühe Hilfen für die Arbeit mit Eltern von der Schwangerschaft bis zum zweiten Lebensjahr des Kindes durch das STEEP™-programm2006StuttgartKlett-Cotta36.WeiszJRJensen-DossAHawleyKMEvidence-based youth psychotherapies versus usual clinical care: a meta-analysis of direct comparisonsAm Psychol.2006616718910.1037/0003-066X.61.7.6711703206837.Koniak-GriffinDVerzemnieksICahillDUsing videotape instruction and feedback to improve adolescents’ mothering behaviorsJ Adolesc Health.199213570510.1016/1054-139X(92)90370-Q134512938.BiringenZRobinsonJEmotional availability in mother-child interactions: a reconceptualization for researchAm J Orthopsychiatry.1991612587110.1037/h0079238204864139.BiringenZEmotional availability: conceptualization and research findingsAm J Orthopsychiatry.2000701041410.1037/h00877111070285540.BiringenZEasterbrooksMAEmotional availability: concept, research, and window on developmental psychopathologyDev Psychopathol.2012241810.1017/S09545794110006172229298941.EasterbrooksMABureauJFLyons-RuthKDevelopmental correlates and predictors of emotional availability in mother-child interaction: a longitudinal study from infancy to middle childhoodDev Psychopathol.201224657810.1017/S09545794110006662229299442.ZivYAviezerOGiniMSagiAKoren-KarieNEmotional availability in the mother-infant dyad as related to the quality of infant-mother attachment relationshipAttach Hum Dev.200021496910.1080/146167300500855361170790843.AviezerOSagiAJoelsTZivYEmotional availability and attachment representations in kibbutz infants and their mothersDev Psychol1999358112110.1037/0012-1649.35.3.8111038087144.Van Den DriesLJufferFVan IjzendoornMHBakermans-KranenburgMJAlinkLRInfants’ responsiveness, attachment, and indiscriminate friendliness after international adoption from institutions or foster care in China: application of emotional availability scales to adoptive familiesDev Psychopathol.201224496410.1017/S09545794110006542229299345.BayleyNBayley scales of infant and toddler development - third edition2005San Antonio, TXPsychological Corporation46.Briggs-GowanMJCarterASIrwinJRWachtelKCicchettiDVThe brief infant-toddler social and emotional assessment: screening for social-emotional problems and delays in competenceJ Pediatr Psychol.2004291435510.1093/jpepsy/jsh0171509653547.GartsteinMARothbarthMKStudying infant temperament via the revised infant behavior questionnaireInfant Behavior Development.200326648610.1016/S0163-6383(02)00169-848.KristenSEisenbeisHThoermerCSodianBDeutsche Version des IBQ-R2007MünchenLudwig-Maximilians-Universität49.PutnamSPGartsteinMARothbartMKMeasurement of fine-grained aspects of toddler temperament: the early childhood behavior questionnaireInfant Behav Dev.20062938640110.1016/j.infbeh.2006.01.0041713829350.AinsworthMDSBellSMAttachment, exploration, and separation: illustrated by the behavior of one-year-olds in a strange situationChild Dev.197041496710.2307/1127388549068051.SpitzerCHammerSLoweBGrabeHJBarnowSRoseM[The short version of the brief symptom inventory (BSI −18): preliminary psychometric properties of the German translation]Fortschr Neurol Psychiatr2011795172310.1055/s-0031-12816022187031252.BeckATSteerRABallRRanieriWComparison of beck depression inventories -IA and -II in psychiatric outpatientsJ Pers Assess.1996675889710.1207/s15327752jpa6703_13899197253.TrösterHEBI. Eltern-Belastungs-Inventar. Deutsche Version des Parenting Stress Index (PSI) von R. R2010Abidin GöttingenHogrefe54.DeegenerGSpanglerGKörnerWBeckerNEBSK. Eltern-Belastungs-Screening zur Kindeswohlgefährdung. Deutsche Form des Child Abuse Potential Inventory (CAPI) by Joel S. Milner2009GöttingenHogrefe55.WeißRHCFT 20-R. Grundintelligenztest Skala 2 (CFT 20-R) [Basic Intelligence Scale 2 (CFT 20-R)]2006GöttingenHogrefe56.SheehanDVLecrubierYSheehanKHAmorimPJanavsJWeillerEThe mini-international neuropsychiatric interview (M.I.N.I.): the development and validation of a structured diagnostic psychiatric interview for DSM-IV and ICD-10J Clin Psychiatry199859 Suppl 202233988153857.WittchenHZaudigMFydrichTStrukturiertes Klinisches Interview für DSM-IV (SKID), Achse II1997GöttingenHogrefe58.Spielberger CD, Gorssuch RL, Lushene PR, Vagg PR, Jacobs GA: Manual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory. Consulting Psychologists Press, Inc; 198359.ChristiansenHKisBHirschOPhilipsenAHenneckMPanczukAGerman validation of the Conners adult ADHD rating scales-self-report (CAARS-S) I: factor structure and normative dataEur Psychiatry.201126100710.1016/j.eurpsy.2009.12.0242061961360.KaessMParzerPMatternMReschFBifulcoABrunnerRChildhood experiences of care and abuse (CECA) - validation of the German version of the questionnaire and interview, and results of an investigation of correlations between adverse childhood experiences and suicidal behaviourZ Kinder Jugendpsychiatr Psychother2011392435210.1024/1422-4917/a0001152166744961.BifulcoAMahonJKwonJHMoranPMJacobsCThe vulnerable attachment style questionnaire (VASQ): an interview-based measure of attachment styles that predict depressive disorderPsychol Med.200333109911010.1017/S00332917030082371294609462.EhrenthalJCDingerULamlaAFunkenBSchauenburgH[evaluation of the German version of the attachment questionnaire “experiences in close relationships–revised” (ECR-RD)]Psychother Psychosom Med Psychol2009592152310.1055/s-2008-10674251860061463.PerrisCJacobssonLLindstromHvon KnorringLPerrisHDevelopment of a new inventory assessing memories of parental rearing behaviourActa Psychiatr Scand.1980612657410.1111/j.1600-0447.1980.tb00581.x744618464.SchumacherJEisemannMBrählerERückblick auf die Eltern: Der Fragebogen zum erinnerten elterlichen Erziehungsverhalten (FEE)Diagnostica.19994519420410.1026//0012-1924.45.4.19465.SpinellaMNormative data and a short form of the Barratt impulsiveness scaleInt J Neurosci.20071173596810.1080/002074506005888811736512066.GratzKRoemerLMultidimensional assessment of emotion regulation and dysregulation: development, factor structure, and initial validation of the difficulties in emotion regulation scaleJ Psychopathol Behav Assess.200426465410.1023/B:JOBA.0000007455.08539.9467.DavisMHA multidimensional approach to individual differences in empathyJSAS Catalog Selected Documents Psychol.1980108568.DavisMHMeasuring individual differences in empathy: evidence for a multidimensional approachJ Pers Soc Psychol.1983441132610.1037/0022-3514.44.1.11369.PaulusCDer Saarbrücker Persönlichkeitsfragebogen SPF (IRI) zur Messung von Empathie: Psychometrische Evaluation der deutschen Version des interpersonal reactivity index, vol. 222009SaarbrückenUniversität des Saarlandes
