<?xml version="1.0"?>
Alzheimers Res TherAlzheimers Res TherAlzheimer's Research &amp; Therapy1758-9193BioMed Central3979126alzrt1892392458410.1186/alzrt189ReviewCognitive training and cognitive rehabilitation for persons with mild to moderate dementia of the Alzheimer's or vascular type: a reviewBahar-FuchsAlex1alex.baharfuchs@anu.edu.auClareLinda2l.clare@bangor.ac.ukWoodsBob2b.woods@bangor.ac.uk1Centre for Research on Ageing, Health, and Wellbeing, Australian National University, 62A Eggleston Road, Canberra, Acton 0200, Australia2School of Psychology, Bangor University, Bangor, Gwynedd LL57 2AS, UK2013782013722014543535Copyright © 2013 BioMed Central Ltd2013BioMed Central LtdCognitive impairments, and particularly memory deficits, are a defining feature of the early stages of Alzheimer's disease and vascular dementia. Interventions that target these cognitive deficits and the associated difficulties with activities of daily living are the subject of ever-growing interest. Cognitive training and cognitive rehabilitation are specific forms of non-pharmacological intervention to address cognitive and non-cognitive outcomes. The present review is an abridged version of a Cochrane Review and aims to systematically evaluate the evidence for these forms of intervention in people with mild Alzheimer's disease or vascular dementia. Randomized controlled trials (RCTs), published in English, comparing cognitive rehabilitation or cognitive training interventions with control conditions and reporting relevant outcomes for the person with dementia or the family caregiver (or both), were considered for inclusion. Eleven RCTs reporting cognitive training interventions were included in the review. A large number of measures were used in the different studies, and meta-analysis could be conducted for several primary and secondary outcomes of interest. Several outcomes were not measured in any of the studies. Overall estimates of the treatment effect were calculated by using a fixed-effects model, and statistical heterogeneity was measured by using a standard chi-squared statistic. One RCT of cognitive rehabilitation was identified, allowing the examination of effect sizes, but no meta-analysis could be conducted. Cognitive training was not associated with positive or negative effects in relation to any of the reported outcomes. The overall quality of the trials was low to moderate. The single RCT of cognitive rehabilitation found promising results in relation to some patient and caregiver outcomes and was generally of high quality. The available evidence regarding cognitive training remains limited, and the quality of the evidence needs to improve. However, there is still no indication of any significant benefits from cognitive training. Trial reports indicate that some gains resulting from intervention may not be captured adequately by available standardized outcome measures. The results of the single RCT of cognitive rehabilitation show promise but are preliminary in nature. Further well-designed studies of cognitive training and cognitive rehabilitation are required to provide more definitive evidence. Researchers should describe and classify their interventions appropriately by using the available terminology.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>This review is an abridged version of a regularly maintained and recently updated Cochrane Review on the topic. For a detailed description of the review methodology, readers are referred to the complete version in the CDSR. Central elements of the methodology are summarized below.</p><sec><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p>To be considered for inclusion, studies had to be RCTs of cognitive training or cognitive rehabilitation (consistent with the definitions provided above) for individuals with mild to moderate AD or VaD and had to be published in English. Interventions could be delivered individually or in groups, with or without the inclusion of family caregivers. At a minimum, studies had to include pre- and post-intervention assessments using standardized measures.</p><p>A range of outcomes were considered, and these were broadly classified into the following:</p><p>1. Cognitive and non-cognitive outcomes for the person with dementia (for example, performance on objective measures by cognitive domain, self-rated cognitive functioning, mood, well-being, and quality of life).</p><p>2. Outcomes for the primary caregiver (mood, burden of care, quality of life, and so on).</p><p>3. Effects of the intervention on the course of dementia (global dementia severity and rates of admission to residential care).</p><p>Outcomes of studies of cognitive training and of cognitive rehabilitation were considered separately. In addition, separate comparisons were conducted for outcomes in the short term (that is, the first assessment after intervention) and, where available, the medium (2 to 12 months after intervention) and long (&gt;12 months) term. To contribute to the meta-analysis of a given outcome, studies had to have measured the outcome with at least one standardized measure or questionnaire.</p></sec><sec><title>Search methods</title><p>The Cochrane Dementia and Cognitive Improvement Group's Specialized Register ALOIS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] - was most recently searched on 2 November 2012. ALOIS is maintained by the Trials Search Co-ordinator of the Cochrane Dementia and Cognitive Improvement Group and contains studies in the areas of dementia prevention, dementia treatment, and cognitive enhancement in healthy individuals. For a comprehensive list of sources included in the ALOIS database, readers are referred to the ALOIS website [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Data collection and analysis</title><p>The latest search results (covering the period of April 2006 to November 2012) were reviewed by AB-F, who identified all relevant RCTs of cognition-based interventions in mild AD or VaD and retrieved the full texts. Two review authors (AB-F and LC) independently reviewed each article to determine whether inclusion criteria were met. There were no disagreements regarding the inclusion of studies. All relevant data were extracted from the studies selected for inclusion, recorded in a data-entry form, and entered into Review Manager (RevMan) for statistical analyses. Additional information was sought from study authors as appropriate. Change from baseline statistics was calculated from the group means and standard deviations at baseline, post-intervention, and follow-up. The meta-analysis was conducted on change-from-baseline scores. Outcome measures were treated as continuous measures. In some cases, outcomes were derived from ordinal rating scales; provided that these contained a reasonably large number of categories (&gt;10), the data were treated as continuous variables arising from a normal distribution.</p><p>The mean difference with 95% confidence intervals was used whenever studies used the same outcome measure, and the standardized mean difference, which is the absolute mean difference divided by the pooled standard deviation, was used when the same outcome was assessed using different measures. Overall estimates of the treatment effect were calculated with a fixed-effects model by using the inverse variance method.</p><p>Statistical heterogeneity was assessed by using a standard chi-squared statistic and associated l2 statistic. Consistent with recommendations, heterogeneity was deemed to be present when the chi-squared statistic was significant at a <italic>P </italic>value of 0.1 or the l2 suggested that more than 40% of the variability in effect estimate was due to heterogeneity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. As no evidence of statistical heterogeneity was found, all analyses were conducted by using a fixed-effects model.</p></sec></sec>AbbreviationsAD: Alzheimer's disease; CDSR: Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews; fMRI: functional magnetic resonance imaging; MCI: mild cognitive impairment; RCT: randomized controlled trial; VaD: vascular dementia.Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.AcknowledgementsAB-F is supported by funding from the Dementia Collaborative Research Centre-Early Detection and Prevention and would like to acknowledge the support of the Rosemary Foundation Travel Fellowship awarded to him by the Alzheimer's Australia Research Foundation.ReiflerBVLarsonELight E, Liebowitz BExcess disability in dementia of the Alzheimer's typeAlzheimer's Disease Treatment and Family Stress: Directions for Research1990New York: HemisphereSalomoneSCaraciFLeggioGMFedotovaJDragoFNew pharmacological strategies for treatment of Alzheimer's disease: focus on disease modifying drugsBr J Clin Pharmacol2012550451710.1111/j.1365-2125.2011.04134.x22035455SmallGWRabinsPVBarryPPBuckholtzNSDeKoskySTFerrisSHFinkelSIGwytherLPKhachaturianZSLebowitzBDMcRaeTDMorrisJCOakleyFSchneiderLSStreimJESunderlandTTeriLATuneLEDiagnosis and treatment of Alzheimer disease and related disorders: consensus statement of the American Association for Geriatric Psychiatry, the Alzheimer's Association and the American Geriatric SocietyJAMA199751363137110.1001/jama.1997.035501600830439343469WoodsRTClareLTuokko H, Hultsch DCognition-based therapies and mild cognitive impairmentPerspectives on Mild Cognitive Impairment. International Perspectives2006New York: Taylor &amp; Francis245264WoodsBAguirreESpectorAEOrrellMCognitive stimulation to improve cognitive functioning in people with dementiaCochrane Database Syst Rev20125CD00556222336813ClareLWoodsRTMoniz-CookEDOrrellMSpectorACognitive rehabilitation and cognitive training for early-stage Alzheimer's disease and vascular dementiaCochrane Database Syst Rev2003CD00326014583963ClareLWoodsRTCognitive training and cognitive rehabilitation for people with early-stage Alzheimer's disease: a reviewNeuropsychol Rehabil2004538540110.1080/09602010443000074ClareLCognitive training and cognitive rehabilitation for people with early-stage dementiaRev Clin Gerontol200357583QuayhagenMPQuayhagenMCorbeilRRRothPARodgersJAA dyadic remediation program for care recipients with dementiaNurs Res199551531597761291DavisRNMassmanPJDoodyRSCognitive intervention in Alzheimer disease: a randomized placebo-controlled studyAlzheimer Dis Assoc Disord200151910.1097/00002093-200101000-0000111236819de VreeseLPNeriMFioravantiMBelloiLZanettiOMemory rehabilitation in Alzheimer's disease: a review of progressInt J Geriatr Psychiatry2001579480910.1002/gps.42811536347HeissWDKesslerJSlanskyIMielkeRSzeliesBHerholzKActivation PET as an instrument to determine therapeutic efficacy in Alzheimer's diseaseAnn N Y Acad Sci1993532733110.1111/j.1749-6632.1993.tb23078.x8239307SchreiberMSchweizerALutzKKalveramKTJänckeLPotential of an interactive computer-based training in the rehabilitation of dementia: an initial studyNeuropsychol Rehabil1999515516710.1080/713755596GalanteEVenturiniGFiaccadoriCComputer-based cognitive intervention for dementia: preliminary results of a randomized clinical trialG Ital Med Lav Ergon20075263218575355ZanettiOZanieriGdi GiovanniGde VreeseLPPezziniAMetitieriTTrabucchiMEffectiveness of procedural memory stimulation in mild Alzheimer's disease patients: a controlled studyNeuropsychol Rehabil2001526327210.1080/09602010042000088LoewensteinDAAcevedoACzajaSJDuaraRCognitive rehabilitation of mildly impaired Alzheimer disease patients on cholinesterase inhibitorsAm J Geriatric Psychiatry2004539515249277NeelyASVikstromSJosephssonSCollaborative memory intervention in dementia: caregiver participation mattersNeuropsychol Rehabil2009569671510.1080/0960201090271910519294562PeretzCKorczynADShatilEAharonsonVBirnboimSGiladiNComputer-based, personalized cognitive training versus classical computer games: a randomized double-blind prospective trial of cognitive stimulationNeuroepidemiology20115919910.1159/00032395021311196OwenAMHampshireAGrahnJAStentonRDajaniSBurnsASHowardRJBallardCGPutting brain training to the testNature2010577577810.1038/nature0904220407435PappKVWalshSJSnyderPJImmediate and delayed effects of cognitive interventions in healthy elderly: a review of current literature and future directionsAlzheimers Dement20095506010.1016/j.jalz.2008.10.00819118809JaeggiSMStuder-LuethiBBuschkuehlMSuYFJonidesJPerrigWJThe relationship between n-back performance and matrix reasoning - implications for training and transferIntelligence2010562563510.1016/j.intell.2010.09.001GatesNSachdevPSinghMFValenzuelaMCognitive and memory training in adults at risk of dementia: a systematic reviewBMC Geriatr201155510.1186/1471-2318-11-5521942932KoltaiDCWelsh-BohmerKASmechelDEInfluence of anosognosia on treatment outcome among dementia patientsNeuropsychol Rehabil2001545547510.1080/09602010042000097Cahn-WeinerDAMalloyPFRebokGWOttBRResults of a placebo-controlled study of memory training for mildly-impaired Alzheimer's Disease patientsAppl Neuropsychol2003521522310.1207/s15324826an1004_314690802QuayhagenMPQuayhagenMCorbeilRRHendrixRCJacksonJESnyderLBowerDCoping with dementia: evaluation of four nonpharmacologic interventionsInt Psychogeriatr2000524926510.1017/S104161020000636010937544NewhousePAPotterALevinEDNicotinic system involvement in Alzheimer's and Parkinson's diseases: implications for therapeuticsDrugs Aging1997520622810.2165/00002512-199711030-000059303280YesavageJAWestphalJRushLSenile dementia: combined pharmacologic and psychologic treatmentJ Am Geriatr Soc198151641717204812BrodatyHGreshamMLuscombeGThe Prince Henry Hospital dementia caregivers' training programmeInt J Geriatr Psychiatry1997518319210.1002/(SICI)1099-1166(199702)12:2&lt;183::AID-GPS584&gt;3.0.CO;2-J9097211McLellanDLSwash MFunctional recovery and the principles of disability medicineClinical Neurology1991London: Churchill Livingstone768790World Health Organization: International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF)http://www.who.int/classifications/icf/en/KoehlerRWilhelmEShoulsonICognitive Rehabilitation Therapy for Traumatic Brain Injury Cognitive Rehabilitation Therapy for Traumatic Brain Injury: Evaluating the Evidence2011Washington, DC: The National Academies PressWilsonBATowards a comprehensive model of cognitive rehabilitationNeuropsychol Rehabil200259711010.1080/09602010244000020YlvisakerMHanksRJohnson-GreeneDPerspectives on rehabilitation of individuals with cognitive impairment after brain injury: rationale for reconsideration of theoretical paradigmsJ Head Trauma Rehabil2002519120910.1097/00001199-200206000-0000212086574RabipourSRazATraining the brain: Fact and fad in cognitive and behavioral remediationBrain Cogn2012515917910.1016/j.bandc.2012.02.00622463872BellevilleSClémentFMellahSGilbertBFontaineFGauthierSTraining-related brain plasticity in subjects at risk of developing Alzheimer's diseaseBrain20115162310.1093/brain/awr03721427462ChristensenHKopelmanMDStanhopeNLorentzLOwenPRates of forgetting in Alzheimer dementiaNeuropsychologia1998554755710.1016/S0028-3932(97)00116-49705065KopelmanMDRates of forgetting in Alzheimer-type dementia and Korsakoff's syndromeNeuropsychologia1985562363810.1016/0028-3932(85)90064-84058708LittleAGVolansPJHemsleyDRLevyRThe retention of new information in senile dementiaBr J Clin Psychol19865717210.1111/j.2044-8260.1986.tb00673.x3955277BäckmanLUtilizing compensatory task conditions for episodic memory in Alzheimer's diseaseActa Neurologica Scandinavica1996suppl 1651091138740997CampCJBirdMJCherryKEHill RD, Backman L, Stigsdotter-Neely ARetrieval strategies as a rehabilitation aid for cognitive loss in pathological agingCognitive Rehabilitation in Old Age2000Oxford: Oxford University PressClareLWilsonBABreenKHodgesJRErrorless learning of face-name associations in early Alzheimer's diseaseNeurocase19995374610.1080/13554799908404063ClareLWilsonBACarterGRothIHodgesJRRelearning of face-name associations in early-stage Alzheimer's diseaseNeuropsychology2002553854712382992AndersonJArensKJohnsonRCoppensPSpaced retrieval vs memory tape therapy in memory rehabilitation for dementia of the Alzheimer's typeClin Gerontol2001512313910.1300/J018v24n01_09JosephssonSBackmanLBorellLBernspangBNygardLRonnbergLSupporting everyday activities in dementia: an intervention studyInt J Geriatr Psychiatry1993539540010.1002/gps.930080505ClareLWilsonBACarterGBreenKGossesAHodgesJRIntervening with everyday memory problems in dementia of Alzheimer type: an errorless learning approachJ Clin Exp Neuropsychol2000513214610.1076/1380-3395(200002)22:1;1-8;FT13210649552DunnJClareLLearning face-name associations in early-stage dementia: comparing the effects of errorless learning and effortful processingNeuropsychol Rehabil2007573575410.1080/0960201070121831717852759BrandtJRichJBBaddeley AD, Kopelman MD, Wilson BAMemory disorders in the dementiasHandbook of Memory Disorders1995Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons LtdMorrisRGWoods R, Clare LThe neuropsychology of Alzheimer's disease and related dementiasHandbook of the Clinical Psychology of Ageing1996Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons LtdKurlychekRTUse of a digital alarm chronograph as a memory aid in early dementiaClin Gerontol198359394BourgeoisMSEvaluating memory wallets in conversations with persons with dementiaJ Speech Hear Res19925134413571494276BirdMBehavioural difficulties and cued recall of adaptive behaviour in dementia: experimental and clinical evidenceNeuropsychol Rehabil2001535737510.1080/09602010042000042ALOI S: a comprehensive register of dementia studieshttp://www.medicine.ox.ac.uk/alois/HigginsJPTAltmanDGSterneJACHiggins JPTChapter 8: Assessing risk of bias in included studiesCochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 5.1.02011Oxford, UK: The Cochrane Collaboration(updated March 2011)ClareLLindenDEWoodsRTWhitakerREvansSJParkinsonCHvan PaasschenJNelisSMHoareZYuenKSRuggMDGoal-oriented cognitive rehabilitation for people with early-stage Alzheimer disease: a single-blind randomized controlled trial of clinical efficacyAm J Geriatr Psychiatry2010592893910.1097/JGP.0b013e3181d5792a20808145BeckCHeacockPMercerSThatcherRThe impact of cognitive skills remediation training on persons with Alzheimer's disease or mixed dementiaJ Geriatr Psychiatry1988573883171111De VreeseLVerlatoCEmilianiSSchioppaSBelloiLSalvioliGNeriMEffect size of a three-month drug treatment in AD when combined with individual cognitive retraining: preliminary results of a pilot studyNeurobiol Aging19985S213HeissWDKesslerJMielkeRSzeliesBLong-term effects of phosphatidylserine, pyritinol, and cognitive training in Alzheimer's disease: a neuropsychological, EEG, and PET investigationDementia1994588988038871van PaasschenJClareLYuenKSWoodsRTEvansSJParkinsonCHRuggMDLindenDECognitive rehabilitation changes memory-related brain activity in people with Alzheimer diseaseNeurorehabil Neural Repair2013544845910.1177/154596831247190223369983BentwichJDobronevskyEAichenbaumSShorerRPeretzRKhaigrekhtMMartonRGRabeyJMBeneficial effect of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation combined with cognitive training for the treatment of Alzheimer's disease: a proof of concept studyJ Neural Transm2011546347110.1007/s00702-010-0578-121246222HwangHRChoiSHYoonDHYoonBNSuhYJLeeDHanITHongCGThe effect of cognitive training in patients with mild cognitive impairment and early Alzheimer's disease: a preliminary studyJ Clin Neurol2012519019710.3988/jcn.2012.8.3.19023091528KurzAThöne-OttoACramerBEgertSFrölichLGertzHJKehlVWagenpfeilSWerheidKCORDIAL: Cognitive rehabilitation and cognitive-behavioral treatment for early dementia in alzheimer disease: a multicenter, randomized, controlled trialAlzheimer Dis Assoc Disord2012524625310.1097/WAD.0b013e318231e46e21986341GraffMJVernooij-DassenMJThijssenMDekkerJHoefnagelsWHRikkertMGCommunity based occupational therapy for patients with dementia and their care givers: randomised controlled trialBMJ20065119610.1136/bmj.39001.688843.BE17114212AlbertMSDeKoskySTDicksonDDuboisBFeldmanHHFoxNCGamstAHoltzmanDMJagustWJPetersenRCSnyderPJCarrilloMCThiesBPhelpsCHThe diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment due to Alzheimer's disease: Recommendations from the National Institute on Aging and Alzheimer's Association workgroupAlzheimers Dement2011527027910.1016/j.jalz.2011.03.00821514249GauthierSReisbergBZaudigMPetersenRCRitchieKBroichKBellevilleSBrodatyHBennettDChertkowHCummingsJLde LeonMFeldmanHGanguliMHampelHScheltensPTierneyMCWhitehousePWinbladBInternational Psychogeriatric Association Expert Conference on mild cognitive impairmentMild cognitive impairmentLancet200651262127010.1016/S0140-6736(06)68542-516631882JeanLBergeronMÈThiviergeSSimardMCognitive intervention programs for individuals with mild cognitive impairment: systematic review of the literatureAm J Geriatr Psychiatry2010528129610.1097/JGP.0b013e3181c37ce920220584MartinMClareLAltgassenAMCameronMHZehnderFCognition-based interventions for healthy older people and people with mild cognitive impairmentCochrane Database Syst Rev20111CD00622021249675ReevesBCDeeksJJHigginsJPTWellsGAHiggins JPTChapter 13: Including non-randomized studiesCochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 510 (updated March 2011)2011Oxford, UK: The Cochrane CollaborationGiordanoMDominguezLJVitranoTCuratoloMFerlisiADi PrimaABelvedereMBarbagalloMCombination of intensive cognitive rehabilitation and donepezil therapy in Alzheimer's disease (AD)Arch Gerontol Geriatr201024524919969381ChoiJTwamleyEWCognitive rehabilitation therapies for Alzheimer's disease: a review of methods to improve treatment engagement and self-efficacyNeuropsychol Rev20135486210.1007/s11065-013-9227-423400790ClareLWilsonBACarterGRothIHodgesJRAwareness in early-stage Alzheimer's disease: relationship to outcome of cognitive rehabilitationJ Clin Exp Neuropsychol2004521522610.1076/jcen.26.2.215.2808815202541SitzerDTwamleyEJesteDCognitive training in Alzheimer's disease: a meta-analysis of the literatureActa Psychiatr Scand20065759010.1111/j.1600-0447.2006.00789.x16836595OlazaránJReisbergBClareLCruzIPeña-CasanovaJDel SerTWoodsBBeckCAuerSLaiCSpectorAFazioSBondJKivipeltoMBrodatyHRojoJMCollinsHTeriLMittelmanMOrrellMFeldmanHHMuñizRNonpharmacological therapies in Alzheimer's disease: a systematic review of efficacyDement Geriatr Cogn Disord2010516117810.1159/00031611920838046
