<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC Complement Altern MedBMC Complement Altern MedBMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine1472-6882BioMed Central39335041472-6882-14-692455578810.1186/1472-6882-14-69Research ArticleEffect of acupuncture on Deqi traits and pain intensity in primary dysmenorrhea: analysis of data from a larger randomized controlled trialShiGuang-Xia1shiguangxia2008@126.comLiQian-Qian1li1986qian@126.comLiuCun-Zhi1lcz623780@126.comZhuJiang2jzhjzh@263.netWangLin-Peng1741503673@qq.comWangJing1princrystal@sina.comHanLi-Li3734399206@qq.comGuanLi-Ping3houqinbuzhangsgx@163.comWuMeng-Meng3gaoma777@163.com1Acupuncture and Moxibustion Department, Beijing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, affiliated to Capital Medical University, 23 Meishuguanhou Street, Dongcheng District, Beijing 100010, China2School of Acupuncture-Moxibustion and Tuina, Beijing University of Chinese Medicine, 11 Bei San Huan East Road, Chao Yang District, Beijing 100010, China3The First Hospital affiliated to Tianjin University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, 312 West Anshan Avenue, Tianjin 300193, China20142122014146969291120121322014Copyright © 2014 Shi et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.2014Shi et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited.BackgroundDeqi is a central concept in traditional Chinese acupuncture. We performed a secondary analysis on data from a larger randomized controlled trial (RCT) in order to assess the effect of acupuncture on deqi traits and pain intensity in primary dysmenorrhea.MethodsA total of 60 primary dysmenorrhea patients were enrolled and randomly assigned to one of three treatment groups. Acupuncture was given at SP6, GB39 or nonacupoint. Subjective pain was measured by a 100-mm visual analogue scale (VAS) before and after acupuncture. The Massachusetts General Hospital acupuncture sensation scales (MASS) with minor modification was used to rate deqi sensations during acupuncture.ResultsThe results showed that VAS scores of pain after acupuncture were significantly decreased comparing to before acupuncture treatment in all three groups (P = 0.000). However, no significant differences were found among three groups at the beginning or end of acupuncture treatment (P = 0.928, P = 0.419).ConclusionsThere was no statistical difference among three groups in terms of intensity of deqi feeling. The types of sensation were similar across the groups with only minor differences among them.Trial registrationTrial registration number: Controlled-Trials.com ISRCTN24863192.AcupunctureDeqi traitsPain intensityPrimary dysmenorrheaBackgroundAcupuncture has been increasingly used as an alternative and complementary therapy in various clinical conditions, especially in the pain management [1-3]. But its mechanism is still unclear. According to both ancient traditional Chinese and modern text books, the deqi feeling of patients is different, which is referred as suan (aching or soreness), ma (numbness or tingling), zhang (fullness/distention or pressure) or zhong (heaviness) around the acupuncture point and/or along the meridians [4,5].Recent controversy in the field of acupuncture research has been generated when several large scale RCTs showed no significant differences between acupuncture and minimal or sham acupuncture. But compared to control cases, the clinical effects of acupuncture treatment are significantly positive [6-8]. It claims that deqi is important in creating a positive clinical outcome [5,9]. Non-penetrative “placebo needles” such as the streitberger needle also elicited deqi, which presenting a problem when acupuncture is evaluated within controlled trials [10,11]. Thus, deqi may have implications both for clinical practice and trial design. Deqi traits mean the nature of the sensation and intensity. There is no consensus for a method or instrument to quantify deqi sensations. Particularly, few studies have investigated the effect of acupuncture on different aspects of deqi or pain relief [12,13]. We had previously designed AAEPD-II to investigate immediate effects of acupuncture at a specific acupoint compared with unrelated acupoint and nonacupoint among primary dysmenorrhea patients. The present data was a secondary analysis from the main RCT to assess the effect of acupuncture on different aspects of deqi and pain relief in primary dysmenorrhea.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study design overview</title><p>The main study was designed as a multicentre RCT with a sample size of 501 in six large hospitals of China (i.e., Dongzhimen Hospital affiliated to Beijing University of Chinese Medicine, Beijing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine affiliated to Capital Medical University, Huguosi Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine affiliated to Beijing University of Chinese Medicine, China-Japan Friendship Hospital, the First Hospital affiliated to Tianjin University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, and the Hospital affiliated to Shandong University of Traditional Chinese Medicine). We used the subset of the data for this paper only from one hospital (the First Hospital affiliated to Tianjin University of Traditional Chinese Medicine) with a total of 60 primary dysmenorrhea patients. That is, 23 patients in SP6 acupuncture group, 26 in GB39 control group and 11 in Nonacupoint control group, respectively. The methodology is the same with the main study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>The trial protocol has been approved by the Research Ethical Committee of the First Hospital affiliated to Tianjin University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, and the study itself was conducted according to common standard guidelines (Declaration of Helsinki, Good Epidemiological Practice: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dundee.ac.uk/iea/GoodPract.htm">http://www.dundee.ac.uk/iea/GoodPract.htm</ext-link>). Written informed consent were obtained from participants or caregivers if children under the age of 18.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes</title><p>Demographic measures collected at the baseline evaluation included age, menstrual cycle and baseline pain intensity.</p><sec><title>Pain intensity</title><p>This was measured on a standard of 100-mm VAS (0 = no pain, 100 = worst pain ever), before and after acupuncture. Mean pain scores were calculated for both pre- and post-acupuncture dysmenorrhea pain.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Deqi</italic> sensations</title><p><italic>Deqi</italic> was monitored with the MASS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Seven most common descriptors in Chinese, which were soreness, numbness, heaviness, warmth, cold, sharp pain and dull pain, were selected for minor modifications. Immediately after the needle was inserted into the skin, the subject was asked by another researcher if <italic>deqi sensations</italic> occurred during the stimulation. And the intensity was rated on the scale of 1–100 mm.</p><p>The “Acupuncture Sensation Spreading Scale” was also used to rate the localization and expansiveness of <italic>deqi sensations</italic> along the lower limbs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Orienting marks on this separate continuum include “none”, “localized”, “ankle”, “upper legs”, “lower legs”, and “knee-joint”, ranging from 0 to 5 scores. Others surrounded kept quiet during the whole intervention until the questionnaire was assessed and filled in.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The SPSS 13.0 for Windows statistical software was used in the statistical analysis. Mean ± Standard Error (Mean ± SE) was given for each parameter. One-way ANOVA or rank sum test were used to compare the between-group differences for quantitative data. Enumeration data were presented as frequency using chi-square test or Fisher exact probability test. The significance was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec>Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsG-XS wrote and revised the manuscript, C-ZL and L-PW developed the original concepts for the review, Q-QLi, L-PG and M-MW have made substantial contributions to acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation of data; L-LH wrote the first draft of the paper. JW revised the manuscript. All authors contributed to the paper during development and read and approved the final version of the manuscript.Pre-publication historyThe pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6882/14/69/prepubAcknowledgmentsThe study was funded by the National Basic Research Program of China (973 Program, reference number: 2012CB518506 and 2006CB504503).LindeKWittCMStrengAWeidenhammerWWagenpfeilSBrinkhausBWillichSNMelchartDThe impact of patient expectations on outcomes in four randomized controlled trials of acupuncture in patients with chronic painPain2007128326427110.1016/j.pain.2006.12.00617257756KaptchukTJAcupuncture: theory, efficacy, and practiceAnn Intern Med2002136537438310.7326/0003-4819-136-5-200203050-0001011874310ShermanKJCherkinDCEisenbergDMErroJHrbekADeyoRAThe practice of acupuncture: who are the providers and what do they do?Ann Fam Med20053215115810.1370/afm.24815798042ChengXNChinese Acupuncture and Moxibustion1987Beijing: Foreign Language PressMacPhersonHAsgharAAcupuncture needle sensations associated with deqi: a classification based on experts’ ratingsJ Altern Complement Med200612763363710.1089/acm.2006.12.63316970533BrinkhausBWittCMJenaSLindeKStrengAWagenpfeilSIrnichDWaltherHUMelchartDWillichSNAcupuncture in patients with chronic low back pain: a randomized controlled trialArch Intern Med2006166445045716505266LindeKStrengAJurgensSHoppeABrinkhausBWittCWagenpfeilSPfaffenrathVHammesMGWeidenhammerWWillichSNMelchartDAcupuncture for patients with migraine: a randomized controlled trialJAMA20052932118212510.1001/jama.293.17.211815870415DienerHCKronfeldKBoewingGLungenhausenMMaierCMolsbergerATegenthoffMTrampischHJZenzMMeinertRGERAC Migraine Study GroupEfficacy of acupuncture for the prophylaxis of migraine, a multicentre randomized controlled clinical trialLancet Neurol2006531031610.1016/S1474-4422(06)70382-916545747MaoJJFarrarJTArmstrongKDonahueANgoJBowmanMADe qi: Chinese acupuncture patients’ experiences and beliefs regarding acupuncture needling sensation–an exploratory surveyAcupunct Med200725415816510.1136/aim.25.4.15818160926LeeHBangHKimYParkJLeeSLeeHParkHJNon-penetrating sham needle, is it an adequate sham control in acupuncture research?Complement Ther Med201119Suppl 1S41821195294ParkJWhiteAStevinsonCErnstEJamesMValidating a new non-penetrating sham acupuncture device: two randomized controlled trialsAcupunct Med200220416817410.1136/aim.20.4.16812512790KongJGollubRHuangTPolichGNapadowVHuiKVangelMRosenBKaptchukTJAcupuncture de qi, from qualitative history to quantitative measurementJ Altern Complement Med200713101059107010.1089/acm.2007.052418166116WhiteACummingsMBarlasPCardiniFFilshieJFosterNELundebergTStener-VictorinEWittCDefining an adequate dose of acupuncture using a neurophysiological approach–a narrative review of the literatureAcupunct Med200826211112010.1136/aim.26.2.11118591910LiuYQMaLXXingJMCaoHJWangYXTangLLiMWangYLiangYPuLYYuXMGuoLZJinJLWangZJuHMJiangYMLiuJJYuanHWLiCHZhangPSheYFLiuJPZhuJDoes Traditional Chinese Medicine pattern affect acupoint specific effect? Analysis of data from a multicenter, randomized, controlled trial for primary dysmenorrheaJ Altern Complement Med2013191434910.1089/acm.2011.040422823583AsgharAUGreenGLythgoeMFLewithGMacPhersonHAcupuncture needling sensation: the neural correlates of Deqi using fMRIBrain Res2010131511111820025853KongJFufaDTGerberAJRosmanISVangelMGGracelyRHGollubRLPsychophysical outcomes from a randomized pilot study of manual, electro, and sham acupuncture treatment on experimentally induced thermal painJ Pain200561556410.1016/j.jpain.2004.10.00515629419WhitePPrescottPLewithGDoes needling sensation (de qi) affect treatment outcome in pain? Analysis of data from a larger single-blind randomized controlled trialAcupunct Med201028312012510.1136/aim.2009.00176820964256VasJPerea-MillaEMéndezCSánchez NavarroCLeón RubioJMBriosoMGarcía ObreroIEfficacy and safety of acupuncture for chronic uncomplicated neck pain: a randomized controlled studyPain20061261–324525516934402WittCBrinkhausBJenaSLindeKStrengAWagenpfeilSHummelsbergerJWaltherHUMelchartDWillichSNAcupuncture in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee: a randomized trialLancet2005366948013614310.1016/S0140-6736(05)66871-716005336ScharfHPMansmannUStreitbergerKWitteSKrämerJMaierCTrampischHJVictorNAcupuncture and knee osteoarthritis: a three-armed randomized trialAnn Intern Med20061451122010.7326/0003-4819-145-1-200607040-0000516818924HaakeMMüllerHHSchade-BrittingerCBaslerHDSchäferHMaierCEndresHGTrampischHJMolsbergerAGerman Acupuncture Trials (GERAC) for chronic low back pain: randomized, multicenter, blinded, parallel-group trial with 3 groupsArch Intern Med2007167171892189810.1001/Archinte.167.17.189217893311LiangFRAcupuncture (Zhen Jiu Xue)2005Beijing: China Traditional Chinese Medicine Publishing195ParkHParkJLeeHLeeHDoes Deqi (needle sensation) exist?Am J Chin Med2002301455010.1142/S0192415X0200005312067096EnblomAHammarMSteineckGBörjesonSCan individuals identify if needling was performed with an acupuncture needle or a non-penetrating sham needle?Complement Ther Med200816528829410.1016/j.ctim.2008.02.01219186344LangevinHMChurchillDLWuJBadgerGJYandowJAFoxJRKragMHEvidence of connective tissue involvement in acupunctureFASEB J200216887287411967233LangevinHMChurchillDLFoxJRBadgerGJGarraBSKragMHBiomechanical response to acupuncture needling in humansJ Appl Physiol20019162471247811717207LinWWangPExperimental Acupuncture1999Shanghai: Shanghai Scientific and Technology Publishing HouseKongJGollubRLWebbJMKongJTVangelMGKwongKTest-retest study of fMRI signal change evoked by electroacupuncture stimulationNeuroimage20073431171118110.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.10.01917157035WhitePBishopFHardyHAbdollahianSWhiteAParkJKaptchukTJLewithGTSouthampton needle sensation questionnaire: development and validation of a measure to gauge acupuncture needle sensationJ Altern Complement Med200814437337910.1089/acm.2007.071418576920HuiKKNixonEEVangelMGLiuJMarinaONapadowVHodgeSMRosenBRMakrisNKennedyDNCharacterization of the “deqi” response in acupunctureBMC Complement Altern Med200773310.1186/1472-6882-7-3317973984HuiKKLiuJMarinaONapadowVHaselgroveCKwongKKKennedyDNMakrisNThe integrated response of the human cerebro-cerebellar and limbic systems to acupuncture stimulation at ST 36 as evidenced by fMRINeuroimage200527347949610.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.04.03716046146HuiKKMarinaOClaunchJDNixonEEFangJLiuJLiMNapadowVVangelMMakrisNChanSTKwongKKRosenBRAcupuncture mobilizes the brain’s default mode and its anti-correlated network in healthy subjectsBrain Res200912878410319559684BirchSClinical research on acupuncture (Part 2). Controlled clinical trials, an overview of their methodsJ Altern Complement Med20041048149810.1089/107555304132391115253852Suarez-AlmazorMELooneyCLiuYCoxVPietzKMarcusDMStreetRLJrA randomized controlled trial of acupuncture for osteoarthritis of the knee: effects of patient-provider communicationArthritis Care Res (Hoboken)2010621229123610.1002/acr.2022520506122
