<?xml version="1.0"?>
Parkinsons DisParkinsons DisPDParkinson's Disease2090-80832042-0080Hindawi Publishing Corporation354089310.1155/2012/767105Review ArticleBright Light Therapy in Parkinson's Disease: An Overview of the Background and EvidenceRuttenSonja
1

2
*VriendChris
1

2
van den HeuvelOdile A.
1

2
SmitJan H.
1
BerendseHenk W.
3
van der WerfYsbrand D.
2

4
1Department of Psychiatry, VU University Medical Center, 1007 MB Amsterdam, The Netherlands2Department of Anatomy and Neuroscience, VU University Medical Center, Van der Boechorststraat 7, 1081 BT Amsterdam, The Netherlands3Department of Neurology, VU University Medical Center, 1007 MB Amsterdam, The Netherlands4Department of Sleep and Cognition, Netherlands Institute for Neuroscience, Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences, Meibergdreef 47, 1105 BA Amsterdam, The Netherlands*Sonja Rutten: s.rutten@vumc.nlAcademic Editor: Douglas Mckay Wallace201223122012201276710527920121611201221112012Copyright © 2012 Sonja Rutten et al.2012This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Sleep disorders are common in Parkinson's disease (PD) and seem to be strongly associated with depression. It has been suggested that sleep disorders as well as depression are caused by a disturbed circadian rhythm. Indeed, PD patients are prone to misalignment of their circadian rhythm due to various factors, and many patients with PD display a phase advance of their circadian rhythm. Current treatment options for sleep disorders and depression in patients with PD are limited and can have serious side effects; alternative treatments are therefore badly needed. Bright light therapy (BLT) restores circadian rhythmicity effectively in mood- and sleep-disturbed patients without PD. The few studies that focused on the efficacy of BLT in patients with PD demonstrated a positive effect of BLT not only on sleep and mood but also on motor function. More research on the neurobiology and efficacy of BLT in PD is warranted.1. IntroductionIn addition to the characteristic motor symptoms, patients with Parkinson's disease (PD) experience many nonmotor symptoms, comprising a variety of cognitive, autonomic, sensory, neuropsychiatric, and sleep disturbances [1, 2]. Sleep disturbances and disorders (as defined in Table 1) including reduced total sleep time, reduced sleep efficiency, increased sleep fragmentation, rapid eye movement (REM) sleep behaviour disorder, and excessive daytime sleepiness, occur in about 60–95% of PD patients [3–6]. Sleep influences motor symptoms. The so-called “sleep benefit”, an improvement of motor functions upon awakening that occurs in more than 40% of PD patients, is attributed to improved dopaminergic function as a result of increased storage of dopamine in nigrostriatal terminals during sleep [7]. Moreover, melatonin, a hormone secreted by the pineal gland at night, has been suggested to worsen motor symptoms in PD patients [8]. Sleep disorders in PD often coincide with depression [6]. Depression occurs in 35–50% of patients throughout the course of the disease [9, 10]. It has a major impact on overall functioning of PD patients: depressed PD patients score lower on scales assessing activities of daily living and exhibit more cognitive problems [9, 11, 12].Sleep disorders and depression are two of the most important factors influencing quality of life of PD patients and their caregivers [4, 9, 13, 14]. Unfortunately, treatment options are limited, and adding pharmacological agents raises nonadherence in PD patients [15]. Moreover, medication can induce serious side effects in PD patients. Hypnotic drugs, often prescribed for sleep disorders, worsen daytime sedation and the risk of falling and are therefore less suitable for PD patients [16]. Melatonin might ameliorate subjective sleep disturbances in PD patients, but objective improvement of sleep quality is minimal [17, 18]. Since a number of studies indicate that melatonin has unfavorable motor effects through interaction with dopamine pathways, more research is warranted on the effects of exogenous melatonin in PD patients [19–22].Tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), used in the treatment of depression in PD, can cause orthostatic hypotension, sedation, cognitive and anticholinergic adverse effects, in addition to extrapyramidal adverse effects, that may potentially worsen motor symptoms [23, 24]. Results of studies focussing on the tolerability of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) are inconclusive [23–25]. Levodopa treatment can alleviate nocturnal akinesia and thus improve sleep but can conversely negatively influence sleep by reducing the duration of REM sleep and increasing REM sleep latency [26]. Anticholinergics and dopamine agonists increase the risk of nighttime hallucinations [27]. The latter are also associated with sudden attacks of daytime sleepiness [26], which may hamper quantity and quality of nighttime sleep. Behavioral and psychotherapeutic interventions are often less feasible due to cognitive dysfunction and dementia [28]. It is evident that there is a great need for an effective and patient-friendly alternative for treating sleep disorders and depression in PD patients. Sleep problems and depressive symptoms often cooccur in PD [6, 14]. Dysfunction of the biological clock might be a common underlying causal factor for these disorders, providing a promising potential target for treatment [29, 30]. Bright light therapy (BLT) restores circadian rhythmicity and therefore effectively treats affective disorders and insomnia, and increases sleep efficiency [31–38]. Additionally, it might lead to improvement of motor symptoms in PD [8, 39, 40]. BLT has few contraindications and side effects and may therefore be an elegant alternative for the treatment of PD-related depression and sleep disturbances.This paper gives an overview of the neurobiology of the biological clock and the factors that contribute to its desynchronization in PD. Furthermore, we review the evidence for BLT as a treatment for sleep disorders, depression and motor symptoms in patients with PD, and provide recommendations for administration of BLT. 2. The Circadian Rhythm and Consequences of DesynchronizationTo understand the effects of BLT, one needs to understand the (patho)physiology of circadian rhythmicity, as explained in this section. The circadian rhythm is generated by the circadian pacemaker, a group of about 10,000 neurons located in the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) of the hypothalamus. Its endogenous rhythm is slightly different from the 24-hour day-night cycle and has to be entrained by signals (or “zeitgebers”) such as light, activity, and food [41]. Light excites specialized melanopsin containing ganglion cells in the retina, that project a “daytime” signal towards the SCN via the retinohypothalamic tract [42]. The output signals of the SCN convey circadian timing information to brain areas regulating behavior, body temperature, autonomic and neuroendocrine systems, including the secretion of melatonin by the pineal gland [42]. The secretion of melatonin is inhibited by the SCN during the light cycle, but the SCN also contains melatonin receptors that inhibit SCN firing, thereby creating a negative feedback loop [43, 44]. Desynchronization of the biological clock can be caused by a variety of factors that influence the input of the SCN [45]. A disturbed circadian rhythm is probably a major common causal factor in both depression and sleep problems [29, 46, 47]. Some of the major neurotransmitters implicated in mood regulation, including serotonin, norepinephrine, and dopamine, as well as their receptors, show a circadian rhythm in their levels, release, and activity [48]. Various polymorphic variations of clock genes such as TIM, BMAL1, and PER2 are associated with mood disorders [29]. Research on the diurnal variability of mood has shown that misalignment of the circadian rhythm can induce mood changes [47]. Some patients with a depressive disorder display a phase advance in circadian rhythm, as exhibited by a shift in melatonin and cortisol rhythms [36, 47]. Dysfunction of the circadian clock can lead to sleep fragmentation or insomnia [42, 45]. The interaction between sleep and depression likely comprises more than a failure of the biological clock. Insomnia or hypersomnia are well-known symptoms of depression, but sleep disturbances can cause depressive symptoms as well [29, 47, 49–55]. Emotional hyperarousal may increase autonomic activity, resulting in sleep difficulties [53]. This is confirmed by the fact that depressed patients show altered sleep architecture, which normalizes after successful treatment [50]. On the other hand, emotionality is frequently negatively toned in insomnia and poor sleep [47, 51], and studies on sleep deprivation showed enhanced emotional physiological responses to negative stimuli [49, 52, 55]. During REM sleep, emotional intensity of previous affective experiences is decreased [54, 56, 57]. Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) studies show that sleep deprivation leads to increased activation of the amygdala in response to negative aversive stimuli [58–60]. These findings strongly suggest that sleep is relevant for maintaining adaptive emotional regulation and reactivity [29, 54]. In short, sleep disturbances and depression seem to be highly correlated. A disturbed biological rhythm might be a common underlying factor and therefore an important starting point for treatment. However, the directionality of the relationship between these three remains uncertain, and more research on this subject is warranted. 3. Desynchronization of the Circadian Rhythm in Parkinson's DiseasePD patients are prone to desynchronization of their biological clock due to various factors that will be discussed in this section. The neurodegenerative process in PD leading to dopamine depletion is one of the underlying causes, since recent research links dopamine directly to the circadian rhythm [61–63]. Striatal dopamine metabolism seems to be regulated by clock proteins such as PER2 [62]. Reciprocally, stimulation of dopamine receptors affects the rhythm of expression of clock genes such as PER1 and PER2 in the striatum [61, 63]. Dopamine also regulates the rhythmic expression of melanopsin in retinal ganglion cells, thereby influencing the entrainment of the circadian rhythm by light [64].In many patients with PD, factors hampering the SCN input contribute to desynchronization of the circadian rhythm. Firstly, exposure and sensitivity to zeitgebers decrease. Retinal illumination decreases in the elderly due to pupillary miosis and reduced crystalline lens light transmission, especially of short wavelengths [65]. This leads to partial light deprivation of the SCN and pineal gland. Additionally, PD patients, just like many elderly patients, may be more inclined to stay indoors due to motor problems or a decreased postural balance and expose themselves less to environmental light and physical activities [45]. Entrainment of the circadian rhythm is thwarted by a decreased exposure to zeitgebers. The amplitude of the circadian rhythm decreases in patients with PD, as reflected by a decrease in sympathetic activity during the day, diminishing of the diurnal variation of cortisol secretion, and a decrease of the amplitude of the melatonin secretion rhythm [19, 66, 67]. This flattening of circadian rhythms makes them more prone to desynchronization. Sleep in PD patients can be disrupted by both motor (e.g., nocturnal akinesia and dystonia) and nonmotor symptoms such as nocturia [1, 68]. Additionally, PD patients may experience periodic limb movement disorder, restless legs syndrome, REM sleep behavior disorder, and excessive daytime sleepiness [4, 26, 68], all contributing to a reduced quality and/or quantity of sleep. PD-related neuropsychiatric disorders such as benign hallucinations and psychosis can also disturb sleep [6]. Emotional stress, caused by having a progressive neurodegenerative disorder that increasingly results in disability, may interact with the basic homeostatic and circadian drives for sleep through the interaction between affect-related regions and regions that control sleep and wake [30]. A disturbed sleep-wake cycle results in conflicting SCN input. Finally, pharmacological treatment of PD with dopaminergic drugs also influences sleep/wakefulness mechanisms. Levodopa use can lead to a decrease of sympathetic activity during the day and disappearance of the sympathetic morning peak [69]. Levodopa influences sleep architecture, reducing the duration of REM sleep and increasing REM sleep latency [26]. All of the abovementioned factors may contribute to a desynchronization of the circadian rhythm in PD, as displayed in Figure 1. In several small studies, levodopa-treated PD patients display a phase-advanced circadian rhythm compared to healthy controls and de novo PD patients [19, 70, 71], making them vulnerable to depression and sleep disorders. Indeed, PD patients have more frequent awakenings at night and a reduced sleep efficiency compared to healthy controls [68]. BLT acts as a strong zeitgeber and may therefore restore circadian rhythmicity in PD patients.4. Efficacy of Bright Light TherapyIn the last couple of years, research on the efficacy of BLT has shifted from adults to the elderly and specifically to PD patients. In 2005 a meta-analysis demonstrated that BLT is effective in treating seasonal affective disorder (SAD) and nonseasonal depression in adults, with effect sizes equivalent or superior to psychopharmacologic treatment [31]. BLT has few side effects and is therefore considered a patient-friendly treatment [32, 72]. Two recent large randomized controlled trials focused on the efficacy of BLT for nonseasonal depression in the elderly [32, 33]. Lieverse et al. stated that the positive effects of BLT were due to improved circadian rhythmicity, as displayed in their study by (1) an increased steepness of the evening rise of salivary melatonin levels, (2) a reduction of 24-hour urinary cortisol excretion, and (3) a trend-significant accelerated diurnal decline in salivary cortisol levels [32]. Riemersma-van der Lek et al. demonstrated that BLT attenuated cognitive and functional decline and positively influenced mood in 189 residents of group care facilities, of which 87% had dementia. In this study, BLT only improved sleep when it was combined with the administration of melatonin [33]. In other studies, BLT as monotherapy was effective in improving both sleep efficiency and quality and in reducing daytime sleepiness in elderly patients with and without dementia [32, 34, 35, 37]. To summarize, BLT seems to be effective in treating sleep disorders as well as depression. Most of the abovementioned studies, however, excluded patients with disorders such as PD. Only four studies have addressed the use of BLT in PD [8, 39, 40, 73]; these will be discussed in the following section. The first study in which BLT was used in PD patients is only available in Russian and is therefore not included in this overview [73]. Willis and Turner described a case series of 12 patients with PD and insomnia and/or depressive symptoms [40]. They used BLT of 1000–1500 Lux for 60 to 90 minutes prior to normal bedtime during two to five weeks. Of the eight participants that reported significant problems with falling asleep, seven showed improvement in the onset and continuity of sleep after BLT treatment. Most patients reported this effect within two to three days after commencing BLT, and this lasted for several days after discontinuation. Six of 11 patients showed a noticeable improvement of mood. The antidepressant effect lasted for several weeks, even after discontinuation of BLT, and was paralleled by increased socialization. BLT resulted in improved motor function in most PD patients, with the strongest effects on bradykinesia and rigidity. After BLT, dopamine replacement therapy was reduced to a level ranging from 13 to 100% in five subjects, while antidepressants and hypnotic drugs were reduced or eliminated in two patients. Younger patients, especially those that were medication naïve, responded better to BLT than those over 75 years of age, and adherent patients had a better therapeutic response than those who used it intermittently. In a RCT by Paus et al., 18 PD patients treated with BLT of 7500 Lux were compared to 18 PD patients receiving placebo light of 950 Lux [39]. Light was administered for 30 minutes in the morning during two weeks. PD-related symptoms were assessed with the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS); depression was measured with the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI). Patients who received BLT showed a significant improvement on UPDRS sections I (evaluation of mentation, behavior, and mood), II (self-evaluation of the activities of daily life), and IV (Hoehn and Yahr Scale) compared with the control group. Improvement of UPDRS I and II did not correlate with changes in BDI scores, implying that the effects of BLT on behavior and daily functioning were independent of changes in mood. There was no significant difference on UPDRS section III (clinician-scored motor evaluation), except for a slight attenuation of tremor. Regarding sleep, the only sleep parameter investigated was a one-item daytime sleepiness scale, which did not show a between-group difference. Mood improved significantly, but moderately, in the BLT group, as demonstrated by an average decrease of 2.2 points on the BDI. No significant improvement of BDI scores occurred in the control group. The short treatment duration and the fact that only mildly depressed patients were included might explain the modest effects of BLT on motor function and depression [49]. (Willis et al. 2012, [8]) performed a retrospective, open label study monitoring 129 levodopa-treated PD patients for a period ranging from a few months to eight years [49]. These patients were all prescribed BLT at a dose of 4000 to 6000 Lux for one hour prior to bedtime. Depending on the degree of adherence, PD patients were divided in the early quit group (EQUIT; patients that withdrew from BLT immediately after intake), the adherent group and the semiadherent group. Twelve patients suffering from other neurological conditions served as a control group. Motor function was assessed with three timed motor tests and a global rating scale. Psychiatric symptoms and sleep were evaluated on a global rating scale during an interview. Total drug burden (TDB) was determined and monitored over time. There was a slight deterioration of insomnia seen in EQUIT patients, while adherent patients showed an acute and dramatic improvement. Adherent patients displayed a significant improvement of bradykinesia, rigidity, balance, and motor tests, while the motor parameters in the EQUIT group deteriorated over time. In the semiadherent group, these parameters varied over time and appeared associated with periods of nonadherence with BLT or changes in drug regimen. All groups displayed an improvement of depression over time, with the most robust improvement seen in adherent patients. Anxiety did not change in the EQUIT group in contrast to other groups, with the greatest improvement in the adherent group. The adherent and semiadherent groups required an increase in TDB in, respectively, 13 and 15% of cases, while 91% in the EQUIT group required increased medication. Moreover, patients in the EQUIT group were on similar doses of dopamine replacement therapy as the other PD patients but displayed more severe PD than those who received BLT. In the adherent group, morbidity improved over the course of years, while in the EQUIT group, progression of PD severity was as expected. Limitations of this study are the fact that the study was not blinded or placebo controlled, and that patients were monitored for different periods of time. Depression can lead to psychomotor retardation [74], so the improvement of motor function in these studies could be attributed to a decrease in depressive symptoms. However, in the study by Paus et al (2007). there was no improvement of motor function in the subjects that demonstrated a significant decrease of the BDI score [39]. More likely, the positive effects of BLT on motor symptoms in PD result from a restored balance between melatonin and dopamine [8]. A number of studies indicate that melatonin has unfavorable motor effects through interaction with dopamine pathways [19–22].  Another point that is not addressed in these studies is the effect of other zeitgebers on the improvement in circadian rhythmicity. All subjects were given BLT at a set time, prior to bedtime or after awakening in the morning. This may have improved the daily rhythm and sleep-wake cycle of participating patients. Behavioral and psychological interventions are also effective in treating insomnia [75, 76]. Taken together, these studies display a positive effect of BLT on mood, sleep, and motor functions in PD patients. However, since these studies were relatively small and suboptimally designed, further studies on the efficacy of BLT in treating both nonmotor motor and motor symptoms in patients with PD are warranted. 5. Recommendations for Administration of BLTIn this section, recommendations for administration of BLT as well as information on contraindications and adverse effects are provided. Due to a lack of research on BLT in PD patients, the majority of these recommendations are based on research in patients without PD, so we must stress that (adverse) effects in PD patients might be different. More research on the effects of BLT in PD patients needs to be done before BLT can be used for PD patients in daily clinical practice.There are many types of light boxes available. Clinically tested models yield a maximum illuminance of 10.000 Lux at a comfortable sitting distance of about 30 cm [38, 77]. At this intensity, a duration of 30 minutes per session is usually sufficient, while lower intensities require longer sessions [31, 78, 79]. It is advisable to use a light box with a complete ultraviolet (UV) filter, since cumulative UV radiation can be harmful to eyes and skin [80, 81].Time of administration of BLT depends on the nature of the patient's complaints and his or her individual chronotype. Morning light advances the biological clock and has proven to be effective in treatment of depression [77, 78]. However, patients with PD probably have a phase-advanced circadian rhythm, and one might argue that evening BLT might be more efficient [8, 19, 40, 70, 71]. On the other hand, Paus et al. (2007) demonstrated that morning light can improve mood and sleep in PD patients as well [39]. BLT is most effective when administered relative to individual chronotype [38, 82]. The chronotype can be assessed with the Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire (MEQ), which correlates with the time of onset of evening rise in melatonin secretion and circadian variation of oral temperature [78, 82, 83]. An online version of the MEQ at the website of the Center for Environmental Therapeutics (http://www.cet.org/) contains a table of the recommended timing of morning BLT based on the MEQ-score. Strict adherence to BLT is necessary to maximize efficacy [8].There is no consensus on the total duration of treatment with BLT in nonseasonal depression or insomnia. In PD patients, followup after discontinuation of BLT was only performed in the study of Willis and Turner (2007) [40]. They observed that the antidepressant effect of BLT lasted after discontinuation of therapy, but sleep deteriorated after a couple of days. These findings correspond with a large study on the effects of BLT in the elderly patients with a nonseasonal depression [32]. Since it might take months before BLT can exert positive effects on motor function, a long treatment duration of PD patients might be necessary [8]. More research on both timing and duration of BLT in patients with PD is warranted.Cumulative light energy can cause damage to skin and eye tissues, especially short-wavelength UV light [78, 80, 81]. Patients with porfyria, macular degeneration, retinal dystrophy, lupus erythematosus, chronic actinic dermatitis, and solar urticaria can have photosensitization reactions to light and should only receive BLT under monitoring of an ophthalmologist or dermatologist [78]. Moreover, some pharmacological agents are known to photosensitize the skin or retina, including some of the tricyclic antidepressants, tetracyclic antibiotics, and antiarrhythmic drugs [78]. These medications should be stopped before commencing BLT.In a study of 70 subjects receiving BLT for a SAD the most often reported adverse effects were headache, eye or vision problems and nausea [72]. No oculoretinal changes were detected during ophthalmologic evaluations of patients receiving treatment with BLT to up to six years [84]. Some cases of BLT-induced (hypo)mania have been described, requiring discontinuation of BLT and medication [72, 85, 86]. However, in patients with a known or suspected bipolar disorder BLT can be administered when the patient is using a mood stabilizer [80]. Nevertheless, side effects of BLT are mostly mild and usually resolve within a couple of days [32, 33, 72].6. ConclusionSleep disturbances are common in PD and are strongly associated with depression [3–6]. A disturbed circadian rhythm may be a common underlying factor in both disorders [29, 46, 47]. PD patients are prone to misalignment of the circadian rhythm due to dopamine deficiency as well as various other factors that disrupt input to the SCN [1, 4, 26, 45, 63, 66, 68]. Indeed, many patients with PD display a phase advance of their circadian rhythm [19, 70, 71], which may contribute to the increased prevalence of sleep disturbances and depression [6, 9, 10]. Since the current treatment options for sleep disturbances and depression in PD are limited and can have serious side effects [16, 23], alternative treatments are badly needed. BLT restores circadian rhythmicity and is an effective treatment for depressive disorders and insomnia in the general population [31–35, 37]. So far, little research has focused on the efficacy of BLT in patients with PD [8, 39, 40, 73]. The studies that have been performed were small and suboptimally designed yet demonstrated a positive effect of BLT on sleep and mood in patients with PD. Moreover, BLT may positively influence motor function, possibly through a restored balance between melatonin and dopamine [8, 40]. It might thus facilitate a dose reduction of dopaminergic medication [8, 40]. BLT has few side-effects and is therefore patient friendly [32, 72]. Nevertheless, more research is warranted to demonstrate the efficacy and underlying mechanism of BLT in PD.1ParkAStacyMNon-motor symptoms in Parkinson’s diseaseJournal of Neurology20092563, supplement2932982-s2.0-69549084753197111192Rodriguez-OrozMCJahanshahiMKrackPInitial clinical manifestations of Parkinson’s disease: features and pathophysiological mechanismsThe Lancet Neurology2009812112811392-s2.0-72149101615199099113ChaudhuriKRHealyDGSchapiraAHVNon-motor symptoms of Parkinson’s disease: diagnosis and managementThe Lancet Neurology2006532352452-s2.0-32544432029164883794DauvilliersYInsomnia in patients with neurodegenerative conditionsSleep Medicine20078supplement 4S27S342-s2.0-40849113601183466745MenzaMDobkinRDMarinHBienfaitKSleep disturbances in Parkinson’s diseaseMovement Disorders201025supplement 1S117S1222-s2.0-77953442615201872366LarsenJPTandbergESleep disorders in patients with Parkinson’s disease: epidemiology and managementCNS Drugs20011542672752-s2.0-0035054370114631327TandbergELarsenJPKarlsenKExcessive daytime sleepiness and sleep benefit in Parkinson's disease: a community-based studyMovement Disorders1999146922927105846658WillisGLMooreCArmstrongSMA historical justification for and retrospective analysis of the systematic application of light therapy in Parkinson's diseaseReviews in the Neurosciences2012232199226224996789AarslandDPahlhagenSBallardCGEhrtUSvenningssonPDepression in Parkinson disease—epidemiology, mechanisms and managementNature Reviews Neurology201281354710CummingsJLDepression and Parkinson’s disease: a reviewAmerican Journal of Psychiatry199214944434542-s2.0-0026582759137279411SchragAJahanshahiMQuinnNWhat contributes to quality of life in patients with Parkinson’s disease?Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp; Psychiatry20006933083122-s2.0-003387582612KarlsenKHLarsenJPTandbergEMaelandJGInfluence of clinical and demographic variables on quality of life in patients with Parkinson’s diseaseJournal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp; Psychiatry19996644314352-s2.0-003304325613AskenasyJJMSleep in Parkinson’s diseaseActa Neurologica Scandinavica19938731671702-s2.0-0027480823847568414Caap-AhlgrenMDehlinOInsomnia and depressive symptoms in patients with Parkinson’s disease: relationship to health-related quality of life. An interview study of patients living at homeArchives of Gerontology and Geriatrics200132123332-s2.0-00350957211125123615AertsMBvan der EijkMKramersKBloemBRInsufficient medication compliance in Parkinson’s diseaseNederlands Tijdschrift voor Geneeskunde2011155p. A30312-s2.0-7995820500816ThorpyMJSleep disorders in Parkinson’s diseaseClinical Cornerstone200461S7S152-s2.0-29427260241525953517DowlingGAMastickJCollingECarterJHSingerCMAminoffMJMelatonin for sleep disturbances in Parkinson’s diseaseSleep Medicine2005654594662-s2.0-243444860061608412518MedeirosCAMCarvalhedo de BruinPFLopesLAMagalhãesMCde Lourdes SeabraMSales de BruinVMEffect of exogenous melatonin on sleep and motor dysfunction in Parkinson’s disease: a randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled studyJournal of Neurology200725444594642-s2.0-342490728171740477919BordetRDevosDBriqueSStudy of circadian melatonin secretion pattern at different stages of Parkinson’s diseaseClinical Neuropharmacology200326265722-s2.0-03452703901267152520ChenHSchernhammerESchwarzschildMAAscherioAA prospective study of night shift work, sleep duration, and risk of Parkinson’s diseaseAmerican Journal of Epidemiology200616387267302-s2.0-336457204911649547221CataláMDCañete-NicolásCIradiATarazonaFJTormosJMPascual-LeoneAMelatonin levels in Parkinson’s disease: drug therapy versus electrical stimulation of the internal globus pallidusExperimental Gerontology1997324-55535582-s2.0-0342275227931545622WillisGLArmstrongSMA therapeutic role for melatonin antagonism in experimental models of Parkinson’s diseasePhysiology and Behavior19996657857952-s2.0-00329737511040510623VajdaFJESolinasCCurrent approaches to management of depression in Parkinson’s diseaseJournal of Clinical Neuroscience20051277397432-s2.0-262444584171602698524MadhusoodananSAlexeenkoLSandersRBrennerRExtrapyramidal symptoms associated with antidepressants—a review of the literature and an analysis of spontaneous reportsAnnals of Clinical Psychiatry20102231481562-s2.0-799521148392068018725RichardIHMcDermottMPKurlanRLynessJMComoPGPearsonNA randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of antidepressants in Parkinson diseaseNeurology20127816122912362249619926DeschenesCLMcCurrySMCurrent treatments for sleep disturbances in individuals with dementiaCurrent Psychiatry Reports200911120262-s2.0-592490857731918770427PahwaRUnderstanding Parkinson’s disease: an update on current diagnostic and treatment strategiesJournal of the American Medical Directors Association200677supplement 24102-s2.0-353489516641794861328AarslandDZaccaiJBrayneCA systematic review of prevalence studies of dementia in Parkinson’s diseaseMovement Disorders20052010125512632-s2.0-278444697511604180329MonteleonePMajMThe circadian basis of mood disorders: recent developments and treatment implicationsEuropean Neuropsychopharmacology200818107017112-s2.0-496491028171866286530BaglioniCSpiegelhalderKLombardoCRiemannDSleep and emotions: a focus on insomniaSleep Medicine Reviews20101442272382-s2.0-779529729732013798931GoldenRNGaynesBNEkstromRDThe efficacy of light therapy in the treatment of mood disorders: a review and meta-analysis of the evidenceAmerican Journal of Psychiatry200516246566622-s2.0-168443813151580013432LieverseRvan SomerenEJWNielenMMAUitdehaagBMJSmitJHHoogendijkWJGBright light treatment in elderly patients with nonseasonal major depressive disorder: a randomized placebo-controlled trialArchives of General Psychiatry201168161702-s2.0-786509041742119996633Riemersma-van der LekRFSwaabDFTwiskJHolEMHoogendijkWJGvan SomerenEJWEffect of bright light and melatonin on cognitive and noncognitive function in elderly residents of group care facilities: a randomized controlled trialThe Journal of the American Medical Association200829922264226552-s2.0-449491750841854472434CampbellSSDawsonDAndersonMWAlleviation of sleep maintenance insomnia with timed exposure to bright lightJournal of the American Geriatrics Society19934188298362-s2.0-0027268206834056135MishimaKOkawaMHishikawaYHozumiSHoriHTakahashiKMorning bright light therapy for sleep and behavior disorders in elderly patients with dementiaActa Psychiatrica Scandinavica1994891172-s2.0-0028013332814090136PailGHufWPjrekEBright-light therapy in the treatment of mood disordersNeuropsychobiology20116431521622-s2.0-799611309582181108537SatlinAVolicerLRossVHerzLCampbellSBright light treatment of behavioral and sleep disturbances in patients with Alzheimer’s diseaseAmerican Journal of Psychiatry19921498102810322-s2.0-0026732585135331338Wirz-JusticeABenedettiFBergerMChronotherapeutics (light and wake therapy) in affective disordersPsychological Medicine20053579399442-s2.0-225444419211604506039PausSSchmitz-HübschTWüllnerUVogelAKlockgetherTAbeleMBright light therapy in Parkinson’s disease: a pilot studyMovement Disorders20072210149514982-s2.0-345480260721751649240WillisGLTurnerEJDPrimary and secondary features of Parkinson’s disease improve with strategic exposure to bright light: a case series studyChronobiology International20072435215372-s2.0-343473856041761294941WelshDKLogothetisDEMeisterMReppertSMIndividual neurons dissociated from rat suprachiasmatic nucleus express independently phased circadian firing rhythmsNeuron19951446977062-s2.0-0028904194771823342RosenwasserAMFunctional neuroanatomy of sleep and circadian rhythmsBrain Research Reviews20096122813062-s2.0-703495514571969528843ArendtJSkeneDJMelatonin as a chronobioticSleep Medicine Reviews20059125392-s2.0-118442934881564973644Pandi-PerumalSRTrakhtISrinivasanVPhysiological effects of melatonin: role of melatonin receptors and signal transduction pathwaysProgress in Neurobiology20088533353532-s2.0-467490974731857130145van SomerenEJWCircadian and sleep disturbances in the elderlyExperimental Gerontology2000359-10122912372-s2.0-00336470481111360446CajochenCMünchMKnoblauchVBlatterKWirz-JusticeAAge-related changes in the circadian and homeostatic regulation of human sleepChronobiology International2006231-24614742-s2.0-336466868521668731947Wirz-JusticeADiurnal variations of depressive symptomsDialogues in Clinical Neuroscience20081033373432-s2.0-554491103581897994748McClungCACircadian genes, rhythms and the biology of mood disordersPharmacology and Therapeutics200711422222322-s2.0-341471733001739526449FranzenPLBuysseDJDahlREThompsonWSiegleGJSleep deprivation alters pupillary reactivity to emotional stimuli in healthy young adultsBiological Psychology20098033003052-s2.0-613491139691904168950BuysseDJFrankELoweKKCherryCRKupferDJElectroencephalographic sleep correlates of episode and vulnerability to recurrence in depressionBiological Psychiatry19974144064182-s2.0-0031568865903453551EspieCAInsomnia: conceptual issues in the development, persistence, and treatment of sleep disorder in adultsAnnual Review of Psychology2002532152432-s2.0-003640475852FranzenPLSiegleGJBuysseDJRelationships between affect, vigilance, and sleepiness following sleep deprivationJournal of Sleep Research200817134412-s2.0-390491106741827555353KalesACaldwellABPrestonTAPersonality patterns in insomnia. Theoretical implicationsArchives of General Psychiatry1976339112811342-s2.0-001717750796249554WalkerMPvan der HelmEOvernight therapy? The role of sleep in emotional brain processingPsychological Bulletin200913557317482-s2.0-699491625051970238055ZoharDTzischinskyOEpsteinRLaviePThe effects of sleep loss on medical residents’ emotional reactions to work events: a cognitive-energy modelSleep200528147542-s2.0-172443761321570072056MaloneyKJCapeEGGotmanJJonesBEHigh-frequency γ electroencephalogram activity in association with sleep-wake states and spontaneous behaviors in the ratNeuroscience19977625415552-s2.0-0031014218901533757CapeEGJonesBEDifferential modulation of high-frequency γ-electroencephalogram activity and sleep-wake state by noradrenaline and serotonin microinjections into the region of cholinergic basalis neuronsJournal of Neuroscience1998187265326662-s2.0-0032053956950282358YooSSGujarNHuPJoleszFAWalkerMPThe human emotional brain without sleep—a prefrontal amygdala disconnectCurrent Biology20071720R877R8782-s2.0-353489235761795674459van der HelmEYaoJDuttSRaoVSaletinJMWalkerMPREM sleep depotentiates amygdala activity to previous emotional experiencesCurrent Biology21232029203260van der HelmEYaoJDuttSRaoVSaletinJMWalkerMPREM sleep depotentiates amygdala activity to previous emotional experiencesCurrent Biology20112123202920322211952661ImbesiMYildizSDirim ArslanASharmaRManevHUzTDopamine receptor-mediated regulation of neuronal “clock” gene expressionNeuroscience200915825375442-s2.0-581494748411901753762HamppGRippergerJAHoubenTRegulation of monoamine oxidase A by circadian-clock components implies clock influence on moodCurrent Biology20081896786832-s2.0-430491168161843982663HoodSCassidyPCossetteMPEndogenous dopamine regulates the rhythm of expression of the clock protein PER2 in the rat dorsal striatum via daily activation of D2 dopamine receptorsJournal of Neuroscience2010304214046140582-s2.0-779585664292096222664SakamotoKLiuCKasamatsuMPozdeyevNVIuvonePMTosiniGDopamine regulates melanopsin mRNA expression in intrinsically photosensitive retinal ganglion cellsEuropean Journal of Neuroscience20052212312931362-s2.0-293444501261636777965TurnerPLMainsterMACircadian photoreception: ageing and the eye’s important role in systemic healthBritish Journal of Ophthalmology20089211143914442-s2.0-554491204471875747366HartmannAVeldhuisJDDeuschleMStandhardtHHeuserITwenty-four hour cortisol release profiles in patients with Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s disease compared to normal controls: ultradian secretory pulsatility and diurnal variationNeurobiology of Aging19971832852892-s2.0-0030739052926319367DevosDKroumovaMBordetRHeart rate variability and Parkinson’s disease severityJournal of Neural Transmission2003110999710112-s2.0-00429130851292883668AdlerCHThorpyMJSleep issues in Parkinson’s diseaseNeurology20056412supplement 3S12S202-s2.0-210444422521599421969BruguerolleBSimonNBiologic rhythms and Parkinson’s disease: a chronopharmacologic approach to considering fluctuations in functionClinical Neuropharmacology20022541942012-s2.0-00363388221215190670FertlEAuffEDoppelbauerAWaldhauserFCircadian secretion pattern of melatonin in de novo Parkinsonian patients: evidence for phase-shifting properties of l-dopaJournal of Neural Transmission1993532272342-s2.0-0027239615836910271FertlEAuffEDoppelbauerAWaldhauserFCircadian secretion pattern of melatonin in Parkinson’s diseaseJournal of Neural Transmission19913141472-s2.0-0025831474206473072KoganAOGuilfordPMSide effects of short-term 10,000-lux light therapyAmerican Journal of Psychiatry199815522932942-s2.0-0031931105946421673ArtemenkoARLevin IaIThe phototherapy of parkinsonism patientsZhurnal Nevrologii i Psikhiatrii imeni S.S. Korsakova1996963636674SobinCSackeimHAPsychomotor symptoms of depressionAmerican Journal of Psychiatry199715414172-s2.0-0031016615898895275MorinCMHauriPJEspieCASpielmanAJBuysseDJBootzinRRNonpharmacologic treatment of chronic insomnia. An American Academy of Sleep Medicine reviewSleep1999228113411562-s2.0-00335734061061717676MorinCMBootzinRRBuysseDJEdingerJDEspieCALichsteinKLPsychological and behavioral treatment of insomnia: update of the recent evidence (1998–2004)Sleep20062911139814142-s2.0-337510838411716298677TermanMTermanJSRossDCA controlled trial of timed bright light and negative air ionization for treatment of winter depressionArchives of General Psychiatry199855108758822-s2.0-0031665985978355778Wirz-JusticeABenedettiFTermanMChronotherapeutics (light and wake therapy) in affective disordersPsychological Medicine20053579399442-s2.0-225444419211604506079TermanJSTermanMSchlagerDEfficacy of brief, intense light exposure for treatment of winter depressionPsychopharmacology Bulletin19902613112-s2.0-0025164675237137180TermanMTermanJSLight therapyPrinciples and Practice of Sleep Medicine2005Philadelphia, Pa, USAElsevier81TermanMReméCERaffertyBGallinPFTermanJSBright light therapy for winter depression: potential ocular effects and theoretical implicationsPhotochemistry and Photobiology19905167817922-s2.0-0025440330219556582Wirz-JusticeABenedettiFTermanMInpatient proceduresChronotherapeutics for Affective Disorders2009Basel, SwitzerlandKarger83HorneJAOstbergOA self assessment questionnaire to determine morningness eveningness in human circadian rhythmsInternational Journal of Chronobiology197642971102-s2.0-0017028456102773884GallinPFTermanMRemeCERaffertyBTermanJSBurdeRMOphthalmologic examination of patients with seasonal affective disorder, before and after bright light therapyAmerican Journal of Ophthalmology199511922022102-s2.0-0028833025783222785SchwitzerJNeudorferCBlechaHGFleischhackerWWMania as a side effect of phototherapyBiological Psychiatry19902865325342-s2.0-0025118734213255586KripkeDFTiming of phototherapy and occurrence of maniaBiological Psychiatry19912911115611572-s2.0-00258763121873376Figure 1The input of the biological clock by zeitgebers is both decreased and conflicted due to various motor and non-motor symptoms in PD. Dopamine depletion due to PD disrupts circadian clock gene expression, and its treatment with levodopa influences both sleep structure and sympathetic activity. These factors all alter output of the biological clock: there is a phase advance and flattening of the circadian rhythm as displayed by hormone levels and sympathetic activity. In turn, the alteration of circadian rhythmicity has a negative influence on (input of) the biological clock, leading to a downward spiral resulting in sleep disturbances and depression.Table 1Definitions of sleep terminology.TermDefinitionSleep disturbanceSleep pattern divergent of what is considered to be normal as objectively measured, for example, by polysomnography. Sleep disorderMedical disorder involving sleep, resulting in suffering or reduced functioning, including dyssomnias and parasomnias. Sleep onset latencyTime interval between time of turning of the lights and onset of sleep. Sleep efficiencyRatio of the time spent asleep to the amount of time spent in bed. ChronotypeIndividual internal timing type regarding preferred time for mental and physical activity and sleep. Homeostatic sleep driveDrive to sleep that gradually increases with prolonged wakefulness and decreases during sleep. Sleep fragmentationDisrupted sleep cycle due to interruption of a sleep stage, as a result of the appearance of a lighter sleep stage or wakefulness. Sleep phase advanceForward shift of the sleep/wake rhythm, as demonstrated by the time of the nocturnal elevation of plasma melatonin. InsomniaSleep disorder comprising difficulty initiating and/or maintaining sleep or nonrestorative sleep for at least one month, resulting in significant distress and/or impaired daytime functioningREM sleep behavior disorderParasomnia characterized by “acting out” of dreams during REM sleep due to absence of normally occurring muscle atonia. Excessive daytime sleepinessParasomnia characterized by excessive sleepiness during the day, often with hypersomnia and the occurrence of sleep attacks. Periodic limb movement disorderSleep disorder characterized by involuntary limb movements causing fragmented sleep. Restless legs syndromeSyndrome characterized by unpleasant sensations in one or more limbs, exacerbated by rest and relieved with activity, paired with a strong urge to move the affected limbs, often with paresthesias or dysesthesias.
