<?xml version="1.0"?>
Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr EpidemiolSoc Psychiatry Psychiatr EpidemiolSocial Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology0933-79541433-9285Springer-VerlagBerlin/Heidelberg349647351310.1007/s00127-012-0513-xOriginal PaperCallous–unemotional traits as a cross-disorders constructHerpersPierre C. M.+31-344-640350+31-344-640351p.herpers@karakter.com1RommelseNanda N. J.n.lambregts-rommelse@psy.umcn.nl1BonsDaniëlle M. A.d.bons@karakter.com1BuitelaarJan K.j.buitelaar@psy.umcn.nl1ScheepersFloor E.f.e.scheepers-2@umcutrecht.nl21Karakter Child and Adolescent Psychiatry University Centre, Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre, Reinier Postlaan 12, 6525 GC Nijmegen, The Netherlands 2Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University Medical Centre Utrecht, P.O. Box 85500, 3508 GA Utrecht, The Netherlands 95201295201212201247122045206425720111442012© The Author(s) 2012PurposeCallous–unemotional (CU) traits are currently viewed as the defining signs and symptoms of juvenile psychopathy. It is unclear, however, whether CU traits have validity only in the context of conduct disorder (CD) as proposed by Frick and Moffitt (A proposal to the DSM-V childhood disorders and the ADHD and disruptive behavior disorders work groups to include a specifier to the diagnosis of conduct disorder based on the presence of callous–unemotional traits, American Psychiatric Association, Washington, DC, 2010), or also outside CD, either in combination with other forms of psychopathology or as a stand-alone construct.MethodsThe current review systematically studied the existent literature on CU traits in juveniles to examine their validity inside and outside CD according to the framework regarding the validity of a psychiatric diagnosis provided by Robins and Guze (Am J Psychiatry 126:983–987, 1970).ResultsInside youth with conduct problems, and CD specifically, it seems that CU traits meet the Robins and Guze criteria. As many of the reviewed studies included youth with ODD and ADHD as well, there are indications the same might be true for ODD and ADHD, although probably to a lesser extent. In other disorders, CU traits may be present as well, but their role is not firmly established. As stand-alone construct, data are lacking or are scarce on all of the above-mentioned criteria.ConclusionsCU traits are a useful specifier in CD, and possibly also in disruptive behaviour disorders (DBDs) more generally. High CU traits outside DBDs exist but it is as yet unknown if there is a clinical need for defining CU traits as a stand-alone construct.KeywordsCallous–unemotional traitsJuvenile psychopathyConduct disorderValidityissue-copyright-statement© Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2012IntroductionThere is an increasing interest in the moderating role psychopathic traits may play regarding long-term outcome and treatment effectiveness of disruptive behaviour [1–3]. Specifically, there is a widely held belief that psychopathy has a poor outcome and is untreatable, although it seems more appropriate to state that a subgroup of patients with disruptive behaviour who portray psychopathic traits may require different treatment than patients with disruptive behaviour without these traits [2].Although the history of the concept of psychopathy goes back to the nineteenth century [4, 5], today’s view on psychopathy is substantially based on Cleckley’s work, first published in 1941 [6], in which psychopathy is seen as a personality disorder. In recent literature, different aspects of psychopathy have been emphasized, such as: (1) disinhibition, poor impulsive regulation and the inclination to immediate gratification; (2) boldness, bravery, and thrill and adventure seeking; and (3) meanness, callousness and coldheartedness [7, 8]. There is now consensus that the presence of impulsive externalizing behaviour is not sufficient for a diagnosis of psychopathy but that boldness and/or meanness are the more typical characteristics. Particularly meanness is viewed by many experts as the core component of psychopathy. Frequently described symptoms of this core component are: lacking guilt and empathy, being very egocentric, showing callous use of others for ones own gain, and lacking normal emotionality, especially in showing a lack of anxiety. These symptoms have been known as callous–unemotional (CU) traits [1].Regarding CU traits specifically, reviews have been published paying attention to the aetiology [9] and diagnostic value [10–12]. Some reviews have specifically focused on the conceptualization of CU traits in youth in relation to conduct problems [13–16], which is of importance because the aetiology and symptom presentation of a disorder in youth and adults may be different and need specific attention [5, 17, 18] and CU traits in antisocial youth seem to designate a distinct group that might develop into adult psychopathy. Furthermore, early detection might result into early intervention strategies preventing the development of adult psychopathy and antisocial behaviour. However, common to these reviews is that their focus is on the role of CU traits as a subtype of conduct disorder (CD) as proposed by the ADHD and Disruptive Behaviour Disorders Work Group for DSM-V [19] (see Table 1). Furthermore, in adults, subtypes of psychopathy can be distinguished. One of these subtypes is characterized by relatively high scores on deficient affective experience (comparable to CU traits) and low on antisocial behaviour [20]. Therefore, several questions remain: do CU traits represent a discrete or dimensional entity; are CU traits indeed related to CD only; does the psychopathological syndrome of CU traits show sufficient validity when assessed clinically (cf. [21])?Table 1Proposed specifier for callous–unemotional traits in the DSM-V1.Meets full criteria for conduct disorder2.Shows two or more of the following characteristics persistently over at least 12 months and in more than one relationship or setting.The clinician should consider multiple sources of information to determine the presence of these traits, such as whether the person self-reports them as being characteristic of him or herself and if they are reported by others (e.g. parents, other family members, teachers, peers) who have known the person for significant periods of time Lack of remorse or guilt: does not feel bad or guilty when he/she does something wrong (except if expressing remorse when caught and/or facing punishment) Callous-lack of empathy: disregards and is unconcerned about the feelings of others Unconcerned about performance: does not show concern about poor/problematic performance at school, work, or in other important activities. Shallow or deficient affect: does not express feelings or show emotions to others, except in ways that seem shallow or superficial (e.g. emotions are not consistent with actions; can turn emotions “on” or “off” quickly) or when they are used for gain (e.g. to manipulate or intimidate others)http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevisions/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=424By following the set of specific criteria for validation of psychiatric constructs, as proposed by Robins [22] and modified by Faraone [23], the current review aimed to contribute to the existing literature by taking a broader perspective on the nosological status of CU traits by focusing on their validity as a potential classifier for CD, other disorders than just CD and as a stand-alone construct (i.e. a separate DSM-diagnosis). These criteria are: (a) the construct has a consistent pattern of signs and symptoms, (b) the construct is dissociable from other related diagnoses, (c) the construct has a characteristic course and outcome, (d) the construct shows evidence of heritability from family and genetic studies, (e) data from laboratory studies demonstrate neurobiological and neuropsychological correlates of the construct, and (f) the construct shows a characteristic response to treatment. Since the Robins and Guze criteria were published more than 40 years ago, they may seem dated. Yet, they have been labelled as golden standard for establishing diagnostic validity, thus providing opportunity for psychiatric diagnoses to be defined as ‘real entities’ [24]. Recent papers have used these criteria for disruptive behaviour disorders [23, 25]. Yet, a few critical remarks can be made. The Robins and Guze criteria partially overlap with the set of criteria for construct validity, as formulated by Cronbach and Meehl [26], which has been of great importance as well [27]. Cronbach and Meehl [26] place an important emphasis on the nomological network, meaning that a construct needs to ‘function’ according to laws in which the construct occurs, while this criterion is not needed in the Robins and Guze criteria. However, the purpose of our paper was not to either investigate or extend the nomological network regarding CU traits, but to investigate the diagnostic validity of CU traits. Therefore, the Robins and Guze criteria seemed to fit better for our purposes. Another critical remark can be made regarding the fact that the Robins and Guze criteria do not seem to take comorbidity into account, yet comorbidity is the rule rather than the exception in mental disorders [28]. Therefore, it is relevant to clarify the distinctiveness of the relationship between CU traits and ‘established’ mental disorders. To our knowledge, this review is the first to apply these criteria to the construct of CU traits in youth.A PubMed search was performed, focusing on research articles published between 1980 and December 2011, addressing CU traits as well as juvenile psychopathy, and review articles that appeared to be key articles (search terms: juvenile psychopathy and callous unemotional traits). Within the articles that were believed to be relevant, we have searched for additional literature. Studies had to use assessment instruments that quantified psychopathic and/or CU traits and had to have included comparison groups. CU traits were operationalized as those subdimensions of psychopathy which include symptoms such as callousness, shallowness and lack of empathy. This led to an initial 981 publications of which 206 (including 6 reviews) were eligible for this review. Findings are reported primarily in a qualitative manner.Criterion 1: Do CU traits have a consistent pattern of signs and symptoms?The first criterion that must be met in order to consider CU traits as a construct inside or outside CD is that a consistent pattern of signs and symptoms must demarcate it from other disorders and from psychiatric wellness [22, 23]. However, there is no universal agreement with respect to how to best measure CU traits. CU traits seem to be a diagnostic construct that is still in a developmental stage.The construct of CU traits has been developed on the basis of the concept of psychopathy. In the past 20 years, there has been an increasing interest in the concept of juvenile psychopathy and to our knowledge, at least 17 instruments have been developed which aim directly at assessing either psychopathic or CU traits, and which have been used in juvenile populations (see Table 2). The Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version (PCL:YV; [29]) seems to be the first assessment tool that specifically focused on psychopathy in youth. Others followed and the versions for self-report were developed, leading to instruments such as the Antisocial Process Screening Device (APSD; [30]), and the Youth Psychopathic Traits Inventory (YPI; [31]). For reviews, we refer to [16, 32].Table 2Assessment instruments for measuring psychopathic traits in youthFull nameAbbreviationReferenceRaterPsychopathy Checklist: revisedPCL-R[228]Clinician ratedSelf-Report Psychopathy Scale: IISRP-II[229]Self-reportPsychopathy Checklist: Screening VersionPCL:SV[230]Clinician ratedSurvey of Attitudes and Life ExperiencesSALE[231]Self-reportChildhood Psychopathy ScaleCPS[232]Clinician ratedPsychopathy Content ScalePCS[105]Self-reportPsychopathy Screening DevicePSD[233]Self-reportAntisocial Process Screening DeviceAPSD[30]Self-reportTeacher-reportParent-reportYouth Psychopathy traits InventoryYPI[31]Self-reportPsychopathy Checklist: Youth VersionPCL:YV[29]Clinician ratedInventory of Callous–Unemotional traitsICU[53]Self-reportTeacher-reportParent-reportMultidimensional Personality QuestionnaireMPQ[141]Self-reportMinnesota Temperament InventoryMTI[136]Self-reportSocial and Emotional Detachment QuestionnaireSEDQ[74]Parent-reportNEO Psychopathy Resemblance IndexNEO PRI[234]Self-reportFive Factor Model Psychopathy countFFM PP count[54]Self-reportParent-reportPsychopathic Personality Inventory Short-FormPPI-SF[235]Self-reportTrying to fractionate the concept of juvenile psychopathy, factor analyses have been applied on various instruments, mostly the PCL:YV, on the basis of scores obtained in community samples as well as in juvenile offenders. Although two-factor models [33–39], a four-factor model (e.g. [40–43]) and a five-factor model [44] have been proposed as underlying psychopathy with confirmatory factor analyses, a three-factor model seems to fit best (e.g. [44–51]). The three-factor model consists of factors which can be labelled as: (a) sensation seeking behaviour, (b) arrogant/deceptive interpersonal style, and (c) callous–unemotional traits. Discussion remains whether a fourth factor, labelled antisocial-aggressive behaviour, should be added [41, 42, 46].The findings from these factor analytic studies are reasonably consistent in finding a distinct factor including lack of empathy, shallow affect and superficial interpersonal relationships, even though the factors are not always labelled similarly and their content may vary somewhat between different studies. This factor, with time increasingly called callous–unemotional traits, is consistently present in all models. This factor can be assessed reliably as from an age of 4 years [44]. Recently, a promising attempt was made to diagnose CU traits in preschoolers [52].In youth, CU traits were increasingly seen as having incremental validity regarding diagnosing youth with conduct problems [19], which led to the development of the Inventory of Callous–Unemotional traits (ICU) [53], for assessment of CU traits specifically. Validation studies are promising, showing good internal consistency (Cronbach’s α = 0.69–0.83; [54–58] and concurrent validity (r2 = 0.45–0.68 between ICU and APSD, and CPS) [57, 58]. However, other expressions of validity (e.g. temporal stability, interrater reliability) of the ICU specifically have to be established yet.The current proposal to include a specifier for CU traits to conduct disorder in the DSM-5 formulates four criteria, of which two have to be met to assess CU traits (Table 1). For the development of this specifier, we refer to [19]. Internal consistency was shown to be moderate (Cronbach’s α = 0.56), yet many questions remain as it is unknown how well clinical validity is [19]. Thus, it seems that though CU traits as a construct show good ‘face validity’, the consistency of signs and symptoms within and specifically outside CD needs further evaluation.Criterion 2: Are CU traits dissociable from other related diagnoses?A second criterion that must be met in order for CU traits to be considered as a valid nosological construct is its relative distinctiveness from other (related) DSM diagnoses. How often do high CU traits co-occur with CD? Are CU traits significantly more often linked to the presence of CD than to other disorders as ODD, ADHD, and ASD? Can high CU traits exist in the absence of other diagnostic entities, as CD, ODD, ADHD, ASD, personality disorder, mental retardation, and substance abuse (see Table 3)?Table 3Relationship between CU traits and specific diagnosesDiagnosisSupportNo supportConduct disorderCore references: [35, 44, 59]Reviews: [15, 63]Oppositional-defiant disorder[75][59, 74, 76]Personality disorder[236][55, 87–91]Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder[79, 80][81–85, 119]Mental retardation[81, 96–99]Substance abuse[101–105]Autism spectrum disorder[93, 94]Anxiety disorder Self-reported anxiety ↓[106, 107, 112, 113][33, 114] Parent-rated anxiety ↓[108–110] Teacher-rated anxiety ↓[110] Clinician-rated anxiety ↓[81]Mood disorder[116]↓, decreased in the presence of high CU traitsDisruptive behaviour disordersSeveral epidemiologic studies investigated the prevalence of CU traits (see Table 4). CD was found to be present in 2 % of community children [59]. 32–46.1 % of community youth with CD was found to score high on CU traits [59, 60]. In the no CD group, 2.9–7 % scored high on CU traits [59, 60]. Comparable overall conclusions can be drawn from other epidemiological studies [19, 39, 61, 62] as well as a factor analytic study [35]. These studies imply that CU traits show overlap with CD, but are not interchangeable. Because of the upcoming CU traits specifier in the DSM-5, it is important to notice that numerous studies reported on a more pervasive and severe pattern of antisocial behaviour in CD patients with CU traits compared to those without CU traits. For reviews we refer to, e.g. [13, 15, 63], with recent publications confirming these observations [64–73].Table 4Prevalence of CU traitsStudySampleMale (%)CD-only (%)CD + CU (%)CU-only (%)CP + CU (%)CP-only (%)[62]Community51n.i.n.i.7.25.67.9[19]Community51–76n.i.n.i.7–11n.i.Incarderated51–76n.i.12–33n.i.n.i.n.i.[60]Community5732 % of those with CD met criteria for specifier for CU traits7 % of those without CD met criteria for specifier for CU traitsClinic-referred6050 % of those with CD met criteria for specifier for CU traits32 % of those without CD met criteria for specifier for CU traits[61]Community040.5 % reported at least once above 1 SD on CU traits over a 4-year period65.5 % of the group meeting criteria for CD had high CU scores44.3 % of the group with high CU traits met criteria for CD[59]Community–1.10.92.9n.i.n.i.[39]Community49n.i.n.i.3.8n.i.Incarcerated42n.i.n.i.8.9n.i.CD conduct disorder, CP conduct problems, CU callous–unemotional traits, SD standard deviation, n.i. no information givenLess is known about the possibility to use CU traits as a classifier in ODD. On the one hand, correlations between CU traits and ODD, and CD were found to be similar [74]; and CU traits have been described in youth with ODD only [75], suggesting CU traits may indeed be a useful specifier for ODD. On the other hand, CU traits are much more prevalent in CD than ODD [59, 76], making the clinical utility of a specifier in ODD less obvious. Further investigation regarding the relationship between CU traits and ODD specifically seems to be needed.CD and ODD are both frequently comorbid with ADHD, making it relevant to examine the relationship between CU traits and ADHD. It has been argued [77] and demonstrated [78–80] that a subgroup of children with conduct problems and hyperactivity, impulsivity and attention problems (HIA-CP) resemble adult psychopathy. In contrast, several studies could not ascertain the relationship between CU traits and ADHD, when controlling for the presence of conduct problems [81–85].Taken together, the presence of CU traits together with CD seems to lead to a specific syndrome with more severe antisocial behaviour, leading the DSM-5 workgroup to conclude CU traits are a useful specifier for CD. However, there are serious indications that CU traits are also present in youth with either ODD or ADHD without CD, albeit less prevalent, making the clinical utility of a specifier in ODD or ADHD less obvious. Regarding the validity of CU traits as a stand-alone construct, findings are scarce. High CU traits without disruptive behaviour do appear to exist based on several epidemiologic studies.Personality disorderIt has been argued that adult psychopathy is not only related to personality, but also that it is personality [86]. Much research in adult psychopathy has used personality questionnaires for delineating signs and symptoms of psychopathy. Findings show a strong negative relationship between psychopathy and agreeableness (expressing concern about interpersonal relationships and strategies) and conscientiousness (expressing ability to plan, organize, and complete behavioural tasks) [86]. As such, the question is whether CU traits in adolescents and adults are interchangeable with the personality disorders as described in DSM-IV-TR.Several studies have investigated the relationship between CU traits and personality traits. These found an inverse association between CU traits with both agreeableness and conscientiousness [55, 87–89]. Furthermore, CU traits were found to be negatively associated with stress reaction (expressing reaction to distress, anxiety) and positively associated to aggression (expressing irritability, aggression) [90], and that CU traits in youth were not specifically related to narcissism [91]. Thus, these studies suggest CU traits to be related to certain personality dimensions/traits that can be apparent before the age of 18 years. However, none of these studies supports CU traits to be seen as equal to personality disorders.Since personality disorders have their onset mostly in adolescence, and persist into adulthood [92], a next question is whether CU traits are predictors of adult personality disorders. However, we could not find any studies addressing this issue.Autism spectrum disorder and mental retardationBecause autism spectrum disorder (ASD) and mental retardation are both related to lower levels of empathy and self-reflection, it is possible that both are related to higher levels of CU traits. In youth with ASD, it was found that the correlation between severity of CU traits and ASD traits was extremely low, and callous antisocial behaviour did not appear to result from those cognitive deficits that are core to autistic disorders, such as ‘mindblindness’ and executive dysfunction [93]. Furthermore, boys with conduct problems and high CU traits were found to have dysfunctional affective empathy, but not cognitive empathy. The contrary was found in boys with ASD [94, 95]. Less is known about the relationship between intelligence (IQ) and CU traits. Some studies report no relationship [79, 96, 97]. Others report that youth with conduct problems and CU traits have a higher IQ [98] or in contrast a lower IQ [99] compared to youth with conduct problems without CU traits. Recently, CU traits were related to poor reading comprehension when controlling for IQ [79, 100]. These results suggest that autism and mental retardation are probably not related to CU traits, although both might hypothetically influence the phenotypic expression of CU traits.Substance abuseAlthough the presence of psychopathic traits in substance-abusing adolescents is related to a higher level of alcohol- and drugs-related problems, there are no indications that CU traits in youth are the result of alcohol or drug abuse [101–105].Anxiety and mood disordersAs CU traits are associated with shallow affect and low fearfulness, anxiety was investigated in ten studies, of which seven controlled for conduct problems [81, 106–111]. CU traits mostly show a significant inverse relationship with subjective ratings of anxiety, either self-, parent-, teacher- or clinician reported [106–113], although this might account only for those children that perceived low levels of parental warmth/involvement [109]. Nevertheless, these correlations are not always found [33, 81, 114]. Mood disorders have been investigated scarcely. In a long-term follow-up study of about 10 years, mood problems in childhood were found to be predictive for CU traits in adulthood [115]. A recent study [116] investigated the relationship between CU traits and suicidality, and found no relationship in boys but an inverse relationship in girls, implying a protective role for CU traits. However, this latter study did not control for either conduct problems or CD. Therefore, there is insufficient information to draw conclusions regarding the relationship between CU traits and mood disorders.Criterion 3: Do CU traits have a characteristic course and outcome?A third criterion for CU traits to meet the standards for a valid disorder is that they have a characteristic, and therefore predictable, course and outcome. This means that assessment of the diagnosis should lead to a clear prognosis. Especially important is the question: when CU traits are a subtype of CD, how strong do CU+ and CU− forms of CD differentiate from each other in external characteristics such as course and prognosis (see Table 5)?Table 5Characteristic course and outcome when CU traits are present in youth with conduct problemsFollow-up studiesResultSupportNo supportShort-term (0–4 years)Social non-conformity ↑Days detained ↑Antisocial behaviour ↑Symptoms of psychopathology ↑[44, 112, 120, 124]Substance use ↑[122]Proactive aggression ↑[119, [118]; non-significantGeneral and violent recidivism ↑[123] PCL:YV[117, 123] APSDDelinquency ↑[121]Seriousness charges ↑[110]Impairment ↑[61]Stability of CU traits[115, 130, 134, 137][140]Long-term (4–12 years)Severeness and chronicity of antisocial behaviour and delinquency ↑[127–129]Affiliation with deviant peers ↑[125, 126]CU traits show long-term stability[52, 132, 135, 136, 139][135], community twin sample; [52, 133], community sample; ↑, increased in the presence of high CU traits; ↓, decreased in the presence of high CU traitsBoth short-term studies (up to 4 years) [44, 61, 110, 112, 117–124] and long-term studies (4–15 years) [115, 125–129] found CU traits to be predictive of more problematic behaviour. Studies investigating the long-term stability of CU traits showed this to be high over longer periods of time (i.e. 1 up to 53 years) [52, 115, 130–139]. Only a short-term study found stability to be low [140]. However, findings are comparable when no correction for conduct problems was made [110, 115, 128] and when a correction was made [119–121, 123, 126, 127], indicating the presence of CU traits quite robustly predicting a poorer outcome over and above the presence of conduct problems. The reviewed studies provide no information regarding CU traits as a stand-alone construct.Criterion 4: Do CU traits show evidence of heritability from family and genetic studies?The next criterion to be met is whether it is possible to find evidence for a heritable nature of CU traits, supporting the hypothesis that CU traits are a valid entity, which can be delineated from environmentally caused psychopathology.Genetic influencesGenetic factors contribute importantly to the expression of CU traits [131, 135, 141–146], although environmental factors play a small-to-moderate role as well [131, 135, 142, 143, 145, 147] (see Table 6). Overlap with conduct problems is large, though not complete [145], indicating some room for unique genetic and environmental risk factors. High stability of CU traits seems to be related to high genetic influence [131, 135, 148], while antisocial behaviour seems to be more strongly related to unique environmental influences [142, 146, 147].Table 6Genetic influences on CU traitsReferenceNAge (years)Male (%)MeasureGenetic influences (variance; %)Shared environmental influences (variance; %)Non-shared environmental influences (variance; %)Genetic stability (variance; %)[135, 141]1,252 twinsSame group at 17 and at 24 years46MPQ17 yr: 4824 yr: 4217 yr: 5224 yr: 5858[148]9,462 twinsSame group at 7, 9 and 12 years47.33 items APSD + 4 items SDQ78a (boys)0a (girls)1a (boys)75a (girls)2a (boys)25a (girls)[131]1,467 twinsSame group at 16 and at 1940YPI82[142]2,198 twins16–1747.6YPI43057[143]39816–18100MTI4258[144]832 twins1,056 probands6–8n.i.3 items APSD + 4 items SDQ67627[145]3,196 twins748.0Idem67 (boys)48 (girls) 4 (boys)20 (girls)29 (boys)32 (girls)[146]464 twins314 probands9n.i.Idem + 2 items ICU750[147]4.508 twinsSame group at 7 and at 12n.i.3 items APSD + 4 items SDQ7 yr/P: 6312 yr/P: 817 yr/T: 7112 yr/T: 567 yr/P: 2712 yr/P: 237 yr/T: 3112 yr/T: 40MPQ Minnesota Personality Questionnaire [141], YPI Youth Psychopathic Traits Inventory [31], MTI Minnesota Temperament Inventory [136], APSD Antisocial Process Screening Device [30], SDQ Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire [237], Yr year, P parent rating, T teacher ratingaStandardized estimates when stability over time was highIn recent studies, focus has not only been directed on phenotypes in twin studies, but also on molecular genetic underpinnings of CU traits as well. Up till now, the few genetic studies at a molecular level implicate multigenetic influences and a gene by environment interaction [149–151]. Possible positive associations have been described for gene variants that affect monoamino oxidase A (MAO-A), catechol-O-methyltransferase (COMT) [150], and serotonin transporter (5HTT) [150, 151]. None of these molecular genetic studies investigated CU traits outside either conduct problems or CD, making it uncertain whether the genetic findings are specific for CU or more broadly associated with disruptive behaviour disorders (DBDs).Environmental influencesSocial and biological environmental factors play a small-to-moderate role as well (see Table 7). Parenting style is found to be negatively related to later developing CU traits [62, 133, 152], as well as positive parenting was found to be related to decreased CU traits [130, 153]. Furthermore, maternal CU traits, resulting in parental hostility and parenting dysfunction, play an important role in the intergenerational continuity of maternal CU traits [152]. In contrast, others suggested that an ineffective parenting style is unrelated to the presence of callousness [154], or only for children with low levels of CU traits [108, 155–157]. Also it is suggested that high CU traits may lead to reduced monitoring behaviours of parents [121], increased parenting stress [158], decreased eye contact towards mothers [159], and to decreased parental involvement towards boys [130]. Furthermore, social economic status is generally found to be lower in children scoring high on CU traits [62, 115, 133, 160, 161]. Interestingly, prenatal risk factors such as maternal problems [62] and tobacco use [115] were found to be a significant predictor for CU traits as well. Finally, several studies indicate that traumatisation [109, 162–164], as well as disorganized attachment [165], and early institutional deprivation [166] can be related to CU traits as well. This leads to the overall impression that the role of environmental influences is present albeit somewhat inconsistent, which might be due to the correlational nature of these studies. Furthermore, only a few studies controlled statistically for conduct problems [114, 115, 152, 153], and none for CD, making it uncertain whether the findings are completely accounted for by the presence of CU traits instead of conduct problems more generally. Nevertheless, social and biological environmental influences might play a role in CU traits co-occurring with CD. Unknown is the role of the environment when CU traits exist independently of other psychiatric disorders.Table 7Correlational environmental studiesType of environmental influenceSupportNo supportParenting style (−)[62, 130, 133, 152, 153, 165, 166][108, 121, 154–159]SES (−)[62, 115, 133, 160, 161]Physical traumatization (+)[109, 162–164]Prenatal risk (+)[62] Prenatal maternal problems[115] Exposure to cigarette smoke−, inverse correlation with CU traits; +, positive correlation with CU traitsCriterion 5: Do CU traits have specific and differentiating neurobiological and neuropsychological correlates?The fifth criterion requires the presence of specific neurobiological correlates of a disorder [23]. Psychological tests, when shown to be reliable and reproducible, may also be considered laboratory studies in this context [22]. The literature on CU traits is too extensive to provide a detailed review. Nevertheless, we will provide a comprehensive summary (see Table 8).Table 8Neurobiological and neuropsychological studies on CU traitsFocusSupportNo supportNeurobiological markersfMRI:Amgdala ↓vmPFC ↓[167–169][170] ?sMRI: Amygdala =[171]Cortisol ↓[76, 115, 173][172] ?Testosteron =[173]Skin Conductance ↓[57, 175, 177, 178]Heart rate ↓[174, 176][52] PreschoolersProsocial reasoningProsocial reasoning ↓[179–182][161, 190, 191] ?Cognitive, but not affective empathy improves during growth[94, 95, 189]Egoistic functioning and acceptance of social deviant behaviour[183–185]Positive labelling of aggression and acceptance of social deviant behaviour[186–188]Reward sensitivityReward sensitivity ↑Impulse inhibition ↓Punishment avoidance ↓[81, 161, 184, 192, 193]Emotional reactivityEmotional reactivity ↓[52, 56, 164, 194]Self-reported arousal ↓[83][195]Emotion recognitionRecognition of fear ↓[196–204]Recognition of sadness ↓[95, 196, 202, 203, 205, 206]↑, increased in the presence of high CU traits; ↓, decreased in the presence of high CU traits, =, no differences between high CU traits and control; ?, results inconsistentNeurobiological markersStudies on neurobiological markers are important to investigate whether it is possible to find neurobiological underpinnings for CU traits. Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies suggest impaired functioning of the amygdala [167, 168] and of the ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) [169], as well as weaker functional connectivity between these two brain areas [168] in youth with conduct problems and CU traits, compared to healthy controls. The only fMRI study controlling for CD could not detect correlations with CU traits [170]. However, this study used only pictures of angry, sad and neutral, but not fearful faces. As discussed below, decreased recognition of fearful faces is most strongly related to CU traits, compared to other types of faces. Furthermore, using structural MRI in a comparison between normal control children with children scoring high on conduct problems and CU traits increased grey matter in several brain areas, specifically in the PFC, has been found, but not in the amygdala [171].As CU traits are associated with decreased anxiety, and cortisol levels are associated with anxiety levels, it is expected that increased CU traits correlate with decreased cortisol levels. One study could not detect this relationship, however probably because the level of CU traits was still low in the CU traits group [172]. In contrast, three studies did find blunted [76] or decreased baseline [115, 173] cortisol levels to correlate with CU traits.Electrophysiological studies are important because CU traits are thought to relate to lower physiological arousal. Indeed, these studies show lower physiologic responsiveness in youth with CU traits, compared to youth without these traits, specifically in reaction to distress, and provocation [57, 120, 124, 174–178], although in preschoolers with high CU traits, higher overall physiological arousal was found [52].Three studies controlled for CD [115, 170, 174], one for ODD [52], and several others for conduct problems [57, 76, 172, 173, 176–178]. Therefore, CU traits appear specifically related to the above-mentioned neurobiological abnormalities. Nevertheless, since no studies have examined neurobiological abnormalities in individuals with CU traits without any psychiatric disorders, it is difficult to infer conclusions about the relationship between neurobiological markers and CU traits outside CD.Prosocial reasoningStudies on prosocial reasoning frequently use stories about hypothetical problematic social situations in which one has to solve moral dilemmas. Three studies specifically controlled for CD [94, 95, 179]. Less prosocial reasoning was found in youth with CD-high CU than in youth with CD-low CU and normal controls [179], while cognitive functioning seems to be unimpaired [94, 95]. Except for two [180, 181], the following studies controlled for conduct problems. Less prosocial reasoning was found as well in youth with conduct problems and high CU traits than in those with low CU traits [180–182], as well as more egoistically functioning, more problems in affective perspective taking, accepting more social deviant behaviour [183–185], and specifically aggression [186–188]. Furthermore, the presence of conduct problems together with CU traits has been associated with deficits in affective empathy, specifically for boys at different ages [95, 189], and improvement of cognitive empathy through the pubertal years [189]. A few studies seemed to find contradictory results, such as less reactivity and hostility [161], decreased expectations regarding the use of aggression [190], and more proactive behaviour [191] in the presence of high CU traits. However, these findings [161, 190, 191] can be explained by an increased orientation towards achieving ones goals. Thus, the reviewed studies support the notion of decreased affective prosocial reasoning in relation to increased CU traits over and above the relation of affective prosocial reasoning to conduct problems. However, virtually no information on prosocial reasoning is available regarding CU traits outside CD.Reward sensitivityFindings on emotion processing have focussed on inhibition deficits, anxiety and response-to-distress as can be shown by psychological tests. These studies suggest a response modulation deficit in which a greater reward sensitivity, accompanied with decreased impulse inhibition and punishment avoidance play an important role when CU traits are high in youth with conduct problems [81, 161, 184, 192, 193]. These studies controlled for conduct problems, although not for CD, suggesting abnormal reward sensitivity is related to the presence of CU traits over and above the presence of conduct problems. We found no studies regarding CU traits outside conduct problems.Emotional reactivityEmotional reactivity refers to the extent in which participants react to psychological discomfort. Four studies in youth with conduct problems [52, 56, 164, 194], with one controlling for CD [194], and one for ODD [52], suggest that CU traits are associated with lowered emotional reactivity in laboratory tests. In contrast, CU traits were not found to be associated with self-reported arousal in a community sample [195], although in a later study, based on the same community sample, high CU traits correlated with decreased self-reported arousal ratings to unpleasant pictures [83]. Thus, CU traits seem to be related to decreased emotional responsiveness, most likely over and above the presence of conduct problems.Emotion recognitionIn the presence of CU traits, the most consistent findings are impaired recognition of fearful faces in community youth [196–200], clinic referred youth [201], and youth with conduct problems [202, 203]. Directing attention to the eyes seems to improve facial emotion recognition [197, 198]. Furthermore, adolescents with conduct problems and high CU traits showed consistent impairments in eye contact to their parents, while higher levels of eye contact between fathers and their sons were associated with better fear recognition [204]. Findings on recognition of sadness are less consistent [95, 196, 202, 203, 205, 206]. All, but two studies [196, 200] controlled for conduct problems, and three for CD specifically [95, 203, 205], indicating that abnormal emotion recognition seems robustly associated with CU traits over and above the presence of abnormal emotion recognition in relation to conduct problems. Again, we found no studies regarding emotion recognition in CU traits outside conduct problems.Criterion 6: Do CU traits show a characteristic treatment response?Response to treatment is the last criterion when viewing the validity of a diagnosis. Accurate diagnosis is important, because it determines the success of treatment. Vice versa, the need for a specific treatment for a specific disorder confirms its validity. To date, there seem to be only few studies that focused on improving treatment response in youth with CU traits (see Table 9).Table 9Treatment response in youth with conduct problems moderated by the presence of CU traitsReferenceNAge (years)% maleDiagnosisMeasureTreatment typeClinical improvement on behaviourLength of treatmentTreatment complianceFollow-up after treatment[208]24812–14100Conduct problemsPCL:YVResidential treatment for adjudicated youth with severe conduct problemsHigh CU = low CU[214]6911–1760Conduct problemsAPSDmCPSJuvenile diversion programProgram failure → high CU &gt; low CURearrest at 1 year → high CU &gt; low CU[209]706–1334.3ODD or CD and ADHD (77.1 %)No Dx (22.9 %)APSDSummer treatment programSocial skills and problem solving → high CU &lt; low CUNegative behaviours in time-out → high CU &lt; low CU[210]564–8n.i.ODD (and conduct probems; and secondary ADHD)APSDParent trainingDisciplinary measures → high CU &lt; low CUTreatment sessions → high CU &gt; low CUOutcome at 6 months after treatment → high CU &lt; low CU[211]564–8n.i.ODD (and conduct probems; and secondary ADHD)APSDParent trainingIn stable-high CU group → most severe conduct problems at 6 months[212]1776–11ODD or CD (and ADHD)APSDModular treatment at (1) outpatient clinic, (2) at home and school and (3) treatment as usualHigh CU = low CUHigh CU = low CU[213]386–1473.7ODD/CDAPSDICU6-month therapeutic program including cognitive behavior programsHigh CU &lt; low CU[215]6415–19100Substance abusePCL:YVSubstance abuse program for adjudicated adolescentsHigh CU &lt; low CUHigh CU &lt; low CURearrest rate → high CU &gt; low CU (p &lt; .10)[216]8511–18100Conduct problemsPCL:YVAPSDmCPSResidential treatment for adjudicated youthPhysical incidents → High CU &gt; low CU(APSD; mCPS)Back to lower level of treatment → high CU &gt; low CU (mCPS)Days of treatment to reach next level → high CU &gt; low CU (mCPS)high CU = low CU (APSD)[217]1007–1766ODD or CD (68 %)Other Dx (32 %)APSDPsychiatric hospitalizationLength of treatment → high CU &gt; low CU[207]377–1378.4ADHD/ODD (43.2 %)ADHD/CD (56.8 %)APSDRCT:BT + Placebo vs. BT + MPHBT + Placebo → high CU &lt; low CUBT + MPH → high CU = low CUCompliance → high CU &lt; low CU (marginally)RCT randomized controlled trial, BT behaviour therapy, MPH methylphenidate, ADHD attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, CD conduct disorder, Dx diagnosis, ODD oppositional-defiant disorder, n.i. no information given, PCL:YV Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version [29], APSD Antisocial Process Screening Device [30], mCPS modified Child Psychopathy Scale [232]We found one study [207] applying a placebo-controlled treatment design. In this study, the response to behaviour modification with and without methylphenidate was examined. Boys with ADHD, conduct problems and high CU traits did not improve as much with behavioural therapy as those with low CU traits. However, when treated with methylphenidate, these differences largely disappeared, suggesting a beneficial effect of methylphenidate.Other studies described treatment effects in open designs, of which seven explicitly controlled for conduct problems [207–213] or CD and ODD [207, 208, 211, 212]. Except two [208, 212], most open studies suggest a negative effect of CU traits, over and above conduct problems, on either treatment progress, outcome or follow-up [208–210, 213–217]. Data are lacking on treatment effect of CU traits in the presence of other disorders than DBDs.Summary and conclusionThis review examined the nosological status of CU traits by focusing on their validity in children and adolescents not only as a subtype of conduct disorder, but also as a potential classifier for other disorders or as a stand-alone construct. CU traits may moderate the treatment of disruptive behaviour disorders and the categorization of patients with these traits could be helpful in developing adequate therapeutic interventions. This topic was addressed by applying criteria for validation of psychiatric diagnoses, as formulated by Robins and Guze [22], and modified by Faraone [23].Based on the reviewed studies, we conclude that the presence of CU traits can be assessed reliably as from school age, with preliminary data suggesting reliable assessment at preschool age as well. Although assessment measures are still in development, a consistent pattern of signs and symptoms is found demarcating it from other disorders. Furthermore, CU traits are associated with a distinct pattern of conduct problems in CD, while there are indications that the same might be true for ODD and ADHD. That is, the presence of CU traits is related to a more aggressive and more pervasive kind of conduct problems. Similarly, CU traits can be distinguished from other psychiatric diagnoses in juveniles, such as autism spectrum disorder, mental retardation, personality disorder, substance abuse, and mood and anxiety disorders. In addition, there is a characteristic course and outcome: the presence of CU traits in youth with disruptive behaviour is increasingly stable with the increase of age and associated with increased levels of conduct problems, delinquency, reoffense and/or substance use over longer periods of time from childhood up to adulthood. Moreover, as antisocial behaviour decreases with aging, CU traits persist through life. In twin studies, genetic influences are shown to account for 43–81 % of CU traits. Furthermore, social and biological environmental influences such as poor parenting and traumatisation were found to cause a detrimental effect. Neurobiological and neuropsychological correlations can be found, in which findings indicate decreased prosocial reasoning, decreased responsiveness to distress cues, and decreased recognition of fearful and perhaps sad faces in youth with CU traits. Furthermore, in youth with conduct problems and high CU traits biological differences can be detected as well, such as impaired amygdala functioning, impaired functioning of the vmPFC, impaired connectivity between these two brain areas, as well as decreased cortisol levels and physiological arousal. Finally, treatment requires specific attention in the presence of CU traits: conduct problems are more severe at the start of the treatment, response to behavioural treatment is worse, and a more intensive treatment is required before improvement can be observed. Thus, there is clear supportive evidence for CU traits as a valid subtype of CD. Hence, we believe that CU traits are a valid and viable sub diagnosis, which give the opportunity to make an important differentiation especially in different kinds of conduct problems and antisocial behaviour. Moreover, given that the majority of studies were conducted in youth with conduct problems (i.e. ODD and CD grouped together) and several studies indicate that CU traits and ODD and to a lesser extent ADHD seem to be correlated as well, we believe CU traits may be a useful specifier for DBDs in general. No compelling evidence exists for CU traits as useful specifier in other psychiatric axis I and II disorders. Furthermore, although many of the above studies controlled for the presence of conduct problems, it still is difficult to mark CU traits as a stand-alone construct. Therefore, the question remains whether CU traits outside conduct problems constitute a clinical problem or not.Future researchAs this review covers a broad range of topics, related to the validity of CU traits, many issues for further research emerge. However, as others have pointed out the importance of further research to determine how the criteria for CU traits can be incorporated in the DSM in a valid and useful way [218, 219], in this paper we will specifically address points for future research concerning the validity of CU traits for DBDs in general and as a stand-alone construct.This review shows that much research has been done in children and adolescents which supports the importance of distinguishing CU traits as an important symptom cluster in addition to conduct problems. We found many studies that combined youth with ODD and youth with CD into a single study group when investigating the moderating role of CU traits, mostly because ODD and CD are reasoned to reflect a single conduct domain (e.g. [136]). Nevertheless, there is still discussion whether these diagnoses represent the same underlying entity, and that ODD symptoms should not be seen as a milder, earlier presentation of CD [220]. Therefore, it is important to further investigate the relationship between CU traits and ODD specifically.This leads us to another important issue. In the vast body of literature, we found only five studies, explicitly reporting on CU traits when scoring low on conduct problems [61, 75, 126, 127, 161]. As the findings from these studies are contradicting, and as the prevalence of CU traits in community samples seems to be relatively high, it seems to be important to direct further research on CU traits outside CD, and in the absence of a disruptive disorder diagnosis. Thus, the relevance of CU traits over and beyond either CD and ODD will become much clearer. Through gathering clearer epidemiologic data, we might improve our knowledge about the overall prevalence of CU traits, identify aetiologic factors, and help to estimate the need for services [221].Further research on the conceptualization of CU traits seems needed as well. Three issues seem to need further attention specifically. First, increased consensus about diagnostic criteria is needed. In this review, we encountered many different conceptualizations of CU traits. However, the proposal of Frick and Moffitt [19] to include CU traits as a specifier to the diagnosis of CD in de the upcoming DSM-5 is especially meaningful for this issue. Second, as there are indications for specific differences between boys and girls regarding either psychopathic or CU traits (e.g. [103, 222–224], gender issues seem to need more attention as well. Third, as Hong Kong children were found to have higher scores on CU traits than United States children [45], cultural issues might play an important role as well. Hence, it is important to invest in specification of diagnostic criteria, which take gender and cultural differences into account.Effective treatment in youth could dramatically reduce violent incidents and victim injury [225]. Although promising results have been shown with interventions that aim at improving prosocial behaviour using positive reinforcement, either by parent training, training of individual social abilities, or medication, still there is a need for further randomized controlled treatment trials in youth with conduct problems and CU traits regarding short-term as well as long-term treatment effects. Also research seems to be warranted on the question whether specific treatment is needed in the presence of CU traits outside conduct problems.Then there is the topic that, although several theories about developmental pathways regarding psychopathy and CU traits have been proposed [2, 164, 226], the ultimate causes in terms of gene-environmental interplay as well as (deviancies in) brain development have to be unravelled. This leads to several questions, such as whether it is possible to extract candidate genes for further genetic research, while new types of genetic research, such as imaging genetic work, seem to be promising in clarifying the role of specific endophenotypes [9]. However, as parenting practices are among the most powerful predictors of later outcomes in children and constitute opportunities for interventions [227], a next question is whether specific parenting practices at young age might decrease the further development of CU traits either in- and outside CD. Finally, the MRI studies raise further questions about the underpinnings of CU traits. Although it is hypothesized that there is a distinct brain development in boys with callous–unemotional conduct problems [171], this needs further exploration.This review has focused on the diagnostic validity of CU traits in- and outside CD. It becomes clear that CU traits have gained increasing attention in the past years, and our understanding on this topic increases steadily. However, much research is needed on the prevalence, aetiology, and need for diagnosis and treatment of CU traits outside CD, to improve our understanding of CU traits as a cross-disorders construct and possibly as a stand-alone construct as well.Open AccessThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.References1.FrickPJEllisMCallous–unemotional traits and subtypes of conduct disorderClin Child Fam Psychol Rev1999214916810.1023/A:1021803005547112270722.SalekinRTPsychopathy and therapeutic pessimism. Clinical lore or clinical reality?Clin Psychol Rev2002227911210.1016/S0272-7358(01)00083-6117935793.StickleTRFrickPJDevelopmental pathways to severe antisocial behavior: interventions for youth with callous/unemotional traitsExpert Rev Neurother2002251152210.1586/14737175.2.4.511198109484.HerpertzSCSassHEmotional deficiency and psychopathyBehav Sci Law20001856758010.1002/1099-0798(200010)18:5&lt;567::AID-BSL410&gt;3.0.CO;2-8111139625.SalekinRTFrickPJPsychopathy in children and adolescents: the need for a developmental perspectiveJ Abnorm Child Psychol20053340340910.1007/s10802-005-5722-2161189886.CleckleyHMThe mask of sanity1988St. LouisMosby7.PatrickCJFowlesDCKruegerRFTriarchic conceptualization of psychopathy: developmental origins of disinhibition, boldness, and meannessDev Psychopathol20092191393810.1017/S0954579409000492195838908.PatrickCJSalekinRTLynamDRConceptualizing the psychopathic personality: disinhibited, bold, or just plain mean?Handbook of child &amp; adolescent psychopathy2010New YorkThe Guilford Press15489.JonesAPVidingEPsychopathic traits in young childrenNeth J Psychol20076311712510.FrickPJHervéHYuilleJCUsing the construct of psychopathy to understand antisocial and violent youthThe psychopath: theory, research and practice2007New JerseyLawrence Erlbaum Associates11.JohnstoneLCookeDJPsychopathic-like traits in childhood: conceptual and measurement concernsBehav Sci Law20042210312510.1002/bsl.5771496388312.RutterMCommentary: What is the meaning and utility of the psychopathy concept?J Abnorm Child Psychol20053349950310.1007/s10802-005-5730-21611899513.EdensJFSkeemJLCruiseKRCauffmanEAssessment of “juvenile psychopathy” and its association with violence: a critical reviewBehav Sci Law200119538010.1002/bsl.4251124168114.FrickPJMarseeMAPatrickCJPsychopathy and developmental pathways to antisocial behaviorHandbook of psychopathy2006New YorkGuilford35337515.FrickPJWhiteSFResearch review: the importance of callous–unemotional traits for developmental models of aggressive and antisocial behaviorJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20084935937510.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01862.x1822134516.KotlerJSMcMahonRJChild psychopathy: theories, measurement, and relations with the development and persistence of conduct problemsClin Child Fam Psychol Rev2005829132510.1007/s10567-005-8810-51636225717.HartSDWattKAVincentGMCommentary on Seagrave and Grisso: impressions of the state of the artLaw Hum Behav20022624124510.1023/A:10146482276881198530018.SeagraveDGrissoTAdolescent development and the measurement of juvenile psychopathyLaw Hum Behav20022621923910.1023/A:10146961108501198529919.Frick PJ, Moffitt TE (2010) A proposal to the DSM-V childhood disorders and the ADHD and disruptive behavior disorders work groups to include a specifier to the diagnosis of conduct disorder based on the presence of callous–unemotional traits. American Psychiatric Association, Washington, DC. http://www.dsm5.org/Proposed%20Revision%20Attachments/Proposal%20for%20Callous%20and%20Unemotional%20Specifier%20of%20Conduct%20Disorder.pdf20.Coid J, Freestone M, Ullrich S (2011) Subtypes of psychopathy in the British household population: findings from the national household survey of psychiatric morbidity. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol Epidemiol. doi:10.1007/s00127-011-0395-321.RutterMChild psychiatric diagnosis and classification: concepts, findings, challenges and potentialJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20115264766010.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02367.x2143491422.RobinsEGuzeSBEstablishment of diagnostic validity in psychiatric illness: its application to schizophreniaAm J Psychiatry1970126983987540956923.FaraoneSVThe scientific foundation for understanding attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder as a valid psychiatric disorderEur Child Adolesc Psychiatry20051411010.1007/s00787-005-0429-z1575651024.AndreasenNCThe validation of psychiatric diagnosis: new models and approachesAm J Psychiatry1995152161162784034625.HofvanderBOssowskiDLundstromSAnckarsaterHContinuity of aggressive antisocial behavior from childhood to adulthood: the question of phenotype definitionInt J Law Psychiatry20093222423410.1016/j.ijlp.2009.04.0041942810926.CronbachLJMeehlPEConstruct validity in psychological testsPsychol Bull19555228130210.1037/h00409571324589627.StraussMEIntroduction to the special section on construct validity of psychological tests: 50 years after Cronbach and Meehl (1955)Psychol Assess20051739510.1037/1040-3590.17.4.3951639300428.KruegerRFThe structure of common mental disordersArch Gen Psychiatry19995692192610.1001/archpsyc.56.10.9211053063429.ForthAEKossonDSHareRDThe Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version2003TorontoMulti-Health Systems30.FrickPJHareRDThe antisocial process screening device2001TorontoMulti-Health Systems31.AndershedHKerrMStattinHKevanderSBlaauwESheridanLPsychopathic traits in non-referred youths: initial test of a new assessment toolPsychopaths—current international perspectives2002Den HaagElsevier13115832.SharpCKineSThe assessment of juvenile psychopathy: strengths and weaknesses of currently used questionnaire measuresChild Adolesc Ment Health200813859510.1111/j.1475-3588.2008.00483.x33.BrandtJRKennedyWAPatrickCJCurtinJJAssessment of psychopathy in a population of incarcerated adolescent offendersPsychol Assess1997942943510.1037/1040-3590.9.4.42934.FrickPJCallous–unemotional traits and conduct problems: a two-factor model of psychopathy in childrenIssues Criminol Leg Psychol199524475135.FrickPJBodinSDBarryCTPsychopathic traits and conduct problems in community and clinic-referred samples of children: further development of the psychopathy screening devicePsychol Assess20001238239310.1037/1040-3590.12.4.3821114710536.LexcenFJVincentGMGrissoTValidity and structure of a self-report measure of youth psychopathyBehav Sci Law200422698410.1002/bsl.5781496388137.MurrieDCMarcusDKDouglasKSLeeZSalekinRTVincentGYouth with psychopathy features are not a discrete class: a taxometric analysisJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20074871472310.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01734.x1759315238.PenneySRMorettiMMSilvaKSStructural validity of the MACI psychopathy and narcissism scales: evidence of multidimensionality and implications for use in research and screeningJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20083742243310.1080/153744108019558881847077839.ScholteEMStoutjesdijkROudheusdenMALodewijksHPloegJDScreening of egocentric and unemotional characteristics in incarcerated and community childrenInt J Law Psychiatry20103316417010.1016/j.ijlp.2010.03.0062038186640.NeumannCSKossonDSForthAEHareRDFactor structure of the Hare Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version (PCL: YV) in incarcerated adolescentsPsychol Assess20061814215410.1037/1040-3590.18.2.1421676859041.PardiniDObradovicJLoeberRInterpersonal callousness, hyperactivity/impulsivity, inattention, and conduct problems as precursors to delinquency persistence in boys: a comparison of three grade-based cohortsJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol200635465910.1207/s15374424jccp3501_51639030242.SalekinRTBrannenDNZalotAALeisticoAMNeumannCSFactor structure of psychopathy in youth: testing the applicability of the new four factor modelCrim Justice Behav20063313515710.1177/009385480528441643.SeveckeKPukropRKossonDSKrischerMKFactor structure of the Hare Psychopathy Checklist: Youth version in German female and male detainees and community adolescentsPsychol Assess200921455610.1037/a00150321929076544.DaddsMRFraserJFrostAHawesDJDisentangling the underlying dimensions of psychopathy and conduct problems in childhood: a community studyJ Consult Clin Psychol20057340041010.1037/0022-006X.73.3.4001598213845.FungALGaoYRaineAThe utility of the child and adolescent psychopathy construct in Hong Kong, ChinaJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol2010391341402039080546.JonesSCauffmanEMillerJDMulveyEInvestigating different factor structures of the Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version: confirmatory factor analytic findingsPsychol Assess200618334810.1037/1040-3590.18.1.331659481047.KossonDSCyterskiTDSteuerwaldBLNeumannCSWalker-MatthewsSThe reliability and validity of the Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version (PCL:YV) in nonincarcerated adolescent malesPsychol Assess2002149710910.1037/1040-3590.14.1.971191105248.VäforsFMRuchkinVKoposovRAfKBAntisocial process screening device: validation on a Russian sample of juvenile delinquents with the emphasis on the role of personality and parental rearingInt J Law Psychiatry20083143844610.1016/j.ijlp.2008.08.0031879053649.VeenVCStevensGWAndershedHRaaijmakersQADoreleijersTAVolleberghWACross-ethnic generalizability of the three-factor model of psychopathy: The Youth Psychopathic Traits Inventory in an incarcerated sample of native Dutch and Moroccan immigrant boysInt J Law Psychiatry20113412713010.1016/j.ijlp.2011.02.0072144411450.VitaccoMJRogersRNeumannCSThe antisocial process screening device: an examination of its construct and criterion-related validityAssess20031014315010.1177/107319110301000200551.VitaccoMJNeumannCSCaldwellMFLeisticoAMRybroekGJTesting factor models of the Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version and their association with instrumental aggressionJ Pers Assess200687748310.1207/s15327752jpa8701_061685678852.WilloughbyMTWaschbuschDAMooreGAPropperCBUsing the ASEBA to screen for callous unemotional traits in early childhood: factor structure, temporal stability, and utilityJ Psychopathol Behav Assess201133193010.1007/s10862-010-9195-42148364753.FrickPJThe inventory of callous–unemotional traits2004New OrleansUniversity of New Orleans54.DecuyperMClercqBBolleMFruytFValidation of FFM PD counts for screening personality pathology and psychopathy in adolescenceJ Pers Disord20092358760510.1521/pedi.2009.23.6.5872000117755.EssauCASasagawaSFrickPJCallous–unemotional traits in a community sample of adolescentsAssessment20061345446910.1177/10731911062873541705091556.KimonisERFrickPJMuñozLCAucoinKJCan a laboratory measure of emotional processing enhance the statistical prediction of aggression and delinquency in detained adolescents with callous–unemotional traits?J Abnorm Child Psychol20073577378510.1007/s10802-007-9136-11751078857.KimonisERFrickPJSkeemJLMarseeMACruiseKMunozLCAucoinKJMorrisASAssessing callous–unemotional traits in adolescent offenders: validation of the Inventory of Callous–Unemotional TraitsInt J Law Psychiatry20083124125210.1016/j.ijlp.2008.04.0021851431558.RooseABijttebierPDecoeneSClaesLFrickPJAssessing the affective features of psychopathy in adolescence: a further validation of the inventory of callous and unemotional traitsAssessment201017445710.1177/10731911093441531979732659.RoweRMaughanBMoranPFordTBriskmanJGoodmanRThe role of callous and unemotional traits in the diagnosis of conduct disorderJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20105168869510.1111/j.1469-7610.2009.02199.x2003999560.Kahn RE, Frick PJ, Youngstrom E, Findling RL, Youngstrom JK (2011) The effects of including a callous–unemotional specifier for the diagnosis of conduct disorder. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. doi:10.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02463.x61.KeenanKWroblewskiKHipwellALoeberRStouthamer-LoeberMAge of onset, symptom threshold, and expansion of the nosology of conduct disorder for girlsJ Abnorm Psychol201011968969810.1037/a00193462085391362.BarkerEDOliverBRVidingESalekinRTMaughanBThe impact of prenatal maternal risk, fearless temperament and early parenting on adolescent callous–unemotional traits: a 14-year longitudinal investigationJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20115287888810.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02397.x2141047263.FrickPJExtending the construct of psychopathy to youth: implications for understanding, diagnosing, and treating antisocial children and adolescentsCan J Psychiatry2009548038122004771964.CrapanzanoAMFrickPJTerranovaAMPatterns of physical and relational aggression in a school-based sample of boys and girlsJ Abnorm Child Psychol20103843344510.1007/s10802-009-9376-32001304565.CrapanzanoAMFrickPJChildsKTerranovaAMGender differences in the assessment, stability, and correlates to bullying roles in middle school childrenBehav Sci Law20112967769410.1002/bsl.10002178977566.FougereAPotterSBoutilierJPsychopathy and offence severity in sexually aggressive and violent youthCrim Behav Ment Health20091924725210.1002/cbm.7351963954667.Kerr M, Van ZM, Stattin H (2011) Psychopathic traits moderate peer influence on adolescent delinquency. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. doi:10.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02492.x68.LawingKFrickPJCruiseKRDifferences in offending patterns between adolescent sex offenders high or low in callous–unemotional traitsPsychol Assess20102229830510.1037/a00187072052805769.MarseeMABarryCTChildsKKFrickPJKimonisERMunozLCAucoinKJFassnachtGMKunimatsuMMLauKSAssessing the forms and functions of aggression using self-report: factor structure and invariance of the peer conflict scale in youthsPsychol Assess20112379280410.1037/a00233692150092270.O’NeillMLNenzelMECaldwellWIntrusive thoughts and psychopathy in a student and incarcerated sampleJ Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry20094014715710.1016/j.jbtep.2008.07.0041876228471.RucevicSPsychopathic personality traits and delinquent and risky sexual behaviors in Croatian sample of non-referred boys and girlsLaw Hum Behav20103437939110.1007/s10979-009-9196-61972805772.Stickle TR, Marini VA, Thomas JN (2011) Gender differences in psychopathic traits, types, and correlates of aggression among adjudicated youth. J Abnorm Child Psychol. doi 10.1007/s10802-011-9588-173.WhiteSFCruiseKRFrickPJDifferential correlates to self-report and parent-report of callous–unemotional traits in a sample of juvenile sexual offendersBehav Sci Law20092791092810.1002/bsl.9111993792274.ScholteEMPloegJDThe development of a rating scale to screen social and emotional detachment in children and adolescentsInt J Methods Psychiatr Res20071613714910.1002/mpr.2221770205575.ChristianREFrickPJHillNLTylerLFrazerDRPsychopathy and conduct problems in children: II. Implications for subtyping children with conduct problemsJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry19973623324110.1097/00004583-199702000-00014903157676.StadlerCKroegerAWeyersPGrasmannDHorschinekMFreitagCClementHWCortisol reactivity in boys with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder and disruptive behavior problems: the impact of callous unemotional traitsPsychiatry Res201118720420910.1016/j.psychres.2010.05.0042081341477.LynamDREarly identification of chronic offenders: who is the fledgling psychopath?Psychol Bull199612020923410.1037/0033-2909.120.2.209883129778.LynamDREarly identification of the fledgling psychopath: locating the psychopathic child in the current nomenclatureJ Abnorm Psychol199810756657510.1037/0021-843X.107.4.566983024479.DelisiMVaughnMBeaverKMWexlerJBarthAEFletcherJMFledgling psychopathy in the classroom: ADHD subtypes psychopathy, and reading comprehension in a community sample of adolescentsYouth Violence Juv Justice20119435810.1177/15412040103719322131808280.Brammer WA, Lee SS (2011) Impairment in children with and without adhd: contributions from oppositional defiant disorder and callous–unemotional traits. J Atten Disord. doi:10.1177/108705471140370981.BarryCTFrickPJDeShazoTMMcCoyMGEllisMLoneyBRThe importance of callous–unemotional traits for extending the concept of psychopathy to childrenJ Abnorm Psychol200010933534010.1037/0021-843X.109.2.3351089557282.FowlerTLangleyKRiceFWhittingerNRossKGoozenSOwenMJO’DonovanMCBreeMBThaparAPsychopathy traits in adolescents with childhood attention-deficit hyperactivity disorderBr J Psychiatry2009194626710.1192/bjp.bp.107.0468701911832883.MichonskiJDSharpCRevisiting Lynam’s notion of the “fledgling psychopath”: are HIA-CP children truly psychopathic-like?Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health201042410.1186/1753-2000-4-242081590684.SeveckeKKossonDSKrischerMKThe relationship between attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, conduct disorder, and psychopathy in adolescent male and female detaineesBehav Sci Law20092757759810.1002/bsl.8701938799285.WaschbuschDAWilloughbyMTAttention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder and callous–unemotional traits as moderators of conduct problems when examining impairment and aggression in elementary school childrenAggress Behav20083413915310.1002/ab.202241769616486.LynamDRDerefinkoKJPatrickCJPsychopathy and personalityHandbook of psychopathy2007New YorkThe Guilford Press13315587.LeeZSalekinRTIselinAMPsychopathic traits in youth: is there evidence for primary and secondary subtypes?J Abnorm Child Psychol20103838139310.1007/s10802-009-9372-71994105088.LynamDRCaspiAMoffittTERaineALoeberRStouthamer-LoeberMAdolescent psychopathy and the big five: results from two samplesJ Abnorm Child Psychol20053343144310.1007/s10648-005-5724-01611899089.SalekinRTLeisticoAMTrobstKKSchrumCLLochmanJEAdolescent psychopathy and personality theory—the interpersonal circumplex: expanding evidence of a nomological netJ Abnorm Child Psychol20053344546010.1007/s10802-005-5726-Y1611899190.SadehNVeronaEJavdaniSOlsonLExamining psychopathic tendencies in adolescence from the perspective of personality theoryAggress Behav20093539940710.1002/ab.203161962142491.BarryCTFrickPJKillianALThe relation of narcissism and self-esteem to conduct problems in children: a preliminary investigationJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol2003321391521257393992.American Psychiatric Association (2000) Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders, 4th edn. American Psychiatric Association, Washington, DC (revision)93.RogersJVidingEBlairRJFrithUHappeFAutism spectrum disorder and psychopathy: shared cognitive underpinnings or double hit?Psychol Med2006361789179810.1017/S00332917060088531701816994.JonesAPHappeFGGilbertFBurnettSVidingEFeeling, caring, knowing: different types of empathy deficit in boys with psychopathic tendencies and autism spectrum disorderJ Child Psychol Psychiatry2010511188119710.1111/j.1469-7610.2010.02280.x2063307095.Schwenck C, Mergenthaler J, Keller K, Zech J, Salehi S, Taurines R, Romanos M, Schecklmann M, Schneider W, Warnke A, Freitag CM (2011) Empathy in children with autism and conduct disorder: group-specific profiles and developmental aspects. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. doi:10.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02499.x96.FontaineNBarkerEDSalekinRTVidingEDimensions of psychopathy and their relationships to cognitive functioning in childrenJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20083769069610.1080/153744108021481111864575997.SalekinRTNeumannCSLeisticoAMZalotAAPsychopathy in youth and intelligence: an investigation of Cleckley’s hypothesisJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20043373174210.1207/s15374424jccp3304_81549874098.FrickPJO’BrienBSWoottonJMMcBurnettKPsychopathy and conduct problems in childrenJ Abnorm Psychol199410370070710.1037/0021-843X.103.4.700782257199.LoneyBRFrickPJEllisMMcCoyMGIntelligence, callous–unemotional traits, and antisocial behaviorJ Psychopathol Behav Assess19982023124710.1023/A:1023015318156100.VaughnMGDelisiMBeaverKMWexlerJBarthAFletcherJJuvenile psychopathic personality traits are associated with poor reading achievementPsychiatr Q20118217719010.1007/s11126-010-9162-y20957434101.Dåderman AM, Edman G, Meurling AW, Levander S, Kristiansson M (2010) Flunitrazepam intake in male offenders. Nord J Psychiatry. doi:10.3109/08039488.2010.522730102.FritzMVWiklundGKoposovRAAfKBRuchkinVVPsychopathy and violence in juvenile delinquents: what are the associated factors?Int J Law Psychiatry20083127227910.1016/j.ijlp.2008.04.01018502509103.HemphäläMTengströmAAssociations between psychopathic traits and mental disorders among adolescents with substance use problemsBr J Clin Psychol20104910912210.1348/014466509X43921619457274104.MaillouxDLForthAEKronerDGPsychopathy and substance use in adolescent male offendersPsychol Rep1997815295309354106105.MurrieDCCornellDGThe Millon adolescent clinical inventory and psychopathyJ Pers Assess20007511012510.1207/S15327752JPA7501_810941704106.DolanMCRennieCEIs juvenile psychopathy associated with low anxiety and fear in conduct-disordered male offenders?J Anxiety Disord2007211028103810.1016/j.janxdis.2006.11.00817270390107.FrickPJLilienfeldSOEllisMLoneyBSilverthornPThe association between anxiety and psychopathy dimensions in childrenJ Abnorm Child Psychol19992738339210.1023/A:102192801840310582839108.HipwellAEPardiniDALoeberRSembowerMKeenanKStouthamer-LoeberMCallous–unemotional behaviors in young girls: shared and unique effects relative to conduct problemsJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20073629330410.1080/1537441070144416517658975109.PardiniDALochmanJEPowellNThe development of callous–unemotional traits and antisocial behavior in children: are there shared and/or unique predictors?J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20073631933310.1080/1537441070144421517658977110.PardiniDAFitePJSymptoms of conduct disorder, oppositional defiant disorder, attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder, and callous–unemotional traits as unique predictors of psychosocial maladjustment in boys: advancing an evidence base for DSM-VJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry2010491134114420970701111.PolierGGHerpertz-DahlmannBMatthiasKKonradKVloetTDAssociations between trait anxiety and psychopathological characteristics of children at high risk for severe antisocial developmentAtten Defic Hyperact Disord2010218519310.1007/s12402-010-0048-521432605112.KimonisERSkeemJLCauffmanEDmitrievaJAre secondary variants of juvenile psychopathy more reactively violent and less psychosocially mature than primary variants?Law Hum Behav20113538139110.1007/s10979-010-9243-320703785113.WarehamJDemboRPoythressNGChildsKSchmeidlerJA latent class factor approach to identifying subtypes of juvenile diversion youths based on psychopathic featuresBehav Sci Law200927719510.1002/bsl.84419156678114.SkeemJLCauffmanEViews of the downward extension: comparing the Youth Version of the Psychopathy Checklist with the Youth Psychopathic traits InventoryBehav Sci Law20032173777010.1002/bsl.56314696029115.BurkeJDLoeberRLaheyBBAdolescent conduct disorder and interpersonal callousness as predictors of psychopathy in young adultsJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20073633434610.1080/1537441070144422317658978116.JavdaniSSadehNVeronaESuicidality as a function of impulsivity, callous–unemotional traits, and depressive symptoms in youthJ Abnorm Psychol201112040041310.1037/a002180521280931117.CorradoRRVincentGMHartSDCohenIMPredictive validity of the Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version for general and violent recidivismBehav Sci Law20042252210.1002/bsl.57414963878118.FitePJStoppelbeinLGreeningLProactive and reactive aggression in a child psychiatric inpatient populationJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20093819920510.1080/1537441080269846119283598119.FrickPJCornellAHBarryCTBodinSDDaneHECallous–unemotional traits and conduct problems in the prediction of conduct problem severity, aggression, and self-report of delinquencyJ Abnorm Child Psychol20033145747010.1023/A:102389970386612831233120.MoranPRoweRFlachCBriskmanJFordTMaughanBScottSGoodmanRPredictive value of callous–unemotional traits in a large community sampleJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry2009481079108410.1097/CHI.0b013e3181b766ab19797982121.MuñozLCPakalniskieneVFrickPJParental monitoring and youth behavior problems: moderation by callous–unemotional traits over timeEur Child Adolesc Psychiatry20112026126910.1007/s00787-011-0172-621487812122.NeumannCSVitaccoMRobertsonASewellKLongitudinal assessment of callous/impulsive traits, substance abuse, and symptoms of depression in adolescents: a latent variable approachAnn N Y Acad Sci2003100827628010.1196/annals.1301.03114998895123.SalekinRTPsychopathy and recidivism from mid-adolescence to young adulthood: cumulating legal problems and limiting life opportunitiesJ Abnorm Psychol200811738639510.1037/0021-843X.117.2.38618489214124.VitaccoMJNeumannCSRobertsonAADurrantSLContributions of impulsivity and callousness in the assessment of adjudicated male adolescents: a prospective studyJ Pers Assess2002788710310.1207/S15327752JPA7801_0611936214125.DandreauxDMFrickPJDevelopmental pathways to conduct problems: a further test of the childhood and adolescent-onset distinctionJ Abnorm Child Psychol20093737538510.1007/s10802-008-9261-518670873126.KimonisERFrickPJBarryCTCallous–unemotional traits and delinquent peer affiliationJ Consult Clin Psychol20047295696610.1037/0022-006X.72.6.95615612843127.FrickPJStickleTRDandreauxDMFarrellJMKimonisERCallous–unemotional traits in predicting the severity and stability of conduct problems and delinquencyJ Abnorm Child Psychol20053347148710.1007/s10648-005-5728-916118993128.McMahonRJWitkiewitzKKotlerJSPredictive validity of callous–unemotional traits measured in early adolescence with respect to multiple antisocial outcomesJ Abnorm Psychol201011975276310.1037/a002079620939651129.StockdaleKCOlverMEWongSCThe Psychopathy Checklist: Youth Version and adolescent and adult recidivism: considerations with respect to gender, ethnicity, and agePsychol Assess20102276878110.1037/a002004420804258130.HawesDJDaddsMRFrostADHaskingPADo childhood callous–unemotional traits drive change in parenting practices?J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20114050751810.1080/15374416.2011.58162421722024131.ForsmanMLichtensteinPAndershedHLarssonHGenetic effects explain the stability of psychopathic personality from mid- to late adolescenceJ Abnorm Psychol200811760661710.1037/0021-843X.117.3.60618729612132.FontaineNMMcCroryEJBoivinMMoffittTEVidingEPredictors and outcomes of joint trajectories of callous–unemotional traits and conduct problems in childhoodJ Abnorm Psychol201112073074210.1037/a002262021341879133.FrickPJKimonisERDandreauxDMFarellJMThe 4 year stability of psychopathic traits in non-referred youthBehav Sci Law20032171373610.1002/bsl.56814696028134.ObradovicJPardiniDALongJDLoeberRMeasuring interpersonal callousness in boys from childhood to adolescence: an examination of longitudinal invariance and temporal stabilityJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20073627629210.1080/1537441070144163317658974135.BlonigenDMHicksBMKruegerRFPatrickCJIaconoWGContinuity and change in psychopathic traits as measured via normal-range personality: a longitudinal-biometric studyJ Abnorm Psychol2006115859510.1037/0021-843X.115.1.8516492099136.LoneyBRTaylorJButlerMAIaconoWGAdolescent psychopathy features: 6-year temporal stability and the prediction of externalizing symptoms during the transition to adulthoodAggress Behav20073324225210.1002/ab.2018417444530137.LynamDRCaspiAMoffittTELoeberRStouthamer-LoeberMLongitudinal evidence that psychopathy scores in early adolescence predict adult psychopathyJ Abnorm Psychol200711615516510.1037/0021-843X.116.1.15517324026138.HarpurTJHareRDHakstianARTwo-factor conceptualization of psychopathy: construct validity and assessment implicationsPsychol Assess1989161710.1037/1040-3590.1.1.6139.HarpurTJHareRDAssessment of psychopathy as a function of ageJ Abnorm Psychol199410360460910.1037/0021-843X.103.4.6047822561140.LeeZKlaverJRHartSDMorettiMMDouglasKSShort-term stability of psychopathic traits in adolescent offendersJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20093859560510.1080/1537441090310353620183645141.BlonigenDMHicksBMKruegerRFPatrickCJIaconoWGPsychopathic personality traits: heritability and genetic overlap with internalizing and externalizing psychopathologyPsychol Med20053563764810.1017/S003329170400418015918340142.LarssonHAndershedHLichtensteinPA genetic factor explains most of the variation in the psychopathic personalityJ Abnorm Psychol200611522123010.1037/0021-843X.115.2.22116737387143.TaylorJLoneyBRBobadillaLIaconoWGMcGueMGenetic and environmental influences on psychopathy trait dimensions in a community sample of male twinsJ Abnorm Child Psychol20033163364510.1023/A:102626220744914658743144.VidingEBlairRJMoffittTEPlominREvidence for substantial genetic risk for psychopathy in 7-year-oldsJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20054659259710.1111/j.1469-7610.2004.00393.x15877765145.VidingEFrickPJPlominRAetiology of the relationship between callous–unemotional traits and conduct problems in childhoodBr J Psychiatry Suppl200749s33s3810.1192/bjp.190.5.s3317470941146.VidingEJonesAPFrickPJMoffittTEPlominRHeritability of antisocial behaviour at 9: do callous–unemotional traits matter?Dev Sci200811172210.1111/j.1467-7687.2007.00648.x18171362147.VidingEFontaineNMOliverBRPlominRNegative parental discipline, conduct problems and callous–unemotional traits: monozygotic twin differences studyBr J Psychiatry200919541441910.1192/bjp.bp.108.06119219880931148.FontaineNMGRijsdijkFVMcCroryEJPVidingEEtiology of different developmental trajectories of callous–unemotional traitsJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry20104965666420610135149.VidingEHanscombeKBCurtisCJDavisOSMeaburnELPlominRIn search of genes associated with risk for psychopathic tendencies in children: a two-stage genome-wide association study of pooled DNAJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20105178078810.1111/j.1469-7610.2010.02236.x20345837150.FowlerTLangleyKRiceFBreeMBRossKWilkinsonLSOwenMJO’DonovanMCThaparAPsychopathy trait scores in adolescents with childhood ADHD: the contribution of genotypes affecting MAOA, 5HTT and COMT activityPsychiatr Genet20091931231910.1097/YPG.0b013e3283328df419829167151.SadehNJavdaniSJacksonJJReynoldsEKPotenzaMNGelernterJLejuezCWVeronaESerotonin transporter gene associations with psychopathic traits in youth vary as a function of socioeconomic resourcesJ Abnorm Psychol201011960460910.1037/a001970920677849152.LoneyBRHuntenburgACounts-AllanCSchmeelkKMA preliminary examination of the intergenerational continuity of maternal psychopathic featuresAggress Behav200733142510.1002/ab.2016317441002153.PasalichDSDaddsMRHawesDJBrennanJDo callous–unemotional traits moderate the relative importance of parental coercion versus warmth in child conduct problems? An observational studyJ Child Psychol Psychiatry2011521308131510.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02435.x21726225154.VitaccoMJNeumannCSRamosVRobertsMKIneffective parenting: a precursor to psychopathic traits and delinquency in Hispanic femalesAnn N Y Acad Sci2003100830030310.1196/annals.1301.03714998901155.EdensJFSkoppNACahillMAPsychopathic features moderate the relationship between harsh and inconsistent parental discipline and adolescent antisocial behaviorJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20083747247610.1080/1537441080195593818470783156.OxfordMCavellTAHughesJNCallous/unemotional traits moderate the relation between ineffective parenting and child externalizing problems: a partial replication and extensionJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20033257758510.1207/S15374424JCCP3204_1014710466157.WoottonJMFrickPJSheltonKKSilverthornPIneffective parenting and childhood conduct problems: the moderating role of callous–unemotional traitsJ Consult Clin Psychol19976530130810.1037/0022-006X.65.2.292.b9086694158.FitePJGreeningLStoppelbeinLRelation between parenting stress and psychopathic traits among childrenBehav Sci Law20082623924810.1002/bsl.80318344170159.Dadds MR, Allen JL, Oliver BR, Faulkner N, Legge K, Moul C, Woolgar M, Scott S (2011) Love, eye contact and the developmental origins of empathy v. psychopathy. Br J Psychiatry. doi:10.1192/bjp.bp.110.085720160.EnebrinkPAndershedHLångströmNCallous–unemotional traits are associated with clinical severity in referred boys with conduct problemsNord J Psychiatry20055943144010.1080/0803948050036069016316895161.FrickPJCornellAHBodinSDDaneHEBarryCTLoneyBRCallous–unemotional traits and developmental pathways to severe conduct problemsDev Psychol20033924626010.1037/0012-1649.39.2.24612661884162.CaputoAAFrickPJBrodskySLFamily violence and juvenile sex offending: potential mediating roles of psychopathic traits and negative attitudes toward womenCrim Justice Behav19992633835610.1177/0093854899026003004163.KrischerMKSeveckeKEarly traumatization and psychopathy in female and male juvenile offendersInt J Law Psychiatry20083125326210.1016/j.ijlp.2008.04.00818514903164.KimonisERFrickPJMuñozLCAucoinKJCallous–unemotional traits and the emotional processing of distress cues in detained boys: testing the moderating role of aggression, exposure to community violence, and histories of abuseDev Psychopathol20082056958910.1017/S095457940800028X18423095165.Bohlin G, Eninger L, Brocki KC, Thorell LB (2011) Disorganized attachment and inhibitory capacity: predicting externalizing problem behaviors. J Abnorm Child Psychol. doi:10.1007/s10802-011-9574-7166.Kumsta R, Sonuga-Barke E, Rutter M (2011) Adolescent callous–unemotional traits and conduct disorder in adoptees exposed to severe early deprivation. Br J Psychiatry. doi:10.1192/bjp.bp.110.089441167.JonesAPLaurensKRHerbaCMBarkerGJVidingEAmygdala hypoactivity to fearful faces in boys with conduct problems and callous–unemotional traitsAm J Psychiatry20091669510210.1176/appi.ajp.2008.0707105018923070168.MarshAAFingerECMitchellDGReidMESimsCKossonDSTowbinKELeibenluftEPineDSBlairRJReduced amygdala response to fearful expressions in children and adolescents with callous–unemotional traits and disruptive behavior disordersAm J Psychiatry200816571272010.1176/appi.ajp.2007.0707114518281412169.FingerECMarshAAMitchellDGReidMESimsCBudhaniSKossonDSChenGTowbinKELeibenluftEPineDSBlairJRAbnormal ventromedial prefrontal cortex function in children with psychopathic traits during reversal learningArch Gen Psychiatry20086558659410.1001/archpsyc.65.5.58618458210170.PassamontiLFairchildGGoodyerIMHurfordGHaganCCRoweJBCalderAJNeural abnormalities in early-onset and adolescence-onset conduct disorderArch Gen Psychiatry20106772973810.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.7520603454171.BritoSAMechelliAWilkeMLaurensKRJonesAPBarkerGJHodginsSVidingESize matters: increased grey matter in boys with conduct problems and callous–unemotional traitsBrain200913284385210.1093/brain/awp01119293245172.PoustkaLMarasAHohmEFellingerJHoltmannMBanaschewskiTLewickaSSchmidtMHEsserGLauchtMNegative association between plasma cortisol levels and aggression in a high-risk community sample of adolescentsJ Neural Transm201011762162710.1007/s00702-010-0386-720217435173.LoneyBRButlerMALimaENCountsCAEckelLAThe relation between salivary cortisol, callous–unemotional traits, and conduct problems in an adolescent non-referred sampleJ Child Psychol Psychiatry200647303610.1111/j.1469-7610.2005.01444.x16405638174.Anastassiou-HadjicharalambousXWardenDPhysiologically-indexed and self-perceived affective empathy in conduct-disordered children high and low on callous–unemotional traitsChild Psychiatry Hum Dev20083950351710.1007/s10578-008-0104-y18792777175.BlairRJRResponsiveness to distress cues in the child with psychopathic tendenciesPers Individ Dif19992713514510.1016/S0191-8869(98)00231-1176.WiedMBoxtelAMatthysWMeeusWVerbal, facial and autonomic responses to empathy-eliciting film clips by disruptive male adolescents with high versus low callous–unemotional traitsJ Abnorm Child Psychol20124021122310.1007/s10802-011-9557-821870040177.MuñozLCFrickPJKimonisERAucoinKJVerbal ability and delinquency: testing the moderating role of psychopathic traitsJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20084941442110.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01847.x18081757178.MuñozLCFrickPJKimonisERAucoinKJTypes of aggression, responsiveness to provocation, and callous–unemotional traits in detained adolescentsJ Abnorm Child Psychol200836152810.1007/s10802-007-9137-017882544179.Anastassiou-HadjicharalambousXWardenDCognitive and affective perspective-taking in conduct-disordered children high and low on callous–unemotional traitsChild Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health200821610.1186/1753-2000-2-1618601753180.HolmqvistRPsychopathy and affect consciousness in young criminal offendersJ Interpers Violence20082320922410.1177/088626050730934118162637181.RogersRVitaccoMJJacksonRLMartinMCollinsMSewellKWFaking psychopathy? An examination of response styles with antisocial youthJ Pers Assess200278314610.1207/S15327752JPA7801_0311936210182.ChandlerMMoranTPsychopathy and moral development: a comparative study of delinquent and nondelinquent youthDev Psychopathol1990222724610.1017/S0954579400000742183.BlairRJRMonsonJFredericksonNMoral reasoning and conduct problems in children with emotional and behavioural difficultiesPers Individ Differ20013179981110.1016/S0191-8869(00)00181-1184.FisherLBlairRJCognitive impairment and its relationship to psychopathic tendencies in children with emotional and behavioral difficultiesJ Abnorm Child Psychol19982651151910.1023/A:10226559197439915656185.ShulmanEPCauffmanEPiqueroARFaganJMoral disengagement among serious juvenile offenders: a longitudinal study of the relations between morally disengaged attitudes and offendingDev Psychol2011471619163210.1037/a002540421910534186.PardiniDALochmanJEFrickPJCallous/unemotional traits and social-cognitive processes in adjudicated youthsJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry20034236437110.1097/00004583-200303000-0001812595791187.Pardini DA, Byrd AL (2011) Perceptions of aggressive conflicts and others’ distress in children with callous–unemotional traits: ‘I’ll show you who’s boss, even if you suffer and I get in trouble’. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. doi:10.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02487.x188.StickleTRKirkpatrickNMBrushLNCallous–unemotional traits and social information processing: multiple risk-factor models for understanding aggressive behavior in antisocial youthLaw Hum Behav20093351552910.1007/s10979-008-9171-719132520189.DaddsMRHawesDJFrostADVassalloSBunnPHunterKMerzSLearning to ‘talk the talk: the relationship of psychopathic traits to deficits in empathy across childhoodJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20095059960610.1111/j.1469-7610.2008.02058.x19445007190.LorberCMHughesTLMillerJACrothersLMMartinECallous and unemotional traits and social cognitive processes in a sample of community-based aggressive youthInt J Offender Ther Comp Criminol2010551291130710.1177/0306624X1138601222114171191.WaschbuschDAWalshTMAndradeBFKingSCarreyNJSocial problem solving, conduct problems, and callous–unemotional traits in childrenChild Psychiatry Hum Dev20073729330510.1007/s10578-006-0033-617103303192.BlairRJRColledgeEMitchellDGSomatic markers and response reversal: is there orbitofrontal cortex dysfunction in boys with psychopathic tendencies?J Abnorm Child Psychol20012949951110.1023/A:101227712511911761284193.O’BrienBSFrickPJReward dominance: associations with anxiety, conduct problems, and psychopathy in childrenJ Abnorm Child Psychol19962422324010.1007/BF014414868743246194.LoneyBRFrickPJClementsCBEllisMLKerlinKCallous–unemotional traits, impulsivity, and emotional processing in adolescents with antisocial behavior problemsJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol200332668012573933195.SharpCGoozenSGoodyerIChildren’s subjective emotional reactivity to affective pictures: gender differences and their antisocial correlates in an unselected sample of 7-11-year-oldsJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20064714315010.1111/j.1469-7610.2005.01464.x16423145196.BlairRJRColesMExpression recognition and behavioral problems in early adolescenceCogn Dev20001542143410.1016/S0885-2014(01)00039-9197.DaddsMRPerryYHawesDJMerzSRiddellACHainesDJSolakEAbeygunawardaneAIAttention to the eyes and fear-recognition deficits in child psychopathyBr J Psychiatry200618928028110.1192/bjp.bp.105.01815016946366198.DaddsMRElMYWimalaweeraSGuastellaAJReduced eye gaze explains “fear blindness” in childhood psychopathic traitsJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry20084745546310.1097/CHI.0b013e31816407f118388767199.MuñozLCCallous–unemotional traits are related to combined deficits in recognizing afraid faces and body posesJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry20094855456210.1097/CHI.0b013e31819c241919318989200.SylversPDBrennanPALilienfeldSOPsychopathic traits and preattentive threat processing in children: a novel test of the fearlessness hypothesisPsychol Sci2011221280128710.1177/095679761142073021881061201.LeistTDaddsMRAdolescents’ ability to read different emotional faces relates to their history of maltreatment and type of psychopathologyClin Child Psychol Psychiatry20091423725010.1177/135910450810088719293321202.BlairRJRBudhaniSColledgeEScottSDeafness to fear in boys with psychopathic tendenciesJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20054632733610.1111/j.1469-7610.2004.00356.x15755308203.FairchildGGoozenSHMCalderAJStollerySJGoodyerIMDeficits in facial expression recognition in male adolescents with early-onset or adolescence-onset conduct disorderJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20095062763610.1111/j.1469-7610.2008.02020.x19432683204.DaddsMRJambrakJPasalichDHawesDJBrennanJImpaired attention to the eyes of attachment figures and the developmental origins of psychopathyJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20115223824510.1111/j.1469-7610.2010.02323.x20883520205.FairchildGStobbeYGoozenSHCalderAJGoodyerIMFacial expression recognition, fear conditioning, and startle modulation in female subjects with conduct disorderBiol Psychiatry20106827227910.1016/j.biopsych.2010.02.01920447616206.WoodworthMWaschbuschDEmotional processing in children with conduct problems and callous/unemotional traitsChild Care Health Dev20083423424410.1111/j.1365-2214.2007.00792.x18028474207.WaschbuschDACarreyNJWilloughbyMTKingSAndradeBFEffects of methylphenidate and behavior modification on the social and academic behavior of children with disruptive behavior disorders: the moderating role of callous/unemotional traitsJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20073662964410.1080/1537441070166276618088220208.CaldwellMFTreatment-related changes in behavioral outcomes of psychopathy facets in adolescent offendersLaw Hum Behav20113527528710.1007/s10979-010-9239-z20658262209.HaasSMWaschbuschDAPelhamWEJrKingSAndradeBFCarreyNJTreatment response in CP/ADHD children with callous/unemotional traitsJ Abnorm Child Psychol20113954155210.1007/s10802-010-9480-421188627210.HawesDJDaddsMRThe treatment of conduct problems in children with callous–unemotional traitsJ Consult Clin Psychol20057373774110.1037/0022-006X.73.4.73716173862211.HawesDJDaddsMRStability and malleability of callous–unemotional traits during treatment for childhood conduct problemsJ Clin Child Adolesc Psychol20073634735510.1080/1537441070144429817658979212.KolkoDJPardiniDAODD dimensions, ADHD, and callous–unemotional traits as predictors of treatment response in children with disruptive behavior disordersJ Abnorm Psychol201011971372510.1037/a002091021090875213.MasiGManfrediAMiloneAMuratoriPPolidoriLRuglioniLMuratoriFPredictors of nonresponse to psychosocial treatment in children and adolescents with disruptive behavior disordersJ Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol201121515510.1089/cap.2010.003921309697214.FalkenbachDMPoythressNGHeideKMPsychopathic features in a juvenile diversion population: reliability and predictive validity of two self-report measuresBehav Sci Law20032178780510.1002/bsl.56214696031215.O’NeillMLLidzVHeilbrunKAdolescents with psychopathic characteristics in a substance abusing cohort: treatment process and outcomesLaw Hum Behav20032729931310.1023/A:102343592456912794966216.SpainSEDouglasKSPoythressNGEpsteinMThe relationship between psychopathic features, violence and treatment outcome: the comparison of three youth measures of psychopathic featuresBehav Sci Law2004228510210.1002/bsl.57614963882217.StellwagenKKKerigPKRelation of callous–unemotional traits to length of stay among youth hospitalized at a state psychiatric inpatient facilityChild Psychiatry Hum Dev20104125126110.1007/s10578-009-0164-719949974218.MoffittTEArseneaultLJaffeeSRKim-CohenJKoenenKCOdgersCLSlutskeWSVidingEResearch review: DSM-V conduct disorder: research needs for an evidence baseJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20084933310.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01823.x18181878219.PardiniDAFrickPJMoffittTEBuilding an evidence base for DSM-5 conceptualizations of oppositional defiant disorder and conduct disorder: introduction to the special sectionJ Abnorm Psychol201011968368810.1037/a002144121090874220.DiamantopoulouSVerhulstFCEndeJThe parallel development of ODD and CD symptoms from early childhood to adolescenceEur Child Adolesc Psychiatry20112030130910.1007/s00787-011-0175-321499848221.RobinsLNPsychiatric epidemiology—a historic reviewSoc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol19902516262406945222.OdgersCLMorettiMMReppucciNDExamining the science and practice of violence risk assessment with female adolescentsLaw Hum Behav20052972710.1007/s10979-005-1397-z15865330223.SeveckeKLehmkuhlGKrischerMKExamining relations between psychopathology and psychopathy dimensions among adolescent female and male offendersEur Child Adolesc Psychiatry200918859510.1007/s00787-008-0707-718807112224.SeveckeKLehmkuhlGKrischerMKPsychopathy, temperament and antisocial behaviour in girlsZ Kinder Jugendpsychiatr Psychother2010389110110.1024/1422-4917.a00001620200826225.CoidJYangMThe impact of psychopathy on violence among the household population of Great BritainSoc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol20114647348010.1007/s00127-010-0212-420354677226.BlairRJRPeschardtKSBudhaniSMitchellDGPineDSThe development of psychopathyJ Child Psychol Psychiatry20064726227610.1111/j.1469-7610.2006.01596.x16492259227.LoeberRFarringtonDPYoung children who commit crime: epidemiology, developmental origins, risk factors, early interventions, and policy implicationsDev Psychopathol20001273776210.1017/S095457940000410711202042228.HareRDHare psychopathy checklist—revised (PCL-R) technical manual1991TorontoMulti-Health Systems229.Hare RD (1991) The self-report psychopathy scale—II. University of British Columbia, Vancouver (unpublished test)230.HartSDCoxDNHareRDManual for the psychopathy checklist: screening version (PCL:SV).1995TorontoMulti-Health Systems231.Rogers R (1996) Survey of Attitudes and Life Experiences (SALE). University of North Texas, Denton (unpublished test)232.LynamDRPursuing the psychopath: capturing the fledgling psychopath in a nomological netJ Abnorm Psychol199710642543810.1037/0021-843X.106.3.4259241944233.FrickPJHareRDThe Psychopathy Screening Device2000TorontoMulti-Health Systems234.CauffmanEKimonisERDmitrievaJMonahanKCA multimethod assessment of juvenile psychopathy: comparing the predictive utility of the PCL:YV, YPI, and NEO PRIPsychol Assess20092152854210.1037/a001736719947787235.EdensJFMarcusDKVaughnMGExploring the taxometric status of psychopathy among youthful offenders: is there a juvenile psychopath taxon?Law Hum Behav201135132410.1007/s10979-010-9230-820431928236.MyersWCBurketRCHarrisHEAdolescent psychopathy in relation to delinquent behaviors, conduct disorder, and personality disordersJ Forensic Sci1995404354397782747237.GoodmanRThe Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire: a research noteJ Child Psychol Psychiatry19973858158610.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01545.x9255702
