<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front NeurosciFront NeurosciFront. Neurosci.Frontiers in Neuroscience1662-45481662-453XFrontiers Media S.A.463182910.3389/fnins.2015.00427PsychologyOriginal ResearchEffectiveness of music therapy as an aid to neurorestoration of children with severe neurological disordersBringasMaria L.12*ZaldivarMarilyn2RojasPedro A.3Martinez-MontesKarelia2ChongoDora M.2OrtegaMaria A.2GalvizuReynaldo2PerezAlba E.2MoralesLilia M.2MaragotoCarlos2VeraHector2GalanLidice1BessonMireille234Valdes-SosaPedro A.131Laboratory of Neuroinformation, School of Life Sciences, University of Electronic Sciences and Technology of ChinaChengdu, China2Centro Internacional de Restauracion NeurologicaHabana, Cuba3Centro de Neurociencias de CubaHabana, Cuba4Laboratoire de Neurosciences Cognitives, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique and Marseille UniversitéMarseille, FranceEdited by: Antoni Rodriguez-Fornells, University of Barcelona, SpainReviewed by: Jennifer Grau-Sánchez, University of Barcelona, Spain; Wendy L. Magee, Temple University, USA*Correspondence: Maria L. Bringas maria@uestc.edu.cnThis article was submitted to Auditory Cognitive Neuroscience, a section of the journal Frontiers in Neuroscience0411201520159427084201421102015Copyright © 2015 Bringas, Zaldivar, Rojas, Martinez-Montes, Chongo, Ortega, Galvizu, Perez, Morales, Maragoto, Vera, Galan, Besson and Valdes-Sosa.2015Bringas, Zaldivar, Rojas, Martinez-Montes, Chongo, Ortega, Galvizu, Perez, Morales, Maragoto, Vera, Galan, Besson and Valdes-SosaThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.This study was a two-armed parallel group design aimed at testing real world effectiveness of a music therapy (MT) intervention for children with severe neurological disorders. The control group received only the standard neurorestoration program and the experimental group received an additional MT “Auditory Attention plus Communication protocol” just before the usual occupational and speech therapy. Multivariate Item Response Theory (MIRT) identified a neuropsychological status-latent variable manifested in all children and which exhibited highly significant changes only in the experimental group. Changes in brain plasticity also occurred in the experimental group, as evidenced using a Mismatch Event Related paradigm which revealed significant post intervention positive responses in the latency range between 308 and 400 ms in frontal regions. LORETA EEG source analysis identified prefrontal and midcingulate regions as differentially activated by the MT in the experimental group. Taken together, our results showing improved attention and communication as well as changes in brain plasticity in children with severe neurological impairments, confirm the importance of MT for the rehabilitation of patients across a wide range of dysfunctions.rehabilitationchildrenERPsmusic therapyneurological disordersData analysisBehavioral analysisIn accordance with recommended best practice for constructing outcome measures for neurological clinical trials, we employed Multivariate Item Response Theory (MIRT) to select informative items and to combine them into summarizing scores (Hobart et al., 2007). Potentially several outcome measures may be obtained from a given set of behavioral tests. Each outcome measure is a summarizing statistic obtained by selecting certain items from the complete set of behavioral tests, and adding them up each multiplied by a weight reflecting their importance for the outcome being probed. Thus the profile of items selected and weights chosen characterize each outcome as a latent variable designed to be independent of the evaluator, independent of the specific test items used in its construction, and robust against chance fluctuations in score recording (Fox, 2010). We must stress that MIRT finds optimal weights by means of a type of nonlinear principal component analysis. A more complete technical description of MIRT is contained in Appendix 2 in Supplementary Material.Once the outcome measures are obtained, MIRT allows the application of mixed ANOVA (random + fixed) effects analysis of variance techniques to the underlying factors to query whether the proposed treatment actually affects the outcome measures.In order to apply MIRT, the data from the behavioral questionnaire was arranged in a data matrix in which each observation (row) consisted of the scores for the 23 items. A separate row was used for each testing “Session” [Time0 = baseline, Time1 = 4, and Time2 = 8 weeks (if applicable)] and for each type of therapist (speech or occupational).For the behavioral data, we addressed three statistical questions:
What is the adequate number of outcome measures that describe the variability of the behavioral data? One and two factor models were calculated using the mirt procedure (from the MIRT package) and the Bayesian Information Criteria (BIC) (Luo et al., 2013) measure was used to select between these models.What items in the questionnaire contain useful information? This was decided on the basis of their factor scores (discriminatory power). Only high scoring items were retained for further analysis. Furthermore what is the interpretation of the outcome measures obtained by MIRT?Was there a significant effect on outcome measures specific to MT? An ANOVA mixed-model including only the “Session” main effect and the interaction “Group by Session” analysis assessed this effect of therapy. The fixed effects considered were: Session (moment of evaluation) taken as a continuous regressor and Group: (experimental vs. control). The random effects considered were: Subjects (in a repeated-measures design) and Evaluators (different therapists).MMR analysisThe EEG was recorded from a subset of 24 children (12 out of 17–5 girls and 7 boys—in each group) in both the experimental and control groups (the first 12 rows in Tables 1A,B respectively). Children who required anesthesia for the initial EEG recordings (Time 0) were not included in the subsequent ERP analysis. Demographical and clinical characteristics did not differ significantly between the treatment groups for this subset of children. ERPs were recorded from all 24 children before (Pre-treatment) and after therapy (Post-treatment -either after 4 or 8 weeks), as indicated in Tables 1A,B, column 4. In order to take into account the duration of therapy for each child this variable was included as a covariate in all statistical analyses.EEG recordings for each subject were segmented into trials from 100 ms before the stimuli (standard or deviant) to 500 ms. Artifact removal was carried out using the EEGLAB Matlab Toolbox (Delorme and Makeig, 2004) (http://sccn.ucsd.edu/eeglab/) as described in detail in Appendix 3 of Supplementary Material. The whole process resulted in sets of trials for each Session (pre/post therapy) and type of Stimulus (standard/deviant) with a range of 492–704 trials for the standard stimulus and a range of 48–72 for each type of deviant stimuli, with a total of 640–920 trials per subject.The statistical analysis of the MMR response comprised the following steps:
Calculation for each individual of the Mismatch Response (MMR) computed as the average of deviant stimuli minus the standard stimuli for each session separately (Pre and Post).Calculation for each individual of the Post- minus Pre-MMR i.e., the “MT difference MMR.”Test for the “MT-specific effect” on the MMR by comparing the treatment difference MMR of the experimental and control groups. This was done by means of both a t-test as well as an ANCOVA analysis using duration of therapy (4 or 8 weeks) as a covariate. The latencies of MT specific effects were of particular interest.Identification of the brain sources of MT-specific MMR effects. The LORETA procedure (Pascual-Marqui et al., 1994) was used to estimate EEG sources for each individual at significant MMR latencies. The significance of “MT-specific source effects” was independently verified by means of permutation techniques (Nichols and Holmes, 2001), and the anatomical locations of the sources were identified according to the AAL atlas (Automated Anatomical Labeling of Activations) (Tzourio-Mazoyer et al., 2002).Steps 1–3 were carried out using a Mass Univariate approach (Groppe et al., 2011) as implemented in the LIMO (LInear MOdeling) Toolbox for Matlab (Pernet et al., 2011) http://www.gnu.org/software/octave/). LIMO carries out statistically robust (resistant to outlier) procedures by computing thresholds using an empirical distribution function based on 1000 bootstrapped samples and the use of Least Trimmed Squared (LTS) estimates. Finally, thresholds to deal with multiple comparisons were obtained by using the one dimensional temporal clustering correction. Step 4 was carried out with in-house software.Author contributionsMLB and MB designed the study. MO, RG, CM, and HV evaluated the children. LM and MZ carried out the electrophysiological recordings. DC was in charge of collecting the behavioral data. AP was in charge of interactions with the parents. KMM was in charge of the music therapy program. Statistical analysis was designed by PVS and carried out by MLB, PVS, LG, and PR. Finally, MLB, MB, and PVS wrote the paper.Conflict of interest statementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.Thanks to all the children and parents who participated in the study. This experimental program was implemented while Prof. Besson was on sabbatical (2012) at CIREN and CNEURO. This work was also supported by the Labex BLRI (ANR-11-LABX-0036) and the French National Agency for Research (ANR), under the program “Investissements d'Avenir” (ANR-11-IDEX-0001-02). We are also very grateful to the nurses and the physical, occupational and speech therapists who devoted so much of their time to this project. We are also grateful to Jorge Bosch, Eduardo Martinez-Montes from CNEURO for their contribution to discussions of a previous version of the paper and to Ma Ling and Chen Chao from UESTC for their assistance in the processing of the ERP data. We especially wish to thank Prof. Keith Kendrick who extensively revised the MS, and helped us with the style and language aspects.ReferencesBelkinM.NiyogiP. (2002). “Laplacian Eigenmaps and spectral techniques for embedding and clustering,” in Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, Vol. 14, eds BeckerS.ThrunS.ObermayerK. (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press), 585–591.BessonM.ChobertJ.MarieC. (2011). Transfer of training between music and speech: common processing, attention, and memory. Front. Psychol.
2:94. 10.3389/fpsyg.2011.0009421738519BishopD. V. M. (2007). Using mismatch negativity to study central auditory processing in developmental language and literacy impairments: where are we and where should we be going?
Psychol. Bull.
133, 651–672. 10.1037/0033-2909.133.4.65117592960BoersmaP.WeeninkD. (2001). Praat (version 4.0). Available online at: http://www.fon.hum.uva.nl/praat/BradtJ. (2012). Randomized controlled trials in music therapy: guidelines for design and implementation. J. Music Ther.
49, 120–149. 10.1093/jmt/49.2.120BrownL. S.JellisonJ. A. (2012). Music research with children and youth with disabilities and typically developing peers: a systematic review. J. Music Ther.
49, 335–364. 10.1093/jmt/49.3.33523259233BrusciaK. E. (1998). Defining Music Therapy, 2nd Edn. Gilsum, NH: Barcelona Publishers.BushG. (2009). “Dorsal anterior midcingulate cortex: roles in normal cognition and disruption in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder,” in Cingulate Neurobiology and Disease, ed VogtB. A. (New York, NY: Oxford University Press), 245–274.BushG.LuuP.PosnerM. I. (2000). Cognitive and emotional influences in anterior cingulate cortex. Trends Cogn. Sci.
4, 215–222. 10.1016/S1364-6613(00)01483-210827444ChobertJ.FrancoisC.VelayJ.-L.BessonM. (2014). Twelve months of active musical training in 8-to10-year-old children enhances the preattentive processing of syllabic duration and voice onset time. Cereb. Cortex
24, 956–967. 10.1093/cercor/bhs37723236208Dehaene-LambertzG.DehaeneS. (1994). Speed and cerebral correlates of syllable discrimination in infants. Nature
370, 292–295. 10.1038/370292a08035876DelormeA.MakeigS. (2004). EEGLAB: an open source toolbox for analysis of single-trial EEG dynamics including independent component analysis. J. Neurosci. Meth.
134, 9–21. 10.1016/j.jneumeth.2003.10.00915102499ForsythR.BasuA. (2015). The promotion of recovery through rehabilitation after acquired brain injury in children. Dev. Med. Child Neurol.
57, 16–22. 10.1111/dmcn.1257525200439FoxJ. P. (2010). Bayesian Item Response Modeling. Theory and Applications.
New York, NY: Springer Science+Business Media, LLC.FrançoisC.ChobertJ.BessonM.SchönD. (2013). Music training for the development of speech segmentation. Cereb. Cortex
23, 2038–2043. 10.1093/cercor/bhs18022784606GeretseggerM.ElefantC.MösslerK. A.GoldC. (2014). Music therapy for people with autism spectrum disorder. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
6:CD004381. 10.1002/14651858.CD004381.pub324936966GoldC.WigramT.ElefantC. (2006). Music therapy for autistic spectrum disorder. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
2:CD004381. 10.1002/14651858.CD004381.pub216625601GordonA. L.Di MaggioA. (2012). Rehabilitation for children after acquired brain injury: current and emerging approaches. Pediatr. Neurol.
46, 339–344. 10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2012.02.02922633627GroppeD. M.UrbachT. P.KutasM. (2011). Mass univariate analysis of event-related brain potentials/fields I: a critical tutorial review. Psychophysiology
48, 1711–1725. 10.1111/j.1469-8986.2011.01273.x21895683HobartJ. C.CanoS. J.ZajicekJ. P.ThompsonA. J. (2007). Rating scales as outcome measures for clinical trials in neurology: problems, solutions, and recommendations. Lancet Neurol.
6, 1094–1105. 10.1016/S1474-4422(07)70290-918031706HommetC.VidalJ.RouxS.BlancR.BarthezM. A.De BecqueB.. (2009). Topography of syllable change-detection electrophysiological indices in children and adults with reading disabilities. Neuropsychologia
47, 761–770. 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2008.12.01019126410Jackson-MaldonadoD.BatesE.ThalD. J. (2003). MacArthur-Bates Inventario I Primeras Palabras y Gestos. Mexico, DF: Paul H. Brookes Publishing Corp.JanataP.TillmannB.BharuchaJ. J. (2002). Listening to polyphonic music recruits domain-general attention and working memory circuits. Cogn. Affect. Behav. Neurosci.
2, 121–140. 10.3758/CABN.2.2.12112455680JasperH. H. (1958). The ten-twenty system of the international federation. Electroencephalogr. Clin. Neurophysiol.
10, 371–375.JosseD. (1997). Revised Brunet–Lezine Scale of Psychomotor Development of First Childhood.
Paris: Etablissement D'applications Psychotechniques.KaneM. J.EngleR. W. (2003). Working-memory capacity and the control of attention: the contributions of goal neglect, response competition, and task set to Stroop interference. J. Exp. Psychol. Gen.
132, 47–70. 10.1037/0096-3445.132.1.4712656297KatonaF. (1989). “Clinical neuro-developmental diagnosis and treatment,” in Challenges to Developmental Paradigms: Implications for Theory, Assessment, and Treatment, eds ZelazoP. R.BarrR. G. (Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates), 167–187. KoelschS. (2009). A neuroscientific perspective on music therapy. Ann. N.Y. Acad. Sci.
1169, 374–384. 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04592.x19673812KoelschS. (2014). Brain correlates of music-evoked emotions. Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
15, 170–180. 10.1038/nrn366624552785KorpilahtiP.KrauseC. M.HolopainenI.LangA. H. (2001). Early and late mismatch negativity elicited by words and speech-like stimuli in children. Brain Lang.
76, 332–339. 10.1006/brln.2000.242611247648KrausN.ChandrasekaranB. (2010). Music training for the development of auditory skills. Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
11, 599–605. 10.1038/nrn288220648064KujalaT.NäätänenR. (2010). The adaptive brain: a neurophysiological perspective. Prog. Neurobiol.
91, 55–67. 10.1016/j.pneurobio.2010.01.00620117165LepistöT.KajanderM.VanhalaR.AlkuP.HuotilainenM.NäätänenR.. (2008). The perception of invariant speech features in children with autism. Biol. Psychol.
77, 25–31. 10.1016/j.biopsycho.2007.08.01017919805LiuH. M.ChenY.TsaoF. M. (2014). Developmental changes in mismatch responses to Mandarin consonants and lexical tones from early to middle childhood. PLoS ONE
9:e95587. 10.1371/journal.pone.009558724755999LuoS.MaJ.KieburtzK. D. (2013). Robust Bayesian inference for multivariate longitudinal data by using normal/independent distributions. Stat. Med.
32, 3812–3828. 10.1002/sim.577823494809MaurerU.BucherK.BremS.BenzR.KranzF.SchulzE.. (2009). Neurophysiology in preschool improves behavioral prediction of reading ability throughout primary school. Biol. Psychiat.
66, 341–348. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.02.03119423082MaurerU.BucherK.BremS.BrandeisD. (2003). Altered responses to tone and phoneme mismatch in kindergartners at familial dyslexia risk. Neuroreport
14, 2245–2250. 10.1097/00001756-200312020-0002214625456MrázováM.CelecP. (2010). A systematic review of randomized controlled trials using music therapy for children. J. Altern. Complem. Med.
16, 1089–1095. 10.1089/acm.2009.043020932195MünteT.AltenmüllerE.JänckeL. (2002). The musician's brain as a model of neuroplasticity. Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
3, 473–478. 10.1038/nrn84312042882NäätänenR.GaillardA. W.MäntysaloS. (1978). Early selective-attention effect on evoked potential reinterpreted. Acta Psychol. 42, 313–329. 10.1016/0001-6918(78)90006-9685709NäätänenR.KujalaT.KreegipuuK.CarlsonS.EsceraC.BaldewegT.. (2011). The mismatch negativity: an index of cognitive decline in neuropsychiatric and neurological diseases and in ageing. Brain
134, 3432–3450. 10.1093/brain/awr06421624926NäätänenR.PaavilainenP.RinneT.AlhoK. (2007). The mismatch negativity (MMN) in basic research of central auditory processing: a review. Clin. Neurophysiol.
118, 2544–2590. 10.1016/j.clinph.2007.04.02617931964NicholsE.HolmesA. (2001). Non parametric permutation test for functional neuroimaging: a primer with examples. Hum. Brain Mapp.
15, 1–25. 10.1002/hbm.105811747097ParkM.GutyrchikE.BaoY.ZaytsevaY.CarlP.WelkerL.. (2014). Differences between musicians and non-musicians in neuro-affective processing of sadness and fear expressed in music. Neurosci. Lett.
566, 120–124. 10.1016/j.neulet.2014.02.04124582901Pascual-MarquiR. D.Gonzalez-AndinoS. L.Valdes-SosaP. A.Biscay-LirioR. (1988). Current source density estimation and interpolation based on the spherical harmonic Fourier expansion. Int. J. Neurosci.
43, 237–249. 10.3109/002074588089861753243682Pascual-MarquiR. D.MichelC. M.LehmanD. (1994). Low resolution electromagnetic tomography: a new method for localizing electrical activity of the brain. Int. J. Psychophysiol.
18, 49–65. 10.1016/0167-8760(84)90014-X7876038PernetC.ChauveauN.GasparC.RousseletG. (2011). LIMO EEG: a toolbox for hierarchical LInear MOdeling of electroencephalographic data. Comput. Intell. Neurosci.
2011:831409. 10.1155/2011/83140921403915Portellano PerezJ. A.Martinez AriasM.delR.Mateos MateosR. (2000). Cuestionario de Madurez Neuropsicológica Infantil. Cumanin. Madrid: Tea Ediciones.PutkinenV. (2014). Musical Activities and the Development of Neural Sound Discrimination. Ph.D. dissertation, University of Helsinki. Available online at: https://helda.helsinki.fi/handle/10138/42756RavenJ. (1938). Progressive Matrices: A Perceptual Test of Intelligence. London: HK Lewis.RiviereA. (2004). IDEA: Inventario de espectro autista. Buenos Aires: FUNDEC Available online at: http://www.casadellibro.com/libro-idea-inventario-de-espectro-autista-incluye-cd-rom/9789879225110/950349Rodriguez-FornellsA.RojoN.AmengualL.RipollésP.AltenmüllerE. (2012). The involvement of audio–motor coupling in the music-supported therapy applied to stroke patients. Ann. N.Y. Acad. Sci.
1252, 282–293. 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2011.06425.x22524370Rosselli-CockM.Matute-VillaseñorE.Ardila-ArdilaA.Botero-GómezV. E.Tangarife-SalazarG. A.Echeverría-PulidoS. E. (2004). Evaluación neuropsicológica infantil (ENI): una batería para la evaluación de niños entre 5 y 16 años de edad. Estudio normativo colombiano. Rev. Neurol.
38, 720–731.15122541RushworthM. F.BehrensT. E.RudebeckP. H.WaltonM. E. (2007). Contrasting roles for cingulate and orbitofrontal cortex in decisions and social behaviour. Trends Cogn. Sci.
11, 168–176. 10.1016/j.tics.2007.01.00417337237SchellenbergE. G. (2011). Examining the association between music lessons and intelligence. Br. J. Psychol. 102, 283–302. 10.1111/j.2044-8295.2010.02000.x21751987ShackmanA. J.SalomonsT. V.SlagterH. A.FoxA. S.WinterJ. J.DavidsonR. J. (2011). The integration of negative affect, pain and cognitive control in the cingulate cortex. Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
12, 154–167. 10.1038/nrn299421331082StegemöllerE. L. (2014). Exploring a neuroplasticity model of music therapy. J. Music Ther.
51, 211–227. 10.1093/jmt/thu02325316915ThautM. H. (2005). Rhythm, Music and the Brain: Scientific Foundations and Clinical Applications. New York, NY: Routledge.ThautM. H.HoembergV. (eds.). (2014). Handbook of Neurologic Music Therapy.
New York, NY: Oxford University Press.ThautM. H.McintoshG. C. (2010). How Music Helps to Heal the Injured Brain: Therapeutic Use Crescendos Thanks to Advances in Brain Science. Cerebrum. Available online at: http://dana.org/news/cerebrum/detail.aspx?id=26122Tzourio-MazoyerN.LandeauB.PapathanassiouD.CrivelloF.EtardO.DelcroixN.. (2002). Automated anatomical labeling of activations in SPM using a macroscopic anatomical parcellation of the MNI MRI single-subject brain. Neuroimage
15, 273–289. 10.1006/nimg.2001.097811771995Valdes-SosaP. A.RoebroeckA.DaunizeauJ.FristonK. (2011). Neuroimage effective connectivity: influence, causality and biophysical modeling. Neuroimage
58, 339–361. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.03.05821477655WechslerD. (1974). WISC-R Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children, Revised. New York, NY: Psychological Corporation.YingerO. S.GoodingL. (2014). Music therapy and music medicine for children and adolescents. Child Adolesc. Psychiatr. Clin. N. Am.
23, 535–553. 10.1016/j.chc.2013.03.00324975624ZatorreR. J. (2013). Predispositions and plasticity in music and speech learning: Neural correlates and implications. Science
342, 585–589. 10.1126/science.123841424179219
