<?xml version="1.0"?>
Neuroimage ClinNeuroimage ClinNeuroImage : Clinical2213-1582Elsevier3777772S2213-1582(12)00033-210.1016/j.nicl.2012.11.004ArticleThalamic medial dorsal nucleus atrophy in medial temporal lobe epilepsy: A VBM meta-analysis☆BarronDaniel S.barrond@uthscsa.edua⁎FoxP. MickleaLairdAngela R.acRobinsonJennifer L.bFoxPeter T.adaResearch Imaging Institute, UT Health Science Center, San Antonio, TX, USAbScott &amp; White, Temple, TX, USAcFlorida International University, Miami, FL, USAdSouth Texas Veteran's Health Care System, San Antonio, TX, USA⁎Corresponding author at: Research Imaging Institute; 8403 Floyd Curl Drive; San Antonio, TX 78229. Tel.: + 1 210 567 8150. barrond@uthscsa.edu16112012161120122013225321092012201020128112012© 2013 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.2012This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.PurposeMedial temporal lobe epilepsy (MTLE) is associated with MTLE network pathology within and beyond the hippocampus. The purpose of this meta-analysis was to identify consistent MTLE structural change to guide subsequent targeted analyses of these areas.MethodsWe performed an anatomic likelihood estimation (ALE) meta-analysis of 22 whole-brain voxel-based morphometry experiments from 11 published studies. We grouped these experiments in three ways. We then constructed a meta-analytic connectivity model (MACM) for regions of consistent MTLE structural change as reported by the ALE analysis.Key findingsALE reported spatially consistent structural change across VBM studies only in the epileptogenic hippocampus and the bilateral thalamus; within the thalamus, the medial dorsal nucleus of the thalamus (MDN thalamus) represented the greatest convergence (P &lt; 0.05 corrected for multiple comparisons). The subsequent MACM for the hippocampus and ipsilateral MDN thalamus demonstrated that the hippocampus and ipsilateral MDN thalamus functionally co-activate and are nodes within the same network, suggesting that MDN thalamic damage could result from MTLE network excitotoxicity.SignificanceNotwithstanding our large sample of studies, these findings are more restrictive than previous reports and demonstrate the utility of our inclusion filters and of recently modified meta-analytic methods in approximating clinical relevance. Thalamic pathology is commonly observed in animal and human studies, suggesting it could be a clinically useful indicator. Thalamus-specific research as a clinical marker awaits further investigation.Highlights► Meta-analyzed 11 studies of pathology in medial temporal lobe epilepsy (MTLE). ► The bilateral thalamus is the most consistent extra-hippocampal pathology. ► Within the thalamus, the medial dorsal nucleus (MDN) was the most significant. ► We suggest the MDN thalamus as a target for future studies in MTLE. ► We recommend these modified methods for future VBM meta-analyses.KeywordsHippocampal sclerosisCortical localizationVolumetric MRIAll epilepsy/seizures1IntroductionMedial temporal lobe epilepsy (MTLE) is the most common epilepsy referred to surgical centers and the most common localization-related epilepsy in adults (Téllez-Zenteno and Hernández-Ronquillo, 2012). Hippocampal sclerosis (HS) is the most common pathology in MTLE (also MTLE-HS) and, by diagnostic definition, is the primary site of seizure onset (Wieser and ILAE Commission on Neurosurgery of Epilepsy, 2004). When it is the sole pathology observed, HS is a predictor of positive surgical outcome (Engel, 2008). Conversely, additional extra-hippocampal pathology is a predictor of poor surgical outcome (Thom et al., 2010). Group-averaged morphometric techniques, however, demonstrate that areas of subtle extra-hippocampal pathology often go undetected on visual inspection of individual subjects. These morphometric techniques have also correlated subtle extra-hippocampal pathology with poor surgical outcome (Thom et al., 2010). If an area of consistent extra-hippocampal pathology could be identified across group-averaged studies of MTLE-HS patients, this could inform a targeted, quantitative analysis on the single-subject level. The purpose of this paper is to determine where extra-hippocampal pathology is most consistent across group-averaged studies of MTLE-HS patients.Voxel-based morphometry (VBM) is a group-averaged morphometric technique used to survey the brain for subtle structural change not observed on visual analysis (Ashburner and Friston, 2000). Many studies have used VBM to localize MTLE-related structural change in both whole-brain and region-specific analyses. VBM studies in MTLE patients constitute a large body of quantitative literature that reports many areas of focal structural change throughout the brain. While the results of voxel-based techniques are not as intuitive as other modalities (e.g. cortical thinning) and criticisms of VBM methods have been reported, the extensive VBM literature permits a robust meta-analysis with a high level of statistical rigor. Furthermore, meta-analytic methods that take advantage of results reported in a standardized, coordinate space are particularly well suited for VBM meta-analysis. Because similar meta-analytic methods do not exist for other morphometric modalities, VBM literature presents a unique opportunity to localize consistent structural change across a large number of independent studies.Coordinate-based meta-analytic methods are a rapidly evolving field. Anatomic likelihood estimation (ALE) is a well-validated and frequently used coordinate-based meta-analytic technique. At the time of writing, the Eickhoff et al. (2012) ALE algorithm is the latest refinement of the ALE algorithm (see online supplementary materials) and offers unprecedented rigor in identifying which regions and pathways demonstrate the most consistent structural change in MTLE (Eickhoff et al., 2012). Here, we used the Eickhoff et al. (2012) ALE algorithm to quantify consistent structural change from 22 whole-brain VBM experiments representing 519 MTLE patients with unilateral HS. We then used meta-analytic connectivity modeling (MACM) (Robinson et al., 2012) to determine hippocampal co-activation patterns and to evaluate whether areas reported in the VBM meta-analysis could function as nodes in the MTLE epileptogenic network.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0030"><label>2.1</label><title>Paper inclusion filters</title><p>We adopted both standard and MTLE-specific paper retrieval filters in selecting papers for inclusion in our meta-analysis (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). (<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Fox et al., 2005a</xref>) The main inclusion criterion was that all studies be whole-brain VBM analyses. We chose an additional criterion for data non-redundancy to avoid within-lab and sample-specific bias. Paper retrieval included an internet and a bibliographic search of relevant retrieved papers.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.2</label><title>Internet search</title><p>A pubmed.gov search cuing [(“Temporal Lobe Epilepsy” OR TLE) AND (voxel OR “voxel-based morphometry” OR VBM)] returned 164 papers (2.Apr.2012). A breakdown of papers excluded per filter from this pubmed.gov search is found in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Upon request, <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Pail et al. (2010)</xref> supplied previously unreported VBM foci for inclusion in our meta-analysis.</p><p>An OVID search using the same search function with limits to “abstracts,” “English language,” and “all adult (19 plus years)” returned 235 papers (2.Apr.2012). No additional papers were added from this search.</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.3</label><title>Bibliographic search</title><p>All bibliographies of papers that passed our filters were reviewed to find additional papers. No additional papers were added from this search. Eleven papers contained experiments that passed our inclusion filters (see <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) (<xref rid="bb0060 bb0045 bb0050 bb0065 bb0070 bb0055 bb0080 bb0085 bb0075 bb0090 bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Keller et al., 2002; Bernasconi et al., 2004; Bonilha et al., 2004; McMillan et al., 2004; Mueller et al., 2006; Bouilleret et al., 2008; Pell et al., 2008; Riederer et al., 2008; Pail et al., 2010; Santana et al., 2010; Tae et al., 2010</xref>). Our ALE meta-analysis (described below) included 22 experimental contrasts from these papers reporting 300 total foci representing 519 MTLE patients. The majority of studies reported foci in MNI space; those reported in Taiairach and Torneux space were transformed to MNI space via the icbm2tal transform (<xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Lancaster et al., 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.4</label><title>Anatomic likelihood estimation (ALE) meta-analysis procedure</title><p>Spatial concordance among the reported VBM foci was computed with the modified anatomic likelihood estimation (ALE) algorithm (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Eickhoff et al., 2012</xref>). As described in previous methods papers (<xref rid="bb0110 bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Eickhoff et al., 2009; Turkeltaub et al., 2012</xref>), to reflect the spatial uncertainty of reported VBM foci, ALE treats each VBM focus as a Gaussian probability distribution. Gaussian distributions are pooled voxel-wise first within experimental contrasts, then across contrasts within a group to create a whole-brain ALE map. Within this whole-brain ALE map, each voxel is assigned a unique ALE value that represents the likelihood of experimental effects (e.g. gray matter structural change) in that voxel. To reflect the random spatial association between different experiments, ALE maps are tested against a null distribution and are thresholded to a user-specified statistical value. Voxels that pass this statistical threshold are reported as ALE clusters of significant meta-analytic convergence. Recent improvements to the ALE algorithm include: statistical limitations on the effects individual foci can have across experiments and groups (<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Turkeltaub et al., 2012</xref>); an analytic, data-driven approach in creating the null-distribution used in statistical inference (previously an empirical permutation process) (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Eickhoff et al., 2012</xref>); and a Monte-Carlo based approach to permit more accurate cluster-level inference (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Eickhoff et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, as used in our analysis, the <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Eickhoff et al. (2012)</xref> algorithm represents the latest in coordinate-based meta-analysis. All ALE analyses were carried out in GingerALE 2.2, (brainmap.org/ale/index.html) using the Cluster-Level threshold (P &lt; 0.05) with a false discovery rate of (pN, P &lt; 0.05).</p><p>We analyzed the 300 VBM foci in 3 groups. To analyze convergence between hemispheres across groups, we rectified L-MTLE VBM foci to the opposite hemisphere by changing the sign of the x-coordinate and concatenating rectified L-MTLE with reported R-MTLE VBM foci. This produced one rectified L + R-MTLE group (Rct). We analyzed convergence between groups across hemispheres in separate R-MTLE (R) and L-MTLE (L) groups.</p></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>2.5</label><title>MACM procedure</title><p>Meta-analytic connectivity modeling (MACM) is a meta-analytic technique that investigates whole-brain coactivation patterns for a user-specified region of interest (ROI) (<xref rid="bb0115 bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2010; Robinson et al., 2012</xref>). BrainMap is a neuroimaging database reporting whole-brain functional activation patterns in healthy subjects (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Fox et al., 2005b</xref>). To determine hippocampal connectivity patterns, we used L and R hippocampal ROIs defined by the Talairach Daemon (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Lancaster et al., 2000</xref>) and searched the BrainMap database for studies reporting activations within these ROIs (search performed 28.April.2012). We only included retrieved studies reporting results in healthy controls. We integrated whole brain activation patterns from these studies using the ALE method, yielding a MACM-ALE map of significant co-activations (FDR pN p &lt; 0.05). MACM-ALE maps have been validated with diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) and connectivity atlases (CocoMac) (<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2010</xref>) and have been demonstrated to be the meta-analytic equivalent of resting-state functional connectivity maps (<xref rid="bb0130 bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Laird et al., 2009; Smith et al., 2009</xref>).</p></sec></sec>Disclosure of conflicts of interestThe authors have no conflicts of interest to report.We confirm that we have read the Journal's position on issues involved in ethical publication and affirm that this report is consistent with those guidelines.ReferencesAggletonJ.P.O'MaraS.M.VannS.D.WrightN.F.TsanovM.Hippocampal–anterior thalamic pathways for memory: uncovering a network of direct and indirect actionsThe European Journal of Neuroscience3120102292230720550571AshburnerJ.FristonK.J.Voxel-based morphometry — the methodsNeuroImage11200080582110860804BartolomeiF.KhalilM.WendlingF.SontheimerA.RegisJ.Entorhinal cortex involvement in human mesial temporal lobe epilepsy: an electrophysiologic and volumetric studyEpilepsia46200567768715857433BehrensT.E.Johansen-BergH.WoolrichM.W.SmithS.M.Wheeler-KingshottC.A.Non-invasive mapping of connections between human thalamus and cortex using diffusion imagingNature Neuroscience62003750757BernasconiN.DuchesneS.JankeA.LerchJ.CollinsD.L.Whole-brain voxel-based statistical analysis of gray matter and white matter in temporal lobe epilepsyNeuroImage23200471772315488421BernhardtB.C.WorsleyK.J.BessonP.ConchaL.LerchJ.P.Mapping limbic network organization in temporal lobe epilepsy using morphometric correlations: insights on the relation between mesiotemporal connectivity and cortical atrophyNeuroImage42200851552418554926BernhardtB.C.BernasconiN.KimH.BernasconiA.Mapping thalamocortical network pathology in temporal lobe epilepsyNeurology78201212913622205759BertramE.H.ScottC.The pathological substrate of limbic epilepsy: neuronal loss in the medial dorsal thalamic nucleus as the consistent changeEpilepsia41Suppl. 62000S3S810999511BertramE.H.ZhangD.WilliamsonJ.M.Multiple roles of midline dorsal thalamic nuclei in induction and spread of limbic seizuresEpilepsia49200825626818028408BettusG.BartolomeiF.Confort-GounyS.GuedjE.ChauvelP.Role of resting state functional connectivity MRI in presurgical investigation of mesial temporal lobe epilepsyJournal of Neurology, Neurosurgery, and Psychiatry81201011471154BlumckeI.PauliE.ClusmannH.SchrammJ.BeckerA.A new clinico-pathological classification system for mesial temporal sclerosisActa Neuropathologica113200723524417221203BonilhaL.RordenC.CastellanoG.PereiraF.RioP.A.Voxel-based morphometry reveals gray matter network atrophy in refractory medial temporal lobe epilepsyArchives of Neurology6120041379138415364683BouilleretV.SemahF.ChassouxF.MantzaridezM.BirabenA.Basal ganglia involvement in temporal lobe epilepsy: a functional and morphologic studyNeurology70200817718418195263DeasyN.P.JaroszJ.M.ElwesR.C.PolkeyC.E.CoxT.C.Thalamic changes with mesial temporal sclerosis: MRINeuroradiology42200034635110872154DelasiauveL.J.F.Traité de l'épilepsie1854Libraire de Victor MassonParisEickhoffS.B.LairdA.R.GrefkesC.WangL.E.ZillesK.Coordinate-based activation likelihood estimation meta-analysis of neuroimaging data: a random-effects approach based on empirical estimates of spatial uncertaintyHuman Brain Mapping3020092907292619172646EickhoffS.B.BzdokD.LairdA.R.KurthF.FoxP.T.Activation likelihood estimation meta-analysis revisitedNeuroImage5920122349236121963913EngelJ.Jr.Surgical treatment for epilepsy: too little, too late?JAMA: The Journal of the American Medical Association30020082548255019050199FisherR.SalanovaV.WittT.WorthR.HenryT.Electrical stimulation of the anterior nucleus of thalamus for treatment of refractory epilepsyEpilepsia51201089990820331461FoxP.T.LairdA.R.LancasterJ.L.Coordinate-based voxel-wise meta-analysis: dividends of spatial normalization. report of a virtual workshopHuman Brain Mapping2520051515846826FoxP.T.LairdA.R.FoxS.P.FoxP.M.UeckerA.M.BrainMap taxonomy of experimental design: description and evaluationHuman Brain Mapping25200518519815846810GuyeM.RegisJ.TamuraM.WendlingF.McGonigalA.The role of corticothalamic coupling in human temporal lobe epilepsyBrain: A Journal of Neurology12920061917192816760199KellerS.S.RobertsN.Voxel-based morphometry of temporal lobe epilepsy: an introduction and review of the literatureEpilepsia49200874175718177358KellerS.S.WieshmannU.C.MackayC.E.DenbyC.E.WebbJ.Voxel based morphometry of grey matter abnormalities in patients with medically intractable temporal lobe epilepsy: effects of side of seizure onset and epilepsy durationJournal of Neurology, Neurosurgery, and Psychiatry732002648655LairdA.R.McMillanK.M.LancasterJ.L.KochunovP.TurkeltaubP.E.A comparison of label-based review and ALE meta-analysis in the stroop taskHuman Brain Mapping25200562115846823LairdA.R.EickhoffS.B.LiK.RobinD.A.GlahnD.C.Investigating the functional heterogeneity of the default mode network using coordinate-based meta-analytic modelingThe Journal of Neuroscience: The Official Journal of the Society for Neuroscience292009144961450519923283LancasterJ.L.WoldorffM.G.ParsonsL.M.LiottiM.FreitasC.S.Automated talairach atlas labels for functional brain mappingHuman Brain Mapping10200012013110912591LancasterJ.L.Tordesillas-GutierrezD.MartinezM.SalinasF.EvansA.Bias between MNI and talairach coordinates analyzed using the ICBM-152 brain templateHuman Brain Mapping2820071194120517266101LavenexP.AmaralD.G.Hippocampal-neocortical interaction: a hierarchy of associativityHippocampus10200042043010985281LiJ.ZhangZ.ShangH.A meta-analysis of voxel-based morphometry studies on unilateral refractory temporal lobe epilepsyEpilepsy Research9820129710322024190MargerisonJ.H.CorsellisJ.A.Epilepsy and the temporal lobes. A clinical, electroencephalographic and neuropathological study of the brain in epilepsy, with particular reference to the temporal lobesBrain: A Journal of Neurology8919664995305922048McMillanA.B.HermannB.P.JohnsonS.C.HansenR.R.SeidenbergM.Voxel-based morphometry of unilateral temporal lobe epilepsy reveals abnormalities in cerebral white matterNeuroImage23200416717415325363MuellerS.G.LaxerK.D.CashdollarN.BuckleyS.PaulC.Voxel-based optimized morphometry (VBM) of gray and white matter in temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE) with and without mesial temporal sclerosisEpilepsia47200690090716686655PailM.BrazdilM.MarecekR.MiklM.An optimized voxel-based morphometric study of gray matter changes in patients with left-sided and right-sided mesial temporal lobe epilepsy and hippocampal sclerosis (MTLE/HS)Epilepsia51201051151819817822PellG.S.BriellmannR.S.PardoeH.AbbottD.F.JacksonG.D.Composite voxel-based analysis of volume and T2 relaxometry in temporal lobe epilepsyNeuroImage3920081151116118042496PieperS.LorensenB.SchroederW.KikinisR.The NA-MIC kit: ITK, VTK, pipelines, grids and 3D slicer as an open platform for the medical image computing communityProceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging: From Nano to Macro12006698701RiedererF.LanzenbergerR.KayaM.PrayerD.SerlesW.Network atrophy in temporal lobe epilepsy: a voxel-based morphometry studyNeurology71200841942518678824RobinsonJ.L.LairdA.R.GlahnD.C.LovalloW.R.FoxP.T.Metaanalytic connectivity modeling: delineating the functional connectivity of the human amygdalaHuman Brain Mapping31201017318419603407RobinsonJ.L.LairdA.R.GlahnD.C.BlangeroJ.SangheraM.K.The functional connectivity of the human caudate: an application of meta-analytic connectivity modeling with behavioral filteringNeuroImage60201211712922197743RosenbergD.S.MauguiereF.DemarquayG.RyvlinP.IsnardJ.Involvement of medial pulvinar thalamic nucleus in human temporal lobe seizuresEpilepsia4720069810716417537RosenbergD.S.MauguiereF.CatenoixH.FaillenotI.MagninM.Reciprocal thalamocortical connectivity of the medial pulvinar: a depth stimulation and evoked potential study in human brainCerebral cortex (New York, N.Y.: 1991)19200914621473SantanaM.T.JackowskiA.P.da SilvaH.H.CabocloL.O.CentenoR.S.Auras and clinical features in temporal lobe epilepsy: a new approach on the basis of voxel-based morphometryEpilepsy Research89201032733820223639SmithS.M.FoxP.T.MillerK.L.GlahnD.C.FoxP.M.Correspondence of the brain's functional architecture during activation and restProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America1062009130401304519620724SpencerS.S.When should temporal-lobe epilepsy be treated surgically?Lancet Neurology1200237538212849399SpencerS.S.WilliamsonP.D.SpencerD.D.MattsonR.H.Human hippocampal seizure spread studied by depth and subdural recording: the hippocampal commissureEpilepsia2819874794893653050SpencerS.S.MarksD.KatzA.KimJ.SpencerD.D.Anatomic correlates of interhippocampal seizure propagation timeEpilepsia3319928628731396429TaeW.S.JooE.Y.KimS.T.HongS.B.Gray, white matter concentration changes and their correlation with heterotopic neurons in temporal lobe epilepsyKorean Journal of Radiology: Official Journal of the Korean Radiological Society112010253620046492Téllez-ZentenoJ.F.Hernández-RonquilloL.A review of the epidemiology of temporal lobe epilepsyEpilepsy Research and Treatment201220125ThomM.MathernG.W.CrossJ.H.BertramE.H.Mesial temporal lobe epilepsy: how do we improve surgical outcome?Annals of Neurology68201042443420976764TurkeltaubP.E.EickhoffS.B.LairdA.R.FoxM.WienerM.Minimizing within-experiment and within-group effects in activation likelihood estimation meta-analysesHuman Brain Mapping33201211321305667VertesR.P.HooverW.B.Szigeti-BuckK.LeranthC.Nucleus reuniens of the midline thalamus: link between the medial prefrontal cortex and the hippocampusBrain Research Bulletin71200760160917292803WieserH.G.ILAE Commission on Neurosurgery of EpilepsyILAE commission report. mesial temporal lobe epilepsy with hippocampal sclerosisEpilepsia45200469571415144438AcknowledgmentsWe thank Kristin S. Budde for her valuable edits. We also thank Kimberly Ray and Juan Saenz for their technical assistance. This study was supported by funds from the National Institute of Health (NIMH: RO1 MH074457).☆This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.Fig. 1Significant areas of convergence in the VBM-ALE analysis in rectified (A), right medial temporal lobe epilepsy (B), and left medial temporal lobe epilepsy (C) groups. MACM analyses (D) of the left (green) and right (red) hippocampal tissue labels; note co-activation in the medial dorsal nucleus thalamus. All clusters thresholded at P &lt; 0.05, corrected for multiple comparisons. See Supplementary materials for full montages of (A), (B) and (C).Table 1Inclusion filters and papers eliminated by each filter for the pubmed.gov search.FilterDescriptionJustificationNumber of papersNumber eliminatedInternet search[(“Temporal Lobe Epilepsy” OR TLE) AND (voxel OR “voxel-based morphometry” OR VBM)]164RelevancePublished in English-language, peer-reviewed journals; reporteda x–y–z foci from whole-brain VBM (modulated or unmodulated) analyses in MNI or T&amp;T spaceStandard relevance criteria (Fox et al., 2005a,b)164142MTLE-HS diagnosisPre-surgical adult MTLE with unilateral HS verified with EEG, structural MRI, and/or post-surgical histologyThe majority of papers reported this diagnostic criteria221Experimental ContrastAnalyses of gray matter reduction in separate R and L-MTLE populations compared to healthy controls, unregressed for other variables. (P &lt; 0.05, uncorr. or more stringent)Excluded analyses included white matter reduction, R vs L-MTLE, and regressions for aura, disease duration, etc.218Non-redundancyOnly one contrast per paper per group per patient populationSome groups reported multiple analyses of a patient population within and across papers132TOTAL11TLE = temporal lobe epilepsy; VBM = voxel-based morphometry; MNI = Montreal Neurological Institute; T&amp;T = Talairach and Tournoux; MTLE = medial temporal lobe epilepsy; HS = hippocampal sclerosis; R = right; L = left.aUpon request, Pell et al. (2008) supplied previously unreported foci.Table 2Overview of included studies.Papern (L-MTLE)n (R-MTLE)n (controls)AgeaL-MTLE focibR-MTLE focibVBM analysisSmoothing kernelSignificance levelcDiagnosis of TLE according todUnilateral HS?Patient typeSoftware: templateBernasconi et al., 200445404735 ± 102613UM5 mm FWHMP (corr.) &lt; 0.05video-EEG monitoring + HSYesUnspecifiedINSECT: MNIBonilha et al., 200422214932 ± 82014UMUnspecifiedP (uncor.) &lt; .0589' ILAE CriteriaYesOutpatientsSPM2: MNIBouilleret et al., 20081203036 ± 10120M12 mm FWHMP (uncorr.) &lt; 0.001EEG-monitor; structural MRIYesUnspecifiedSPM2:T&amp;TKeller et al., 2002585858341413UM10 mm FWHMP (corr.) &lt; 0.05Scalp + Invasive EEGUnspecifiedPre-surgicalSPM99:T&amp;TMcMillan et al., 200413126232.2 ± 11715M12 mm FWHMP (corr.) &lt; 0.05video-EEG monitoring + HSYesPre-SurgicalSPM2: MNIMueller et al., 20060263035.6 ± 9.7033 (R + Rct L)M + UM8 mm FWHMP (corr.) &lt; 0.05Video-EEG TelemetryYesPre-surgicalSPM2: MNIPail et al., 201020204039.5 ± 9.7611MUnspecifiedP (corr.) &lt; 0.001, 100 voxels89' ILAE CriteriaYesUnspecifiedSPM2: MNIPell et al., 200819011539.3 ± 12180M6 mm FWHMP (corr.) &lt; 0.05Institutional CriteriaYesPre-surgicalSPM2: MNIRiederer et al., 20089131238 ± 11103M4 mm FWHMP (uncorr.) &lt; 0.001Video-EEG + HSYesPre-surgicalSPM2: MNISantana et al., 201059413037.291610M8 mm FWHMP (uncorr.) &lt; 0.001Video-EEG TelemetryYesPre-surgicalSPM5: MNITae et al., 2010161547R: 29L: 332831M + UM8 mm FWHMP (corr.) &lt; 0.05EEG monitoring + HSYesPre-surgicalSPM2: MNITotal273246520157143L-MTLE = left medial temporal lobe epilepsy; R-MTLE = right medial temporal lobe epilepsy; MNI = Montreal Neuroimaging Institute; FWHM = Full Width at Half Maximum; Corr. = corrected; Uncorr. = Uncorrected; HS = hippocampal sclerosis; UM = unmodified; M = Modified; Rct = Rectified (consult methods for further explanation); T&amp;T = Talairach and Tournoux.aOf MTLE patients. Presented in mean ± SD(range) years.bFoci listed report gray matter reduction only.cSignificance levels reported on whole-brain level.dTerminology used in the original articles.Table 3Anatomic likelihood estimation (ALE) summary for Rct, L-MTLE, and R-MTLE analyses.Cluster #LabelVolume (mm3)Weighted center (x, y, z)ALE Mx (× 102)Total foci% RepRct1IHippocampus211232− 16− 187.82377%2BThalamus16320− 1793.71855%– Med Dorsal Nuc3.7– Vent Post Med Nuc3.43ILimbic Lobe.BA 3017625− 3813.2314%LTLE1IHippocampus904− 31− 16− 184.8764%2IThalamus. Med Dorsal Nuc1603− 1652.5327%RTLE1IHippocampus118434− 17− 173.51282%2CThalamus. Vent Post Med Nuc200− 14− 1772.5218%Rct = Rectified (R-MTLE foci + L-MTLE foci rectified to R hemisphere); L = left medial temporal lobe epilepsy; R = right medial temporal lobe epilepsy; ALEmx = maximum ALE score for listed cluster; B = bilateral; I = ipsilateral to epileptogenic hippocampus; C = contralateral to epileptogenic hippocampus; % Rep = number of studies contributing VBM foci to ALE cluster/number of total studies.All (x, y, z) foci are reported in Montreal Neuroimaging Institute (MNI) space.All tissue labels are derived from the Talairach Daemon.Table 4Conditional probability of observing thalamic and hippocampal structural changes. We tabulated whether each VBM experiment reported structural change (as an x, y, z focus) within each of our reported ALE clusters. It should be noted that the conditional probability that each VBM experiment reported both author-labeled thalamic and hippocampal structural change was 1.0, i.e. thalamic and hippocampal labels were co-reported in 100% of experiments.Number of fociProbability (P)RctReport Hipp Struct ChangeHipp = 7P(Hipp) = 0.32Report Thal Struct ChangeThal = 2P(Thal) = 0.09Report BothHipp&amp;Thal = 10P(Hipp&amp;Thal) = 0.45Report Hipp, Thal, or Hipp&amp;ThalTotal = 19P(Hipp OR Thal OR Hipp&amp;Thal) = 0.86  L-MTLEReport Hipp Struct ChangeHipp = 6P(Hipp) = 0.55Report Thal Struct ChangeThal = 2P(Thal) = 0.18Report BothHipp&amp;Thal = 1P(Hipp&amp;Thal) = 0.09Report Hipp, Thal, or Hipp&amp;ThalTotal = 9P(Hipp OR Thal OR Hipp&amp;Thal) = 0.82  R-MTLEReport Hipp Struct ChangeHipp = 8P(Hipp) = 0.36Report Thal Struct ChangeThal = 1P(Thal) = 0.05Report BothHipp&amp;Thal = 1P(Hipp&amp;Thal) = 0.05Report Hipp, Thal, or Hipp&amp;ThalTotal = 10P(Hipp OR Thal OR Hipp&amp;Thal) = 0.45Rct = rectified (R-MTLE foci + L-MTLE foci rectified to R hemisphere); L = left medial temporal lobe epilepsy; R = right medial temporal lobe epilepsy; Struct = Structural; Hipp = Hippocampus; Thal = Thalamus.
