<?xml version="1.0"?>
Biol PsychiatryBiol. PsychiatryBiological Psychiatry0006-32231873-2402Elsevier2734077S0006-3223(09)00570-810.1016/j.biopsych.2009.04.036Archival ReportDorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex Activity Predicts Responsiveness to Cognitive–Behavioral Therapy in SchizophreniaKumariVeenav.kumari@iop.kcl.ac.ukad⁎PetersEmmanuelle R.adFannonDominicbAntonovaElenaaPremkumarPreethiaAnilkumarAnantha P.bWilliamsSteven C.R.cKuipersElizabethadaDepartment of Psychology, Institute of Psychiatry, King's College London, United KingdombDivision of Psychological Medicine, Institute of Psychiatry, King's College London, United KingdomcCentre for Neuroimaging Sciences, Institute of Psychiatry, King's College London, United KingdomdNational Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Biomedical Research Centre for Mental Health, South London and Maudsley National Health Service Foundation Trust, London, United Kingdom⁎Address correspondence to Veena Kumari, Ph.D., PO78, Institute of Psychiatry, King's College London, De Crespigny Park, London SE5 8AF, United Kingdom v.kumari@iop.kcl.ac.uk159200915920096665946022210200824320092142009© 2009 Elsevier Inc.2009Society of Biological PsychiatryOpen Access under CC BY 4.0 licenseBackgroundGiven the variable response to cognitive–behavioral therapy (CBT) when added to antipsychotic medication in psychosis and the evidence for a role of pretherapy level of frontal lobe–based cognitive function in responsiveness to CBT in other disorders, this study examined whether pretherapy brain activity associated with working memory neural network predicts clinical responsiveness to CBT in schizophrenia.MethodsFifty-two outpatients stable on medication with at least one distressing symptom of schizophrenia and willing to receive CBT in addition to their usual treatment and 20 healthy participants underwent functional magnetic resonance imaging during a parametric n-back task. Subsequently, 26 patients received CBT for psychosis (CBT+treatment-as-usual [TAU], 19 completers) for 6–8 months, and 26 continued with TAU alone (17 completers). Symptoms in both patient groups were assessed (blindly) at entry and follow-up.ResultsThe CBT+TAU and TAU-alone groups did not differ clinically or in performance at baseline. The CBT+TAU group showed significant improvement in relation to the TAU-alone group, which showed no change, at follow-up. Stronger dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) activity (within the normal range) and DLPFC–cerebellum connectivity during the highest memory load condition (2-back &gt; 0-back) were associated with post-CBT clinical improvement.ConclusionsDLPFC activity and its connectivity with the cerebellum predict responsiveness to CBT for psychosis in schizophrenia. These effects may be mediated by PFC–cerebellum contributions to executive processing.Key WordsCBTcerebellumconnectivityDLPFCfMRIpsychosisschizophreniaA number of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) have demonstrated that persistent positive symptoms, particularly delusions, and secondary disturbances such as depression, are improved by cognitive–behavioral therapy for psychosis (CBT-P) in patients with schizophrenia (1–3). These effects, however, are seen with modest effect sizes and present, to a noticeable degree, in only about 50% of such patients. Given the variable response to CBT-P, it is important to elucidate the predictors of CBT efficacy for psychosis.Cognitive functions may play a role in CBT responsiveness across most disorders but perhaps more so in disorders, such as schizophrenia, which are characterized by cognitive impairment (4). Although skilled therapy adaptations attempt to compensate for such impairment, it may still hinder effectiveness of CBT, perhaps by impeding patients' ability to remember information discussed in sessions; to acquire new, more flexible thinking styles or coping strategies; or to generalize specific issues discussed in therapy to other situations in life. For example, in depression better executive functioning and problem-solving ability predict a more favorable clinical outcome following CBT, but not following treatment with antidepressant or placebo or waiting for CBT (5,6). Intact executive functioning also predicts a favorable response to CBT for generalized anxiety disorder (7). Similarly, initial cognitive flexibility predicted a better outcome in an RCT of CBT-P (8). In a recent study (9), neurocognitive deficits predicted poorer function overall in older psychotic patients but did not moderate CBT effects. The therapy in this study, however, was targeted specifically at social functioning rather than at distress and symptom reduction. In general, clinical responsiveness to CBT across disorders may relate to executive processes (5–8) modulated by the frontal lobes, especially the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) (10–12).This study tested the hypothesis, for the first time to our knowledge, that pretherapy DLPFC activity, elicited with a parametric n-back working memory (WM) task (13,14) and detected with functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), would predict clinical responsiveness to CBT-P in schizophrenia. Given known associations between impaired cognition and disrupted DLPFC connectivity in schizophrenia (15), we also examined DLPFC connectivity with other brain regions as a predictor of responsiveness to CBT-P.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1"><title>Methods and Materials</title><sec id="sec1.1"><title>Participants and Design</title><p>This investigation involved three groups. Group 1 consisted of 26 outpatients with schizophrenia (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) who received CBT-P for 6–8 months in addition to their treatment-as-usual (TAU; CBT+TAU), Group 2 of 26 outpatients with schizophrenia who received TAU during the course of this investigation (TAU alone), and Group 3 of 20 healthy participants (HC) who did not have a clinical diagnosis (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p><p>All participants were right-handed and had no history of neurological conditions or head injury. All patients 1) had been on stable doses of antipsychotics for ≥2 years and on their present antipsychotic for &gt;3 months, 2) received a rating of ≥60 on the Positive and Negative Symptoms scale (PANSS) (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and reported at least one positive “distressing” symptom, and 3) wished/agreed to receive 6–8 months of CBT-P in addition to their usual drug treatment. Patients for both (CBT+TAU, TAU-alone) groups 1) were from the same geographic area, 2) had been identified by their psychiatrists as suitable for CBT-P, and 3) wished to receive CBT in addition to their usual treatment. Those accepted for CBT-P by the Psychological Interventions Clinic for Outpatients with Psychosis (PICuP), South London and Maudsley (SLAM) National Health Service (NHS) Foundation Trust went into the CBT+TAU group; others, matched to those in the CBT+TAU group as much as possible, went into the TAU-alone group. With the resources available to the SLAM NHS Foundation Trust, only approximately 10% of eligible patients are offered CBT-P. The final CBT+TAU group had 19 patients (consent withdrawal, <italic>n</italic> = 4; medication noncompliance before follow-up, <italic>n</italic> = 1; nonusable data, <italic>n</italic> = 2), and the TAU-alone group had 17 patients (consent withdrawal, <italic>n</italic> = 5; acutely unwell/admitted to a secure hospital before follow-up, <italic>n</italic> = 2; nonusable data, <italic>n</italic> = 2). <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents participants' characteristics. All participants provided written informed consent after the study procedures had been explained to them.</p><p>All participants underwent fMRI during the n-back task and clinical assessment at entry. The CBT+TAU group then received 6–8 months of CBT-P following a published manual (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) in a specialist clinical service (PICuP, SLAM NHS Foundation Trust). Therapy sessions were conducted weekly or fortnightly, as preferred by the patient, for up to 1 hour. Patients received an average of 16 sessions. All CBT interventions were formulation-driven and focused on the therapy goals of the patient. The therapists were supervised by one of two investigators (E.K. or E.R.P.). TAU-alone patients were followed up over the same period as CBT+TAU patients. Symptoms were rated in all patients, using the PANSS (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), at entry and then 6–8 months later by an experienced and independent psychiatrist (<italic>DF</italic>) who was blind to whether patients received CBT.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><title>fMRI Paradigm and Procedure</title><p>The task (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), modified from Callicott <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), involved monitoring locations of dots (presentation time: 450 msec; interstimulus-interval: 1500 msec) within a diamond-shaped box on the screen at a given delay from the original occurrence (0-back, 1-back, or 2-back; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). There were three 30-sec active conditions (0-back, 1-back, 2-back) presented to participants five times in pseudo-random order, controlling for order effect. Each active block had 15 stimulus presentations, started with a 15-sec rest block (“Rest” on the screen), and began with a 750-msec text delay allowing the participants to notice a change in task demand/condition. The experiment lasted 11.25 min. Participants viewed the paradigm projected onto a screen through a prismatic mirror. They were required to press the button on every trial, using the right thumb, corresponding to the correct location of the 0-back, 1-back, or 2-back stimulus (chance performance = 25%; location of dots purely random). Participants abstained from alcohol for at least 24 hours and underwent task familiarization before scanning.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.3"><title>Image Acquisition</title><p>Echoplanar MR brain images were acquired using a 1.5-T GE Signa system (General Electric, Milwaukee, Wisconsin). In each of 16 near-axial noncontiguous planes parallel to the intercommissural plane, 225 T2*-weighted MR images depicting blood oxygen level–dependent contrast were acquired over the experiment with echo time (TE) = 40 msec, repetition time (TR) = 3 sec, in-plane resolution = 3.1 mm, slice thickness = 7.0 mm, and interslice gap = .7 mm. In the same session, a high-resolution three-dimensional inversion recovery prepared spoiled gradient recalled acquisition in a steady state volume data set was acquired with TE = 5.3 msec, inversion time = 300 msec, TR = 12.2 msec, in-plane resolution = .94 mm, and slice thickness = 1.5 mm.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.4"><title>Data Analysis: Demographic, Clinical, and Behavioral Measures</title><p>The HC, CBT+TAU, and TAU-alone groups were compared on age, education, and predicted IQ (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) using a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), followed by mean comparisons as appropriate. Group differences in performance were examined by a Group (HC, CBT+TAU, TAU-alone) × Load (0-back, 1-back, 2-back) ANOVA (separately for accuracy [% correct responses] and latency [in msec] of correct responses) with Group as a between-subjects factor and Load as the within-subjects factor, followed by analysis of lower order effects as appropriate. A significant Group effect in latency (Results), given the potential effect of age in this measure, was reevaluated using analyses of covariance (ANCOVA), covarying for age.</p><p>The CBT+TAU and TAU-alone groups were compared on clinical variables using independent-sample <italic>t</italic> tests. The change in symptoms from baseline to follow-up was investigated using a Group (CBT+TAU, TAU-alone) × Time (baseline, follow-up) ANOVA with Group as a between-subjects factor and Time as a within-subjects factor. A significant Group × Time effect was followed up by paired <italic>t</italic> tests on total and subscale PANSS scores separately in the CBT+TAU and TAU-alone groups. Following the observation of significant symptom reduction in the CBT+TAU group, but not in the TAU-alone group, we examined potential associations between baseline symptom severity and symptom change (baseline minus follow-up) in the CBT+TAU group using Pearson's correlations and confirmed the effects of CBT-P using ANCOVAs on symptom change scores covarying for baseline symptoms. We also computed the degree of change in symptoms independent of initial severity as residual change in symptoms by regressing the initial PANSS (total and subscales) scores on follow-up scores as a further outcome measure of CBT responsiveness for fMRI analysis following the method used by Siegle and colleagues (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The association between performance variables and responsiveness to CBT was examined using Pearson's correlations.</p><p>All analyses were performed in SPSS windows (version 15). Before running the described analyses, each variable was evaluated for the normality of the distribution to ensure it met the criteria of parametric statistics. Alpha level for testing significance of effects was maintained at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.5"><title>Functional MRI: Image Pre-Processing</title><p>For each participant, the 225-volume functional time series were motion corrected, transformed into stereotactic space (Montreal Neurological Institute), smoothed with a 10 mm full-width-at-half-maximum Gaussian filter, and band-pass filtered using statistical parametric mapping software (SPM2; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm">http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.6"><title>Models and Statistical Inferences</title><p>Data were analyzed using a random-effect procedure (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Subject-specific activations were identified with a factorial model consisting of three active conditions and rest as an implicit baseline. Generic task-related activity changes were identified using one-sample <italic>t</italic> tests (height threshold, <italic>p</italic> = .001; cluster-corrected <italic>p</italic> ≤ .05) separately in CBT+TAU and HC groups.</p><p>To examine the relationship of CBT response with pretherapy brain activity in patients, we regressed residual symptom change scores on task-related activations (0-back vs. rest; 1- and 2-back vs. 0-back) across the entire brain (height threshold <italic>p</italic> = .05, cluster-corrected <italic>p</italic> ≤ 05). For the positive associations of a priori hypothesized regions in the frontal lobe with CBT responsiveness, the following significance criteria to maxima voxels of clusters that did not survive whole-brain correction for multiple comparisons were applied: 1) <italic>T</italic> value of ≥3.80 (corresponding to uncorrected voxel <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) and ≥100 contiguous voxels, and 2) survival of small volume correction (SVC) within a locally defined volume (15-mm radius sphere) with family-wise error corrected <italic>p</italic> ≤ .05. (No cluster in any other regions met this SVC criterion for positive associations with CBT response.) We explored negative associations between CBT responsiveness and pretherapy activations using a more conservative criteria (height threshold, <italic>p</italic> = .005; whole-brain cluster-corrected <italic>p</italic> ≤ .05) because we did not have a specific hypothesis or a region of interest (ROI).</p><p>To examine whether a positive association between pretherapy brain activity and CBT responsiveness reflected a hyperresponse or a stronger response within the normal range in CBT+TAU patients, we compared CBT+TAU patients and HC using two-sample <italic>t</italic> tests on 2-back &gt; 0 back contrasts (these revealed the strongest association with CBT responsiveness; see Results).</p><p>Further, we examined functional connectivity of the left and right frontal regions (that associated with CBT responsiveness in earlier analyses) with other regions as predictors of CBT responsiveness. For this purpose, the activity time series from the left DLPFC (seed −48[x], 34[y], 30[z]; this had the most consistent positive association with CBT response) and right inferior-middle PFC (seed 52[x], 24[y], and 22[z]) were extracted (2-back &gt; 0-back) and used as a regressor (separately for left and right PFC) to investigate their connectivity with other regions. The regions with significantly covarying increases or decreases in activity with the two ROIs were identified for each participant, and the group connectivity maps constructed using one-sample <italic>t</italic> tests (height threshold <italic>p</italic> = .005; cluster-corrected <italic>p</italic> ≤ .05). The relationship of CBT response with connectivity of the left and right PFC with other regions was identified by regressing residual symptom change scores on connectivity SPM maps in CBT+TAU patients (height threshold <italic>p</italic> = .005; cluster-corrected <italic>p</italic> ≤ .05).</p></sec></sec>References1PfammatterM.JunghanU.M.BrennerH.D.Efficacy of psychological therapy in schizophrenia: Conclusions from meta-analysesSchizophr Bull32suppl 12006S64S80169056342WykesT.SteelC.EverittB.TarrierN.Cognitive behavior therapy for schizophrenia: Effect sizes, clinical models, and methodological rigorSchizophr Bull342008523537179622313PillingS.BebbingtonP.KuipersE.GaretyP.GeddesJ.OrbachG.Psychological treatments in schizophrenia: I. Meta-analysis of family intervention and cognitive behaviour therapyPsychol Med322002763782121713724ReichenbergA.HarveyP.D.Neuropsychological impairments in schizophrenia: Integration of performance-based and brain imaging findingsPsychol Bull1332007833858177230325MooreyS.HoltingC.HughesP.KnynenbergP.MichaelA.Does problem solving ability predict therapy outcome in a clinical setting?Behav Cognit Psychother2920014854956JulianL.J.MohrD.C.Cognitive predictors of response to treatment for depression in multiple sclerosisJ Neuropsychiatr Clin Neurosci1820063563637MohlmanJ.GormanJ.M.The role of executive functioning in CBT: A pilot study with anxious older adultsBehav Res Ther432005447465157013568GaretyP.FowlerD.KuipersE.FreemanD.DunnG.BebbingtonP.London-East Anglia randomised controlled trial of cognitive-behavioural therapy for psychosis: II: predictors of outcomeBr J Psychiatry171199742042694635999GranholmE.McQuaidJ.R.LinkP.C.FishS.PattersonT.JesteD.V.Neuropsychological predictors of functional outcome in cognitive behavioral social skills training for older people with schizophreniaSchizophr Res10020081331431822264810CabezaR.NybergL.Imaging cognition II: An empirical review of 275 PET and fMRI studiesJ Cogn Neurosci1220001471076930411DuncanJ.OwenA.M.Common regions of the human frontal lobe recruited by diverse cognitive demandsTrends Neurosci2320004754831100646412KrawczykD.C.Contributions of the prefrontal cortex to the neural basis of human decision makingNeurosci Biobehav Rev2620026316641247984013KumariV.AasenI.TaylorP.FfytcheD.H.DasM.BarkatakiI.Neural dysfunction and violence in schizophrenia: An fMRI investigationSchizophr Res8420061441641661683214KumariV.AasenI.FfytcheD.WilliamsS.C.SharmaT.Neural correlates of adjunctive rivastigmine treatment to antipsychotics in schizophrenia: A randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind fMRI studyNeuroimage2920065455561618179215YoonJ.H.MinzenbergM.J.UrsuS.WaltersR.WendelkenC.RaglandJ.D.Association of dorsolateral prefrontal cortex dysfunction with disrupted coordinated brain activity in schizophrenia: Relationship with impaired cognition, behavioral disorganization, and global functionAm J Psychiatry1652008100610141851952716FirstM.B.SpitzerR.L.GibbonM.WilliamsJ.B.W.Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis I Disorders, Patient Edition (SCID-P), Version 21995New York State Psychiatric Institute, Biometrics ResearchNew York17FirstM.B.SpitzerR.L.GibbonM.WilliamsJ.B.W.Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV-TR Axis I Disorders, Research Version, Non-Patient Edition2002New York State Psychiatric Institute, Biometrics ResearchNew YorkSCID-I/NP18KayS.R.FiszbeinA.OplerL.A.The positive and negative syndrome scale (PANSS) for schizophreniaSchizophr Bull131987261276361651819FowlerD.GaretyP.A.KuipersE.Cognitive Behaviour Therapy for Psychosis: Theory and Practice1995WileyChichester, UK20CallicottJ.H.MattayV.S.BertolinoA.FinnK.CoppolaR.FrankJ.A.Physiological characteristics of capacity constraints in working memory as revealed by functional MRICereb Cortex9199920261002249221NelsonH.WillisonJ.National Adult Reading Test Manual1991NFER-NelsonWindsor, United Kingdom22SiegleG.J.CarterC.S.ThaseM.E.Use of FMRI to predict recovery from unipolar depression with cognitive behavior therapyAm J Psychiatry16320067357381658545223FristonK.J.HolmesA.P.WorsleyK.J.How many subjects constitute a study?Neuroimage101999151038557624WagnerA.D.MarilA.BjorkR.A.SchacterD.L.Prefrontal contributions to executive control: fMRI evidence for functional distinctions within lateral prefrontal cortexNeuroimage142001133713471170708925ChaseH.W.ClarkL.SahakianB.J.BullmoreE.T.RobbinsT.W.Dissociable roles of prefrontal subregions in self-ordered working memory performanceNeuropsychologia462008265026611855602826MaestuF.CampoP.CapillaA.SimosP.G.PaulN.FernandezS.Prefrontal brain magnetic activity: Effects of memory task demandsNeuropsychology1920053013081591011627HoneyG.D.BullmoreE.T.SharmaT.Prolonged reaction time to a verbal working memory task predicts increased power of posterior parietal cortical activationNeuroimage1220004955031103485728WaltzJ.KnowltonB.HolyoakK.BooneK.MishkinF.de MenedezesA system for relational reasoning in human prefrontal cortexPsychol Sci199911912529GaravanH.RossT.J.MurphyK.RocheR.A.SteinE.A.Dissociable executive functions in the dynamic control of behavior: Inhibition, error detection, and correctionNeuroimage172002182018291249875530van der GaagM.A neuropsychiatric model of biological and psychological processes in the remission of delusions and auditory hallucinationsSchizophr Bull32Suppl 12006S113S1221690563531ManoachD.S.Prefrontal cortex dysfunction during working memory performance in schizophrenia: Reconciling discrepant findingsSchizophr Res6020032852981259159032MacdonaldA.W.IIIThermenosH.W.BarchD.M.SeidmanL.J.Imaging genetic liability to schizophrenia: Systematic review of fMRI studies of patients' nonpsychotic relatives[published online ahead of print June 12]Schizophr Bull2008Available at: http://schizophreniabulletin.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/sbn053v133JansmaJ.M.RamseyN.F.van der WeeN.J.KahnR.S.Working memory capacity in schizophrenia: A parametric fMRI studySchizophr Res6820041591711509960034KarlsgodtK.H.SanzJ.van ErpT.G.BeardenC.E.NuechterleinK.H.CannonT.D.Re-evaluating dorsolateral prefrontal cortex activation during working memory in schizophreniaSchizophr Res10820091431501919649435DavisC.E.JesteD.V.EylerL.T.Review of longitudinal functional neuroimaging studies of drug treatments in patients with schizophreniaSchizophr Res78200545601597928736BruderG.E.StewartJ.W.MercierM.A.AgostiV.LeiteP.DonovanS.Outcome of cognitive-behavioral therapy for depression: Relation to hemispheric dominance for verbal processingJ Abnorm Psychol1061997138144910372537WagerT.D.SmithE.E.Neuroimaging studies of working memory: A meta-analysisCogn Affect Behav Neurosci320032552741504054738RamnaniN.BehrensT.E.Johansen-BergH.RichterM.C.PinskM.A.AnderssonJ.L.The evolution of prefrontal inputs to the corticopontine system: Diffusion imaging evidence from macaque monkeys and humansCereb Cortex1620068118181612079339RamnaniN.The primate corticocerebellar system: Anatomy and functionNat Rev Neurosci720065115221679114140BellebaumC.DaumI.Cerebellar involvement in executive controlCerebellum620071841921778681441AndreasenN.C.O'LearyD.S.CizadloT.ArndtS.RezaiK.PontoL.L.Schizophrenia and cognitive dysmetria: A positron-emission tomography study of dysfunctional prefrontal-thalamic-cerebellar circuitryProc Natl Acad Sci U S A93199699859990879044442AndreasenN.C.ParadisoS.O'LearyD.S.“Cognitive dysmetria” as an integrative theory of schizophrenia: A dysfunction in cortical-subcortical-cerebellar circuitry?Schizophr Bull241998203218961362143AndreasenN.C.NopoulosP.O'LearyD.S.MillerD.D.WassinkT.FlaumM.Defining the phenotype of schizophrenia: Cognitive dysmetria and its neural mechanismsBiol Psychiatry4619999089201050917444GreiciusM.D.KrasnowB.ReissA.L.MenonV.Functional connectivity in the resting brain: A network analysis of the default mode hypothesisProc Natl Acad Sci U S A10020032532581250619445RaichleM.E.MacLeodA.M.SnyderA.Z.PowersW.J.GusnardD.A.ShulmanG.L.A default mode of brain functionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A9820016766821120906446KennedyD.P.RedcayE.CourchesneE.Failing to deactivate: Resting functional abnormalities in autismProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1032006827582801670254847TianL.JiangT.WangY.ZangY.HeY.LiangM.Altered resting-state functional connectivity patterns of anterior cingulate cortex in adolescents with attention deficit hyperactivity disorderNeurosci Lett400200639431651024248WilliamsonP.Are anticorrelated networks in the brain relevant to schizophrenia?Schizophr Bull33200799410031749395749BucknerR.L.Andrews-HannaJ.R.SchacterD.L.The brain's default network: Anatomy, function, and relevance to diseaseAnn NY Acad Sci112420081381840092250GarrityA.G.PearlsonG.D.McKiernanK.LloydD.KiehlK.A.CalhounV.D.Aberrant “default mode” functional connectivity in schizophreniaAm J Psychiatry16420074504571732947051Pomarol-ClotetE.SalvadorR.SarroS.GomarJ.VilaF.MartinezA.Failure to deactivate in the prefrontal cortex in schizophrenia: Dysfunction of the default mode network?Psychol Med382008118511931850788552SenskyT.TurkingtonD.KingdonD.ScottJ.L.ScottJ.SiddleR.A randomized controlled trial of cognitive-behavioral therapy for persistent symptoms in schizophrenia resistant to medicationArch Gen Psychiatry5720001651721066561953McGurkS.R.TwamleyE.W.SitzerD.I.McHugoG.J.MueserK.T.A meta-analysis of cognitive remediation in schizophreniaAm J Psychiatry1642007179118021805623354PattersonT.L.LeeuwenkampO.R.Adjunctive psychosocial therapies for the treatment of schizophreniaSchizophr Res100200810811918226500This research was supported by the Wellcome Trust (Grant No. 067427/z/02/z). We thank Dr. Angus MacDonald for his comments on an earlier version of this article and Ms. Ingrid Aasen and Dr. Michael A Cooke for their help with data collection.Competing Interests: The authors report no biomedical financial interests or potential conflicts of interest.Supplementary material cited in this article is available online.Figure 1Illustration of 1-back and 2-back trials.Figure 2Brain activity associated with response to cognitive–behavioral therapy in patients with schizophrenia during the 2-back &gt; 0-back contrast. The top row shows positive associations and the bottom row negative associations (maps thresholded at p = .05 uncorrected) in sagittal and transverse views with associated Montreal Neurological Institute coordinates (x, y, z). Left hemisphere is shown on the left of the transverse view. AC, anterior cingulate; CBT, cognitive-behavioral therapy; DLPFC, dorsolateral prefrontal cortex.Figure 3Scatterplots of task-load-related activity (2-back &gt; 0-back) in the left (x= −54, y = 12, z = 26) and right (x = 52, y = 24, z = 22) frontal lobes against the change in symptoms (reduction from baseline) separately for the cognitive–behavioral therapy in addition to treatment-as-usual (CBT+TAU) and treatment-as-usual (TAU-alone) groups.Figure 4Left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) connectivity association with response to cognitive–behavioral therapy (CBT) in patients with schizophrenia during the 2-back &gt; 0-back contrast. The top row shows positive associations, and the bottom row shows negative associations (maps thresholded at p = .005 uncorrected) in transverse views with associated Montreal Neurological Institute z coordinates. Left hemisphere is shown on the left.Table 1Demographics, Task Performance, and Clinical Characteristics of ParticipantsHealthy Participants (n = 20; 14 men)PatientsCBT+TAU Group (n = 19, 14 men)TAU-Alone Group (n = 17, 15 men)DemographicsMean (SD)Mean (SD)Mean (SD)Age (Years)33.20 (11.28)35.20 (7.79)40.24 (10.34)Education (Years)15.55 (2.78)13.79 (3.34)13.35 (1.54)Predicted IQa♢115.05 (7.53)110.44 (9.75)106.17 (8.63)PerformanceMean (SEM)Mean (SEM)Mean (SEM)Accuracy (%; Chance Performance = 25%) 0-back89.13 (2.87)86.18 (2.95)88.08 (2.68) 1-back76.29 (4.23)65.56 (4.34)75.97 (4.99) 2-back58.54 (5.29)45.18 (5.43)44.52 (5.88)Reaction Time (msec) 0-back136.78 (14.26)Δ209.07 (22.02)Δ207.56 (25.97) 1-back209.01 (31.80)Δ222.52 (30.11)Δ274.58 (42.51) 2-back296.79 (43.96)Δ562.23 (94.70)Δ426.08 (58.77)Patients OnlyCBT+TAU Group Mean (SD)TAU-alone Group Mean (SD)Clinical VariablesBaselineFollow-upChange (Baseline Minus Follow-up)BaselineFollow-upChange (Baseline Minus Follow-up)Age at Illness Onset (Years)24.26 (7.91)24.82 (8.43)Duration of Illness (Years)10.74 (8.06)15.41 (12.21)bPositive Symptoms17.89 (4.86)▾14.79 (4.39)▴3.11 (3.88)18.53 (3.10)18.23 (3.67)0.29 (4.13)bNegative Symptoms16.89 (3.52)15.21 (4.04)▴1.68 (3.90)18.82 (3.94)20.06 (4.53)−1.24 (4.38)bGeneral Psychopathology32.95 (5.27)▾28.05 (7.48)▴4.89 (7.06)34.82 (4.72)34.76 (7.04)0.06 (6.57)bTotal Symptoms67.74 (10.87)▾58.05 (14.93)▴9.68 (12.29)72.17 (9.47)73.06 (12.91)−0.88 (12.07)Antipsychotic medication17 patients on atypical and 2 on both atypical and typical antipsychotics.As baseline15 patients on atypical and 2 on both atypical and typical antipsychotics.As baselineAntipsychotic Dose in Chlorpromazine Equivalents (mg)544.00 (426.46)As baseline474.68 (338.70)As baselineDuration of illness = current age minus age of illness onset;CBT, cognitive-behavioral therapy; TAU, treatment-as-usual.aNational Adult Reading Test (21);bPositive and Negative Symptom Scale (18);♢N = 19 (missing IQ data in one healthy participant) and IQ in healthy participants significantly higher than TAU-alone;ΔLonger latencies (p &lt; .05) in patients relative to healthy participants even when controlling for age;▾Lower symptom scores (p &lt; .05) at follow-up in the CBT+TAU, but not in the TAU-alone, group;▴Symptom reduction (p &lt; .05) in the CBT+TAU, relative to the TAU-alone, group.Table 2Brain Areas Showing Positive and Negative Associations with CBT Responsiveness in PatientsPositive AssociationsBACluster Size (voxels)SideMNI CoordinatesVoxel T ValueCorrected pXYZTotal Symptoms 2-back &gt; 0-back  Inferior-middle frontal gyrus441048L−5412264.85.01546L−4834304.43  Inferior-middle frontal gyrus45/461132R5224223.99.03346R4224262.95Positive Symptoms 2-back &gt; 0-back  Inferior-middle frontal gyrus9–461263L−4832324.61.02144L−5212284.039L−5422323.75Negative Symptoms 2-back &gt; 0-back  Caudate nucleusn/a12802L−142145.60&lt;.001  Anterior cingulate/medial prefrontal cortex32/8L−622524.57  Middle frontal gyrus9–46L−4636284.55General Psychopathology 2-back &gt; 0-back  Inferior-middle frontal gyrus44874L−5410264.51.02546L−4834303.83  Middle frontal gyrus46723R5226244.48.026Negative AssociationsTotal Symptoms 1-back &gt; 0-back  Insulan/a15746L−30−2865.50&lt;.001  Middle temporal gyrus20/21L−36−34−145.32  Parahippocampal gyrus36L−20−40−144.65 2-back &gt; 0-back  Brain stemn/a7729L−8−20−23.83.006  Middle temporal gyrus21L−600−103.65  Inferior parietal lobe40L−50−40483.54Positive Symptoms 1-back &gt; 0-back  Transverse temporal gyrus4111704L−30−30104.94&lt;.001  Posterior cingulate23R10−36284.9123/31R14−56204.82 2-back &gt; 0-back  Brain stemn/a6593R6−18−24.24.016n/aR8−12−83.92  Middle temporal gyrus39R36−62183.60Negative Symptoms NoneGeneral Psychopathology 1-back &gt; 0 back  Middle temporal gyrus21/2016245L−38−32−145.31&lt;.001  Parahippocampal gyrus35/36L−18−38−145.14  Fusiform gyrus37L−32−40−165.02 2-back &gt; 0-back  Brain stemn/a17435R8−20−24.37&lt;.001  Posterior cingulate31L−24−60184.09  Inferior parietal lobe5L−24−44543.94BA, Brodmann area; MNI, Montreal Neurological Institute. In italics: SVC criterion applied. All others: cluster p corrected for multiple comparisons across the entire brain.
