<?xml version="1.0"?>
Bipolar DisordBipolar Disord10.1111/(ISSN)1399-5618BDIBipolar Disorders1398-56471399-5618John Wiley and Sons Inc.Hoboken571687310.1111/bdi.12556BDI12556Task Force PapersResearch ArticlesReviewsThe International Society for Bipolar Disorders Task Force report on pediatric bipolar disorder: Knowledge to date and directions for future researchGOLDSTEIN et al.GoldsteinBenjamin Ihttp://orcid.org/0000-0003-0340-349Xbenjamin.goldstein@sunnybrook.ca
1

2
BirmaherBoris
3
CarlsonGabrielle A
4
DelBelloMelissa P
5
FindlingRobert L
6
FristadMary
7
KowatchRobert A
7
MiklowitzDavid J
8
NeryFabiano G
5
Perez‐AlgortaGuillermohttp://orcid.org/0000-0001-6610-4951
9
Van MeterAnnahttp://orcid.org/0000-0003-0012-206X
10
ZeniCristian Phttp://orcid.org/0000-0001-9810-3929
11
CorrellChristoph U
12

13
KimHyo‐Won
14
WozniakJanet
15
ChangKiki D
16
HillegersManon
17
YoungstromEric Ahttp://orcid.org/0000-0003-2251-6860
18

1
Centre for Youth Bipolar Disorder
Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre
Toronto
Canada

2
Departments of Psychiatry and Pharmacology
University of Toronto
Toronto
Canada

3
Department of Psychiatry
University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine
Pittsburgh
PA
USA

4
Department of Psychiatry
Stony Brook University School of Medicine
Stony Brook
NY
USA

5
Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Neuroscience
University of Cincinnati
Cincinnati
OH
USA

6
Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences
The Johns Hopkins University
Baltimore
MD
USA

7
Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center/Nationwide Children's Hospital
Columbus
OH
USA

8
Department of Psychiatry
UCLA
Los Angeles
CA
USA

9
Division of Health Research
Lancaster University
Lancaster
UK

10
Ferkauf Graduate School of Psychology
Yeshiva University
Bronx
NY
USA

11
Department of Psychiatry
University of Texas
Houston
TX
USA

12
The Zucker Hillside Hospital
Department of Psychiatry
Northwell Health
Glen Oaks
NY
USA

13
Department of Psychiatry and Molecular Medicine
Hofstra Northwell School of Medicine
Hempstead
NY
USA

14
Department of Psychiatry
University of Ulsan College of Medicine
Asan Medical Center
Seoul
Korea

15
Clinical and Research Program in Pediatric Psychopharmacology
Massachusetts General Hospital
Harvard Medical School
Boston
MA
USA

16
Department of Psychiatry
Stanford University
Palo Alto
CA
USA

17
Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Psychology
Erasmus Medical Center‐Sophia
Rotterdam
The Netherlands

18
Department of Psychology and Neuroscience
University of North Carolina
Chapel Hill
NC
USA
*Correspondence
Benjamin I Goldstein, Centre for Youth Bipolar Disorder, Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, Toronto, Canada.
Email: benjamin.goldstein@sunnybrook.ca259201711201719710.1111/bdi.2017.19.issue-752454305420171482017© 2017 The Authors Bipolar Disorders Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons LtdThis is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution‐NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes.ObjectivesOver the past two decades, there has been tremendous growth in research regarding bipolar disorder (BD) among children and adolescents (ie, pediatric BD [PBD]). The primary purpose of this article is to distill the extant literature, dispel myths or exaggerated assertions in the field, and disseminate clinically relevant findings.MethodsAn international group of experts completed a selective review of the literature, emphasizing areas of consensus, identifying limitations and gaps in the literature, and highlighting future directions to mitigate these gaps.ResultsSubstantial, and increasingly international, research has accumulated regarding the phenomenology, differential diagnosis, course, treatment, and neurobiology of PBD. Prior division around the role of irritability and of screening tools in diagnosis has largely abated. Gold‐standard pharmacologic trials inform treatment of manic/mixed episodes, whereas fewer data address bipolar depression and maintenance/continuation treatment. Adjunctive psychosocial treatment provides a forum for psychoeducation and targets primarily depressive symptoms. Numerous neurocognitive and neuroimaging studies, and increasing peripheral biomarker studies, largely converge with prior findings from adults with BD.ConclusionsAs data have accumulated and controversy has dissipated, the field has moved past existential questions about PBD toward defining and pursuing pressing clinical and scientific priorities that remain. The overall body of evidence supports the position that perceptions about marked international (US vs elsewhere) and developmental (pediatric vs adult) differences have been overstated, although additional research on these topics is warranted. Traction toward improved outcomes will be supported by continued emphasis on pathophysiology and novel therapeutics.adolescentbipolar disorderchildpediatricyouthNational Institute of Mental HealthRandom House, Inc.Lippincott Williams &amp; WilkinsAPA PressUpToDatePatient Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI)MerckNIDDKOtsukaLundbeckSunovionPfizerJohnson and JohnsonSupernusAmarexShireTakedaNeuroneticsAkiliActavisAlcobraAmerican Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent PsychiatryAmerican Psychiatric PressBracketCogCubedCognition GroupCoronado BiosciencesElsevierEpharma SolutionsForestGenentechGuilford PressIronshoreJohns Hopkins University PressKemPharmMedgenicsNIHNeurimNovartisPhysicians Postgraduate PressPurdueRhodes PharmaceuticalsRocheSageSyneurxTevaTrisValidusWebMDJanssenJohn Wiley &amp; SonsUCB PharmaNeuroMetrixLuitpoldsource-schema-version-number2.0component-idbdi12556cover-dateNovember 2017details-of-publishers-convertorConverter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:5.2.8 mode:remove_FC converted:12.12.2017


Goldstein
BI
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Carlson
GA
, et al. The International Society for Bipolar Disorders Task Force report on pediatric bipolar disorder: Knowledge to date and directions for future research. Bipolar Disord. 2017;19:524–543. https://doi.org/10.1111/bdi.12556
28944987
[Correction added on 6 October 2017, after first online publication: Copyright License changed.]1INTRODUCTIONOver the past two decades, there has been tremendous growth in the scientific literature regarding bipolar disorder (BD) among children and adolescents (ie, pediatric BD [PBD]) (Figure 1). The literature now contains numerous gold‐standard clinical trials of pharmacologic agents for mania, an increasing evidence base for adjunctive psychosocial treatments, several large‐scale prospective clinical cohort studies, representative epidemiologic studies (particularly focused on adolescents) with international representation, numerous neurocognitive and neuroimaging studies, and an accelerating number of biomarker studies. Despite the volume, quality, and international spectrum of available literature, and regardless of the general consensus about some of the field's previously most divisive and controversial topics, there remains a perspective in the popular press, other branches of medicine, and even within mental health that the field of PBD lacks evidence and is replete with controversy. Therefore, the primary purpose of this article is to distill the extant literature, dispel myths or exaggerated assertions in the field, and disseminate clinically relevant findings. In this paper, an international group of experts completed a selective review of the extant literature (including PubMed and Web of Science/PsycINFO searches, querying other databases or conference proceedings and unpublished reports on an ad hoc basis), emphasizing areas of established findings and consensus, identifying limitations and gaps in the literature, and highlighting future directions to mitigate these gaps.Figure 1Articles about pediatric bipolar disorder indexed in PubMed each year. Search terms were (“bipolar disorder” or mania or manic) and (child or adole* or pediatric or juvenile)2EPIDEMIOLOGY2.1Established findings and consensusIn community samples around the world, it is now well established that bipolar spectrum disorders—an umbrella that covers bipolar I disorder, bipolar II disorder, cyclothymic disorder [CycD], bipolar disorder not otherwise specified (NOS) and other specified bipolar and related disorders (OS‐BRD)—occur in youths. The update of a published meta‐analysis of epidemiologic studies1 using an identical search strategy identified six new studies satisfying inclusion criteria. The update includes 17 studies (seven from the USA) with 31 443 youth aged 7‐21 years, 576 of whom met criteria for bipolar spectrum disorders.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17 The updated weighted average prevalence rate of bipolar spectrum disorders is 2.06% (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.44%‐2.95%).There was substantial heterogeneity across studies, but it was not explained by year of data collection, lifetime prevalence (vs other time periods), or sex. Studies that included more adolescents had significantly higher prevalence estimates. Differences in the definition of BD explained the largest portion of variance between studies. As expected, broader definitions (ie, including NOS or CycD) had the highest rates while narrow definitions (ie, BD‐I and ‐II only) had lower rates, but even this was not a complete explanation. The weighted average prevalence of BD‐I was 0.49% (95% CI 0.22%‐1.09%), with four of 12 studies reporting no BD‐I cases. Although there is no epidemiologic study on PBD in Asia, several studies from clinical samples reported that PBD is also prevalent in Asia.18, 19, 20
Community rates are not higher in the USA, nor do rates appear to be increasing over time. In contrast, billing and services data show a marked increase in rates of diagnoses in the USA over a 20‐year period.21, 22 Differences in training, conceptualization of cases and insurance demands appear more of a factor23 than underlying differences in prevalence.In summary, PBD prevalence rates appear relatively stable across studies. PBD is more common than autism or schizophrenia and much less common than depression or attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) in the community; more data are available with post‐pubertal samples, and they find higher rates than before puberty.24
2.2Limitations, gaps, and future directionsNew epidemiologic studies need to systematically assess hypomania and mania and differentiate them from other non‐mood psychopathology. Even the newest epidemiologic data were collected at least 10 years ago (range 1986‐2005), and fewer than 1% of indexed papers on pediatric epidemiology include data about BD.1 Documenting age of onset of the first mood episode of each type will be vital, with more studies including prepubertal children, to clarify onset and course. If depression manifests first, it may not be clear that it is following a bipolar course until later. Onset age may be bimodal25, 26 and American youth may be at higher risk for very early onset.27 Existing literature confounds age and informant effects: studies with older participants are less likely to include interviews of parents. Studies relying only on retrospective self‐report are likely to underestimate hypomania or mania, as people forget or minimize the events, whereas depression may be more salient. Using more consistent criteria across studies will reduce the largest source of variance identified in extant meta‐analyses.3INTERNATIONAL FINDINGS3.1Established findings and consensusPrior studies in adults suggested that, although BD occurs worldwide, there could be international differences in the clinical characteristics of BD, including age of onset, comorbidity, early adversity, and familiality.28, 29 Although international differences in BD are less well studied in youth as compared to adults, there now are PBD data from multiple countries including Australia/New Zealand, Brazil, China, France, India, Italy, South Korea, Spain, the Netherlands, Turkey, and the UK.30 In addition to the epidemiologic studies reviewed above, international BD data now include phenomenological,19, 31, 32, 33 comorbidity,19, 34 longitudinal,35, 36 treatment,37, 38 neuroimaging and biomarker,39, 40, 41 and high‐risk studies.42, 43 Numerous commentaries discuss purported international differences in the prevalence of PBD, which may be attributable to including more subtypes,1 differences in the interview method,44 training,23, 45 or the type of sample studied (predominantly manic, depressive, treatment‐seeking or registry), or a combination of these.46
Some findings converge with US data. For example, Brazilian families with PBD also show lower positive regard and higher negative expressed emotion (EE) compared to control families.47 There are, however, examples of non‐replication. In contrast to US data, a recent Brazilian imaging study did not find white matter microstructure differences between PBD youth, healthy bipolar offspring and healthy controls,48 and parent report of youth mood symptoms showed much lower discriminative validity than parent report in other countries.49 However, it is unclear whether this a true international difference or a difference owing to methodologic factors.A recent study directly compared Dutch and US samples of offspring of parents with BD.50 Both projects used the Achenbach Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL)51 as well as similar semi‐structured interviews (eg, the Kiddie Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia).52 After controlling for age, rates of DSM‐IV BD‐I (2.2% in the US sample and 1.5% in the Dutch sample) and BD‐II (2% and 1%, respectively) were similar. In contrast, other disorders were significantly more common in the US sample, including depressive disorders (13% vs 4% in the Dutch sample), anxiety disorders (31% vs 9%, respectively), ADHD (22% vs 8%, respectively), and disruptive behavior disorder (19% vs 6%, respectively). CBCL Externalizing scores were higher in the US sample (mean + standard deviation 15.0 + 9.7 vs 10.8 + 7.6, respectively, P = .03). However, Internalizing scores did not differ between samples (raw M ~ 15), despite higher rates of anxiety and depressive disorders in the US sample. In the US, fewer parents had BD‐I, affected parents were younger at their own illness onset, parental substance abuse rates were higher, and rates of parental employment and youth living with both biological parents were lower. These stressors may have contributed to the greater rates of problems in the US sample. The differences also illustrate the importance of the psychopathology of the parent bipolar sample to understanding rates of offspring psychopathology. The internalizing findings also suggest that there could be differences in clinical interpretation of similar levels of pathology, even using semi‐structured approaches.3.2Limitations, gaps, and future directionsFuture work needs to determine whether there are meaningful international differences in the prevalence, phenomenology, course, treatment, and biology of PBD. Translating scales into multiple languages and pursuing cross‐cultural validation are accelerating progress by using consistent definitions,50 revealing considerable continuity in phenomenology.53 Combining data sets internationally would help calibrate definitions and examine common risk factors.4CLINICAL CHARACTERISTICS, DIFFERENTIAL DIAGNOSES, AND COURSE4.1Established findings and consensus4.1.1Clinical characteristicsInterest in BD phenotypes spans decades. Over 25 years ago, the issue of severe chronic irritability as part of the bipolar spectrum polarized the field; this issue is now largely resolved.46, 54, 55 With regard to symptom presentations, one position held that elation and/or grandiosity was required for a diagnosis of BD in youth.56 There now is substantial consensus that chronic irritability, regardless of explosiveness or severity, is not sufficient for a diagnosis of BD, in contrast with formulations that focused on rages or severe aggression.57 However, irritability is commonly present in youth with BD. Counting irritability as part of the diagnostic criteria for a manic or hypomanic episode requires that the irritability either begins or significantly increases in intensity in conjunction with the presence of accompanying manic (DSM Criterion B) symptoms. Thus, a youth with BPD may have chronic irritability, but the diagnosis would not be made based on that mood state.58, 59, 60, 61 Although severe irritability and emotional dysregulation are not proxies for BD, they are also not mutually exclusive of episodic, DSM‐adherent BD. Irritability that waxes and wanes spontaneously or in conjunction with other episodic changes in energy or sleep is much more suggestive of a mood disorder than other pathology.While calls to include severe, chronic irritability as a developmental type of BD among youth have waned, substantial data have accrued concerning repeated brief discrete episodes of hypomania for less than 4 days as part of the BD spectrum. As among adults,62 youth manifest CycD63 and episodic OS‐BRD, as well as BD‐I and BD‐II. However, as described below, youth with brief but well‐defined episodes of mania or hypomania are at very high risk to switch into BD‐I or BD‐II (particularly if they have a family history of BD),64 and they have as much psychosocial impairment, suicidality, comorbidity (eg, substance abuse), and family history of BD as those with BD‐I.65 Less research has specifically addressed CycD, which is often subsumed within the BD‐NOS category due to lack of operationalized criteria.1, 63, 66
Ultra‐rapid or “ultradian” cycling also has been associated with pediatric (as well as adult) BD.67 Although youth with BD, particularly younger children, often have more mood fluctuations than adults, it appears that “ultra‐rapid cycles” describes mood fluctuation within an episode, and they are not themselves distinct episodes.68
Similar to adult BD, PBD has extensive comorbidity, both in representative epidemiologic studies with largely untreated samples17, 69, 70 and in clinical samples.71 With the exception of developmental disorders like ADHD and autism spectrum disorders, the patterns of comorbidity are broadly consistent between youth and adult presentations.71, 72 Apparent differences may partly reflect limited assessment of ADHD and autism spectrum disorders in adult samples rather than a true difference in comorbidities between these age groups, although some studies also suggest an association between ADHD and earlier age of onset of bipolar illness in adult samples.73, 74 The presence of comorbid disorders worsens the course and outcome of PBD, indicating the need for their identification and treatment. When determining comorbid diagnoses, it is important not to “double‐count” overlapping diagnostic symptoms (eg, hyperactivity in ADHD and irritability in multiple disorders), as this leads to artificially high rates of comorbidity. Identifying discrete mood episodes and ensuring that overlapping symptoms are (i) over and above what can be expected from the individual's baseline and (ii) concurrent with mood episodes helps disentangle clinical presentations. Conversely, symptoms that persist in periods of euthymia suggest a non‐mood etiology, and thus a “true” comorbidity. Finally, there is increasing evidence that medical comorbidity is relevant to PBD, both in terms of the association of physical health characteristics such as obesity with suicidality, neurocognition, and other markers of psychiatric symptom burden, and in terms of future premature cardiovascular disease.75, 76, 77, 78, 79 Medical comorbidity is closely related to both the mood symptoms and related lifestyle behaviors such as sedentary lifestyle and binge‐eating in PBD.80, 81
4.1.2Differential diagnosisDiagnosing PBD requires changes in mood and behavior that are uncharacteristic of the individual and more extreme than developmentally appropriate, persist long enough to satisfy duration criteria, and have a clear impact on functioning. If comorbid disorders are present, mood symptoms need to be above and beyond the regular symptoms for the other disorder. For example, if symptoms of ADHD get worse episodically, and during these episodes the youth presents symptoms more specific to mania (eg, decreased need for sleep), a PBD diagnosis should be considered. Symptom sequence may help differentiate BD from some other disorders: a teen with BD might first experience symptoms of hypomania and depression and then begin using substances, in contrast to another teen who experimented with drugs first and then began showing irritability. However, it can be difficult to separate onset of a comorbid disorder from onset of manic/hypomanic symptoms.Although the new and controversial DSM‐5 diagnosis of disruptive mood dysregulation disorder (DMDD) cannot formally be diagnosed if the youth has BD,82 the phenotype commonly overlaps with those of all BD subtypes60, 83, 84 as well as other conditions, particularly oppositional defiant disorder (ODD).85, 86 Thus, one must evaluate the potential presence of BD even if DMDD is identified, and vice versa. The reliability of DMDD diagnoses was low in the DSM‐5 field trials, suggesting that it may be challenging to accurately identify clinically.4.1.3CourseMultiple longitudinal studies have prospectively followed cohorts of youths for 4 or more years. Consistent findings include (i) high rates of progression from BD‐NOS or CycD to BD‐I or BD‐II (eg, 43%),64 particularly in youth with a family history of BD; (ii) high rates of recovery from episodes, particularly with treatment (eg, 81.5%);87, 88 (iii) high rates of recurrence of depression, hypomania, or mania (eg, 62.5%);64, 87, 89, 90 and (iv) patterns of comorbidity91 and treatment response congruent with adult BD.92 The prodrome of BD‐I or BD‐II, often identified retrospectively in adult studies, commonly involves attenuated mood symptoms; and sleep disturbance may be a marker clinically (see reference for detailed discussion of prodrome).93
4.2Limitations, gaps, and future directionsRemaining controversies include whether ADHD might be a prodrome for BD. Some studies suggest that ADHD might be a prodrome,94, 95 although some used interviews that blurred the distinction between mood episodes and more chronic presentations.44 Longitudinal studies of ADHD cohorts tend to find no or only small increases in risk of BD.96 Adding the DMDD diagnosis to DSM‐5 created several gaps in terms of evidence‐based assessment methods to differentiate DMDD from mood disorders, and lack of clarity regarding effective treatments. DMDD has its own definitional problems, as irritability includes both mood (often loses temper) and behavior (what happens when temper is lost).46 The next version of ICD will not add DMDD as a diagnosis, instead making a mood disturbance specifier for ODD.97 Research needs to evaluate the relative effectiveness of psychosocial (eg, parent training; emotion regulation strategies) and pharmacologic interventions for DMDD.61, 98 Longitudinal data also raise interesting questions about the possibility of remission of DMDD and bipolar disorders,55, 99 a topic that warrants further study.5MEASUREMENT5.1Established findings and consensusThere has been a large increase in the number of scales available and supported by data to measure different aspects of PBD. Myths ready for retirement include: (i) there is no validated rating scale or checklist for assessing manic symptoms in youth, (ii) a profile of scores on the CBCL51 can be used as a proxy for a diagnosis of PBD, and (iii) thinking in polarized terms about the value of a particular informant perspective in the evaluation of PBD (see Table 1). Common (and mistaken) beliefs include “teacher report is essential for confirming a diagnosis of mania,” vs “teacher report is useless in the evaluation of PBD”, or “parents’ perspective is always right” vs “parents’ perspective is hopelessly contaminated by their own mood or agenda.”Table 1Summary of myths, consensus, and next actions for research on pediatric bipolar disorderAreaMythsDataFive‐year needs1. Epidemiology
Doesn't happen in children

Evident in epidemiologic samples in ages 5 years and higherConvergent adolescent dataNo difference in overall or BD‐I/II ratesInconsistent inclusion and/or definition of NOS/OS‐BRD

Include full age rangeUse consistent definition of BD spectrum (NOS and OS‐BRD)Examine BMI, pubertal status, and comorbidity
2. International perspectives
No evidence outside of US

Evidence base includes multiple non‐US studies covering assessment, genetics, treatment, imaging, outcome, and comorbidity

Ensure valid translation available in multiple languagesMove toward Kessler/Harvard/Michigan‐team model (WHO) using CIDI, to allow data integration and direct comparisons
3. Clinical characteristics, differential diagnoses, and course
Adult criteria do not applyCan forego the requirement for episodesPredominantly chronic, and characterized by irritability without elation

Most youth have both irritability and elation at most severe episodeApplying adult criteria yields convergent findings with adult BDIrritable‐only (hypo)mania is uncommon but otherwise symptomatically similar to other types of PBDMost research defines BD based on DSM, and requires episodes

Study ADHD and related neurocognitive profiles as indicators of risk for BDExamine comorbid DMDD‐type phenotype in terms of prognostication and treatment
4. Measurement
Screeners are not helpfulCBCL is sufficientOne type of informant is inherently superior (teacher, parent, or child)

Multiple published measures report high validity coefficientsCBCL is a poor proxy for diagnosisScreeners can be part of evidence‐based medicine approach to diagnosis, and inform next steps

Examine incremental value of biomarkers, imaging, and cognitive testing for diagnostic accuracyTest measures in samples that allow meaningful comparison groups to BD (eg, ADHD and depression, rather than healthy controls)
5. Course, outcome, and comorbidity
Chronic, non‐episodicNo evidence of diagnostic continuity into adulthood

When defined based on episodicity, continues to evince episodicity prospectivelyComorbidity largely dependent on ageComorbidity by late adolescence is similar to that in adulthood (higher rates of SUD and anxiety; lower rates of ADHD)Overlapping symptoms of mania and ADHD should not be simply double counted

Include cognition, imaging, and biomarkers in prospective studies to inform staging modelsBe consistent about hierarchical exclusions (CD vs ODD)Examine DMDD with/without BD exclusions
6. Pharmacologic treatment
SGAs effectiveYouth extra‐sensitive to metabolic side effectsMood‐stabilizers less efficacious than in adultsStimulants for comorbid ADHD, in the context of a mood stabilizer, are usually safe and efficaciousAdjunctive nutritional interventions show promise

Determine if early stimulant or antidepressant treatment for ADHD and depression/anxiety, respectively, precipitates BDExplore treatment for bipolar depression and maintenanceStudy clinical staging using low‐risk interventions for high‐risk youth
7. Psychosocial treatment
No validated treatmentsSpecific elements of treatment not relevant

Family psychoeducation plus skill building is a well‐established category of psychotherapyHigh EE predicts response to different treatments

Determine core components linked to positive outcomeMatch patients to treatments based on EE, etc.Develop novel methods to access psychotherapy contentStudy dissemination and implementation strategies
8. Imaging and neurocognition
No specific findings; overlap with ADHD/ODD

Several distinguishing features, but also overlapping findings with SMD/ADHD

Complete larger, repeated‐measures studiesUse multimodal imaging
9. Biomarkers
Few data

Increase uptake of biomarker researchUse multimethod research (eg, integrate imaging)
ADHD, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder; BD, bipolar disorder; BMI, body mass index; CBCL, Achenbach Child Behavior Checklist; CD, conduct disorder; CIDI, Composite International Diagnostic Interview; DMDD, disruptive mood dysregulation disorder; EE, expressed emotion; NOS, not otherwise specified; PBD, pediatric bipolar disorder; ODD, oppositional defiant disorder; OS‐BRD, other specified bipolar and related disorders; SGA, second‐generation antipsychotic; SMD, severe mood dysregulation; WHO, World Health Organization.John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd5.1.1Current state of assessmentThe current generation of practitioners completed their training before the bulk of research on PBD was available. Consequently, agreement between clinicians about the presence or absence of PBD in a particular case is poor.100, 101 Agreement also tends to be worse around CycD and OS‐BRD,23, 102 which is unfortunate given that these may be more common than BD‐I.1, 66
5.1.2Cross‐informant report on checklistsMultiple studies have evaluated parent, youth, and teacher report on both broad symptom checklists, such as the Achenbach System of Empirically Based Assessment,51 and manic symptom scales. Agreement between informants on ratings of the youth's mood symptoms tends to be only “fair,” ie, in the r = .2 to .3 range, consistent with meta‐analyses of agreement about youth mood and behavior in general.103
Checklists can detect cases needing more in‐depth evaluation for potential PBD. A recent meta‐analysis found 63 effect sizes—38 based on caregiver, 14 on youth, and 11 on teacher report, with eight checklists providing at least two different effect sizes. Teacher and youth reports had medium effect sizes, and parent/caregiver reports had the largest effect sizes. The Achenbach Externalizing Scale outperformed the putative “bipolar” profile, consistent with findings that the “bipolar” profile is not specific to PBD.104, 105 Manic symptom scales fared better at identifying PBD, with three top tier options: The Parent General Behavior Inventory106 and its 10‐item mania short form,107 the Child Mania Rating Scale108 and its 10‐item short form,109 and the parent version of the Mood Disorder Questionnaire.110
These scales are not accurate enough to justify their use as universal screening devices or as substitutes for a (semi‐)structured diagnostic interview. However, they can change the probability of a PBD diagnosis within an evidence‐based medicine or Bayesian decision‐making framework111, 112 and substantially improve the accuracy of clinical interpretation and agreement about next clinical action.102, 112 Some checklists have also shown sensitivity to treatment effects in masked randomized controlled trials (RCTs), with effect sizes equal to those based on direct interview of the youth and primary caregiver.113, 114 Checklists can improve diagnostic decision making in a range of clinical settings, as well as measuring treatment response.90, 100, 101, 102
5.1.3Diagnostic and severity interviewsSemi‐structured or structured diagnostic interviews that systematically evaluate mood symptoms remain the best available method to establish PBD diagnoses52, 115 as well as symptom severity. The Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS)116 and Child Depression Rating Scale Revised117 have been the industry standard interviews to quantify severity. Newer alternatives were designed for pediatric patients, with developmentally appropriate anchors and complete coverage of DSM mood symptoms.118 Psychometric differences between severity interviews are small,119, 120 so the choice is more conceptual than statistical. Interview length and training requirements are barriers to routine clinical use.44 More structured methods are faster and easier to use consistently, and are surprisingly popular with patients.121 It is important to check for mood episodes in the context of developmental history at the outset of the interview. Few methods provide a clear algorithm for CycD or OS‐BRD—a key omission given the data on prevalence and burden.5.1.4Risk factors as part of clinical evaluationRisk factors inform the initial diagnostic evaluation process, and may guide treatment selection. Family history of mood disorders—and BD in particular—is the best‐validated risk factor, recommended for routine clinical evaluation, while keeping in mind that the majority of youth with a family history will not necessarily develop BD. Brief screening tools make adding family history clinically feasible.122 High EE (ie, criticism, hostility, and emotional overinvolvement) and high family conflict are risk factors for treatment drop‐out and more rapid relapse.90 High‐EE families may show larger responses to family‐focused psychotherapeutic interventions.123
5.2Limitations, gaps, and future directionsAlthough considerable advances have been made in the use of rating scales, checklists, and structured diagnostic interviews, little work has been done with neurocognitive or neuroimaging methods using clinically generalizable comparison groups to establish whether these methods have diagnostic specificity. Productive next steps in assessment research would be to examine hybrid batteries that combine checklists and neurocognitive measures, biomarkers, or imaging to test incremental validity (ie, the degree to which each measure improves diagnostic accuracy) in order to guide the most cost‐effective test sequences. Better assessment of developmental phenomenology would be valuable to clarify prodromal presentations and trajectories. Structured interviews could be redesigned to better capture duration, potential prodrome, and trajectories. Rapid changes in Internet‐based and smartphone delivery of clinical assessments need to be integrated with traditional assessment and treatment. Finally, feasibility, acceptability and utility of translation of research tools into real‐world measurement‐based care need to be studied.6PHARMACOLOGIC TREATMENT6.1Established findings and consensusThis section summarizes extant literature about pharmacologic treatment of PBD, emphasizing RCTs. For additional detail, the reader is referred to recent reviews on this topic.37, 124, 125, 126, 127, 128, 129
6.1.1Manic/mixed episodesSecond‐generation antipsychotics (SGAs) approved by the United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for the treatment of acute mania and/or mixed mania in children and adolescents (10‐17 years) include risperidone, aripiprazole and quetiapine, olanzapine, and asenapine13, 14, 15, 16, 17 (http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cder/daf/). Lithium has FDA indication for the treatment and recurrence prevention of mania in youths aged 12 years and older, bolstered by a recently published positive 8‐week RCT for youths 7‐17 years old with BD‐I manic/mixed episodes.130 In that study, change in mania symptom scores was significantly larger in lithium‐treated participants, as was global improvement at week 8, compared to placebo‐treated participants.A large (n = 153) 8‐week National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)‐funded RCT compared lithium vs divalproex vs placebo in youths aged 7‐17 years with BD‐I mania.127 Participants randomized to divalproex had a significantly larger reduction in YMRS scores (ΔM = 8.3) from baseline compared to those randomized to placebo (ΔM = 5.3) (P = .04). There was not a statistically significant difference in YMRS scores for subjects randomized to lithium (7.2) compared to placebo (P = .19), or divalproex vs lithium (P = .35). However, another 4‐week RCT of divalproex extended‐release was negative when comparing an active group (n = 74) to placebo (n = 70).131 In this investigation, treatment with divalproex extended release (ER) promoted a mean reduction of 8.8 points in the YMRS, and the placebo group presented a mean reduction of mania of 7.9 points (P = .6). In an open extension of this trial with divalproex ER, where only 26 of 66 patients completed a 6‐month follow‐up, the mean YMRS score decreased by 2.2 points from a baseline of 20.3.An early meta‐analysis on the treatment of PBD (N = 2666 participants across 46 trials) reported that SGAs were highly efficacious and superior to the modest anti‐manic effects for traditional mood‐stabilizing agents, such as lithium carbonate, divalproex sodium, and carbamazepine, when used as monotherapy.129 Another meta‐analysis of double‐masked placebo‐controlled RCTs of treatment for BD‐I mania among youth (n = 1609) and adults (n = 6501) found that SGAs were more efficacious but more metabolically burdensome compared to traditional mood stabilizers among youth, but showed no such differences among adults.132 However, these meta‐analyses predated recent studies supporting the efficacy of lithium.The anticonvulsants divalproex sodium and carbamazepine have not fared well head‐to‐head with SGAs. In two meta‐analyses, treatment effect was less robust with anticonvulsants than with SGAs.105, 106 An RCT of divalproex extended release was negative,131 as was a large RCT of oxcarbazepine,110 and a topiramate RCT in youth was interrupted prior to its completion due to negative results in adult studies; it failed to show efficacy in youth given inadequate power.133 A study of 10 outpatients with BD (11‐17 years old) whose weight increased by &gt; 5% during treatment with mood‐stabilizer or antipsychotic monotherapy were switched to topiramate; reductions in manic symptoms and weight were observed.133, 134
In the “Treatment of Early Age Mania” 8‐week trial, which included 290 youths aged 6‐15 years with BD‐I manic or mixed episodes, response rates were 68% for risperidone, 35% for lithium, and 24% for divalproex sodium.135 The advantage of risperidone vs lithium was greater for youth with ADHD (vs non‐ADHD) and non‐obese (vs obese) youth.136 However, rates of comorbid ADHD in this study were &gt; 90%, limiting power for ADHD vs no‐ADHD comparisons, and some sites showed similar response rates for risperidone and lithium. Concerns have been raised regarding several characteristics in this sample, including prolonged episodes, very early childhood onset, and high rates of rapid cycling, constraining comparisons with adult studies.137
6.1.2Bipolar depressionThe combination of olanzapine and fluoxetine has an FDA indication for BD depression in youth aged 10‐17 years old.138 In a recently presented RCT of 347 youth 10–17 years old, lurasidone was associated with significantly greater improvement in depression symptoms at 6 weeks as compared to placebo (effect size, 0.45). 139 There have been two negative RCTs of quetiapine for bipolar depression.140, 141 In a sample of 193 adolescents (10‐17 years old) with BD‐I or BD‐II who received quetiapine or placebo for 8 weeks, although nonsignificant differences were observed between the responses in the placebo and quetiapine groups (P = .63), high rates of response were observed in both groups (placebo: 55%, and quetiapine ER: 63%).127 A smaller trial of 32 adolescents (12‐18 years old) with BD‐I where subjects were randomized for 8 weeks to placebo (n = 15) or quetiapine (n = 17) revealed no statistically significant differences in response rates between the placebo (67%) and quetiapine (71%) groups.128 Positive preliminary open trials142, 143 or chart reviews144 of lithium and lamotrigine warrant future RCTs. However, high placebo response rates in depression studies require larger samples than mania trials or blinded placebo lead‐in. Although the precise frequency of antidepressant‐induced mania is uncertain,145, 146 practice parameters and guidelines suggest avoiding antidepressant monotherapy; this approach is supported by pharmaco‐epidemiologic data.147
6.1.3Maintenance/continuation treatmentThere have been few maintenance/continuation treatment studies in youth, most of which have been previously reviewed.125 An early observational study of continuation treatment with lithium found an increased risk of relapse among adolescents who were not treated with lithium following hospitalization for mania.148 A subsequent study of children and adolescents with BD who had been stabilized on the combination of lithium and divalproex found a similar survival time to recurrence among those randomized to continuation treatment with monotherapy with lithium or divalproex.149 In a larger continuation study of 226 youth with BD (mean duration 124.4 days), YMRS scores decreased a further 12.4 points.150 In a 72‐week maintenance study, 96 outpatient children, 4‐9 years old, with PBD who had been stabilized on aripiprazole (mean dose 6.4 mg) were randomized to continuation with aripiprazole or placebo (n = 30/group).151 Although children randomized to aripiprazole, vs placebo, were enrolled significantly longer until time to discontinuation for a mood event or for any reason, the study was constrained by high drop‐out rates within the first 4 weeks (50% for the aripiprazole group; 90% for the placebo group), understood by the authors as a nocebo effect. No significant between‐group treatment effects on symptom rating or changes over time were observed for mania, depression, general impression, or global assessment. Another placebo‐controlled continuation study of aripiprazole (10 mg or 30 mg) in youths (10‐17 years old) with manic/mixed episodes followed participants for 26 weeks under double‐blind conditions after a 4‐week acute treatment phase.152 For both aripiprazole dosages, there were greater reductions in YMRS symptoms (in last observation carried forward analyses only) and time to all‐cause discontinuation was longer for both aripiprazole dosages compared to placebo. There were also higher response rates, greater improvements in global functioning, and greater reductions in clinical global impression bipolar severity for each of the aripiprazole groups vs placebo. Another recent study of 301 children and adolescents with BD‐I stabilized for at least 6 weeks on adjunctive lamotrigine, in combination with up to two mood stabilizers or antipsychotics, randomized participants to 36 weeks of either continuation treatment with lamotrigine or placebo.153 Although the primary analysis was negative, continuation with lamotrigine was superior to placebo (hazard ratio 0.46) in 13‐17‐year‐olds, but not in 10‐12‐year‐olds (hazard ratio 0.94). Although reasons for this discrepancy are uncertain, it may relate to higher rates of ADHD in the younger group. Finally, a 50‐week open‐label, flexible‐dose extension study of 321 youth, 10‐17 years old, with BD‐I (lead‐in study treatment: placebo, n = 80; asenapine, n = 241) reported that: (i) there was a mean 9.2‐point reduction in YMRS at week 50; (ii) 79.2% were considered responders based on 50% reduction in YMRS relative to acute trial baseline; (iii) somnolence/sedation/hypersomnia (42.4%) and significant weight gain (34.8%) were very common.154
6.1.4ComorbidityPositive results have been reported regarding the treatment of comorbid ADHD with mixed amphetamine salts and methylphenidate, albeit in modest‐sized samples, particularly in euthymic youth.37, 155, 156 Aripiprazole did not differ from placebo in ADHD symptom reduction.157 Preliminary findings from open trials and case reports suggest promise for adjunctive atomoxetine.158 Although stimulants, as well as antidepressants, hold some risk of precipitating mania, precise estimates of this risk are lacking, both with and without ongoing mood stabilizer cotreatment.145 A single small RCT found that lithium improved mood symptoms and comorbid substance use disorder among adolescents with, or at risk for, BD.159
6.1.5Nutritional interventionsFour open‐label nutritional trials, three of Omega 3 (Ω3) monotherapy (n = 3) and one of a commercially available multinutrient, in youth with BPSD provide preliminary evidence of potential benefits in terms of manic and depressive symptoms, global functioning, and parent‐rated internalizing and externalizing behaviors.160, 161, 162 A 12‐week pilot RCT (N = 23 youth with BD‐NOS or CycD) found that the combination of Ω3 and psychoeducation was superior to placebo and active monitoring.163 An RCT of flax seed oil (alpha‐linolenic acid [ALA]) in youth with BD‐I/BD‐II was negative.164
6.2Limitations, gaps, and future directionsPositive RCTs for maintenance treatment and bipolar depression are lacking, although preliminary positive open trials hold promise. Pharmacologic treatment of comorbidities other than ADHD is another gap. Given concerns about heterogeneity of longitudinal course, it would be helpful to examine whether subtype of BD or age of onset moderates treatment response. Future studies should include neuroimaging, neurocognition, and peripheral biomarkers as moderators and predictors of treatment response. Large‐scale RCTs of nutritional interventions are warranted, based on positive pilot RCTs and open‐label trials. Studies concentrating on CycD and OS‐BRD are crucial to address the need for titrated and evidence‐based options, along with more masked maintenance studies to look at altering trajectories, and head‐to‐head trials and trials of combinations with non‐pharmacologic treatments. Although systematically addressing the topic of offspring of parents with BD was beyond the scope of this article, it is important to note that there is also a need for large‐scale RCTs examining the relative efficacy, tolerability, and safety of antidepressants vs mood stabilizers for anxiety and/or depression, and the efficacy, tolerability, and safety of stimulants for ADHD, among BD offspring.7PSYCHOSOCIAL TREATMENTS7.1Established findings and consensusAdult psychotherapy trials provide substantial evidence for the effectiveness of family‐focused therapy (FFT),165 group psychoeducation,166, 167, 168 and interpersonal and social rhythm therapy169 in improving symptoms, reducing rates of recurrence, and hastening recovery in adults with BD. In recent years, an accumulating body of evidence similarly supports the use of manualized psychotherapies for the treatment of PBD. A recent review highlighted 13 unique studies170 and three studies published since that review further strengthen the evidence base,171, 172, 173, 174 whereas one additional study offers mixed evidence.175 The category of family psychoeducation plus skill building can be considered as a well‐established treatment, meaning that two or more research groups have, via independent RCTs, demonstrated efficacy.176 Dialectical behavior therapy171 can be considered possibly efficacious, based on a single RCT or multiple studies by the same group, while interpersonal and social rhythm therapy177 remains experimental in youths at this time. Effectiveness trials suggest that family psychoeducation plus skill‐building approaches have excellent acceptability and sustainability in community settings.178, 179
Treatment mediator analyses suggest that psychoeducation leads families to improve the quality of services they utilize, mediated by parental treatment beliefs; improved quality of services, in turn, mediates improved outcomes.180 Improved parenting skills and coping, family flexibility and family positive reframing are linked to improved mood and global functioning in youth with PBD.181 Treatment moderators include youth impairment182 and family EE,123 along with comorbid disorders, youth age, and family socioeconomic status (SES). Predictors of better treatment response include greater impairment, more stress/trauma history for the child, less Cluster B personality symptoms in parents,182 and comorbid anxiety disorders.131
With regard to secondary outcomes other than mood, family psychoeducation plus skill building are also associated with a reduction in behavioral symptoms.183 In an open trial of an adaptation of family psychoeducation and skill building, benefits were observed for adolescents with BD and comorbid substance use disorders.184 While no dismantling studies have been conducted, therapeutic ingredients common to the psychotherapy category family psychoeducation and skill building should be used. These include family involvement; psychoeducation about etiology, symptoms, course, medications, risk and protective factors, and effective treatment of BD; skill building (especially communication, problem‐solving, and emotion regulation skills); and relapse and recurrence prevention.170
In regard to prevention, or delay of onset, two RCTs have examined the impact of family psychoeducation plus skill building in youth at high risk for developing BD. Youth who received FFT had more rapid recovery from their initial mood symptoms, experienced more weeks in remission, and had lower YMRS scores over 1 year compared to youth who received enhanced care.185 In a second study, youth with depression and transient manic symptoms were 4 times less likely to convert to BPSD at 12‐month follow‐up if they received multi‐family psychoeducational psychotherapy plus treatment as usual (TAU) compared to the group who received only TAU.186
7.2Limitations, gaps, and future directionsMore work is needed to (i) determine the impact of low‐risk interventions (eg, psychosocial treatments and nutritional interventions) in preventing or delaying the onset of BD in high‐risk youth; (ii) test psychotherapies in diverse populations, including different SES and cultural backgrounds; (iii) determine what modifications are appropriate based on age or treatment format (eg, group or individual/family); (iv) determine the impact of psychotherapy on functional and quality of life outcomes as well as symptoms; (v) develop efficient ways to train large numbers of clinicians in these treatments; (vi) identify mechanisms of change and essential treatment components;170 (vii) examine the potential benefits of smartphone or Internet‐based delivery; (viii) evaluate combinations of pharmacotherapy and psychotherapy; and (ix) determine how best to disseminate manual‐based psychotherapies into health care settings.8NEUROIMAGING AND NEUROCOGNITION8.1Established findings and consensusPrevailing pathophysiologic models of BD implicate abnormalities in brain regions that regulate emotion and attention, namely the emotional control network (ECN).187 The ECN is comprised of ventrolateral and ventromedial prefrontal networks, which modulate the limbic system, specifically the amygdala, in conjunction with subcortical nuclei, such as the thalamus and striatum.187, 188 Increasing evidence suggests that there are anatomical, neurochemical, functional and cognitive abnormalities within the ECN in PBD.188, 189 Pathophysiologic abnormalities underlying other cognitive functions that are altered in BD, such as reward processing, have also been studied.190
8.1.1NeuroimagingBrain structureWithin the ECN, the amygdala plays a central role in emotional regulation. Two meta‐analyses of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) studies reported that youth with PBD present with smaller amygdala volumes compared with controls.191, 192 One prospective study that evaluated youth after their first manic episode showed that amygdala volumes failed to show a normal increase with aging in patients, whereas this did not occur in controls or in youth with ADHD, suggesting that hampered neurodevelopment of the amygdala may underlie the dysfunctional emotional processing present in the ventral‐limbic pathway.193 Diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) studies have investigated abnormalities in the white matter microstructure of youth with PBD. Preliminary findings suggest the presence of abnormal white matter microstructure in superior frontal regions,194, 195 and inferior/ventral frontal areas, such as the orbitofrontal or anterior cingulate cortex, and anterior regions of the corpus callosum196, 197, 198, 199, 200 compared to controls. One study found even greater reduction in white matter integrity in the anterior limb of the internal capsule in PBD vs adult BD.201 Most of these studies had very small sample sizes, but, together, they are consistent with a hypothesis of structural connectivity deficits between prefrontal‐subcortical areas that underlie the prefrontal‐limbic dysfunction in PBD.Brain functionMeta‐analyses of over 20 task‐based functional MRI (fMRI) studies with approximately 500 youth concluded that BD involves hypoactivation of prefrontal areas and hyperactivation of limbic areas.202, 203 Weigbreit et al (2014) included more emotional (emotional face processing) than non‐emotional (or cognitive) tasks whereas Lee et al (2014) did not discriminate the effects of emotional vs cognitive tasks. PBD presents with greater activation in the right amygdala, parahippocampal gyrus, and left putamen, and lower activation in the right ventrolateral and dorsolateral prefrontal cortices compared with controls in paradigms that involve emotional stimuli.202, 203 These findings suggest that prefrontal regions are unable to modulate hyperactive limbic regions,203 due either to a primary prefrontal dysfunction or to altered connectivity between prefrontal and limbic regions. Studies using non‐emotional tasks (eg, reversal learning and reward anticipation) also showed abnormal functional activity of prefrontal areas, such as the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, parietal regions, such as the temporal gyrus, and subcortical regions, such as the thalamus, during processing of the tasks.204, 205, 206 fMRI studies using tasks of attention and response inhibition have also found that prefrontal areas involved in attention and inhibitory control (namely the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex) are hypoactive while processing a continuous performance task in patients with PBD and comorbid ADHD, while posterior parietal and temporal areas are hyperactive, possibly as a compensatory mechanism.207 Other studies using continuous performance task and response inhibition also have found underactivation of the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex.208, 209 The few resting state fMRI studies in PBD show that youth with PBD present with fronto‐temporal, amygdala‐hippocampus and amygdala‐precuneus functional connectivity alterations,210, 211, 212 with similar alterations observed during bipolar depression.213 Together, these studies suggest that PBD is characterized by abnormal prefrontal‐limbic functional connectivity in the processing of emotion, attention, and reward. Although still too preliminary to allow any definitive conclusions about the neurophysiology of PBD, these findings converge with adult BD findings.Brain chemistryProton magnetic resonance spectroscopy studies are particularly important to help understand two current neurobiological hypotheses of BD, ie, glutamatergic dysfunction and mitochondrial dysfunction or energy metabolism dysfunction. Several studies in PBD have shown abnormalities in glutamate or glutamine levels in prefrontal brain areas.214, 215 Abnormal levels of metabolites that are considered to be biomarkers of mitochondrial dysfunction or cell energy metabolism, such as decreased N‐acetyl‐aspartate or increased myo‐inositol levels, were found in dorsal and ventral areas of the prefrontal cortex in PBD.216, 217, 218, 219, 220, 221, 222, 223, 224
Although very valuable given the possibility of in vivo measurement of metabolites that might relate to pathophysiologic processes of neuronal integrity/viability, glutamatergic neurotransmission, and cell energy metabolism, the exact meaning of these results is poorly understood, partly because they are difficult to replicate or to predict. For instance, although several proton spectroscopy studies reported positive results for specific metabolite differences between patients and controls (eg, N‐acetyl‐aspartate or glutamine),215, 220, 223, 224 within the same experiment, results are often negative for other metabolites (eg, creatine, myo‐inositol and choline).215
8.2Neuroimaging in relation to treatmentThere is a preliminary literature regarding neuroimaging studies in relation to treatment of PBD. For instance, an association between change in prefrontal glutamate concentrations and change in manic symptoms was reported in patients who achieved remission of mania after treatment with divalproex sodium.225 Remission of mania after olanzapine treatment was associated with an increase in ventromedial prefrontal N‐acetyl aspartate and choline levels.226 Quetiapine treatment for bipolar depression may lead to decreased neural activity in the left occipital cortex, and increased neural activity in the left insula, left cerebellum, and right ventrolateral prefrontal cortex during performance of a face emotion recognition task.227 Treatment of mania with ziprasidone was associated with an increase in activation in the right ventrolateral prefrontal cortex in response to a sustained attention task, which suggests that the ziprasidone antimanic effect is associated with improved prefrontal modulation of emotional regulation.228 Carbamazepine treatment of mania was also associated with increased activation in Brodmann area 10 of the right prefrontal cortex in a small sample of 11 adolescents,229 further suggesting that mood stabilizers might exert their beneficial effects by improving the top‐down prefrontal modulation of limbic areas. Treatment response to risperidone and divalproex sodium for mania may lead to increased functional connectivity of the amygdala within the ECN.230 These preliminary findings offer insights regarding putative mechanisms of action of these medications. One recent study provided evidence that some psychotherapy modalities, such as FFT, improve dorsolateral prefrontal cortex activation and decrease amygdala activation in youth with mood dysregulation at familial risk for BD,231 which is consistent with the putative treatment effects of mood stabilizers (ie, improved prefrontal modulation of limbic areas, or better “top‐down control”). Additional studies are necessary to better understand the physiology of treatment response and guide improved therapeutic strategies.8.2.1NeurocognitionPBD is associated with impairment in several cognitive domains.232 A meta‐analysis of 10 cognitive studies reported overall cognitive deficits in PBD (n = 352) compared to healthy controls (HCs; n = 439) with mean effect sizes that are: large in verbal memory; moderate to large in attention and working memory; moderate in executive functioning, visual perceptual skills, and visual memory; and small to moderate in motor speed, reading achievement, full‐scale IQ, and verbal fluency.232 A prospective study showed that youth with PBD may exhibit a delay in cognitive development compared with controls in some cognitive domains (eg, executive functioning and verbal memory), despite optimal pharmacologic management.233 Thus, it is essential to investigate therapeutic strategies, such as cognitive remediation234 and/or optimizing cardiometabolic health,78 that might be useful to restore these cognitive deficits and improve academic, social and functional impairments in youth with PBD.In summary, in the last two decades, many neuroimaging and cognition studies have demonstrated anomalous brain structure, brain function, and cognition, alongside preliminary evidence of lagging neurocognitive development in PBD, mainly relating to the ECN.8.3Limitations, gaps, and future directionsFurther studies are necessary to understand whether abnormal neurodevelopment is present across other brain regions and to what extent abnormal neurostructure is related to abnormal brain function, behavioral aspects of the disease, and alterations in cognitive, social and functional development. Essential questions that remain unanswered concern how these abnormalities predict clinical course or the social, academic, personal, and functional impairments present in PBD. Additionally, it is largely unknown which brain abnormalities represent risk factors, resilience factors, early disease markers, or some combination of these. Studies that integrate information from different imaging modalities and theoretical perspectives should help parse these effects. Longitudinal studies will be crucial to help to discern developmental and progressive neurophysiological aspects of PBD. Finally, future studies need to parse the independent and interactive effects of PBD in relation to treatment effects and response markers, as well as common comorbidities such as ADHD, anxiety, and substance use disorders.9PERIPHERAL BIOMARKERS9.1Established findings and consensusNumerous studies over the past decade have examined peripheral biomarkers among adults with BD, focusing most consistently on a pattern of increased inflammatory and oxidative stress markers and decreased neurotrophic markers, particularly during acute mood episodes.235, 236, 237, 238 Peripheral biomarkers, particularly those that fluctuate in relation to symptoms, have the potential for clinical application such as in the selection, prediction, and assessment of treatments. In contrast to the relatively broad literature on neuroimaging and neurocognition, there is a relative dearth of studies on peripheral biomarkers among youth with BD. However, in recent years there has been growing interest in this topic. Given the nascent literature, the following is a synopsis rather than a conclusive demonstration of replicated findings.In a study of 30 adolescents with PBD, hypomanic symptoms were associated with levels of high‐sensitivity c reactive protein (hsCRP). Brain‐derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) and interleukin 6 (IL‐6) were negatively associated with each other, and cardiovascular high‐risk levels of hsCRP were observed in 40% of the sample.239 A subsequent larger study on the topic based on 123 young adults in the Course and Outcome of Bipolar Youth study found that, controlling for comorbidity and treatment, tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF‐α) was associated with the proportion of time with psychosis, IL‐6 was associated with the proportion of time with subthreshold mood symptoms and with any suicide attempt, and hsCRP was associated with maximum depression severity over the preceding 6 months.240
Two controlled studies of adolescents with PBD provide support for elevated inflammation. The first study (18 BD patients, 13 major depressive disorder [MDD] patients and 20 HCs) found significantly higher levels of nuclear factor kappa beta (NF‐κβ) in peripheral blood mononuclear cells, monocytes, and lymphocytes, higher IL‐1β plasma levels, and greater TNF‐α‐induced elevations in NF‐κβ in adolescents with mood disorders than in HCs.241 The second study (40 BD patients and 20 HCs) found elevated IL‐6 and TNF‐α levels among adolescents with PBD.242
A recent study of 30 adolescents with BD found that oxidative stress markers were lower as compared to adults with BD, and lipid hydroperoxide (LPH) levels were associated with a proxy measure of atherosclerosis but not with mood symptoms or medications.243 A population‐based study of young adults found that those with BPSD, but not those with MDD, had increased protein oxidative damage compared to HCs.244 A study of adolescents with or at risk for PBD found that adolescents with PBD had significantly lower LPH vs controls, with non‐symptomatic adolescents at familial risk falling between the other groups.245 Finally, a study of 29 adolescents with PBD and 25 HCs found that LPH−BDNF correlations were significantly different between adolescents with PBD and HCs, and that, among adolescents with PBD in the top half of the distribution of BDNF levels, greater LPH levels were associated with poorer executive function.246
In an early biomarker study, platelet‐derived BDNF protein and lymphocyte‐derived BDNF mRNA levels were reduced among 26 medication‐free youth with PBD compared to HCs; mRNA BDNF levels increased significantly in a subset of 19 participants after 8 weeks of treatment.247 A study of 30 adolescents with BD found a significant association between BDNF levels and amygdala volumes,248 whereas other findings from the same sample indicated no association between neurotrophic factors and hippocampal volumes.249
Similar to blood‐based biomarkers, the literature regarding the genetics of PBD is sparse. A family‐based association study found that genes coding for the serotonin transporter (solute carrier family 6 member 4), BDNF, and catechol‐O‐methyltransferase (COMT) were not significantly associated with PBD,250 whereas a prior study based on the same sample found that four of 28 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the dopamine transporter gene (SLC6A3) were associated with PBD, of which only rs40184 remained significant after correction for multiple comparisons.251 Another family‐based association study found that two SNPs in early growth gene 3 (EGR3) were nominally significantly associated with PBD,252 as were glutamate decarboxylase 1 (GAD1)253 and BDNF val66 alleles.254 Most recently, a genetic study based on participants in the Treatment of Early Age Mania study found that a calcium channel, voltage‐dependent, L type, alpha 1c subunit (CACNA1C) haplotype was associated with PBD. Whereas the CACNA1C rs1006737 SNP has been previously associated with adult BD in genome‐wide association studies,255 it was the rs10848632 CACNA1C SNP that was nominally associated with PBD in SNP analyses.256
9.2Limitations, gaps, and future directionsDespite the substantial increase in research findings in this area over the past 5 years, important limitations and gaps remain. Most studies have been constrained by small samples, limited covariate modeling, and cross‐sectional design. Ultimately, the clinical application of peripheral biomarkers will require that findings are significant in the heterogeneous samples in which these biomarkers would be employed, as reflected by a variety of comorbidities, different subtypes of PBD, and varying medication regimens. Studies using repeated measures afford the advantage of within‐subject analyses, which mitigate the impact of heterogeneity and state‐related changes. With regard to genetics, larger studies are needed, as are studies examining the link between genetic markers and intermediate phenotypes, such as neuroimaging, in PBD. In addition to these considerations, studies that incorporate biomarkers as objective predictors, treatment targets, and/or correlates of treatment response are warranted.10CONCLUSIONSThere has been substantial progress in the area of PBD over the past 20 years. As data have accumulated and controversy has dissipated, the field has moved past existential questions about PBD toward defining and pursuing pressing clinical and scientific priorities that remain. The overall body of evidence supports the position that perceptions about marked international and developmental differences have been overstated, albeit that additional research on these topics is warranted. Traction toward improved outcomes will be supported by continued emphasis on phenomenology, prospective clinical epidemiology, pathophysiology, measurement‐based quantitative approaches including digital phenotyping, and novel therapeutics.Despite the substantial increase in consensus regarding phenomenology and epidemiology, there remain outstanding questions about the prevalence of PBD in pre‐pubertal children. Whereas the existence of PBD in pre‐pubertal children has long been recognized, and indeed described in Kraepelin's seminal text,257 reliable and valid estimates of the epidemiologic and clinical prevalence of PBD in pre‐pubertal children are lacking. With the progress that has been made, in terms of parsing PBD from chronic irritability without episodic mania/hypomania, in terms of increased recognition of PBD, and in terms of screening and diagnostic instruments, the field is now better positioned to examine this topic than it was as recently as a decade ago.In terms of pathophysiology, it is important to consider the context of the Research Domain Criteria (RDoC) initiative, which suggests the value of integrating dimensional liability traits alongside DSM‐driven diagnoses and diagnostic criteria. In addition to all the inherent complexity of BD in adults, including differences across mood states, comorbidities, and BD subtypes, among others, research focusing on youth includes the added challenge of developmental differences. Future research should focus on age effects on the biology, manifestations, and treatment of PBD.Future research should also focus on meaningfully integrating multiple methodologic levels of analysis. Thus far, there is a paucity of research that combines, for example, multiple neuroimaging approaches, neuroimaging and/or neurocognition with biomarkers, and/or neurobiology and clinical epidemiology. To the extent that the field can apply the large sample sizes and prospective measures of cohort studies toward improved understanding of the neurobiology of PBD, findings will become increasingly clinically and heuristically relevant.From a treatment perspective, it will be important to begin addressing functional outcomes, rather than simply focusing on symptom reduction. Even during recovery, youth with PBD demonstrate impaired psychosocial functioning. Improved understanding of the factors underlying these impairments will allow for targeted preventive and treatment approaches. More studies with longer periods of acute treatment and maintenance studies will both help to clarify stabilization and relapse prevention. Representative epidemiologic, not just clinical, PBD samples show very high rates of suicidality and multi‐comorbidity alongside very low rates of treatment, even though “over‐treatment” and “over‐diagnosis” garner more attention.258, 259 The high degree of complexity and severity of PBD, even in the relatively early years of the disease, is in part an outcome of delaying or avoiding treatment altogether. It is crucial that the clinical and scientific community continues collaborative efforts, together with consumers, families, schools, and other stakeholders, toward public education and stigma reduction.Finally, prevention strategies must be an area of emphasis in the decade ahead. Findings suggest that some psychotherapies and perhaps nutritional interventions might be low‐risk options for early stage/prodromal intervention. Here, prevention refers not only to the prevention of BD, which is an important but relatively distal goal, but also to the prevention of comorbidity accumulation (eg, substance use disorders), suicidality, treatment refractoriness, neurocognitive and functional impairment, and adverse physical health outcomes. Indeed, the physical implications of BD, particularly in terms of future cardiovascular disease, are increasingly recognized.79 Just as it is important for primary care providers to recognize the increased cardiovascular risk associated with PBD, it is important for our own field to begin integrating brain−body considerations in the assessment and treatment of PBD. The therapeutic and preventive potential of physical exercise for PBD, for example, is an almost entirely untouched topic.260, 261
While many questions remain unanswered, or insufficiently answered, we are hopeful that progress over the next decade will be far less constrained by controversies that, although critical in defining the directions of the field, also slowed progress and limited collaboration. At a time when clinically relevant psychiatric research faces the ironically dichotomous pressures of the RDoC era (ie, choosing between DSM and RDoC), it is important to retain focus on the importance of the categorical BD diagnosis in terms of treatment selection, clinical course, and familial risk. We are optimistic that liberally applied integration strategies (ie, dimensional as well as categorical views, neurobiology alongside clinical epidemiology, and pharmacologic alongside psychosocial interventions) will best serve the needs of our field and our constituents.DISCLOSURESDr Birmaher receives funds for research from the National Institute of Mental Health. He receives royalties for publications from: Random House, Inc., Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, APA Press, and UpToDate. Dr. Carlson receives funds for research from the NIMH and Patient Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI). Dr. Chang is an unpaid consultant for GSK, Lilly, and BMS. He is on the DSMB for Sunovion. In the past 3 years he has received research support from GSK and Merck, and has been a consultant for Actavis and Janssen. Dr. DelBello has received research support from NIMH, NIDDK, and PCORI, as well as Otsuka, Lundbeck, Sunovion, Pfizer, Johnson and Johnson, Supernus, Amarex, and Shire; and has received consulting/advisory board fees/honoraria from Pfizer, Lundbeck, Sunovion, Supernus, Takeda, Johnson and Johnson, Neuronetics, and Akili. Dr. Findling receives or has received research support from, acted as a consultant for and/or served on a speaker's bureau for Actavis, Akili, Alcobra, American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, American Psychiatric Press, Bracket, CogCubed, Cognition Group, Coronado Biosciences, Elsevier, Epharma Solutions, Forest, Genentech, GlaxoSmithKline, Guilford Press, Ironshore, Johns Hopkins University Press, KemPharm, Lundbeck, Medgenics, Merck, NIH, Neurim, Novartis, Otsuka, PCORI, Pfizer, Physicians Postgraduate Press, Purdue, Rhodes Pharmaceuticals, Roche, Sage, Shire, Sunovion, Supernus Pharmaceuticals, Syneurx, Takeda, Teva, Tris, Validus, and WebMD. Dr. Fristad receives research funds from Janssen, publication royalties from Guilford Press, American Psychiatric Press and Child &amp; Family Psychological Services, and honoraria from Physician's Post‐Graduate Press. Dr. Goldstein has nothing to disclose. Dr. Hillegers has nothing to disclose. Dr. Kim has nothing to disclose. Dr. Kowatch is a consultant on data‐safety monitoring boards for Forest and Pfizer; he is faculty for the REACH Institute. Dr. Miklowitz receives funds for research from the NIMH and royalties from Guilford Press and John Wiley &amp; Sons. Dr. Nery's spouse is an employee of Eli Lilly &amp; Company. Dr. Perez Algorta has no disclosures/conflicts of interest. Dr. Van Meter has no disclosures/conflicts of interest. Dr. Wozniak has nothing to disclose personally; her spouse has received speaker honoraria from Otsuka, royalties from UptoDate, consultation fees from Advance Medical, FlexPharma, and Merck; and research support from UCB Pharma, NeuroMetrix, and Luitpold. Dr. Youngstrom has consulted with Pearson, Otsuka, Lundbeck, Joe Startup Technologies, and Western Psychological Services about psychological assessment, and receives funding from NIMH.REFERENCES1

Van Meter
AR
, 
Moreira
AL
, 
Youngstrom
EA
. Meta‐analysis of epidemiological studies of bipolar disorder. J Clin Psychiatry. 2011;72:1250‐1256.216725012

Andrade
N
, 
Hishinuma
E
, 
McDermott
J
, et al. The National Center on Indigenous Hawaiian Behavioral Health Study of Prevalence of Psychiatric Disorders in Native Hawaiian Adolescents. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2006;45:26‐36.163275783

Anselmi
L
, 
Fleitlich‐Bilyk
B
, 
Menezes
A
, 
Araújo
C
, 
Rohde
L
. Prevalence of psychiatric disorders in a Brazilian birth cohort of 11‐year‐olds. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol. 2010;45:135‐142.193814264

Benjet
C
, 
Borges
G
, 
Medina‐Mora
ME
, 
Zambrano
J
, 
Aguilar‐Gaxiola
S
. Youth mental health in a populous city of the developing world: results from the Mexican Adolescent Mental Health Survey. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2009;50:386‐395.190404995

Canals
J
, 
Domenech
E
, 
Carbajo
G
, 
Blade
J
. Prevalence of DSM‐III‐R and ICD‐10 psychiatric disorders in a Spanish population of 18‐year‐olds. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1997;96:287‐294.93509586

Costello
EJ
, 
Angold
A
, 
Burns
BJ
, et al. The Great Smoky Mountains Study of Youth: goals, design, methods, and the prevalence of DSM‐III‐R disorders. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1996;53:1129‐1136.89566797

Gould
M
, 
King
R
, 
Greenwald
S
, et al. Psychopathology associated with suicidal ideation and attempts among children and adolescents. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1998;37:915‐923.97356118

Kessler
R
, 
Avenevoli
S
, 
Green
J
, et al. National Comorbidity Survey Replication Adolescent Supplement (NCS‐A): III. Concordance of DSM‐IV/CIDI diagnoses with clinical reassessments. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;48:386‐399.192524509

Kim‐Cohen
J
, 
Caspi
A
, 
Moffitt
T
, 
Harrington
H
, 
Milne
B
, 
Poulton
R
. Prior juvenile diagnoses in adults with mental disorder: developmental follow‐back of a prospective‐longitudinal cohort. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2003;60:709‐717.1286077510

Lewinsohn
P
, 
Klein
D
, 
Seeley
J
. Bipolar disorders in a community sample of older adolescents: prevalence, phenomenology, comorbidity, and course. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1995;34:454‐463.775125911

Lynch
F
, 
Mills
C
, 
Daly
I
, 
Fitzpatrick
C
. Challenging times: prevalence of psychiatric disorders and suicidal behaviours in Irish adolescents. J Adolesc. 2006;29:555‐573.1620244812

Päären
A
. Hypomania spectrum disorder in adolescence: a 15‐year follow‐up of non‐mood morbidity in adulthood. BMC Psychiatry. 2014;14:9.2442893813

Pan
PM
, 
Salum
GA
, 
Gadelha
A
, et al. Manic symptoms in youth: dimensions, latent classes, and associations with parental psychopathology. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2014;53:625‐634.2483988114

Stringaris
A
, 
Santosh
P
, 
Leibenluft
E
, 
Goodman
R
. Youth meeting symptom and impairment criteria for mania‐like episodes lasting less than four days: an epidemiological enquiry. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2009;51:31‐38.1968633015

Tijssen
MJ
, 
Van Os
J
, 
Wittchen
HU
, 
Lieb
R
, 
Beesdo
K
, 
Wichers
M
. Risk factors predicting onset and persistence of subthreshold expression of bipolar psychopathology among youth from the community. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2010;122:255‐266.2019949016

Verhulst
F
, 
Van der Ende
J
, 
Ferdinand
R
, 
Kasius
M
. The prevalence of DSM‐III‐R diagnoses in a national sample of Dutch adolescents. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1997;54:329‐336.910714917

Kozloff
N
, 
Cheung
AH
, 
Schaffer
A
, et al. Bipolar disorder among adolescents and young adults: results from an epidemiological sample. J Affect Disord. 2010;125:350‐354.2022653518

Oh
J
, 
Chang
JG
, 
Lee
SB
, 
Song
DH
, 
Cheon
KA
. Comparison of aripiprazole and other atypical antipsychotics for pediatric bipolar disorder: a retrospective chart review of efficacy and tolerability. Clin Psychopharmacol Neurosci. 2013;11:72‐79.2402355119

Shon
SH
, 
Joo
Y
, 
Park
J
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Kim
HW
. Comparison of clinical characteristics of bipolar and depressive disorders in Korean clinical sample of youth: a retrospective chart review. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2013;23:307‐316.2396364420

Oh
H‐J
, 
Glutting
JJ
, 
McDermott
PA
. An epidemiological‐cohort study of DAS processing speed factor: how well does it identify concurrent achievement and behavior problems?
J Psychoeduc Assess. 1999;17:362‐375.21

Moreno
C
, 
Laje
G
, 
Blanco
C
, 
Jiang
H
, 
Schmidt
AB
, 
Olfson
M
. National trends in the outpatient diagnosis and treatment of bipolar disorder in youth. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2007;64:1032‐1039.1776826822

Blader
JC
, 
Carlson
GA
. Increased rates of bipolar disorder diagnoses among U.S. child, adolescent, and adult inpatients, 1996‐2004. Biol Psychiat. 2007;62:107‐114.1730677323

Dubicka
B
, 
Carlson
GA
, 
Vail
A
, 
Harrington
R
. Prepubertal mania: diagnostic differences between US and UK clinicians. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2008;17:153‐161.1787650324

Costello
EJ
, 
Egger
H
, 
Angold
A
. 10‐year research update review: the epidemiology of child and adolescent psychiatric disorders: I. Methods and public health burden. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2005;44:972‐986.1617510225

Correll
CU
, 
Hauser
M
, 
Penzner
JB
, et al. Type and duration of subsyndromal symptoms in youth with bipolar I disorder prior to their first manic episode. Bipolar Disord. 2014;16:478‐492.2459778226

Post
RM
, 
Ballenger
JC
, 
Rey
AC
, 
Bunney
WE
Jr
. Slow and rapid onset of manic episodes: implications for underlying biology. Psychiatry Res. 1981;4:229‐237.693901227

Bellivier
F
, 
Etain
B
, 
Malafosse
A
, et al. Age at onset in bipolar I affective disorder in the USA and Europe. World J Biol Psychiatry. 2014;15:369‐376.2218836628

Post
RM
, 
Luckenbaugh
DA
, 
Leverich
GS
, et al. Incidence of childhood‐onset bipolar illness in the USA and Europe. Br J Psychiatry. 2008;192:150‐151.1824503529

Post
RM
, 
Leverich
GS
, 
Kupka
R
, et al. Increased parental history of bipolar disorder in the United States: association with early age of onset. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2014;129:375‐382.2413829830

Diler
RS
. Pediatric Bipolar Disorder: A Global Perspective. New York: Nova Science; 2007.31

Masi
G
, 
Perugi
G
, 
Millepiedi
S
, et al. Clinical implications of DSM‐IV subtyping of bipolar disorders in referred children and adolescents. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2007;46:1299‐1306.1788557132

Diler
RS
, 
Uguz
S
, 
Seydaoglu
G
, 
Erol
N
, 
Avci
A
. Differentiating bipolar disorder in Turkish prepubertal children with attention‐deficit hyperactivity disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2007;9:243‐251.1743029933

Benarous
X
, 
Mikita
N
, 
Goodman
R
, 
Stringaris
A
. Distinct relationships between social aptitude and dimensions of manic‐like symptoms in youth. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2016;25:831‐842.2665048234

Masi
G
, 
Toni
C
, 
Perugi
G
, 
Mucci
M
, 
Millepiedi
S
, 
Akiskal
HS
. Anxiety disorders in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder: a neglected comorbidity. Can J Psychiatry. 2001;46:797‐802.1176163035

Jairam
R
, 
Srinath
S
, 
Girimaji
SC
, 
Seshadri
SP
. A prospective 4‐5 year follow‐up of juvenile onset bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2004;6:386‐394.1538313136

Srinath
S
, 
Janardhan Reddy
YC
, 
Girimaji
SR
, 
Seshadri
SP
, 
Subbakrishna
DK
. A prospective study of bipolar disorder in children and adolescents from India. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1998;98:437‐442.987978437

Zeni
CP
, 
Tramontina
S
, 
Ketzer
CR
, 
Pheula
GF
, 
Rohde
LA
. Methylphenidate combined with aripiprazole in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder and attention‐ deficit/hyperactivity disorder: a randomized crossover trial. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2009;19:553‐561.1987798038

Masi
G
, 
Perugi
G
, 
Millepiedi
S
, et al. Pharmacological response in juvenile bipolar disorder subtypes: a naturalistic retrospective examination. Psychiatry Res. 2010;177:192‐198.2038117039

Zeni
CP
, 
Tramontina
S
, 
Zeni
TA
, et al. The Val66Met polymorphism at the BDNF gene does not influence Wisconsin Card Sorting Test results in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder. Rev Bras Psiquiatr. 2013;35:44‐50.2356759940

Lauxen Peruzzolo
T
, 
Anes
M
, 
Kohmann Ade
M
, et al. Correlation between peripheral levels of brain‐derived neurotrophic factor and hippocampal volume in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder. Neural Plast. 2015;2015:324825.2607509741

Zeni
CP
, 
Tramontina
S
, 
Aguiar
BW
, et al. BDNF Val66Met polymorphism and peripheral protein levels in pediatric bipolar disorder and attention‐deficit/hyperactivity disorder. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2016;134:268‐274.2720907342

Manon
HJH
, 
Catrien
GR
, 
Marjolein
W
, 
Frank
CV
, 
Johan
O
, 
Willem
AN
. Five‐year prospective outcome of psychopathology in the adolescent offspring of bipolar parents. Bipolar Disord. 2005;7:344‐350.1602648743

Grigoroiu‐Serbanescu
M
, 
Christodorescu
D
, 
Jipescu
I
, 
Totoescu
A
, 
Marinescu
E
, 
Ardelean
V
. Psychopathology in children aged 10‐17 of bipolar parents: psychopathology rate and correlates of the severity of the psychopathology. J Affect Disord. 1989;16:167‐179.252211644

Galanter
CA
, 
Hundt
SR
, 
Goyal
P
, 
Le
J
, 
Fisher
PW
. Variability among research diagnostic interview instruments in the application of DSM‐IV‐TR criteria for pediatric bipolar disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2012;51:605‐621.2263262045

Galanter
CA
, 
Patel
VL
. Medical decision making: a selective review for child psychiatrists and psychologists. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2005;46:675‐689.1597206546

Carlson
GA
. Disruptive mood dysregulation disorder: where did it come from and where is it going. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016;26:90‐93.2700745147

Nader
EG
, 
Kleinman
A
, 
Gomes
BC
, et al. Negative expressed emotion best discriminates families with bipolar disorder children. J Affect Disord. 2013;148:418‐423.2321889648

Teixeira
AM
, 
Kleinman
A
, 
Zanetti
M
, et al. Preserved white matter in unmedicated pediatric bipolar disorder. Neurosci Lett. 2014;579:41‐45.2501782749

Lee
HJ
, 
Joo
Y
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Yum
SY
, 
Findling
RL
, 
Kim
HW
. Diagnostic validity and reliability of a Korean version of the Parent and Adolescent General Behavior Inventories. Compr Psychiatry. 2014;55:1730‐1737.2496244750

Mesman
E
, 
Birmaher
BB
, 
Goldstein
BI
, et al. Categorical and dimensional psychopathology in Dutch and US offspring of parents with bipolar disorder: a preliminary cross‐national comparison. J Affect Disord. 2016;205:95‐102.2742342451

Achenbach
TM
, 
Rescorla
LA
. Manual for the ASEBA School‐Age Forms &amp; Profiles. Burlington, VT: University of Vermont; 2001.52

Kaufman
J
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Brent
D
, et al. Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for School‐Age Children‐Present and Lifetime version (K‐SADS‐PL): initial reliability and validity data. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1997;36:980‐988.920467753

Youngstrom
EA
, 
Genzlinger
JE
, 
Egerton
GA
, 
Van Meter
AR
. Multivariate meta‐analysis of the discriminative validity of caregiver, youth, and teacher rating scales for pediatric bipolar disorder: mother knows best about mania. Arch Sci Psychol. 2015;3:112‐137.54

Leibenluft
E
, 
Charney
DS
, 
Towbin
KE
, 
Bhangoo
RK
, 
Pine
DS
. Defining clinical phenotypes of juvenile mania. Am J Psychiatry. 2003;160:430‐437.1261182155

Axelson
DA
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Findling
RL
, et al. Concerns regarding the inclusion of temper dysregulation disorder with dysphoria in the diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders, fifth edition. J Clin Psychiatry. 2011;72:1257‐1262. https://doi.org/10.4088/jcp.10com06220:e1-e6.2167249456

Geller
B
, 
Craney
JL
, 
Bolhofner
K
, 
DelBello
MP
, 
Williams
M
, 
Zimerman
B
. One‐year recovery and relapse rates of children with a prepubertal and early adolescent bipolar disorder phenotype. Am J Psychiatry. 2001;158:303‐305.1115681557

Carlson
GA
, 
Klein
DN
. How to understand divergent views on bipolar disorder in youth. Annu Rev Clin Psychol. 2014;10:529‐551.2438723758

Hunt
J
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Leonard
H
, et al. Irritability without elation in a large bipolar youth sample: frequency and clinical description. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;48:730‐739.1946587859

Fonseka
TM
, 
Swampillai
B
, 
Timmins
V
, et al. Significance of borderline personality‐spectrum symptoms among adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Affect Disord. 2015;170:39‐45.2523323760

Mitchell
RHB
, 
Timmins
V
, 
Collins
J
, 
Scavone
A
, 
Iskric
A
, 
Goldstein
BI
. Prevalence and correlates of disruptive mood dysregulation disorder among adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016;26:147‐153.2684470761

Fristad
MA
, 
Wolfson
H
, 
Algorta
GP
, et al. Disruptive mood dysregulation disorder and bipolar disorder not otherwise specified: fraternal or identical twins?
J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016;26:138‐146.2685963062

Merikangas
KR
, 
Jin
R
, 
He
J‐P
, et al. Prevalence and correlates of bipolar spectrum disorder in the world mental health survey initiative. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2011;68:241‐251.2138326263

Van Meter
AR
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Findling
RL
. Cyclothymic disorder: a critical review. Clin Psychol Rev. 2012;32:229‐243.2245978664

Axelson
DA
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Strober
MA
, et al. Course of subthreshold bipolar disorder in youth: diagnostic progression from bipolar disorder not otherwise specified. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2011;50:1001‐1016.2196177565

Axelson
D
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Strober
M
, et al. Phenomenology of children and adolescents with bipolar spectrum disorders. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2006;63:1139‐1148.1701581666

Van Meter
A
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Demeter
C
, 
Findling
RL
. Examining the validity of cyclothymic disorder in a youth sample: replication and extension. J Abnorm Child Psychol. 2013;41:367‐378.2296849167

Geller
B
, 
Zimerman
B
, 
Williams
M
, et al. Diagnostic characteristics of 93 cases of a prepubertal and early adolescent bipolar disorder phenotype by gender, puberty and comorbid attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2000;10:157‐164.1105240568

Youngstrom
EA
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Findling
RL
. Pediatric bipolar disorder: validity, phenomenology, and recommendations for diagnosis. Bipolar Disord. 2008;10:194‐214.1819923769

Merikangas
KR
, 
J‐p
H
, 
Burstein
M
, et al. Lifetime prevalence of mental disorders in U.S. adolescents: results from the National Comorbidity Survey Replication‐Adolescent Supplement (NCS‐A). J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2010;49:980‐989.2085504370

Wittchen
HU
, 
Frohlich
C
, 
Behrendt
S
, et al. Cannabis use and cannabis use disorders and their relationship to mental disorders: a 10‐year prospective‐longitudinal community study in adolescents. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2007;88(Suppl 1):S60‐S70.1725777971

Van Meter
AR
, 
Burke
C
, 
Kowatch
RA
, 
Findling
RL
, 
Youngstrom
EA
. Ten‐year updated meta‐analysis of the clinical characteristics of pediatric mania and hypomania. Bipolar Disord. 2016;18:19‐32.2674867872

Birmaher
B
, 
Axelson
D
, 
Strober
M
, et al. Clinical course of children and adolescents with bipolar spectrum disorders. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2006;63:175‐183.1646186173

Sachs
GS
, 
Baldassano
CF
, 
Truman
CJ
, 
Guille
C
. Comorbidity of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder with early‐ and late‐onset bipolar disorder. Am J Psychiatry. 2000;157:466‐468.1069882974

Nierenberg
AA
, 
Miyahara
S
, 
Spencer
T
, et al. Clinical and diagnostic implications of lifetime attention‐deficit/hyperactivity disorder comorbidity in adults with bipolar disorder: data from the first 1000 STEP‐BD participants. Biol Psychiat. 2005;57:1467‐1473.1595002275

Goldstein
BI
, 
Blanco
C
, 
He
J‐P
, 
Merikangas
K
. Correlates of overweight and obesity among adolescents with bipolar disorder in the National Comorbidity Survey‐Adolescent Supplement (NCS‐A). J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2016;55:1020‐1026.2787163676

Shapiro
J
, 
Mindra
S
, 
Timmins
V
, et al. Controlled study of obesity among adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016;27:95‐100.2677122677

Naiberg
MR
, 
Newton
DF
, 
Collins
JE
, 
Bowie
CR
, 
Goldstein
BI
. Impulsivity is associated with blood pressure and waist circumference among adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Psychiatr Res. 2016;83:230‐239.2766553578

Naiberg
MR
, 
Newton
DF
, 
Collins
JE
, 
Dickstein
DP
, 
Bowie
CR
, 
Goldstein
BI
. Elevated triglycerides are associated with decreased executive function among adolescents with bipolar disorder. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2016;134:241‐248.2732974379

Goldstein
BI
, 
Carnethon
MR
, 
Matthews
KA
, et al. Major depressive disorder and bipolar disorder predispose youth to accelerated atherosclerosis and early cardiovascular disease: a Scientific Statement From the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2015;132:965‐986.2626073680

Martin
K
, 
Woo
J
, 
Timmins
V
, et al. Binge eating and emotional eating behaviors among adolescents and young adults with bipolar disorder. J Affect Disord. 2016;195:88‐95.2689028881

Jewell
L
, 
Abtan
R
, 
Scavone
A
, 
Timmins
V
, 
Swampillai
B
, 
Goldstein
BI
. Preliminary evidence of disparities in physical activity among adolescents with bipolar disorder. Ment Health Phys Act. 2015;8:62‐67.82
APA
. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders. 5th edn
Arlington, VA: American Psychiatric Publishing; 2013.83

Axelson
D
, 
Findling
RL
, 
Fristad
MA
, et al. Examining the proposed disruptive mood dysregulation disorder diagnosis in children in the Longitudinal Assessment of Manic Symptoms study. J Clin Psychiatry. 2012;73:1342‐1350.2314065384

Freeman
AJ
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Youngstrom
JK
, 
Findling
RL
. Disruptive mood dysregulation disorder in a community mental health clinic: prevalence, comorbidity and correlates. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016;26:123‐130.2674532585

Copeland
WE
, 
Shanahan
L
, 
Egger
H
, 
Angold
A
, 
Costello
EJ
. Adult diagnostic and functional outcomes of DSM‐5 disruptive mood dysregulation disorder. Am J Psychiatry. 2014;171:668‐674.2478138986

Mayes
SD
, 
Waxmonsky
JD
, 
Calhoun
SL
, 
Bixler
EO
. Disruptive mood dysregulation disorder symptoms and association with oppositional defiant and other disorders in a general population child sample. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016;26:101‐106.2674544287

Birmaher
B
, 
Axelson
D
, 
Goldstein
B
, et al. Four‐year longitudinal course of children and adolescents with bipolar spectrum disorders: the Course and Outcome of Bipolar Youth (COBY) study. Am J Psychiatry. 2009;166:795‐804.1944819088

Shankman
SA
, 
Lewinsohn
PM
, 
Klein
DN
, 
Small
JW
, 
Seeley
JR
, 
Altman
SE
. Subthreshold conditions as precursors for full syndrome disorders: a 15‐year longitudinal study of multiple diagnostic classes. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2009;50:1485‐1494.1957303489

Wozniak
J
, 
Petty
CR
, 
Schreck
M
, 
Moses
A
, 
Faraone
SV
, 
Biederman
J
. High level of persistence of pediatric bipolar‐I disorder from childhood onto adolescent years: a four year prospective longitudinal follow‐up study. J Psychiatr Res. 2011;45:1273‐1282.2168396090

Geller
B
, 
Tillman
R
, 
Bolhofner
K
, 
Zimerman
B
. Child bipolar I disorder: prospective continuity with adult bipolar I disorder; characteristics of second and third episodes; predictors of 8‐year outcome. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2008;65:1125‐1133.1883862991

Kowatch
RA
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Danielyan
A
, 
Findling
RL
. Review and meta‐analysis of the phenomenology and clinical characteristics of mania in children and adolescents. Bipolar Disord. 2005;7:483‐496.1640317492

McClellan
J
, 
Kowatch
R
, 
Findling
RL
. Practice parameter for the assessment and treatment of children and adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2007;46:107‐125.1719573593

Van Meter
AR
, 
Burke
C
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Faedda
GL
, 
Correll
CU
. The bipolar prodrome: meta‐analysis of symptom prevalence prior to initial or recurrent mood episodes. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2016;55:543‐555.2734388294

Tillman
R
, 
Geller
B
. Controlled study of switching from attention‐deficit/hyperactivity disorder to a prepubertal and early adolescent bipolar I disorder phenotype during 6‐year prospective follow‐up: rate, risk, and predictors. Dev Psychopathol. 2006;18:1037‐1053.1706442895

Biederman
J
, 
Petty
CR
, 
Byrne
D
, 
Wong
P
, 
Wozniak
J
, 
Faraone
SV
. Risk for switch from unipolar to bipolar disorder in youth with ADHD: a long term prospective controlled study. J Affect Disord. 2009;119:16‐21.1932442296

Molina
BSG
, 
Hinshaw
SP
, 
Swanson
JM
, et al. The MTA at 8 Years. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;48:484‐500.1931899197

Evans
SC
, 
Burke
JD
, 
Roberts
MC
, et al. Irritability in child and adolescent psychopathology: an integrative review for ICD‐11. Clin Psychol Rev. 2017;53:29‐45.2819277498

Dickstein
DP
, 
Towbin
KE
, 
Van Der Veen
JW
, et al. Randomized double‐blind placebo‐controlled trial of lithium in youths with severe mood dysregulation. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2009;19:61‐73.1923202499

Cicero
DC
, 
Epler
AJ
, 
Sher
KJ
. Are there developmentally limited forms of bipolar disorder?
J Abnorm Psychol. 2009;118:431‐447.19685942100

Jensen‐Doss
A
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Youngstrom
JK
, 
Feeny
NC
, 
Findling
RL
. Predictors and moderators of agreement between clinical and research diagnoses for children and adolescents. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2014;82:1151‐1162.24773574101

Rettew
DC
, 
Lynch
AD
, 
Achenbach
TM
, 
Dumenci
L
, 
Ivanova
MY
. Meta‐analyses of agreement between diagnoses made from clinical evaluations and standardized diagnostic interviews. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2009;18:169‐184.19701924102

Jenkins
MM
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Washburn
JJ
, 
Youngstrom
JK
. Evidence‐based strategies improve assessment of pediatric bipolar disorder by community practitioners. Prof Psychol Res Pr. 2011;42:121‐129.21625392103

Achenbach
TM
, 
McConaughy
SH
, 
Howell
CT
. Child/Adolescent behavioral and emotional problems: implication of cross‐informant correlations for situational specificity. Psychol Bull. 1987;101:213‐232.3562706104

Althoff
RR
, 
Ayer
LA
, 
Rettew
DC
, 
Hudziak
JJ
. Assessment of dysregulated children using the Child Behavior Checklist: a receiver operating characteristic curve analysis. Psychol Assess. 2010;22:609‐617.20822273105

Diler
RS
, 
Birmaher
B
, 
Axelson
D
, et al. The Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL) and the CBCL‐bipolar phenotype are not useful in diagnosing pediatric bipolar disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2009;19:23‐30.19232020106

Youngstrom
EA
, 
Findling
RL
, 
Danielson
CK
, 
Calabrese
JR
. Discriminative validity of parent report of hypomanic and depressive symptoms on the General Behavior Inventory. Psychol Assess. 2001;13:267‐276.11433802107

Youngstrom
EA
, 
Frazier
TW
, 
Findling
RL
, 
Calabrese
JR
. Developing a ten item short form of the Parent General Behavior Inventory to assess for juvenile mania and hypomania. J Clin Psychiatry. 2008;69:831‐839.18452343108

Pavuluri
MN
, 
Henry
DB
, 
Devineni
B
, 
Carbray
JA
, 
Birmaher
B
. Child mania rating scale: development, reliability, and validity. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2006;45:550‐560.16601399109

Henry
DB
, 
Pavuluri
MN
, 
Youngstrom
E
, 
Birmaher
B
. Accuracy of brief and full forms of the Child Mania Rating Scale. J Clin Psychol. 2008;64:368‐381.18302291110

Wagner
KD
, 
Kowatch
RA
, 
Emslie
GJ
, et al. A double‐blind, randomized, placebo‐controlled trial of oxcarbazepine in the treatment of bipolar disorder in children and adolescents. Am J Psychiatry. 2006;163:1179‐1186.16816222111

Straus
SE
, 
Glasziou
P
, 
Richardson
WS
, 
Haynes
RB
. Evidence‐based medicine: How to practice and teach EBM, 4th edn
New York, NY: Churchill Livingstone; 2011.112

Jenkins
MM
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Youngstrom
JK
, 
Feeny
NC
, 
Findling
RL
. Generalizability of evidence‐based assessment recommendations for pediatric bipolar disorder. Psychol Assess. 2012;24:269‐281.22004538113

West
AE
, 
Celio
CI
, 
Henry
DB
, 
Pavuluri
MN
. Child Mania Rating Scale‐Parent Version: a valid measure of symptom change due to pharmacotherapy. J Affect Disord. 2011;128:112‐119.20858565114

Youngstrom
EA
, 
Zhao
J
, 
Mankoski
R
, et al. Clinical significance of treatment effects with aripiprazole versus placebo in a study of manic or mixed episodes associated with pediatric bipolar I disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2013;23:72‐79.23480324115

Geller
B
, 
Zimerman
B
, 
Williams
M
, et al. Reliability of the Washington University in St. Louis Kiddie Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia (WASH‐U‐KSADS) mania and rapid cycling sections. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2001;40:450‐455.11314571116

Young
RC
, 
Biggs
JT
, 
Ziegler
VE
, 
Meyer
DA
. A rating scale for mania: reliability, validity, and sensitivity. Br J Psychiatry. 1978;133:429‐435.728692117

Poznanski
EO
, 
Miller
E
, 
Salguero
C
, 
Kelsh
RC
. Preliminary studies of the reliability and validity of the Children's Depression Rating Scale. J Am Acad Child Psychiatry. 1984;23:191‐197.6715741118

Axelson
DA
, 
Birmaher
BJ
, 
Brent
D
, et al. A preliminary study of the Kiddie Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia for School‐Age Children mania rating scale for children and adolescents. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2003;13:463‐470.14977459119

Demeter
CA
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Carlson
GA
, et al. Age differences in the phenomenology of pediatric bipolar disorder. J Affect Disord. 2013;147:295‐303.23219057120

Yee
AM
, 
Algorta
GP
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, et al. Unfiltered administration of the YMRS and CDRS‐R in a clinical sample of children. J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol. 2015;44:992‐1007.24885078121

Suppiger
A
, 
In‐Albon
T
, 
Hendriksen
S
, 
Hermann
E
, 
Margraf
J
, 
Schneider
S
. Acceptance of structured diagnostic interviews for mental disorders in clinical practice and research settings. Behav Ther. 2009;40:272‐279.19647528122

Algorta
GP
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Phelps
J
, 
Jenkins
MM
, 
Youngstrom
JK
, 
Findling
RL
. An inexpensive family index of risk for mood issues improves identification of pediatric bipolar disorder. Psychol Assess. 2013;25:12‐22.22800090123

Miklowitz
DJ
, 
Axelson
DA
, 
George
EL
, et al. Expressed emotion moderates the effects of family‐focused treatment for bipolar adolescents. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;48:643‐651.19454920124

Peruzzolo
TL
, 
Tramontina
S
, 
Rohde
LA
, 
Zeni
CP
. Pharmacotherapy of bipolar disorder in children and adolescents: an update. Rev Bras Psiquiatr. 2013;35:393‐405.24402215125

Goldstein
BI
, 
Sassi
R
, 
Diler
RS
. Pharmacological treatment of bipolar disorder in children and adolescents. Child Adolesc Psychiatr Clin N Am. 2012;21:911‐939.23040907126

Singh
MK
, 
Ketter
TA
, 
Chang
KD
. Atypical antipsychotics for acute manic and mixed episodes in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder. Drugs. 2010;70:433‐442.20205485127

Kowatch
R
, 
Findling
R
, 
Scheffer
R
, 
Stanford
K
. Placebo controlled trial of divalproex versus lithium for bipolar disorder. Boston, MA: American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry 54th Annual Meeting; 2007.128

Correll
CU
. Weight gain and metabolic effects of mood stabilizers and antipsychotics in pediatric bipolar disorder: a systematic review and pooled analysis of short‐term trials. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2007;46:687‐700.17513981129

Liu
HY
, 
Potter
MP
, 
Woodworth
KY
, et al. Pharmacologic treatments for pediatric bipolar disorder: a review and meta‐analysis. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2011;50:749‐762.21784295130

Findling
RL
, 
Robb
A
, 
McNamara
NK
, et al. Lithium in the acute treatment of bipolar I disorder: a double‐blind, placebo‐controlled study. Pediatrics. 2015;136:885‐894.26459650131

Wagner
KD
, 
Redden
L
, 
Kowatch
RA
, et al. A double‐blind, randomized, placebo‐controlled trial of divalproex extended‐release in the treatment of bipolar disorder in children and adolescents. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;48:519‐532.19325497132

Correll
CU
, 
Sheridan
EM
, 
DelBello
MP
. Antipsychotic and mood stabilizer efficacy and tolerability in pediatric and adult patients with bipolar I mania: a comparative analysis of acute, randomized, placebo‐controlled trials. Bipolar Disord. 2010;12:116‐141.20402706133

Delbello
MP
, 
Findling
RL
, 
Kushner
S
, et al. A pilot controlled trial of topiramate for mania in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2005;44:539‐547.15908836134

Tramontina
S
, 
Zeni
CP
, 
Pheula
G
, 
Rohde
LA
. Topiramate in adolescents with juvenile bipolar disorder presenting weight gain due to atypical antipsychotics or mood stabilizers: an open clinical trial. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2007;17:129‐134.17343561135

Geller
B
, 
Luby
JL
, 
Joshi
P
, et al. A randomized controlled trial of risperidone, lithium, or divalproex sodium for initial treatment of bipolar I disorder, manic or mixed phase, in children and adolescents. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2012;69:515‐528.22213771136

Vitiello
B
, 
Riddle
MA
, 
Yenokyan
G
, et al. Treatment moderators and predictors of outcome in the Treatment of Early Age Mania (TEAM) study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2012;51:867‐878.22917200137

Stringaris
A
. What we can all learn from the Treatment of Early Age Mania (TEAM) trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2012;51:861‐863.22917198138

Detke
HC
, 
DelBello
MP
, 
Landry
J
, 
Usher
RW
. Olanzapine/fluoxetine combination in children and adolescents with bipolar i depression: a randomized, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2015;54:217‐224.25721187139

Delbello
MP
, 
Goldman
R
, 
Phillips
D
, 
Deng
L
, 
Cucchiaro
J
, 
Loebel
A
. Efficacy and Safety of Lurasidone in Children and Adolescent Patients with Bipolar I Depression. Presented at the annual meeting of the International Society for Bipolar Disorders, May 4–7 2017, Washington DC.140

Findling
RL
, 
Pathak
S
, 
Earley
WR
, 
Liu
S
, 
DelBello
MP
. Efficacy and safety of extended‐release quetiapine fumarate in youth with bipolar depression: an 8 week, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled trial. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2014d;24:325‐335.24956042141

DelBello
MP
, 
Chang
K
, 
Welge
JA
, et al. A double‐blind, placebo‐controlled pilot study of quetiapine for depressed adolescents with bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2009;11:483‐493.19624387142

Patel
NC
, 
DelBello
MP
, 
Bryan
HS
, et al. Open‐label lithium for the treatment of adolescents with bipolar depression. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2006;45:289‐297.16540813143

Chang
K
, 
Saxena
K
, 
Howe
M
. An open‐label study of lamotrigine adjunct or monotherapy for the treatment of adolescents with bipolar depression. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2006;45:298‐304.16540814144

Shon
SH
, 
Joo
Y
, 
Lee
JS
, 
Kim
HW
. Lamotrigine treatment of adolescents with unipolar and bipolar depression: a retrospective chart review. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2014;24:285‐287.24813210145

Goldsmith
M
, 
Singh
M
, 
Chang
K
. Antidepressants and psychostimulants in pediatric populations: is there an association with mania?
Paediatr Drugs. 2011;13:225‐243.21692547146

Park
KJ
, 
Shon
S
, 
Lee
HJ
, 
Joo
Y
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Kim
HW
. Antidepressant‐emergent mood switch in korean adolescents with mood disorder. Clin Neuropharmacol. 2014;37:177‐185.25384075147

Bhowmik
D
, 
Aparasu
RR
, 
Rajan
SS
, 
Sherer
JT
, 
Ochoa‐Perez
M
, 
Chen
H
. Risk of manic switch associated with antidepressant therapy in pediatric bipolar depression. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2014;24:551‐561.25470655148

Strober
M
, 
Schmidt‐Lackner
S
, 
Freeman
R
, 
Bower
S
, 
Lampert
C
, 
DeAntonio
M
. Recovery and relapse in adolescents with bipolar affective illness: a five‐year naturalistic, prospective follow‐up. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1995;34:724‐731.7608045149

Findling
RL
, 
McNamara
NK
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, et al. Double‐blind 18‐month trial of lithium versus divalproex maintenance treatment in pediatric bipolar disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2005;44:409‐417.15843762150

Redden
L
, 
DelBello
M
, 
Wagner
KD
, et al. Long‐term safety of divalproex sodium extended‐release in children and adolescents with bipolar I disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2009;19:83‐89.19232026151

Findling
RL
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
McNamara
NK
, et al. Double‐blind, randomized, placebo‐controlled long‐term maintenance study of aripiprazole in children with bipolar disorder. J Clin Psychiatry. 2012;73:57‐63.22152402152

Findling
RL
, 
Correll
CU
, 
Nyilas
M
, et al. Aripiprazole for the treatment of pediatric bipolar I disorder: a 30‐week, randomized, placebo‐controlled study. Bipolar Disord. 2013;15:138‐149.23437959153

Findling
RL
, 
Chang
K
, 
Robb
A
, et al. Adjunctive maintenance lamotrigine for pediatric bipolar I disorder: a placebo‐controlled, randomized withdrawal study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2015;54:1020.e3‐1031.e3.26598477154

Findling
RL
, 
Landbloom
RL
, 
Mackle
M
, et al. Long‐term safety of asenapine in pediatric patients diagnosed with bipolar I disorder: a 50‐week open‐label, flexible‐dose trial. Pediatr Drugs. 2016;18:367‐378.155

Scheffer
RE
, 
Kowatch
RA
, 
Carmody
T
, 
Rush
AJ
. Randomized, placebo‐controlled trial of mixed amphetamine salts for symptoms of comorbid ADHD in pediatric bipolar disorder after mood stabilization with divalproex sodium. Am J Psychiatry. 2005;162:58‐64.15625202156

Findling
RL
, 
Short
EJ
, 
McNamara
NK
, et al. Methylphenidate in the treatment of children and adolescents with bipolar disorder and attention‐deficit/hyperactivity disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2007;46:1445‐1453.18049294157

Tramontina
S
, 
Zeni
CP
, 
Ketzer
CR
, 
Pheula
GF
, 
Narvaez
J
, 
Rohde
LA
. Aripiprazole in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder comorbid with attention‐deficit/hyperactivity disorder: a pilot randomized clinical trial. J Clin Psychiatry. 2009;70:756‐764.19389329158

Hah
M
, 
Chang
K
. Atomoxetine for the treatment of attention‐deficit/hyperactivity disorder in children and adolescents with bipolar disorders. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2005;15:996‐1004.16379520159

Geller
B
, 
Cooper
TB
, 
Sun
K
, et al. Double‐blind and placebo‐controlled study of lithium for adolescent bipolar disorders with secondary substance dependency. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1998;37:171‐178.9473913160

Wozniak
J
, 
Biederman
J
, 
Mick
E
, et al. Omega‐3 fatty acid monotherapy for pediatric bipolar disorder: a prospective open‐label trial. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol. 2007;17:440‐447.17258897161

Frazier
EA
, 
Fristad
MA
, 
Arnold
LE
. Feasibility of a nutritional supplement as treatment for pediatric bipolar spectrum disorders. J Altern Complement Med. 2012;18:678‐685.22747095162

Clayton
EH
, 
Hanstock
TL
, 
Hirneth
SJ
, 
Kable
CJ
, 
Garg
ML
, 
Hazell
PL
. Reduced mania and depression in juvenile bipolar disorder associated with long‐chain [omega]‐3 polyunsaturated fatty acid supplementation. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2009;63:1037‐1040.19156158163

Fristad
MA
, 
Young
AS
, 
Vesco
AT
, et al. A randomized controlled trial of individual family psychoeducational psychotherapy and omega‐3 fatty acids in youth with subsyndromal bipolar disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2015;25:764‐774.26682997164

Gracious
BL
, 
Chirieac
MC
, 
Costescu
S
, 
Finucane
TL
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Hibbeln
JR
. Randomized, placebo‐controlled trial of flax oil in pediatric bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2010;12:142‐154.20402707165

Geddes
JR
, 
Miklowitz
DJ
. Treatment of bipolar disorder. Lancet. 2013;381:1672‐1682.23663953166

Colom
F
, 
Vieta
E
, 
Martinez‐Aran
A
, 
Reinares
M
, 
Goikolea
JM
, 
Martínez‐Arán
A
. A randomized trial on the efficacy of group psychoeducation in the prophylaxis of bipolar disorder: a five year follow‐up. Br J Psychiatry. 2009;194:260‐265.19252157167

Bauer
MS
, 
McBride
L
, 
Williford
W
, et al. Collaborative care for bipolar disorder: part II. Impact on clinical outcome, function, and costs. Psychiatr Serv. 2006;57:937‐945.16816277168

Simon
GE
, 
Ludman
EJ
, 
Bauer
MS
, 
Unutzer
J
, 
Operskalski
B
. Long‐term effectiveness and cost of a systematic care program for bipolar disorder. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2006;63:500‐508.16651507169

Frank
E
, 
Kupfer
DJ
, 
Thase
ME
, et al. Two‐year outcomes for interpersonal and social rhythm therapy in individuals with bipolar I disorder. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2005;62:996‐1004.16143731170

Fristad
MA
, 
MacPherson
H
. Evidence‐based psychosocial treatments for bipolar disorder in youth. J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol. 2014;43:339‐355.23927375171

Goldstein
TR
, 
Fersch‐Podrat
RK
, 
Rivera
M
, et al. Dialectical behavior therapy for adolescents with bipolar disorder: results from a pilot randomized trial. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2015;25:140‐149.25010702172

Miklowitz
DJ
, 
O'Brien
MP
, 
Schlosser
DA
, et al. Family‐focused treatment for adolescents and young adults at high risk for psychosis: results of a randomized trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2014a;53:848‐858.25062592173

West
AE
, 
Weinstein
SM
, 
Peters
AT
, et al. Child‐and family‐focused cognitive‐behavioral therapy for pediatric bipolar disorder: a randomized clinical trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2014;53:1168‐1178.25440307174

Goldstein
BI
, 
Goldstein
TR
, 
Miklowitz
DJ
, et al. Development of integrated family ‐focused treatment (FFT) for adolescents with bipolar disorder and comorbid substance use disorders. Phoenix, AZ: NCDEU; 2008.175

Miklowitz
DJ
, 
Schneck
CD
, 
George
EL
, et al. A 2‐year randomized trial of pharmacotherapy and family‐focused treatment for adolescents with bipolar I and II disorders. Am J Psychiatry. 2014b;171:658‐667.24626789176

Fristad
MA
. Evidence‐based psychotherapies and nutritional interventions for children with bipolar spectrum disorders and their families. J Clin Psychiatry. 2016;77:e4.27570930177

Hlastala
SA
, 
Kotler
JS
, 
McClellan
JM
, 
McCauley
EA
. Interpersonal and social rhythm therapy for adolescents with bipolar disorder: treatment development and results from an open trial. Depress Anxiety. 2010;27:457‐464.20186968178

MacPherson
HA
, 
Mackinaw‐Koons
B
, 
Leffler
JM
, 
Fristad
MA
. Pilot effectiveness evaluation of community‐based multi‐family psychoeducational psychotherapy for childhood mood disorders. Couple Family Psychol. 2016;5:43‐59.27057423179

MacPherson
HA
, 
Leffler
JM
, 
Fristad
MA
. Implementation of multi‐family psychoeducational psychotherapy for childhood mood disorders in an outpatient community setting. J Marital Fam Ther. 2014;40:193‐211.24749838180

Mendenhall
AN
, 
Fristad
MA
, 
Early
TJ
. Factors influencing service utilization and mood symptom severity in children with mood disorders: effects of multifamily psychoeducation groups (MFPGs). J Consult Clin Psychol. 2009;77:463.19485588181

MacPherson
HA
, 
Weinstein
SM
, 
Henry
DB
, 
West
AE
. Mediators in the randomized trial of Child‐ and Family‐Focused Cognitive‐Behavioral Therapy for pediatric bipolar disorder. Behav Res Ther. 2016;85:60‐71.27567973182

MacPherson
HA
, 
Algorta
GP
, 
Mendenhall
AN
, 
Fields
BW
, 
Fristad
MA
. Predictors and moderators in the randomized trial of multi‐family psychoeducational psychotherapy for childhood mood disorders. J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol. 2014;43:459‐472.23795823183

Boylan
K
, 
MacPherson
HA
, 
Fristad
MA
. Examination of disruptive behavior outcomes and moderation in a randomized psychotherapy trial for mood disorders. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2013;52:699‐708.23800483184

Goldstein
BI
, 
Goldstein
TR
, 
Collinger
KA
, et al. Treatment development and feasibility study of family‐focused treatment for adolescents with bipolar disorder and comorbid substance use disorders. J Psychiatr Pract. 2014;20:237‐248.24847999185

Miklowitz
DJ
, 
Schneck
CD
, 
Singh
MK
, et al. Early intervention for symptomatic youth at risk for bipolar disorder: a randomized trial of family‐focused therapy. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2013;52:121‐131.23357439186

Nadkarni
RB
, 
Fristad
MA
. Clinical course of children with a depressive spectrum disorder and transient manic symptoms. Bipolar Disord. 2010;12:494‐503.20712750187

Strakowski
SM
, 
Adler
CM
, 
Almeida
J
, et al. The functional neuroanatomy of bipolar disorder: a consensus model. Bipolar Disord. 2012;14:313‐325.22631617188

DelBello
MP
, 
Kowatch
RA
. Neuroimaging in Pediatric Bipolar Disorder. Bipolar Disorder in Children and Early Adolescence. New York, NY: Guilford Press; 2003:158‐174.189

Schneider
MR
, 
DelBello
MP
, 
McNamara
RK
, 
Strakowski
SM
, 
Adler
CM
. Neuroprogression in bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2012;14:356‐374.22631620190

Phillips
ML
, 
Swartz
HA
. A critical appraisal of neuroimaging studies of bipolar disorder: toward a new conceptualization of underlying neural circuitry and a road map for future research. Am J Psychiatry. 2014;171:829‐843.24626773191

Pfeifer
JC
, 
Welge
J
, 
Strakowski
SM
, 
Adler
CM
, 
DelBello
MP
. Meta‐analysis of amygdala volumes in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2008;47:1289‐1298.18827720192

Usher
J
, 
Leucht
S
, 
Falkai
P
, 
Scherk
H
. Correlation between amygdala volume and age in bipolar disorder—a systematic review and meta‐analysis of structural MRI studies. Psychiatry Res. 2010;182:2010.193

Bitter
SM
, 
Mills
NP
, 
Adler
CM
, 
Strakowski
SM
, 
DelBello
MP
. Progression of amygdala volumetric abnormalities in adolescents after their first manic episode. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2011;50:1017‐1026.21961776194

Adler
CM
, 
Adams
J
, 
DelBello
MP
, et al. Evidence of white matter pathology in bipolar disorder adolescents experiencing their first episode of mania: a diffusion tensor imaging study. Am J Psychiatry. 2006;163:322‐324.16449490195

Frazier
J
, 
Breeze
J
, 
Papadimitriou
G
, et al. White matter abnormalities in children with and at risk for bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2007;9:799‐809.18076529196

Pavuluri
MN
, 
Yang
S
, 
Kamineni
K
, et al. Diffusion tensor imaging study of white matter fiber tracts in pediatric bipolar disorder and attention‐deficit/hyperactivity disorder. Biol Psychiat. 2009;65:586‐593.19027102197

Kafantaris
V
, 
Kingsley
P
, 
Ardekani
B
, et al. Lower orbital frontal white matter integrity in adolescents with bipolar I disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;48:79‐86.19050654198

Saxena
K
, 
Tamm
L
, 
Walley
A
, et al. A preliminary investigation of corpus callosum and anterior commissure aberrations in aggressive youth with bipolar disorders. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2012;22:112‐119.22375854199

Gao
W
, 
Jiao
Q
, 
Qi
R
, et al. Combined analyses of gray matter voxel‐based morphometry and white matter tract‐based spatial statistics in pediatric bipolar mania. J Affect Disord. 2013;150:70‐76.23477846200

James
A
, 
Hough
M
, 
James
S
, et al. Structural brain and neuropsychometric changes associated with pediatric bipolar disorder with psychosis. Bipolar Disord. 2011;13:16‐27.21320249201

Lu
LH
, 
Zhou
XJ
, 
Fitzgerald
J
, et al. Microstructural abnormalities of white matter differentiate pediatric and adult‐onset bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2012;14:597‐606.22882719202

Wegbreit
E
, 
Cushman
GK
, 
Puzia
ME
, et al. Developmental meta‐analyses of the functional neural correlates of bipolar disorder. JAMA Psychiatry. 2014;71:926‐935.25100166203

Lee
MS
, 
Anumagalla
P
, 
Talluri
P
, 
Pavuluri
MN
. Meta‐analyses of developing brain function in high‐risk and emerged bipolar disorder. Front Psychiatry. 2014;5:141.25404919204

Dickstein
DP
, 
Finger
EC
, 
Skup
M
, 
Pine
DS
, 
Blair
JR
, 
Leibenluft
E
. Altered neural function in pediatric bipolar disorder during reversal learning. Bipolar Disord. 2010;12:707‐719.21040288205

Singh
MK
, 
Chang
KD
, 
Kelley
RG
, et al. Reward processing in adolescents with bipolar I disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2013;52:68‐83.23265635206

Urosevic
S
, 
Luciana
M
, 
Jensen
JB
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Thomas
KM
. Age associations with neural processing of reward anticipation in adolescents with bipolar disorders. Neuroimage Clin. 2016;11:476‐485.27114896207

Adler
CM
, 
Delbello
MP
, 
Mills
NP
, 
Schmithorst
V
, 
Holland
S
, 
Strakowski
SM
. Comorbid ADHD is associated with altered patterns of neuronal activation in adolescents with bipolar disorder performing a simple attention task. Bipolar Disord. 2005;7:577‐588.16403183208

Cerullo
MA
, 
Adler
CM
, 
Lamy
M
, et al. Differential brain activation during response inhibition in bipolar and attention‐deficit hyperactivity disorders. Early Interv Psychiatry. 2009;3:189‐197.22640382209

Leibenluft
E
, 
Rich
BA
, 
Vinton
DT
, et al. Neural circuitry engaged during unsuccessful motor inhibition in pediatric bipolar disorder. Am J Psychiatry. 2007;164:52‐60.17202544210

Dickstein
DP
, 
Gorrostieta
C
, 
Ombao
H
, et al. Fronto‐temporal spontaneous resting state functional connectivity in pediatric bipolar disorder. Biol Psychiat. 2010;68:839‐846.20739018211

Singh
MK
, 
Kelley
RG
, 
Chang
KD
, 
Gotlib
IH
. Intrinsic amygdala functional connectivity in youth with bipolar I disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2015;54:763‐770.26299298212

Xiao
Q
, 
Zhong
Y
, 
Lu
D
, et al. Altered regional homogeneity in pediatric bipolar disorder during manic state: a resting‐state fMRI study. PLoS ONE. 2013;8:e57978.23526961213

Gao
W
, 
Jiao
Q
, 
Lu
S
, et al. Alterations of regional homogeneity in pediatric bipolar depression: a resting‐state fMRI study. BMC Psychiatry. 2014;14:222.25095790214

Castillo
M
, 
Kwock
L
, 
Courvoisie
H
, 
Hooper
SR
. Proton MR spectroscopy in children with bipolar affective disorder: preliminary observations. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 2000;21:832‐838.10815657215

Moore
CM
, 
Frazier
JA
, 
Glod
CA
, et al. Glutamine and glutamate levels in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder: a 4.0‐T proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy study of the anterior cingulate cortex. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2007;46:524‐534.17420688216

Davanzo
P
, 
Thomas
MA
, 
Yue
K
, et al. Decreased anterior cingulate myo‐inositol/creatine spectroscopy resonance with lithium treatment in children with bipolar disorder. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2001;24:359‐369.11182531217

Davanzo
P
, 
Yue
K
, 
Thomas
MA
, et al. Proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy of bipolar disorder versus intermittent explosive disorder in children and adolescents. Am J Psychiatry. 2003;160:1442‐1452.12900307218

Cecil
KM
, 
DelBello
MP
, 
Sellars
MC
, 
Strakowski
SM
. Proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy of the frontal lobe and cerebellar vermis in children with a mood disorder and a familial risk for bipolar disorders. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2003;13:545‐555.14977467219

Chang
K
, 
Adleman
N
, 
Dienes
K
, 
Barnea‐Goraly
N
, 
Reiss
A
, 
Ketter
T
. Decreased N‐acetylaspartate in children with familial bipolar disorder. Biol Psychiatry. 2003;53:1059‐1065.12788251220

Patel
NC
, 
DelBello
MP
, 
Cecil
KM
, 
Stanford
KE
, 
Adler
CM
, 
Strakowski
SM
. Temporal change in N‐acetyl‐aspartate concentrations in adolescents with bipolar depression treated with lithium. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2008;18:132‐139.18439111221

Brambilla
P
, 
Stanley
JA
, 
Nicoletti
MA
, et al. 1H magnetic resonance spectroscopy investigation of the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in bipolar disorder patients. J Affect Disord. 2005;86:61‐67.15820271222

Caetano
SC
, 
Olvera
RL
, 
Hatch
JP
, et al. Lower N‐acetyl‐aspartate levels in prefrontal cortices in pediatric bipolar disorder: a (1)H magnetic resonance spectroscopy study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2011;50:85‐94.21156273223

Sassi
RB
, 
Stanley
JA
, 
Axelson
D
, et al. Reduced NAA levels in the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex of young bipolar patients. Am J Psychiatry. 2005;162:2109‐2115.16263851224

Olvera
RL
, 
Caetano
SC
, 
Fonseca
M
, et al. Low levels of N‐acetyl aspartate in the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex of pediatric bipolar patients. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2007;17:461‐473.17822341225

Strawn
JR
, 
Patel
NC
, 
Chu
WJ
, et al. Glutamatergic effects of divalproex in adolescents with mania: a proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2012;51:642‐651.22632623226

DelBello
MP
, 
Cecil
KM
, 
Adler
CM
, 
Daniels
JP
, 
Strakowski
SM
. Neurochemical effects of olanzapaine in first‐hospitalization manic adolescents: a proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy study. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2006;31:1264‐1273.16292323227

Diler
RS
, 
Ladouceur
CD
, 
Segreti
A
, et al. Neural correlates of treatment response in depressed bipolar adolescents during emotion processing. Brain Imaging Behav. 2013;7:227‐235.23355265228

Schneider
MR
, 
Adler
CM
, 
Whitsel
R
, et al. The effects of ziprasidone on prefrontal and amygdalar activation in manic youth with bipolar disorder. Isr J Psychiatry Relat Sci. 2012;49:112‐120.22801290229

Schneider
MR
, 
Klein
CC
, 
Weber
W
, et al. The effects of carbamazepine on prefrontal activation in manic youth with bipolar disorder. Psychiatry Res. 2014;223:268‐270.25035298230

Wegbreit
E
, 
Ellis
JA
, 
Nandam
A
, et al. Amygdala functional connectivity predicts pharmacotherapy outcome in pediatric bipolar disorder. Brain Connect. 2011;1:411‐422.22432455231

Garrett
AS
, 
Miklowitz
DJ
, 
Howe
ME
, et al. Changes in brain activation following psychotherapy for youth with mood dysregulation at familial risk for bipolar disorder. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry. 2015;56:215‐220.25283342232

Joseph
MF
, 
Frazier
TW
, 
Youngstrom
EA
, 
Soares
JC
. A quantitative and qualitative review of neurocognitive performance in pediatric bipolar disorder”. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2008;18:595‐605.19108664233

Pavuluri
MN
, 
West
A
, 
Hill
SK
, 
Jindal
K
, 
Sweeney
JA
. Neurocognitive function in pediatric bipolar disorder: 3‐year follow‐up shows cognitive development lagging behind healthy youths. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;48:299‐307.19182689234

Dickstein
DP
, 
Cushman
GK
, 
Kim
KL
, 
Weissman
AB
, 
Wegbreit
E
. Cognitive remediation: potential novel brain‐based treatment for bipolar disorder in children and adolescents. CNS Spectr. 2015;20:382‐390.26135596235

Munkholm
K
, 
Braüner
JV
, 
Kessing
LV
, 
Vinberg
M
. Cytokines in bipolar disorder vs. healthy control subjects: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. J Psychiatr Res. 2013;47:1119‐1133.23768870236

Frey
BN
, 
Andreazza
AC
, 
Houenou
J
, et al. Biomarkers in bipolar disorder: a positional paper from the International Society for Bipolar Disorders Biomarkers Task Force. Aust N Z J Psychiatry. 2013;47:321‐332.23411094237

Berk
M
, 
Kapczinski
F
, 
Andreazza
AC
, et al. Pathways underlying neuroprogression in bipolar disorder: focus on inflammation, oxidative stress and neurotrophic factors. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2011;35:804‐817.20934453238

Kapczinski
F
, 
Dias
VV
, 
Kauer‐Sant'Anna
M
, et al. The potential use of biomarkers as an adjunctive tool for staging bipolar disorder. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry. 2009;33:1366‐1371.19666076239

Goldstein
BI
, 
Collinger
KA
, 
Lotrich
F
, et al. Preliminary findings regarding pro‐inflammatory markers and brain‐derived neurotrophic factor among adolescents with bipolar spectrum disorders. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2011;21:479‐484.22040193240

Goldstein
BI
, 
Lotrich
F
, 
Axelson
DA
, et al. Inflammatory markers among adolescents and young adults with bipolar spectrum disorders. J Clin Psychiatry. 2015;76:1556‐1563.26646032241

Miklowitz
DJ
, 
Portnoff
LC
, 
Armstrong
CC
, et al. Inflammatory cytokines and nuclear factor‐kappa B activation in adolescents with bipolar and major depressive disorders. Psychiatry Res. 2016;241:315‐322.27227701242

Hatch
JK
, 
Scola
G
, 
Olowoyeye
O
, et al. Inflammatory markers and brain‐derived neurotrophic factor as potential bridges linking bipolar disorder and cardiovascular risk among adolescents. J Clin Psychiatry. 2017;78:e286‐e293.28199074243

Hatch
J
, 
Andreazza
A
, 
Olowoyeye
O
, 
Rezin
GT
, 
Moody
A
, 
Goldstein
BI
. Cardiovascular and psychiatric characteristics associated with oxidative stress markers among adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Psychosom Res. 2015;79:222‐227.25934154244

Magalhaes
PV
, 
Jansen
K
, 
Pinheiro
RT
, et al. Peripheral oxidative damage in early‐stage mood disorders: a nested population‐based case‐control study. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol. 2012;15:1043‐1050.22008234245

Scola
G
, 
McNamara
RK
, 
Croarkin
PE
, et al. Lipid peroxidation biomarkers in adolescents with or at high‐risk for bipolar disorder. J Affect Disord. 2016;192:176‐183.26735329246

Newton
DF
, 
Naiberg
MR
, 
Andreazza
AC
, 
Scola
G
, 
Dickstein
DP
, 
Goldstein
BI
. Association of lipid peroxidation and brain‐derived neurotrophic factor with executive function in adolescent bipolar disorder. Psychopharmacology. 2017;234:647‐656.27957714247

Pandey
GN
, 
Rizavi
HS
, 
Dwivedi
Y
, 
Pavuluri
MN
. Brain‐derived neurotrophic factor gene expression in pediatric bipolar disorder: effects of treatment and clinical response. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2008;47:1077‐1085.18664999248

Inal‐Emiroglu
FN
, 
Karabay
N
, 
Resmi
H
, et al. Correlations between amygdala volumes and serum levels of BDNF and NGF as a neurobiological markerin adolescents with bipolar disorder. J Affect Disord. 2015;182:50‐56.25973783249

Inal‐Emiroglu
FN
, 
Resmi
H
, 
Karabay
N
, et al. Decreased right hippocampal volumes and neuroprogression markers in adolescents with bipolar disorder. Neuropsychobiology. 2015;71:140‐148.25925781250

Mick
E
, 
Wozniak
J
, 
Wilens
TE
, 
Biederman
J
, 
Faraone
SV
. Family‐based association study of the BDNF, COMT and serotonin transporter genes and DSM‐IV bipolar‐I disorder in children. BMC Psychiatry. 2009;9:2.19193231251

Mick
E
, 
Kim
JW
, 
Biederman
J
, et al. Family based association study of pediatric bipolar disorder and the dopamine transporter gene (SLC6A3). Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet. 2008;147B:1182‐1185.18361424252

Gallitano
AL
, 
Tillman
R
, 
Dinu
V
, 
Geller
B
. Family‐based association study of early growth response gene 3 with child bipolar I disorder. J Affect Disord. 2012;138:387‐396.22370066253

Geller
B
, 
Tillman
R
, 
Bolhofner
K
, 
Hennessy
K
, 
Cook
EH
. GAD1 single nucleotide polymorphism is in linkage disequilibrium with a child bipolar i disorder phenotype. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2007;18:25‐29.254

Geller
B
, 
Badner
JA
, 
Tillman
R
, 
Christian
SL
, 
Bolhofner
K
, 
Cook
EH
. Linkage disequilibrium of the brain‐derived neurotrophic factor Val66Met polymorphism in children with a prepubertal and early adolescent bipolar disorder phenotype. Am J Psychiatry. 2004;161:1698‐1700.15337662255

Ferreira
MAR
, 
O'Donovan
MC
, 
Meng
YA
, et al. Collaborative genome‐wide association analysis supports a role for ANK3 and CACNA1C in bipolar disorder. Nat Genet. 2008;40:1056‐1058.18711365256

Croarkin
PE
, 
Luby
JL
, 
Cercy
K
, et al. Genetic risk score analysis in early‐onset bipolar disorder. J Clin Psychiatry. 2017
https://doi.org/10.4088/JCP.15m10314
257

Kraepelin
E
. Manic‐Depressive Insanity and Paranoia. Edinburgh: E. &amp; S. Livingstone; 1921.258

Parens
E
, 
Johnston
J
. Controversies concerning the diagnosis and treatment of bipolar disorder in children. Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health. 2010;4:9.20219111259

Mitchell
PB
. Bipolar disorder: the shift to overdiagnosis. Can J Psychiatry. 2012;57:659‐665.23149281260

Subramaniapillai
M
, 
Goldstein
BI
, 
MacIntosh
BJ
, et al. Characterizing exercise‐induced feelings after one bout of exercise among adolescents with and without bipolar disorder. J Affect Disord. 2016;190:467‐473.26551406261

Metcalfe
AW
, 
MacIntosh
BJ
, 
Scavone
A
, 
Ou
X
, 
Korczak
D
, 
Goldstein
BI
. Effects of acute aerobic exercise on neural correlates of attention and inhibition in adolescents with bipolar disorder. Transl Psychiatry. 2016;6:e814
https://doi.org/10.1038/tp.2016.85.27187236
