<?xml version="1.0"?>
F1000ResF1000ResF1000ResearchF1000Research2046-1402F1000ResearchLondon, UK49432932742974410.12688/f1000research.8769.1ReviewArticlesMotor SystemsMovement DisordersNeurobiology of Disease &amp; RegenerationNeuropharmacology &amp; PsychopharmacologyTourette syndrome research highlights 2015[version 1; referees: 3 approved]RichardsCheryl A.a12BlackKevin J.1345
1Department of Psychiatry, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, Missouri, USA
2Department of Medicine, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, Missouri, USA
3Department of Neurology, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, Missouri, USA
4Department of Radiology, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, Missouri, USA
5Department of Neuroscience, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, Missouri, USAaRichardsC@WUSTL.eduBoth authors contributed to all phases of this work and have agreed to the final content.
Competing interests: KJB participated in clinical trials supported by Psyadon Pharmaceuticals, Neurocrine Biosciences, Inc., and Acadia Pharmaceuticals, and was compensated by Acadia for advisory board and speakers bureau participation.24620162016514931362016Copyright: © 2016 Richards CA and Black KJ2016This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We present selected highlights from research that appeared during 2015 on Tourette syndrome and other tic disorders. Topics include phenomenology, comorbidities, developmental course, genetics, animal models, neuroimaging, electrophysiology, pharmacology, and treatment. We briefly summarize articles whose results we believe may lead to new treatments, additional research or modifications in current models of TS.Tourette syndrometic disordersgeneticsanimal modelsneuroimagingpremonitorytherapyreviewNational Institutes of HealthK24 MH087913R21 NS091635This work was supported in part by U.S. National Institutes of Health (NIH) grants K24 MH087913 and R21 NS091635, by a research grant from the Tourette Association of America to author CAR, and by the McDonnell Center for Systems Neuroscience at Washington University.The authors confirm that the funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. The opinions expressed are the authors’ and may not reflect the opinion of the funders.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>We searched PubMed on 22 Jan 2016 using the search strategy: (“Tic Disorders”[MeSH] OR Tourette NOT Tourette[AU]) AND 2015[PDAT]. This search returned 202 citations and includes articles appearing online in 2015 but not officially published by year end (from journals that still focus on the paper user interface). We also reviewed F1000Prime recommendations and presentations of interest at selected medical conferences. Articles were chosen based on a purely subjective assessment of interest, guided by our judgment of possible future impact on the field.</p></sec>1
RichardsCABlackKJ:
Tourette Syndrome research highlights 2014 [version 2; referees: 1 approved, 2 approved with reservations].
F1000Res.
2015;4:69.
10.12688/f1000research.6209.2

265123192
BlackKJ:

F1000Research: Tics welcomes you to 21st century biomedical publishing [version 1; referees: not peer reviewed].
F1000Res.
2014;3:272.
10.12688/f1000research.5664.1

255802343
GanosCBongertJAsmussL:
The somatotopy of tic inhibition: Where and how much?
Mov Disord.
2015;30(9):1184–9.
10.1002/mds.26188
257866754
GreeneDJKollerJMRobichaux-ViehoeverA:
Reward enhances tic suppression in children within months of tic disorder onset.
Dev Cogn Neurosci.
2015;11:65–74. The ability to suppress tics is present within months of tic onset. Immediate, contingent reward enhances these children’s ability to suppress tics.
10.1016/j.dcn.2014.08.005

252200755
MatsudaNKonoTNonakaM:
Self-initiated coping with Tourette’s syndrome: Effect of tic suppression on QOL.
Brain Dev.
2016;38(2):233–41.
10.1016/j.braindev.2015.08.006
263602576
KanoYMatsudaNNonakaM:
Sensory phenomena related to tics, obsessive-compulsive symptoms, and global functioning in Tourette syndrome.
Compr Psychiatry.
2015;62:141–146.
10.1016/j.comppsych.2015.07.006
263434787
GanosCGarridoANavalpotro-GómezI:
Premonitory urge to tic in Tourette’s is associated with interoceptive awareness.
Mov Disord.
2015;30(9):1198–202.
10.1002/mds.26228
258798198
WongLCHuangHLWengWC:
Increased risk of epilepsy in children with Tourette syndrome: A population-based case-control study.
Res Dev Disabil.
2016;51–52:181–7.
10.1016/j.ridd.2015.10.005
265974169
HirschtrittMELeePCPaulsDL:
Lifetime prevalence, age of risk, and genetic relationships of comorbid psychiatric disorders in Tourette syndrome.
JAMA Psychiatry.
2015;72(4):325–333.
10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.2650

2567141210
EapenVRobertsonMM:
Are there distinct subtypes in Tourette syndrome? Pure-Tourette syndrome versus Tourette syndrome-plus, and simple versus complex tics.
Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat.
2015;11:1431–6.
10.2147/NDT.S72284

2608967211
CoxJHCavannaAE:
Irritability symptoms in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci.
2015;27(1):42–7.
10.1176/appi.neuropsych.13060143
2571648612
EddyCMMacerolloAMartinoD:
Interpersonal reactivity differences in Tourette syndrome.
Psychiatry Res.
2015;228(3):932–5.
10.1016/j.psychres.2015.05.070
2614458313
BudmanCLRosenMShadS:
Fits Tantrums, and Rages in TS and Related Disorders.
Curr Dev Disord Rep.
2015;2(4):273–284.
10.1007/s40474-015-0059-1
14
BalottinLSelviniCLuoniC:
Personality Profile of Male Adolescents With Tourette Syndrome: A Controlled Study.
J Child Neurol.
2016;31(3):294–9.
10.1177/0883073815589762
2607841915
TrilliniMOMüller-VahlKR:
Patients with Gilles de la Tourette syndrome have widespread personality differences.
Psychiatry Res.
2015;228(3):765–73.
10.1016/j.psychres.2015.04.043
2611245016
ZappellaMEinspielerCBartl-PokornyKD:
What do home videos tell us about early motor and socio-communicative behaviours in children with autistic features during the second year of life--An exploratory study.
Early Hum Dev.
2015;91(10):569–75.
10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2015.07.006
2624613717
RicherFDaghfalRRouleauGA:
Clinical features associated with an early onset in chronic tic disorders.
Psychiatry Res.
2015;230(3):745–8.
10.1016/j.psychres.2015.11.018
2659636418
LichterDGFinneganSG:
Influence of gender on Tourette syndrome beyond adolescence.
Eur Psychiatry.
2015;30(2):334–340.
10.1016/j.eurpsy.2014.07.003
2519304219
HuangAYuDDavisL:
A large-scale study of rare copy number variation identifies novel loci associated with Tourette’s syndrome.2015
http://eventmobi.com/api/events/7343/documents/download/40ae88af-e882-4b97-a43a-b361d8ff3d67.pdf/as/Aarchivedby WebCite®.
Reference Source
20
ClarkeRAEapenV:
Balance within the Neurexin Trans-Synaptic Connexus Stabilizes Behavioral Control.
Front Hum Neurosci.
2014;8:52.
10.3389/fnhum.2014.00052

2457868521
YeHTanYLPonniahS:
Neural recognition molecules CHL1 and NB-3 regulate apical dendrite orientation in the neocortex via PTP alpha.
EMBO J.
2008;27(1):188–200.
10.1038/sj.emboj.7601939

1804645822
TakedaYAkasakaKLeeS:
Impaired motor coordination in mice lacking neural recognition molecule NB-3 of the contactin/F3 subgroup.
J Neurobiol.
2003;56(3):252–65.
10.1002/neu.10222
1288426423
HuJLiaoJSathanooriM:

CNTN6 copy number variations in 14 patients: a possible candidate gene for neurodevelopmental and neuropsychiatric disorders.
J Neurodev Disord.
2015;7(1):26.
10.1186/s11689-015-9122-9

2625783524
BertelsenBStefánssonH Riff JensenL:
Association of
AADAC Deletion and Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome in a Large European Cohort.
Biol Psychiatry.
2016;79(5):383–391.
10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.08.027
2644407525
de LeeuwCGoudriaanASmitAB:
Involvement of astrocyte metabolic coupling in Tourette syndrome pathogenesis.
Eur J Hum Genet.
2015;23(11):1519–1522.
10.1038/ejhg.2015.22

2573548326
YuDMathewsCAScharfJM:
Cross-disorder genome-wide analyses suggest a complex genetic relationship between Tourette’s syndrome and OCD.
Am J Psychiatry.
2015;172(1):82–93.
10.1176/appi.ajp.2014.13101306

2515807227
de HaanMJDelucchiKLMathewsCM:
Tic symptom dimensions and their heritabilities in Tourette’s syndrome.
Psychiatr Genet.
2015;25(3):112–8.
10.1097/YPG.0000000000000084
2571444928
Ben-ShlomoYScharfJMMillerLL:
Parental mood during pregnancy and post-natally is associated with offspring risk of Tourette syndrome or chronic tics: prospective data from the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children (ALSPAC).
European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry.
2016;25(4):373–381.
10.1007/s00787-015-0742-0

2617422729
LenningtonJBCoppolaGKataoka-SasakiY:
Transcriptome analysis of the human striatum in Tourette Syndrome.
Biol Psychiatry.
2016;79(5):372–382. pii: S0006-3223(14)00551-4.
10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.07.018

2519995630
XuMKobetsADuJC:
Targeted ablation of cholinergic interneurons in the dorsolateral striatum produces behavioral manifestations of Tourette syndrome.
Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.
2015;112(3):893–898.
10.1073/pnas.1419533112

2556154031
IsraelashviliMBar-GadI:
Corticostriatal Divergent Function in Determining the Temporal and Spatial Properties of Motor Tics.
J Neurosci.
2015;35(50):16340–51.
10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2770-15.2015

2667486132
PogorelovVXuMSmithHR:
Corticostriatal interactions in the generation of tic-like behaviors after local striatal disinhibition.
Exp Neurol.
2015;265:122–8.
10.1016/j.expneurol.2015.01.001

2559765033
NordstromEJBittnerKCMcGrathMJ:
"Hyperglutamatergic cortico-striato-thalamo-cortical circuit" breaker drugs alleviate tics in a transgenic circuit model of Tourette׳s syndrome.
Brain Res.
2015;1629:38–53.
10.1016/j.brainres.2015.09.032
2645328934
GreeneDJBlackKJSchlaggarBL:
Considerations for MRI study design and implementation in pediatric and clinical populations.
Dev Cogn Neurosci.
2016;18:101–12.
10.1016/j.dcn.2015.12.005

2675446135
ReuterMTisdallMDQureshiA:
Head motion during MRI acquisition reduces gray matter volume and thickness estimates.
Neuroimage.
2015;107:107–15.
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.12.006

2549843036
TisdallMDReuterMQureshiA:
Prospective motion correction with volumetric navigators (vNavs) reduces the bias and variance in brain morphometry induced by subject motion.
Neuroimage.
2016;127:11–22.
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.11.054

2665478837
DraperAJacksonGMMorganPS:
Premonitory urges are associated with decreased grey matter thickness within the insula and senso-rimotor cortex in young people with Tourette syndrome.
J Neuropsychol.
2016;10(1):143–53.
10.1111/jnp.12089
2653828938
TinazSMalonePHallettM:
Role of the right dorsal anterior insula in the urge to tic in Tourette syndrome.
Mov Disord.
2015;30(9):1190–7.
10.1002/mds.26230
2585508939
PowerJDSchlaggarBLPetersenSE:
Recent progress and outstanding issues in motion correction in resting state fMRI.
Neuroimage.
2015;105:536–51.
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.10.044

2546269240
ZapparoliLPortaMPaulesuE:
The anarchic brain in action: the contribution of task-based fMRI studies to the understanding of Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
Curr Opin Neurol.
2015;28(6):604–11.
10.1097/WCO.0000000000000261
2640240341
ZapparoliLPortaMGandolaM:
A functional magnetic resonance imaging investigation of motor control in Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome during imagined and executed movements.
Eur J Neurosci.
2016;43(4):494–508.
10.1111/ejn.13130
2656618542
WilliamsACIIIGreeneDJKollerJM:
A pilot multicenter study of brain structure in pediatric Tourette syndrome.2015;
http://eventmobi.com/tourette2015/documents/112809archived by WebCite®.
Reference Source
43
WolffNLuehrISenderJ:
A DTI study on the corpus callosum of treatment-naïve boys with ’pure’ Tourette syndrome.
Psychiatry Res.
2016;247:1–8.
10.1016/j.pscychresns.2015.12.003
2674757944
Morand-BeaulieuSFernandesISauvéG:
Electrophysiological similarities in Tourette syndrome and chronic tic disorder.
Int J Dev Neurosci.
2015;47(Part A):63
10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2015.04.176
45
GermainMChuangMNSauvéG:
The impact of comorbidity on event-related brain topography in patients presenting chronic tic disorders and Tourette syndrome.
Int J Dev Neurosci.
2015;47(Part A):102
10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2015.04.278
46
BourLJAckermansLFonckeEM:
Tic related local field potentials in the thalamus and the effect of deep brain stimulation in Tourette syndrome: Report of three cases.
Clin Neurophysiol.
2015;126(8):1578–88.
10.1016/j.clinph.2014.10.217
2543551447
PutsNAHarrisADCrocettiD:
 Reduced GABAergic inhibition and abnormal sensory symptoms in children with Tourette syndrome.
J Neurophysiol.
2015;114(2):808–17.
10.1152/jn.00060.2015

2604182248
Abi-JaoudeESeguraBObesoI:
Similar striatal D2/D3 dopamine receptor availability in adults with Tourette syndrome compared with healthy controls: A [
11C]-(+)-PHNO and [
11C]raclopride positron emission tomography imaging study.
Hum Brain Mapp.
2015;36(7):2592–601.
10.1002/hbm.22793
2578822249
RobertsonCLIshibashiKMandelkernMA:
Striatal D
1- and D
2-type dopamine receptors are linked to motor response inhibition in human subjects.
J Neurosci.
2015;35(15):5990–7.
10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4850-14.2015

2587827250
CoxSMFrankMJLarcherK:
Striatal D1 and D2 signaling differentially predict learning from positive and negative outcomes.
Neuroimage.
2015;109:95–101.
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.12.070
2556282451
BolamJPEllenderTJ:
Histamine and the striatum.
Neuropharmacology.
2015; pii: S0028-3908(15)30059-9.
10.1016/j.neuropharm.2015.08.013
2627584952
EddyCMCavannaAE:
Triangles, tricks and tics: Hyper-mentalizing in response to animated shapes in Tourette syndrome.
Cortex.
2015;71:68–75.
10.1016/j.cortex.2015.06.003
2617711953
GülerASBerkemMYazganY:
Cognitive Flexibility and Social Responsiveness in Children and Adolescents with Tourette Syndrome.
Child Psychiatry Hum Dev.
2015;46(6):940–50.
10.1007/s10578-015-0533-3
2563195154
LuckeIMLinCContehF:
Continuous performance test in pediatric obsessive-compulsive disorder and tic disorders: the role of sustained attention.
CNS Spectr.
2015;20(5):479–89.
10.1017/S1092852914000467
2529657055
TharpJAWendelkenCMathewsCA:
Tourette Syndrome: Complementary Insights from Measures of Cognitive Control, Eyeblink Rate, and Pupil Diameter.
Front Psychiatry.
2015;6:95.
10.3389/fpsyt.2015.00095
2617569456
LiuWYYa-TingHsuLienHY:
Deficits in sensory organization for postural stability in children with Tourette syndrome.
Clin Neurol Neurosurg.
2015;129(Suppl 1):S36–40.
10.1016/S0303-8467(15)30010-X
2568331157
SchunkeOGrashornWKahlU:
Quantitative Sensory Testing in adults with Tourette syndrome.
Parkinsonism Relat Disord.
2016;24:132–6.
10.1016/j.parkreldis.2016.01.006
2681862858
BrandtVCLynnMTObstM:
Visual feedback of own tics increases tic frequency in patients with Tourette’s syndrome.
Cogn Neurosci.
2015;6(1):1–7.
10.1080/17588928.2014.954990
2518580059
MisirlisoyEBrandtVGanosC:
The relation between attention and tic generation in Tourette syndrome.
Neuropsychology.
2015;29(4):658–65.
10.1037/neu0000161
2548638460
BodeckSLappeCEversS:
Tic-reducing effects of music in patients with Tourette’s syndrome: Self-reported and objective analysis.
J Neurol Sci.
2015;352(1–2):41–47.
10.1016/j.jns.2015.03.016
2580545461
DelormeCSalvadorAValabrègueR:
Enhanced habit formation in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
Brain.
2016;139(pt 2):605–15.
10.1093/brain/awv307
2649032962
HimleMMouton-OdumSReamerR:
Development and Initial Feasibility Testing of TicHelper: A Self-Administered Interactive Program for Teaching Comprehensive Behavioral Intervention for Tics.2015
Reference Source
63
McGuireJFPiacentiniJScahillL:
Bothersome tics in patients with chronic tic disorders: Characteristics and individualized treatment response to behavior therapy.
Behav Res Ther.
2015;70:56–63.
10.1016/j.brat.2015.05.006

2598836564
McGuireJFArnoldEParkJM:
Living with tics: Reduced impairment and improved quality of life for youth with chronic tic disorders.
Psychiatry Res.
2015;225(3):571–9.
10.1016/j.psychres.2014.11.045

2550034865
ReeseHEVallejoZRasmussenJ:
Mindfulness-based stress reduction for Tourette Syndrome and Chronic Tic Disorder: a pilot study.
J Psychosom Res.
2015;78(3):293–298.
10.1016/j.jpsychores.2014.08.001
2514987966
O’ConnorKLavoieMBlanchetP:
Evaluation of a cognitive psychophysiological model for management of tic disorders: an open trial.
Br J Psychiatry.
2015; pii: bjp.bp.114.154518.
10.1192/bjp.bp.114.154518
2625074267
Morand-BeaulieuSO’ConnorKPSauvéG:
Cognitive-behavioral therapy induces sensorimotor and specific electrocortical changes in chronic tic and Tourette’s disorder.
Neuropsychologia.
2015;79(pt B):310–21.
10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2015.05.024
2602206068
LemmonMEGradosMKlineT:
Efficacy of Glutamate Modulators in Tic Suppression: A Double-Blind, Randomized Control Trial of D-serine and Riluzole in Tourette Syndrome.
Pediatr Neurol.
2015;52(6):629–34.
10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2015.02.002

2600205269
CohenSCMulqueenJMFerracioli-OdaE:
Meta-Analysis: Risk of Tics Associated With Psychostimulant Use in Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trials.
J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry.
2015;54(9):728–36.
10.1016/j.jaac.2015.06.011
2629929470
Tourette’s Syndrome Study Group:
Treatment of ADHD in children with tics: a randomized controlled trial.
Neurology.
2002;58(4):527–36.
10.1212/WNL.58.4.527
1186512871
DenysDde VriesFCathD:
Dopaminergic activity in Tourette syndrome and obsessive-compulsive disorder.
Eur Neuropsychopharmacol.
2013;23(11):1423–31.
10.1016/j.euroneuro.2013.05.012
2387637672
Catalyst Pharmaceutical Partners Inc.:
Catalyst Pharmaceuticals Announces Encouraging Top-Line Results in Proof-of-Concept Trial of Vigabatrin in Patients With Treatment-Refractory Tourette's Disorder.2015;
http://ir.catalystpharma.com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=919254archived by WebCite®, Accessed: 2015-09-05.
Reference Source
73
SchrockLEMinkJWWoodsDW:
Tourette syndrome deep brain stimulation: a review and updated recommendations.
Mov Disord.
2015;30(4):448–471.
10.1002/mds.26094
2547681874
MinkJWWalkupJFreyKA:
Patient selection and assessment recommendations for deep brain stimulation in Tourette syndrome.
Mov Disord.
2006;21(11):1831–8.
10.1002/mds.21039
1699114475
KefalopoulouZZrinzoLJahanshahiM:
Bilateral globus pallidus stimulation for severe Tourette’s syndrome: a double-blind, randomised crossover trial.
Lancet Neurol.
2015;14(6):595–605.
10.1016/S1474-4422(15)00008-3
2588202976
ZekajESalehCPortaM:
Temporary deep brain stimulation in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome: A feasible approach?
Surg Neurol Int.
2015;6:122.
10.4103/2152-7806.161242

2629077377
Landeros-WeisenbergerAMantovaniAMotlaghMG:
Randomized Sham Controlled Double-blind Trial of Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation for Adults With Severe Tourette Syndrome.
Brain Stimul.
2015;8(3):574–81.
10.1016/j.brs.2014.11.015

2591229678
BlochYAradSLevkovitzY:
Deep TMS add-on treatment for intractable Tourette syndrome: A feasibility study.
World J Biol Psychiatry.
2014;1–5. in press.
10.3109/15622975.2014.964767
2441017879
QiaoJWengSWangP:
Normalization of Intrinsic Neural Circuits Governing Tourette’s Syndrome Using Cranial Electrotherapy Stimulation.
IEEE Trans Biomed Eng.
2015;62(5 ):1272–80.
10.1109/TBME.2014.2385151
2554685080
BennettSWalkupJHindinJ:
Proof of Concept Study of an Oral Orthotic in Reducing Tic Severity in Youth with Chronic Tic Disorder and Tourette Syndrome.2015;
http://eventmobi.com/api/events/7343/documents/download/178e10b8-091c-411f-b9dc-97d62a321f39.pdf/as/Proofarchivedby WebCite®.
Reference Source
81
StewartSBGreeneDJLessov-SchlaggarCN:
Clinical correlates of parenting stress in children with Tourette syndrome and in typically developing children.
J Pediatr.
2015;166(5):1297–1302.e3.
10.1016/j.jpeds.2015.01.041

2576923582
GousséVCzerneckiVDenisP:
Impact of Perceived Stress, Anxiety-Depression and Social Support on Coping Strategies of Parents Having A Child With Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome.
Arch Psychiatr Nurs.
2016;30(1):109–13.
10.1016/j.apnu.2015.08.017
2680451183
CuencaJGlazebrookCKendallT:
Perceptions of treatment for tics among young people with Tourette syndrome and their parents: a mixed methods study.
BMC Psychiatry.
2015;15(1):46.
10.1186/s12888-015-0430-0

2587920584
ShprecherDRKiousBMHimleMH:
Advances in mechanistic understanding and treatment approaches to Tourette syndrome.
Discov Med.
2015;20(111):295–301.
2664590185
RobertsonMM:
A personal 35 year perspective on Gilles de la Tourette syndrome: prevalence, phenomenology, comorbidities, and coexistent psychopathologies.
Lancet Psychiatry.
2015;2(1):68–87.
10.1016/S2215-0366(14)00132-1
2635961486
RobertsonMM:
A personal 35 year perspective on Gilles de la Tourette syndrome: assessment, investigations, and management.
Lancet Psychiatry.
2015;2(1):88–104.
10.1016/S2215-0366(14)00133-3
2635961587
RobertsonMM:
Corrections. A personal 35 year perspective on Gilles de la Tourette syndrome: prevalence, phenomenology, comorbidities, and coexistent psychopathologies.
Lancet Psychiatry.
2015;2(4):291.
10.1016/S2215-0366(15)00132-7
2636006788
RobertsonMM:
Corrections. A personal 35 year perspective on Gilles de la Tourette syndrome: assessment, investigations, and management.
Lancet Psychiatry.
2015;2(4):291.
10.1016/S2215-0366(15)00131-5
2636006889
JankovicJ:
Therapeutic Developments for Tics and Myoclonus.
Mov Disord.
2015;30(11):1566–1573.
10.1002/mds.26414
2631561490
BachmannCJRoessnerVGlaeskeG:
Trends in psychopharmacologic treatment of tic disorders in children and adolescents in Germany.
Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry.
2015;24(2):199–207.
10.1007/s00787-014-0563-6
2488875191
JacksonGMDraperADykeK:
Inhibition, Disinhibition, and the Control of Action in Tourette Syndrome.
Trends Cogn Sci.
2015;19(11):655–65.
10.1016/j.tics.2015.08.006
2644012092
HawksleyJCavannaAENagaiY:
The role of the autonomic nervous system in Tourette Syndrome.
Front Neurosci.
2015;9:117.
10.3389/fnins.2015.00117
2607475293
HanksCELewinABJaneMP:
Social Deficits and Autism Spectrum Disorders in Tourette’s Syndrome.
Curr Dev Disord Rep.
2015;2(4):285–292.
10.1007/s40474-015-0060-8
94
Coffey BarbaraJ:
Complexities for Assessment and Treatment of Co-Occurring ADHD and Tics.
Curr Dev Disord Rep.
2015;2(4):293–299.
10.1007/s40474-015-0061-7
95
McGuireJFRickettsEJPiacentiniJ:
Behavior Therapy for Tic Disorders: an Evidenced-Based Review and New Directions for Treatment Research.
Curr Dev Disord Rep.
2015;2(4):309–317.
10.1007/s40474-015-0063-5

2654379796
GreeneDJSchlaggarBLBlackKJ:
Neuroimaging in Tourette Syndrome: Research Highlights From 2014–2015.
Curr Dev Disord Rep.
2015;2(4):300–308.
10.1007/s40474-015-0062-6

2654379697
Tourette Association of America:
Recently published scientific articles.2015; Accessed: 2015-09-05.
Reference Source
10.5256/f1000research.9438.r14669Referee response for version 1WoodsDouglas1Referee
1Department of Psychology, Marquette University, Milwaukee, WI, USA
Competing interests: Dr. Woods receives royalties from Oxford University Press and Guilford Press. He receives speaking fees from a program partnership between the CDC and the Tourette Association of America.1272016Version 1recommendationapproveThis was a well-written overview of research published in the TS field during 2015.  I have no major concerns with the paper, but a couple of issues should be addressed in the paper.
The authors should make clear that this is not a methodological critique of any particular study or set of studies. It is simply an overview.The authors should take care not to insert their subjective opinions into the paper. For example, on page 2, the authors note that "The most important genetic news of the year may have been...." I would like the readers to make that conclusion rather than the authors.The authors conclusions about the effects of why vocal tics responded so well to CBIT are speculative (p. 8), and the authors should note that such an explanation would require confirmation.At the end of the paper, I think the authors should make calls for additional studies. The 2015 year had things to say about why CBIT may or may not work, and the authors should call for additional work in that area. The authors should also call for large-scale translational studies that bring together various areas of basic science in the context of a clinical trial. This arrangement will lead to exciting new discoveries about tics and how treatments work. Finally, the authors should consider calling for research on optimizing treatment sequencing.
 Overall, this was a useful review.I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard.10.5256/f1000research.9438.r14670Referee response for version 1CoffmanKeith A.1Referee
1Division of Pediatric Neurology, Children's Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.1272016Version 1recommendationapproveI read, with great interest, the manuscript by Richards and Black. Overall, it was outstanding and provides an excellent, comprehensive review of the latest literature on Tourette Syndrome. I recommend that it be indexed, without revisions.I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard.10.5256/f1000research.9438.r14667Referee response for version 1HartmannAndreas1Referee
1Department of Neurology, Assistance Publique- Hopitaux de Paris, Paris, France
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.672016Version 1recommendationapproveA very comprehensive review of the TS literature in 2015 for which the authors must be thanked. Generally speaking, they provide a brief overview of the main results / points of each paper but do not dwell into interpretations and discussions, which is fine with me; all readers interested can look up the primary article. Also, there are no relevant articles missing from what I can gather as I have a weekly Pubcrawler alert for TS. The choice of papers is subjective, of course, and I was surprised not to find a few of our own group’s contributions, listed below, but I leave it up to the authors to elaborate on them or not.I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard.References1
WorbeYLehericySHartmannA:
Neuroimaging of tic genesis: Present status and future perspectives.
Mov Disord.2015;30(9) :
10.1002/mds.26333
1179-83
10.1002/mds.26333
263771512
MuellnerJDelmaireCValabrégueRSchüpbachMManginJFVidailhetMLehéricySHartmannAWorbeY:
Altered structure of cortical sulci in gilles de la Tourette syndrome: Further support for abnormal brain development.
Mov Disord.2015;30(5) :
10.1002/mds.26207
655-61
10.1002/mds.26207
258208113
WorbeYMarrakchi-KacemLLecomteSValabregueRPouponFGuevaraPTucholkaAManginJFVidailhetMLehericySHartmannAPouponC:
Altered structural connectivity of cortico-striato-pallido-thalamic networks in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
Brain.2015;138(Pt 2) :
10.1093/brain/awu311
472-82
10.1093/brain/awu311
25392196
