<?xml version="1.0"?>
J Neurogastroenterol MotilJ Neurogastroenterol MotilJournal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility2093-08792093-0887Korean Society of Neurogastroenterology and Motility50565682741313810.5056/jnm16018jnm-22-589ReviewEffect of Probiotics on Central Nervous System Functions in Animals and Humans: A Systematic ReviewWangHuiying123LeeIn-Seon123BraunChristoph24EnckPaul1*1Department of Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, University of Tübingen, 
Germany2MEG Center, University Hospital Tübingen, 
Germany3Graduate Training Center of Neuroscience, IMPRS for Cognitive and Systems Neuroscience, Tübingen, 
Germany4CIMeC, Center for Mind/Brain Sciences, University of Trento, 
Italy*Correspondence: Paul Enck, PhD, Department of Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, University Hospital Tübingen, Osianderstr. 5, 72076 Tübingen, Germany, Tel: +49-7071-2989118, Fax: +49-7071-294382, E-mail: paul.enck@uni-tuebingen.de10201601102016224589605271201625420161852016© 2016 The Korean Society of Neurogastroenterology and Motility2016This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.To systematically review the effects of probiotics on central nervous system function in animals and humans, to summarize effective interventions (species of probiotic, dose, duration), and to analyze the possibility of translating preclinical studies. Literature searches were conducted in Pubmed, Medline, Embase, and the Cochrane Library. Only randomized controlled trials were included. In total, 38 studies were included: 25 in animals and 15 in humans (2 studies were conducted in both). Most studies used Bifidobacterium (eg, B. longum, B. breve, and B. infantis) and Lactobacillus (eg, L. helveticus, and L. rhamnosus), with doses between 109 and 1010 colony-forming units for 2 weeks in animals and 4 weeks in humans. These probiotics showed efficacy in improving psychiatric disorder-related behaviors including anxiety, depression, autism spectrum disorder (ASD), obsessive-compulsive disorder, and memory abilities, including spatial and non-spatial memory. Because many of the basic science studies showed some efficacy of probiotics on central nervous system function, this background may guide and promote further preclinical and clinical studies. Translating animal studies to human studies has obvious limitations but also suggests possibilities. Here, we provide several suggestions for the translation of animal studies. More experimental designs with both behavioral and neuroimaging measures in healthy volunteers and patients are needed in the future.AnimalsAnxietyDepressionHumansProbiotics<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Search Strategy</title><p>This systematic review was conducted according to guidelines of the “Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions”, following the Preferred Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-analysis guidelines.<xref rid="b32-jnm-22-589" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="b33-jnm-22-589" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Relevant studies were found by searches in the Pubmed, Medline, Embase, and Cochrane Library databases. Articles from 1950 to April 2016 were initially searched using the search terms “(probiotic OR gut microbiota) AND (behavior OR central nervous system)”. Additional citations were sought using references in articles retrieved from searches. We only included articles written in English. The first search was undertaken by analyzing text words contained in the title and abstract, and of the key words describing the articles. The second search was conducted according to the citations from all identified reports and relevant review articles.</p></sec><sec><title>Study Selection</title><p>We included all animal and human studies using different strains of probiotics. In human studies reports of both healthy volunteers and patients were considered.</p><p>The abstracts of the retrieved papers were screened for matching the following criteria: (1) the study included a probiotic intervention and (2) the study tested CNS function. After exclusion of non-relevant studies, the remaining articles were screened for the following criteria: (1) the study was described as a randomized controlled study (RCT), (2) the study was described as double-blind if studied in human participants, (3) the study involved use of probiotics in single- and/or multi-strains and those that only used pre-biotics or antibiotics were not included, and (4) the study included measures of behavioral experiments, neuropsychological measures (eg, electroencephalography, magnetoencephalography, and functional magnetic resonance imaging). Those that only involved neurophysiological measures were not included in the qualitative analysis but only in the Discussion (eg, measuring neurochemical level, HPA axis activity) because different studies tested quite divergent aspects of lower-level CNS activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Collection and Analysis</title><p>A data extraction and assessment form from the Cochrane Collaboration was used to further exclude inappropriate studies and to extract data we needed to analyze.<xref rid="b33-jnm-22-589" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Double extraction of data was conducted: important data included the source of participants (animal species/strains, patient types), intervention groups (probiotic, placebo, or any other intervention), sample size, duration of interventions, and outcomes (behavioral changes as the primary outcome and lower-level changes [eg, biochemical changes] as secondary outcomes).</p><p>We assessed the quality of each study included using the Quality Assessment Tool for Quantitative Studies and the Quality Assessment Tool for Quantitative Studies Dictionary developed by The Effective Public Health Practice Project (EPHPP) (National Collaborating Centre for Methods and Tools [2008]).<xref rid="b34-jnm-22-589" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p><p>The inclusion of both animals and human studies resulted in great heterogeneity of participants, interventions, and CNS functions measured. The outcomes of each study were described. A qualitative synthesis of selected studies was made with the aim of coming to conclusions about which probiotic interventions, at which dose, and for how long, were more/most effective with regard to certain CNS functions. Because of the heterogeneity of designs a meta-analysis was deemed to be inappropriate.</p></sec></sec>Financial support: The research leading to these results has received funding from the People Programme of the European Union’s Seventh Framework Programme under REA grant agreement No. 607652 (NeuroGut).Conflicts of interest: None.Author contributions: Paul Enck conceptualized the paper; Huiying Wang reviewed and evaluated the literature; and Huiying Wang, In-Seon Lee, Christoph Braun, and Paul Enck wrote the manuscript.References1LeyREPetersonDAGordonJIEcological and evolutionary forces shaping microbial diversity in the human intestineCell200612483784810.1016/j.cell.2006.02.017164975922GillSRPopMDeboyRTMetagenomic analysis of the human distal gut microbiomeScience20063121355135910.1126/science.1124234167411153FarmerADRandallHAAzizQIt’s a gut feeling: how the gut microbiota affects the state of mindJ Physiol20145922981298810.1113/jphysiol.2013.270389246650994KeightleyPCKoloskiNATalleyNJPathways in gut-brain communication: evidence for distinct gut-to-brain and brain-to-gut syndromesAust N Z J Psychiatry20154920721410.1177/0004867415569801257108265DinanTGStantonCCryanJFPsychobiotics: a novel class of psycho-tropicBiol Psychiatry20137472072610.1016/j.biopsych.2013.05.001237592446CollinsSMSuretteMBercikPThe interplay between the intestinal microbiota and the brainNat Rev Microbiol20121073574210.1038/nrmicro2876230009557CryanJFO’MahonySMThe microbiome-gut-brain axis: from bowel to behaviorNeurogastroenterol Motil20112318719210.1111/j.1365-2982.2010.01664.x213034288CryanJFDinanTGMind-altering microorganisms: the impact of the gut microbiota on brain and behaviourNat Rev Neurosci20121370171210.1038/nrn3346229681539SudoNChidaYAibaYPostnatal microbial colonization programs the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal system for stress response in miceJ Physiol2004558Pt 126327510.1113/jphysiol.2004.0633881513306210TomovaAHusarovaVLakatosovaSGastrointestinal microbiota in children with autism in SlovakiaPhysiol Behav201513817918710.1016/j.physbeh.2014.10.0332544620111KangDWParkJGIlhanZEReduced incidence of Prevotella and other fermenters in intestinal microflora of autistic childrenPLoS One20138e6832210.1371/journal.pone.00683222384418712ScheperjansFAhoVPereiraPAGut microbiota are related to Parkinson’s disease and clinical phenotypeMov Disord20153035035810.1002/mds.260692547652913RijkersGTde VosWMBrummerRJMorelliLCorthierGMarteauPHealth benefits and health claims of probiotics: bridging science and marketingBr J Nutr20111061291129610.1017/S000711451100287X2186194014LillyDMStillwellRHProbiotics: growth-promoting factors produced by microorganismsScience196514774774810.1126/science.147.3659.7471424202415MazurakNBroelzEStorrMEnckPProbiotic therapy of the irritable bowel syndrome: why is the evidence still poor and what can be done about it?J Neurogastroenterol Motil20152147148510.5056/jnm150712635125316FordACQuigleyEMLacyBEEfficacy of prebiotics, probiotics, and synbiotics in irritable bowel syndrome and chronic idiopathic constipation: systematic review and meta-analysisAm J Gastroenterol20141091547156110.1038/ajg.2014.2022507005117LeeBJBakYTIrritable bowel syndrome, gut microbiota and probioticsJ Neurogastroenterol Motil20111725226610.5056/jnm.2011.17.3.2522186081718DuPontHLBiologic properties and clinical uses of rifaximinExpert Opin Pharmacother20111229330210.1517/14656566.2011.5463472122663919ChichlowskiMRudolphCVisceral pain and gastrointestinal microbiomeJ Neurogastroenterol Motil20152117218110.5056/jnm150252582933720LiuYWLiuWHWuCCPsychotropic effects of Lactobacillus plantarum PS128 in early life-stressed and naïve adult miceBrain Res2016163111210.1016/j.brainres.2015.11.0182662054221LiuWHChuangHLHuangYTAlteration of behavior and monoamine levels attributable to Lactobacillus plantarum PS128 in germ-free miceBehav Brain Res201629820220910.1016/j.bbr.2015.10.0462652284122BercikPParkAJSinclairDThe anxiolytic effect of Bifidobacterium longum NCC3001 involves vagal pathways for gut-brain communicationNeurogastroenterol Motil2011231132113910.1111/j.1365-2982.2011.01796.x2198866123BravoJAForsythePChewMVIngestion of Lactobacillus strain regulates emotional behavior and central GABA receptor expression in a mouse via the vagus nerveProc Natl Acad Sci USA2011108160501605510.1073/pnas.11029991082187615024O’SullivanEBarrettEGrenhamSBDNF expression in the hippocampus of maternally separated rats: does Bifidobacterium breve 6330 alter BDNF levels?Benef Microbes2011219920710.3920/BM2011.00152198635925Ait-BelgnaouiADurandHCartierCPrevention of gut leakiness by a probiotic treatment leads to attenuated HPA response to an acute psychological stress in ratsPsychoneuroendocrinology2012371885189510.1016/j.psyneuen.2012.03.0242254193726DesbonnetLGarrettLClarkeGBienenstockJDinanTGThe probiotic Bifidobacteria infantis: an assessment of potential antidepressant properties in the ratJ Psychiatr Res20084316417410.1016/j.jpsychires.2008.03.0091845627927DesbonnetLGarrettLClarkeGKielyBCryanJFDinanTGEffects of the probiotic Bifidobacterium infantis in the maternal separation model of depressionNeuroscience20101701179118810.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.08.0052069621628KwokLYWangLZhangJGuoZZhangHA pilot study on the effect of Lactobacillus casei Zhang on intestinal microbiota parameters in Chinese subjects of different ageBenef Microbes2014529530410.3920/BM2013.00472485495829SmithCJEmgeJRBerzinsKProbiotics normalize the gut-brain-microbiota axis in immunodeficient miceAm J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol2014307G793G80210.1152/ajpgi.00238.20142519047330WangTHuXLiangSLactobacillus fermentum NS9 restores the antibiotic induced physiological and psychological abnormalities in ratsBenef Microbes2015670771710.3920/BM2014.01772586928131HsiaoEYMcBrideSWHsienSMicrobiota modulate behavioral and physiological abnormalities associated with neurodevelopmental disordersCell20131551451146310.1016/j.cell.2013.11.0242431548432MoherDShamseerLClarkeMPreferred reporting items for systematic review and meta-analysis protocols (PRISMA-P) 2015 statementSyst Rev201542046405310.1186/2046-4053-4-133HigginsJPTGreenSCochrane handbook for systematic reviews of interventions. Version 5.1.0The Cochrane Collaboration2011Available from URL: http://handbook.cochrane.org/accessed 22 Sep 201634National Collaborating Centre for Methods and Tools2008Quality assessment tool for quantitative studiesHamiltonMaMaster University(updated 13 April 2010). Available from URL: http://www.nccmt.ca/resources/search/14accessed 22 Sep 201635BercikPVerduEFFosterJAChronic gastrointestinal inflammation induces anxiety-like behavior and alters central nervous system biochemistry in miceGastroenterology201013921022112e110.1053/j.gastro.2010.06.0632060001636SavignacHMKielyBDinanTGCryanJFBifidobacteria exert strain-specific effects on stress-related behavior and physiology in BALB/c miceNeurogastroenterol Motil2014261615162710.1111/nmo.124272525118837OhlandCLKishLBellHEffects of Lactobacillus helveticus on murine behavior are dependent on diet and genotype and correlate with alterations in the gut microbiomePsychoneuroendocrinology2013381738174710.1016/j.psyneuen.2013.02.0082356663238LiangSWangTHuXAdministration of Lactobacillus helveticus NS8 improves behavioral, cognitive, and biochemical aberrations caused by chronic restraint stressNeuroscience201531056157710.1016/j.neuroscience.2015.09.0332640898739MessaoudiMLalondeRViolleNAssessment of psychotropic-like properties of a probiotic formulation (Lactobacillus helveticus R0052 and Bifidobacterium longum R0175) in rats and human subjectsBr J Nutr201110575576410.1017/S00071145100043192097401540SinghPKChopraKKuhadAKaurIPRole of Lactobacillus acidophilus loaded floating beads in chronic fatigue syndrome: behavioral and biochemical evidencesNeurogastroenterol Motil201224366e17010.1111/j.1365-2982.2011.01861.x2229629441Arseneault-BréardJRondeauIGilbertKCombination of Lactobacillus helveticus R0052 and Bifidobacterium longum R0175 reduces post-myocardial infarction depression symptoms and restores intestinal permeability in a rat modelBr J Nutr20121071793179910.1017/S00071145110051372193345842LuoJWangTLiangSHuXLiWJinFIngestion of Lactobacillus strain reduces anxiety and improves cognitive function in the hyperammonemia ratSci China Life Sci20145732733510.1007/s11427-014-4615-42455447143SavignacHMTramullasMKielyBDinanTGCryanJFBifidobacteria modulate cognitive processes in an anxious mouse strainBehav Brain Res2015287597210.1016/j.bbr.2015.02.0442579493044LiuJSunJWangFNeuroprotective Effects of Clostridium butyricum against Vascular Dementia in Mice via Metabolic ButyrateBiomed Res Int201520154129462652327845GareauMGWineERodriguesDMBacterial infection causes stress-induced memory dysfunction in miceGut20116030731710.1136/gut.2009.2025152096602246DavariSTalaeiSAAlaeiHSalamiMProbiotics treatment improves diabetes-induced impairment of synaptic activity and cognitive function: behavioral and electrophysiological proofs for microbiome-gut-brain axisNeuroscience201324028729610.1016/j.neuroscience.2013.02.0552350010047JeongJJKimKAAhnYTProbiotic mixture KF attenuates age-dependent memory deficit and lipidemia in Fischer 344 ratsJ Microbiol Biotechnol2015251532153610.4014/jmb.1505.050022597561148KantakPABobrowDNNybyJGObsessive-compulsive-like behaviors in house mice are attenuated by a probiotic (Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG)Behav Pharmacol201425717910.1097/FBP.00000000000000132425743649D’MelloCRonaghanNZaheerRProbiotics improve inflammation-associated sickness behavior by altering communication between the peripheral immune system and the brainJ Neurosci201535108211083010.1523/JNEUROSCI.0575-15.20152622486450TakadaMNishidaKKataoka-KatoAProbiotic Lactobacillus casei strain Shirota relieves stress-associated symptoms by modulating the gut-brain interaction in human and animal modelsNeurogastroenterol Motil2016281027103610.1111/nmo.128042689629151RaoAVBestedACBeaulneTMA randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled pilot study of a probiotic in emotional symptoms of chronic fatigue syndromeGut Pathog20091610.1186/1757-4749-1-61933868652MohammadiAAJazayeriSKhosravi-DaraniKThe effects of probiotics on mental health and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial in petrochemical workersNutr NeurosciPublished Online First: 16 Apr 201510.1179/1476830515Y.000000002353SteenbergenLSellaroRvan HemertSBoschJAColzatoLSA randomized controlled trial to test the effect of multispecies probiotics on cognitive reactivity to sad moodBrain Behav Immun20154825826410.1016/j.bbi.2015.04.0032586229754DickersonFBStallingsCOrigoniAEffect of probiotic supplementation on schizophrenia symptoms and association with gastrointestinal functioning: a randomized, placebo-controlled trialPrim Care Companion CNS DisordPublished Online First: 13 Feb 201410.4088/PCC.13m0157955Vaghef-MehrabanyEAlipourBHomayouni-RadASharifSKAsghari-JafarabadiMZavvariSProbiotic supplementation improves inflammatory status in patients with rheumatoid arthritisNutrition20143043043510.1016/j.nut.2013.09.0072435543956DapoignyMPicheTDucrottePLunaudBCardotJMBernalier-DonadilleAEfficacy and safety profile of LCR35 complete freeze-dried culture in irritable bowel syndrome: a randomized, double-blind studyWorld J Gastroenterol2012182067207510.3748/wjg.v18.i17.20672256319457SimrénMOhmanLOlssonJClinical trial: the effects of a fermented milk containing three probiotic bacteria in patients with irritable bowel syndrome - a randomized, double-blind, controlled studyAliment Pharmacol Ther2010312182271986349558WhorwellPJAltringerLMorelJEfficacy of an encapsulated probiotic Bifidobacterium infantis 35624 in women with irritable bowel syndromeAm J Gastroenterol20061011581159010.1111/j.1572-0241.2006.00734.x1686356459RealeMBoscoloPBellanteVDaily intake of Lactobacillus casei Shirota increases natural killer cell activity in smokersBr J Nutr201210830831410.1017/S00071145110056302214289160ParrachoHMRTGibsonGRKnottFBosscherDKleerebezemMMcCartneyALA double blind, placebo controlled, crossover designed probiotic feeding study in children diagnosed with autistic spectrum disordersInternational Journal of Probiotics and Prebiotics201056961MessaoudiMViolleNBissonJFDesorDJavelotHRougeotCBeneficial psychological effects of a probiotic formulation (Lactobacillus helveticus R0052 and Bifidobacterium longum R0175) in healthy human volunteersGut Microbes2011225626110.4161/gmic.2.4.161082198307062BentonDWilliamsCBrownAImpact of consuming a milk drink containing a probiotic on mood and cognitionEur J Clin Nutr20076135536110.1038/sj.ejcn.16025461715159463TillischKLabusJKilpatrickLConsumption of fermented milk product with probiotic modulates brain activityGastroenterology201314413941401e1e410.1053/j.gastro.2013.02.0432347428364SungVCollettSde GooyerTHiscockHTangMWakeMProbiotics to prevent or treat excessive infant crying: systematic review and meta-analysisJAMA Pediatr20131671150115710.1001/jamapediatrics.2013.25722410044065RomijnARRucklidgeJJSystematic review of evidence to support the theory of psychobioticsNutr Rev20157367569310.1093/nutrit/nuv0252637026366AnabreesJIndrioFPaesBAlFalehKProbiotics for infantile colic: a systematic reviewBMC Pediatr20131318610.1186/1471-2431-13-1862423810167GroegerDO’MahonyLMurphyEFBifidobacterium infantis 35624 modulates host inflammatory processes beyond the gutGut Microbes2013432533910.4161/gmic.254872384211068LomasneyKWCryanJFHylandNPConverging effects of a Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus probiotic strain on mouse intestinal physiologyAm J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol2014307G241G24710.1152/ajpgi.00401.20132485256769SaulnierDMRingelYHeymanMBThe intestinal microbiome, probiotics and prebiotics in neurogastroenterologyGut Microbes20134172710.4161/gmic.229732320279670O’MahonyLMcCarthyJKellyPLactobacillus and Bifidobacterium in irritable bowel syndrome: symptom responses and relationship to cytokine profilesGastroenterology200512854155110.1053/j.gastro.2004.11.0501576538871McFarlandLVFrom yaks to yogurt: the history, development, and current use of probioticsClin Infect Dis201560suppl 2S85S9010.1093/cid/civ0542592240672FlochMHWalkerWASandersMERecommendations for probiotic use--2015 update: proceedings and consensus opinionJ Clin Gastroenterol201549suppl 1S69S7310.1097/MCG.00000000000004202644796973DedovicKNgiamJThe cortisol awakening response and major depression: examining the evidenceNeuropsychiatr Dis Treat2015111181118910.2147/NDT.S622892599972274OsborneDMPearson-LearyJMcNayECThe neuroenergetics of stress hormones in the hippocampus and implications for memoryFront Neurosci2015916410.3389/fnins.2015.001642599981175MarigaAMitreMChaoMVConsequences of brain-derived neurotrophic factor withdrawal in CNS neurons and implications in diseaseNeurobiol DisPublished Online First: 22 Mar 201610.1016/j.nbd.2016.03.00976TsaiSJAttention-deficit hyperactivity disorder may be associated with decreased central brain-derived neurotrophic factor activity: clinical and therapeutic implicationsMed Hypotheses20076889689910.1016/j.mehy.2006.06.0251691989177Julio-PieperMBravoJAAliagaEGottelandMReview article: intestinal barrier dysfunction and central nervous system disorders – a controversial associationAliment Pharmacol Ther2014401187120110.1111/apt.129502526296978DesbonnetLClarkeGShanahanFDinanTGCryanJFMicrobiota is essential for social development in the mouseMol Psychiatry20141914614810.1038/mp.2013.652368953679Diaz HeijtzRWangSAnuarFNormal gut microbiota modulates brain development and behaviorProc Natl Acad Sci USA20111083047305210.1073/pnas.10105291082128263680LyteMLiWOpitzNGaykemaRPGoehlerLEInduction of anxiety-like behavior in mice during the initial stages of infection with the agent of murine colonic hyperplasia Citrobacter rodentiumPhysiol Behav20068935035710.1016/j.physbeh.2006.06.0191688715481NeufeldKMKangNBienenstockJFosterJAReduced anxiety-like behavior and central neurochemical change in germ-free miceNeurogastroenterol Motil201123255264e11910.1111/j.1365-2982.2010.01620.x2105468082NishinoRMikamiKTakahashiHCommensal microbiota modulate murine behaviors in a strictly contamination-free environment confirmed by culture-based methodsNeurogastroenterol Motil20132552152810.1111/nmo.121102348030283AsturRSOrtizMLSutherlandRJA characterization of performance by men and women in a virtual Morris water task: a large and reliable sex differenceBehav Brain Res19989318519010.1016/S0166-4328(98)00019-9965999984AsturRSTaylorLBMamelakANPhilpottLSutherlandRJHumans with hippocampus damage display severe spatial memory impairments in a virtual Morris water taskBehav Brain Res2002132778410.1016/S0166-4328(01)00399-01185386085KalováEVlcekKJarolímováEBuresJAllothetic orientation and sequential ordering of places is impaired in early stages of Alzheimer’s disease: corresponding results in real space tests and computer testsBehav Brain Res200515917518610.1016/j.bbr.2004.10.0161581718186LaczóJAndelRVyhnalekMHuman analogue of the morris water maze for testing subjects at risk of Alzheimer’s diseaseNeurodegener Dis2010714815210.1159/0002892262019769587KirschbaumCPirkeKMHellhammerDHThe ‘Trier Social Stress Test’ – a tool for investigating psychobiological stress responses in a laboratory settingNeuropsychobiology199328768110.1159/000119004825541488SebastianCVidingEWilliamsKDBlakemoreSJSocial brain development and the affective consequences of ostracism in adolescenceBrain Cogn20107213414510.1016/j.bandc.2009.06.0081962832389WilliamsKDJarvisBCyberball: a program for use in research on interpersonal ostracism and acceptanceBehav Res Methods20063817418010.3758/BF031927651681752990AllenAPKennedyPJCryanJFDinanTGClarkeGBiological and psychological markers of stress in humans: focus on the Trier Social Stress TestNeurosci Biobehav Rev2014389412410.1016/j.neubiorev.2013.11.0052423985491SchwabeLHaddadLSchachingerHHPA axis activation by a socially evaluated cold-pressor testPsychoneuroendocrinology20083389089510.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.03.0011840313092CianCBarraudPAMelinBRaphelCEffects of fluid ingestion on cognitive function after heat stress or exercise-induced dehydrationInt J Psychophysiol20014224325110.1016/S0167-8760(01)00142-81181239193VickersKJafarpourSMofidiARafatBWoznicaAThe 35% carbon dioxide test in stress and panic research: overview of effects and integration of findingsClin Psychol Rev20123215316410.1016/j.cpr.2011.12.00422322014Figure 1Mechanisms of probiotic effects on the central nervous system. Probiotics influence central nervous system (CNS) function through direct and indirect mechanisms. Probiotics affect the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, by altering corticosteroid (CORT) and/or adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) levels. The immune system is influenced by limited pro-inflammatory cytokine production and inflammation, and this, in turn, has effects on the CNS. Probiotics can also directly alter CNS biochemistry, such as by affecting brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), c-Fos, γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA), 5 hydroxytryptamine (5-HT), and dopamine (DA) levels, thus influencing mind and behavior. The vagus and enteric nerves are also involved in this gut-brain interaction and are affected by certain probiotics. Probiotics manipulate the gut microbiota (GM) by increasing microbiota diversity and beneficial bacteria composition. An “improved” GM changes metabolites, such as short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) and tryptophan, and so improves CNS function indirectly. The GM also interacts with the endocrine, immune, and neural systems.Figure 2Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses (PRISMA) scheme of retrieved literature. CNS, central nervous system.Table 1Studies of Effects of Probiotics on Central Nervous System Functions in AnimalsStudyAnimalCNS functionProbiotic (species, dosage [CFU/day], duration)Outcome (behavioral level)Secondary outcomeLiu et al,20 2016ELS miceNaïve miceLocomotor activity (open-field test)Anxiety (open-field test, elevated plus maze)Depression (sucrose-preference test, forced-swimming test)L. plantarum PS12810928 daysLocomotor activity ↑Anxiety (only in naïve mice) ↓Depression (only in ELS mice) ↓Corticosteroids (CORT) ↓Cytokine: inflammatory cytokine TNF-α, IL-6 ↓, anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 ↑Brain monoamines and metabolites: 5-HT ↑, 5-HIAA ↓, DA ↑, DOPAC ↓, HVA ↓Liu et al,21 2016GF miceLocomotor activity (open-field test)Anxiety (elevated-plus maze)Depression (forced-swimming test)L. plantarum PS12810916 daysLocomotor activity ↑Anxiety ↓Depression (−)CORT: NABrain monoamines and metabolites: DA ↑, HVA ↑, 5-HT ↑ and 5-HIAA ↑Liang et al,38 2015SPF CRS ratsStress (chronic-restraint stress)Depression (sucrose-preference test)Anxiety (elevated-plus maze, open-field test)Non-spatial memory (object-recognition test, object-placement test)L. helveticus NS8109Initial 21 daysAnxiety ↓Depression ↓Non-spatial memory ↑CORT and ACTH ↓Cytokines: IL-10 ↑Brain monoamines: 5-HT ↑ and NE ↑BDNF expression ↑Wang et al,30 2015Ampicillin-treated ratsAnxiety (elevate-plus maze)Spatial memory (Morris water maze)L. fermentum N93109Initial 30 daysAnxiety ↓Spatial memory ↑CORT and ACTH ↓Brain monoamines: MR ↑, NMDA ↑, GR: NABrain BDNF: NAColon inflammation: myeloperoxidase activity ↓Fecal microbiota: Bacteroides ↑, C. coccoides ↓, Firmicutes ↓, Lactobacillus ↑Smith et al,29 2014RagI−/− miceStress response (water-avoidance stress)Anxiety (light/dark box test)Non-spatial memory (novel-object test)L. rhamnosus R0011 + L. helveticus R00526 × 10928 daysAnxiety ↓Non-spatial memory ↑CORT: NABrain c-Fos expression ↑Intestinal permeability ↓Fecal microbiota: Bacteroides ↑, Enterobacteriaceae ↑, Firmicutes ↑Luo et al,42 2014Hyperammonemia ratsAnxiety (elevate-plus maze)Spatial memory (Morris water maze)L. helveticus NS810914 daysAnxiety ↓Spatial memory ↑Neuroinflammation: PGE2 ↓, IL-1β ↓Brain monoamines: 5-HT ↓Plasma kynurenine pathway: KYN/TRP ↑, KA/KYN ↓Savignac et al,36 2014MiceAnxiety (defensive marble burying, elevated-plus maze, open field)depression (tail-suspension test, forced-swim test)B. longum 1714/B. breve 1205109Initial 21 daysB. longum: Anxiety ↓ Depression ↓B. breve: Anxiety ↓CORT: NAOhland et al,37 2013Il-10 deficient miceAnxiety (elevated Barnes Maze)Spatial memory (elevated Barnes maze)L. helveticus R005210921 daysAnxiety ↓Spatial memory ↑Colon inflammation ↓Cytokines: NACORT ↓SCFA metabolites: NAMessaoudi et al,39 2011RatsAnxiety (conditioned defensive burying)B. longum R0175 + L. helveticus R005210914 daysAnxiety ↓NABravo et al,23 2011MiceAnxiety (open arms, elevated-plus maze, fear conditioning)Depression (forced-swim test)L. rhamnosus JB-110928 daysAnxiety ↓Depression ↓CORT ↓GABA receptor expression influence depending on brain areasProbiotic effect via vagus nerveBercik et al,22 2011Chronic colitis miceAnxiety (step-down test)B. longum NCC3001101014 daysAnxiety ↓Colon inflammation: NABrain BDNF expression: NAEnteric neurons excitability ↓Probiotic effect via vagus nerveBercik et al,35 2010T-muris infected miceAnxiety (light/dark behavior, step-down test)B. longum NCC3001/L. rhamnosus NCC4007101010 daysAnxiety ↓ (B. longum only)Colon inflammation ↓Plasma cytokines: NABDNF expression ↑ (only by B. longum)Tryptophan and kynurenine: NANo effect of vagotomySingh et al,40 2012RatsCFS and depression induced by forced-swim test (immobility period, post-swim fatigue time)L. acidophilus as LAB or LAB FB1077 daysDepression ↓ (larger effect of LAB FB than LAB);Brain oxido-nitrosative stress biomarker ↓Cytokines: TNF-α ↓Arseneautl-Bread et al,41 2012MI ratsPost-MI depression (forced-swim test); social behavior (social interaction test); emotional memory (passive avoidance step-down test)B. longum R0175 + L. helveticus R005210914 daysDepression ↓Social interaction ↑Non-spatial memory ↑Cytokines: pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-1β ↓Intestinal barrier permeability ↓Desbonnet et al,27 2010MS ratsDepression (forced-swim test)B. infantis 356241010Initial 40 daysDepression ↓CORT: NACytokines: IL-10 ↓Tryptophan: NABrain monoamines (−)Noradrenaline ↑Desbonnet et al,26 2008RatsDepression (forced-swim test)B. infantis 35624101014 daysNo behavioral changeCytokines: pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-6, IFN-γ ↓; anti-inflammatory cytokines IL-10 ↓Tryptophan ↑Brain monoamines and metabolites – 5-HIAA ↓, DOPAC ↓Neuroendocrine: NA, CORT: NA, AVP: NA, CRF: NALiu etal,44 2015VaD (vascular dementia) miceLocomotor activity (open-field test)Spatial memory (Morris water maze)C. butyricum WZMC1016 (CGMCC 9831)106/107/10842 daysLocomotor activity ↑Spatial memory ↑Morphological change of hippocampus ↓BDNF expression ↑Butyrate in feces and brain ↑Fecal bacteria diversity ↑Jeong et al,47 2015Aged ratsSpatial memory (Y-maze, Morris water maze)L. plantarum KY1032 + L. curvatus HY7601101048 daysSpatial memory ↑Cytokines: pro-inflammatory cytokines NF-κB, ↓BDNF ↑Lipidemia ↓Savignac et al,43 2015MiceNon-spatial memory (object recognition, fear conditioning)Spatial memory (Barnes Maze)B. longum 1714/B. breve 1205109initial 21 daysB. longum: Non-spatial memory ↑ Spatial memory ↑B. breve: Non-spatial memory ↑Visceral sensitivity -colon distension: NACORT: NAGareau et al,45 2011C. rodentium infected miceMemory dysfunction induced by water avoidance (novel-object test, T-maze);L. rhamnosus R0011 + L. helveticus R00526 × 10917 daysNon-spatial memory ↑CORT ↓Colon epithelial cell hyperplasia ↓Cytokine: pro-inflammatory cytokines IFN γ ↓Brain BDNF and c-Fos expression ↑Microbiota: Firmicutes ↓, Enterobacteriaceae ↓, Eubacteria rectale ↓, Lactobacillus ↑Davari et al,46 2013Diabetic ratsSpatial memory (Morris water maze)L. acidophilus 4356 + B. lactis 10140 + L. fermentum ATCC93382 × 101056 daysSpatial memory ↑Hippocampal long-term potentiation ↑Serum glucose ↓ and insulin ↑Oxidative stress biomarkers: SOD ↑, 8-OHdG ↓Hsiao et al,31 2013MIA miceAutism spectrum disorder:Anxiety (open field, marble burying);Sensory gating (prepulse inhibition);Communicative behavior (ultrasonic vocalizations);Social interaction (3-chamber social test)B. fragilis NCTC934310106 daysAnxiety ↓Sensory gating ↑Communicative behavior ↑Social interaction (−)Intestinal permeability ↓Tryptophan metabolites: indolepyruvate ↓Microbiota: Lachnospiraceae ↓, Bacteroidales ↓Kantak et al,48 2014Male miceobsessive-compulsive-disorder-like behavior (open field, marble burying, ultrasonic vocalizations, intermale aggression)L. rhamnosus GG (ATCC 53103)10914, 28 daysLocomotor behavior ↓Marble burying ↓Ultrasonic vocalizations (−)Intermale aggression (−)NAD’Mello et al,49 2015Male miceInflammation associated sickness behavior (social exploratory)VSL#31.7 × 10910 daysSocial exploratory behavior in bile duct ligation treated mice ↑Intestinal permeability: NACytokine: pro-inflammatory cytokine TNF-α ↓Monocyte infiltration ↓Microglial activation ↓Fecal Microbiota (−)Takada et al,50 2016Male ratsStress response to water avoidance stressL. casei Shirota YIT 90293 × 10914 daysNACORT ↓c-Fos expression in the paraventricular nucleus ↓Gastric vagal afferent activity ↑Neuronal excitability of NTS ↑ELS, early life stress; CORT, corticosterone; 5-HT, 5-hydroxytryptamine; 5-HIAA, 5-Hydroxyindoleacetic acid; DA, dopamine; DOPAC, 3,4-dihydroxyphenylacetic acid; HVA, homovanillic acid; GF, germ free; NA, not applicable; SPF, specific pathogen free; CRS, chronic restraint stress; ACTH, adrenocorticotropic hormone; NE, norepinephrine; BDNF, brain-derived neurotrophic factor; MR, mineralocorticoid; NMDA, N-methyl-D-aspertate; GR, glucocorticoid; RagI−/−, RagI knockout; PGE2, prostaglandin E2; KYN, L-kynurenine; TRP, tryptophan; KA, kynurenic acid; SCFA, short-chain fatty acid; GABA, gamma-Aminobutyric acid; CFS, chronic fatigue syndrome; LAB, Lactobacillus acidophilus; FB, floating bead; MI, myocardial infarction; MS, maternal separation; AVP, arginine vasopressin; CRF, corticotrophin-releasing factor; VaD, vascular dementia; NF-κB, nuclear factor-kappa B; SOD, superoxide dismutase; 8-OHdG, 8-hydroxy-2’deoxyguanosine; MIA, maternal immune activation; VSL#3, a high-concentration probiotic preparation of 8 live freeze-dried bacterial (Lactobacillus casei, Lactobacillus plantarum, Lactobacillus acidophilus, Lactobacillus bulgaricus, Bifidobacterium longum, Bifidobacterium breve, Bifidobacterium infantis, and Streptococcus thermophiles); NTS, nucleus tractus solitary; B. breve, Bifidobacterium breve; B. fragilis, Bifidobacterium fragilis; B. infantis, Bifidobacterium infantis; B. lactis, Bifidobacterium lactis; B. longum, Bifidobacterium longum; C. butyricum, Clostridium butyricum; C. coccoides, Clostridium coccoides; C. rodentium, Citrobacter rodentium; L. acidophilus, Lactobacillus acidophilus; L. casei, Lactobacillus casei; L. curvatus, Lactobacillus curvatus; L. fermentum, Lactobacillus fermentum; L. helveticus, Lactobacillus helveticus; L. plantarum, Lactobacillus plantarum; L. rhamnosus, Lactobacillus rhamnosus.Table 2Studies of Probiotic Effects on Central Nervous System Functions in HumansStudyParticipantsProbioticDosage (CFU/day) and durationCNS functionOutcomeSecondary outcomeTakada et al,50 2016140 healthy studentsL. casei Shirota YIT 90291 × 1098 weeksSTAINo difference of STAI scoreChange in salivary cortisol level before exam ↓Decrease in physical symptoms ↓Mohammadi et al,52 201570 petrochemical workersprobiotic yogurt (L. acidophilus LA5 + B. lactis Bb12) + placebo capsule;Conventional yogurt (S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus.) + probiotic capsule (L. casei, L. acidophilus, L. rhamnosus, L. bulgaricus, B. breve, B. longum, S. thermophilus)probiotic yogurt: 107 in totalProbiotic capsule: 3 × 103, 3 × 107, 7 × 109, 5 × 108, 2 × 1010; 109, 3 × 108, respectively (2.88 × 1010 in total)/6 weeksGHQDASSHPA axis activityImprovement of GHQ and DASS in probiotics yogurt and probiotics capsule groups; no difference in HPA axis activityNASteenbergen et al,53 201540 healthy volunteersEcologic Barrier: B. bifidum W23, B. lactis W52, L. acidophilus W37, L. brevis W63, L. casei W56, L. salivarius W24, Lactococcus lactis (W19 and W58).5 × 1094 weeksLEIDS-rBDIBAIImprovement of total score and item ‘rumination’ of LEIDS-r.No difference of scores of Beck Depression and Beck Anxiety InventoryNADickerson et al,54 201465 schizophrenia patientsL. rhamnosus GG (ATCC 53103+B. animalis subsp. lactis Bb122 × 10914 weeksPANSSNo difference of toll score or positive, negative or general scores.Severe difficulty in bowel movement ↓Vaghef-Mehrabany et al,55 201446 patients with rheumatoid arthritisL. casei 011088 weeksSTAINo difference of STAI scoreDietary: NACytokines: pro inflammatory cytokine TNF-α, IL-6, and IL-12 ↓, anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 ↑Dapoigny et al,56 201250 IBS patientsL. casei subsp. rhamnosus LCR356 × 1084 weeksHADSNo difference in HADS scoreIBS severity score: only clinically relevant decreased in subtype IBS-D ↓Presence of Lactobacillus in feces: 85% of patientsSimrén et al,57 201074 IBS patientsMilk fermented with yoghurt bacteria L. bulgaricus + S. thermophilus and containing L. paracasei F19 + L. acidophilus La5 + B. lactis Bb122 × 10108 weeksHADSNo difference of HADS scoreDiet: same among groupsWhorwell et al,58 2006362 female IBS patientsB. infantis 35624106, 108, 10104 weeksHADSNo difference in any of the dosagesIBS symptom: ↓ in 108 groupReale et al,59 201272 male smokersL. casei Shirota4 × 10103 weeksSTAINo difference in STAI scoreNatural killer cell activity ↑CD16+ cell ↑BMI: NABowel function ↑Parracho et al,60 201015 children (4–16Y) with ASDL. plantarum WCFS14.5 × 10103 weeksDBCNo significant difference in DBC scoreBowel function: only different in stool consistencyFecal microbiota: Lactobacillus Lab 158 ↑, Clostridium Erec482 ↓Messaoudi et al,39 201155 healthy volunteersL. helveticus R0052 + B. longum R01753 × 1094 weeksHSCL-90HADSPSSCCLImprovement of anxiety, depression and problem solving, and reduced UFC level in probiotics groupMedian urinary free cortisol ↓Messaoudi et al,61 201125 healthy volunteers (with lower UFC levels than median value at baselineL. helveticus R0052 + B. longum R01753 × 1094 weeksHSCL-90HADSPSSCCLImprovement of anxiety and depression in probiotics groupNARao et al,51 200935 CFS patientsL. casei Shirota2.4 × 10108 weeksBDIBAIDecreased anxiety symptoms in probiotic groupFecal microbiota: aerobes ↑, anaerobes ↑ Bifidobacteria ↑, Lactobacillus ↑Benton et al,62 2007124 healthy volunteersL. casei Shirota (containing milk)6.5 × 10910/20 daysQuestionnaire-based POMSEpisodic memory (Wechsler Memory Scale)Retrieval from long-term memoryVerbal fluencyEating-associated behaviorNARTImproved mood in the bottom third of the POMS depressed/elated distribution at baseline in probiotics group after 20 daysImproved memory in probiotics group after 20 daysNATillisch et al,63 201336 healthy femalesFMPP (B. lactis I-2494 [DN-173 010], containing yogurt starters include S. thermophilus I–1630, L. bulgaricus I–1632 and I–1519) and Lactococcus lactis subsp lactis I–1631B. lactis : 1.25 × 1010S. thermophilus and L. bulgaricus : 1.2 × 1094 weeksStandard emotional faces-attention task for fMRIDecreased activity to emotional faces in a large distributed networkChanges in midbrain connectivity during resting stateNASTAI, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory; NA, not applicable; GHQ, General Health Questionnaire; DASS, Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale; HPA, hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal; BMI, body mass index; LEIDS-r, Leiden Index of Depression Sensitivity-Revised; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; BAI, Beck Anxiety Inventory; PANSS, Positive and Negative Symptom Scale; IBS, irritable bowel syndrome; HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale; ASD, autism spectrum disorder; IBS-D, diarrhea-predominant IBS; DBC, Development Behavior Checklist; HSCL-90, Hopkins Symptom Checklist; PSS, Perceived Stress Scale; CCL, Coping Checklist; UFC, urinary free cortisol; CFS, chronic fatigue syndrome; POMS, questionnaire-based Profile of Mood State; NART, National Adult Reading Rest; FMPP, fermented milk product with probiotic; fMRI, functional magnetic resonance imaging; B. animalis, Bifidobacterium animalis; B. breve, Bifidobacterium breve; B. bifidum, Bifidobacterium bifidum; B. infantis, Bifidobacterium infantis; B. lactis, Bifidobacterium lactis; B. longum, Bifidobacterium longum; L. acidophilus, Lactobacillus acidophilus; L. brevis, Lactobacillus brevis; L. bulgaricus, Lactobacillus bulgaricus; L. casei, Lactobacillus casei; L. helveticus, Lactobacillus helveticus; L. paracasei, Lactobacillus paracasei; L. plantarum, Lactobacillus plantarum; L. rhamnosus, Lactobacillus rhamnosus; L. salivarius, Lactobacillus salivarius; S. thermophiles, Streptococcus thermophiles.
