<?xml version="1.0"?>
TrialsTrialsTrials1745-6215BioMed CentralLondon461953299910.1186/s13063-015-0999-0Study ProtocolWould transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) enhance the effects of working memory training in older adults with mild neurocognitive disorder due to Alzheimer’s disease: study protocol for a randomized controlled trialChengCalvin P. W.cpw182@ha.org.hkChanSandra S. M.schan@cuhk.edu.hkMakArthur D. P.arthurdpmak@cuhk.edu.hkChanWai Chiwaicchan@hku.hkChengSheung Taktakcheng@ied.edu.hkShiLinshilin@cuhk.edu.hkWangDefengdfwang@cuhk.edu.hkLamLinda Chiu-Wacwlam@cuhk.edu.hkDepartment of Psychiatry, Tai Po Hospital, 9 Chuen On Road, Tai Po, Hong Kong Department of Psychiatry, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Rm G25, G/F, Multi-center, Tai Po Hospital, 9 Chuen On Road, Tai Po, Hong Kong Department of Psychiatry, The University of Hong Kong, 3/F, HKJC for Interdisciplinary Research, 5 Sassoon Road, Pokfulam, Hong Kong Department of Health and Physical Education, Hong Kong Institute of Education, Rm D4-2/F-03, Block D4, 10 Lo Ping Road, Tai Po, NT Hong Kong Department of Medicine and Therapeutics, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, 9/F, Lui Che Woo Sciences Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, Hong Kong Department of Imaging and Interventional Radiology, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, Hong Kong 241020152410201520151647923620156102015© Cheng et al. 2015
Open AccessThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundThere has been longstanding interesting in cognitive training for older adults with cognitive impairment. In this study, we will investigate the effects of working memory training, and explore augmentation strategies that could possibly consolidate the effects in older adults with mild neurocognitive disorder. Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) has been demonstrated to affect the neuronal excitability and reported to enhance memory performance. As tDCS may also modulate cognitive function through changes in neuroplastic response, it would be adopted as an augmentation strategy for working memory training in the present study.Methods/DesignThis is a 4-week intervention double-blind randomized controlled trial (RCT) of tDCS. Chinese older adults (aged 60 to 90 years) with mild neurocognitive disorder due to Alzheimer’s disease (DSM-5 criteria) would be randomized into a 4-week intervention of either tDCS-working memory (DCS-WM), tDCS-control cognitive training (DCS-CC), and sham tDCS-working memory (WM-CD) groups. The primary outcome would be working memory test – the n-back task performance and the Chinese version of the Alzheimer’s Disease Assessment Scale – Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog). Secondary outcomes would be test performance of specific cognitive domains and mood. Intention-to-treat analysis would be carried out. Changes of efficacy indicators with time and intervention would be tested with mixed effect models.DiscussionThis study adopts the theory of neuroplasticity to evaluate the potential cognitive benefits of non-invasive electrical brain stimulation, working memory training and dual stimulation in older adults at risk of cognitive decline. It would also examine the tolerability, program adherence and adverse effects of this novel intervention. Information would be helpful for further research of dementia prevention studies.Trial registrationChiCTR-TRC-14005036 Date of registration: 31 July 2014.KeywordsAlzheimer’s diseaseBrain stimulationCognitive functionNeurocognitive disorderRandomized clinical trialTranscranial direct current stimulationWorking memoryissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2015<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods/Design</title><p>A 4-week intervention (12-week observation) double-blind randomized controlled trial (RCT) of tDCS. Participants will be randomized into three groups:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The working memory (Adaptive n-back) training-sham tDCS group (WM-CD).</p><p>Participants would receive 20 minutes of sham tDCS, followed by 5 minutes of rest and 20 minutes of Adaptive n-back training.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The tDCS-control cognitive training group (DCS-CC).</p><p>Participants would receive 20 minutes of tDCS, followed by 5 minutes of rest and 20 minutes of controlled cognitive training with continuous performance tasks.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The tDCS-working memory training (DCS-WM) group.</p><p>Participants would receive 20 minutes of tDCS, followed by 5 minutes of rest and 20 minutes of Adaptive n-back training.</p></list-item></list></p><p>The intervention would be of 4 weeks duration, with 3 training sessions (45 minutes) per week. All groups would receive the same training schedule.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Participants and recruitment</title><p>Participants would be recruited through existing research cohorts and local advertisements at older persons’ social centers in Hong Kong. Informed consent would be obtained from each eligible participant. Interested participants would first undergo a cognitive and clinical assessment for mild neurocognitive disorder due to AD (MND-AD) before recruitment for intervention. The cognitive assessment was derived from previous studies of the research team [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Potential participants would be assessed by psychiatrists of the research team for eligibility.</p><p>Inclusion criteria are as follows:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Subjects from 60 to 90 years old;</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th edition</italic> (DSM-5) diagnosis of MND-AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>];</p></list-item></list></p><p>Exclusion criteria are set as:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Previous diagnosis of other major neurocognitive disorders;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Past history of bipolar affective disorder or psychosis;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Physical frailty affecting attendance at training sessions;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Already attending regular cognitive training;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Taking a psychotropic or other medication known to affect cognition (e.g. benzodiazepines, anti-dementia medication, etc.);</p></list-item><list-item><p>History of major neurological deficit including history of stroke, transient ischemic attack or traumatic brain injury;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Significant communicative impairments</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Aims and hypotheses to be tested</title><p>The present proposal aims to address the above question with a paradigm having high potential for clinical practice. The proposed neuroenhancement intervention combined the dual approach of mental and electrical stimulation. We hypothesized that<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Adaptive n-back task training (with sham tDCS) would be associated with improved test performance in both working memory and other cognitive domains.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Stimulation to the right temporal cortex by tDCS (controlled cognitive training) would be associated with enhancement of test performance in memory and other cognitive domains. (Please refer to Intervention paradigms for details).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The effects of improvement in global cognitive domains would be comparable in single- modality brain stimulation and Adaptive n-back training or tDCS.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Combined tDCS and Adaptive n-back task training would be associated with more significant improvement in cognitive performance over single-modality brain stimulation by either Adaptive n-back task or tDCS.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Randomization procedure</title><p>This will be a double-blind RCT of tDCS. Participants will be individually randomized into WM-CD, DCS-CC, or DCS-WM groups. Randomization with blocks of six would be adopted to ensure a balanced allocation of groups. The participants would be blind to the tDCS status. The assessors for clinical outcomes would be blinded to the randomization status. The staff who perform the intervention would not know the assessment results.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Definition of outcome measures (Appendix 1)</title><p>Primary outcomes<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Working memory test – the n-back task performance at baseline, fourth, eighth and twelfth weeks would be recorded as a direct measure of improvement in task performance.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Global Cognitive function would be measured by the Chinese version of the Alzheimer’s Disease Assessment Scale – Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog). This is a standard global cognitive assessment for clinical intervention of AD. The scale score ranges from 0 to 70, with increasing scores indicating higher severity of global cognitive impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p></list-item></list></p><p>Secondary outcomes<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Memory and language tests – logical memory, 10 minutes list learning delay recall, category verbal fluency and trail-making tests would also be evaluated to examine the effects of both tDCS and working memory training on other cognitive abilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>The Chinese Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] would be used to assess changes in neuropsychiatric symptoms across different twelve domains. In the current study, NPI would evaluate potential mood and behavioral change, especially mood and euphoria that may theoretically be affected by tDCS administration.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A checklist of potential adverse effects associated with computer-based cognitive training and t-DCS administration would be generated from available literature reports. The checklist would be used to monitor tolerability and adverse events throughout intervention.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Intervention paradigms</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Working memory (Adaptive n-back) and Control cognitive training (Appendix 2)</p></list-item></list></p><p>n-back task is a continuous performance test proposed by Kirschner for measurement of working memory capacity. During the n-back task, subjects are usually presented with a sequence of stimuli, and required to indicate which stimulus matches the one from n steps earlier in the sequence. Adaptive n-back task refers to automatic adjustment of the level of difficulty of the task according to the accuracy of the performance. Participants with high degree of accuracy would be advanced to another level of difficulty, whereas a suboptimal performance would be adjusted to an easier practice level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The Adaptive n-back visual training paradigm (WM) is programed using the E-Prime. The adaptive training offers a feedback mechanism and has a higher demand for attention throughout the training session. As the participants are older adults with little previous computer experience and may be more limited in working memory capacity, visual stimuli would be offered for training at the initial five levels. The dual task with auditory-visual stimuli would be offered after the participant has passed the 6-back training. It is considered that this approach would ensure higher motivation for long-term practice.</p><p>The Control cognitive training (CC) would be a continuous performance test paradigm. This is considered as an active control as the paradigm demands sustained attention similar to the n-back task. However, it does not offer training of the working memory component embedded in the n-back task.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>2.</label><p>Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS)</p></list-item></list></p><p>In each session, tDCS (DCS) would be administered with a current strength of 2 mA for 20 minutes (NeuroConn, DC-stimulator Plus, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.neuroconn.de/kontakt_en/">http://www.neuroconn.de/kontakt_en/</ext-link>). The decisions regarding the location of stimulus and electrodes are made with reference to a recent fMRI DMN study of Chinese older adults with mild cognitive impairment (MCI) conducted by the project team. In our study, subjects with MCI were found to have reduced activity of the left temporal lobe, but with increased activity of the right frontal lobe (Shi et al., submitted). Anodal stimulation would be applied to the left temporal cortex, positioned over T3 and T4 according to the 10–20 electroencephalogram (EEG) international system. The reference electrode would be place over the right deltoid muscle. The selection of non-cephalic reference electrode is to avoid interference of compensatory brain networks of the subjects with MCI. The electrodes used for tDCS were 35 cm<sup>2</sup> in area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The sham tDCS (CD) schedule would include 30 seconds of 2-mA electrical stimulation to the temporal cortex; the electric current would then stop while the device would be retained until the end of the 20-minute period. Afterwards, the subject would rest for 5 minutes before commencement of 20 minutes of Adaptive n-back task.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Multilevel generalized linear modeling would be employed to account for the correlations from within subjects and different time points of measurement. Baseline cognitive characteristics between tDCS-working memory training (DCS-WM), tDCS-control cognitive training group (DCS-CC) and working memory training–-ham tDCS (WM-CD) groups would be evaluated. Changes of cognitive function and behavioral symptoms from baseline to each follow-up point and intervention differences would be tested with occasions (time points) at level 1 and subjects at level 2. Global cognitive function between DCS-WM, DCS-CC would be made with WM-CD (reference group). Covariates including baseline differences would be entered in the regression model. Secondary analyses of specific cognitive function would be performed to compute for group differences in outcome. Incidence of adverse events and characteristics of program adherence would be recorded. Statistical significance will be set at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. Bonferroni corrections would be adopted for adjustment of multiple comparisons. Computations would be performed using SPSS (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) for windows version 20.0 and Stata (StataCorp, College Station, TX, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Sample size estimation</title><p>The sample size is estimated with using GPower 3.1. Measurements would be evaluated comparing the cognitive test performance across time and intervention groups. The potential effect size of cognitive enhancement of the cognitive training and tDCS is estimated from the findings of a cognitive activity intervention conducted with older adults with MCI in Hong Kong (2012). After 12 weeks, the 3 sessions of weekly cognitive activity intervention was associated with improvement in ADAS-Cog (11.3 ± 3.2 versus 8.8 ± 3.5), and delay recall tests (3.5 ± 2.3 versus 5.8 ± 2.1) (Cheng et al., unpublished data). Sixteen subjects in each group will be required to achieve a power of 0.8 in detecting improvements with intervention. Assuming a medium effect size of 0.5 of cognitive enhancement at the 12th week in dual stimulation over single-modality intervention, 51 subjects are required in each group. Taking into account the dropout rate of 25 %, 64 participants per arm should be recruited.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Ethical consideration</title><p>A psychogeriatrician who is familiar with mental capacity assessment would assess mental capacity for participation in this research. Participants would be recruited if they are considered mentally fit to sign consent. First degree relatives of participants will also be informed before intervention. Ethics approval from The Joint Chinese University of Hong Kong – New Territories East Cluster Clinical Research Ethics Committee has been obtained, and the protocol registered with the Center for Clinical Research and Biostatistics, Clinical Trials Registry of the Chinese University of Hong Kong and linked to the Chinese Clinical Trials Registry (ChiCTR), World Health Organization – International Clinical Trials Registry Platform (WHO-ICTRP) China Primary Registry (ChiCTR-TRC-14005036). The study will comply with the Declaration of Helsinki and the Good Clinical Practice guidelines of the International Conference on Harmonization of technical requirements for registration of pharmaceuticals for human use (ICH-GCP). The results will be reported according to Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) Guidelines for non-pharmacological interventions.</p></sec></sec>Trial statusRecruitment started in March 2015. Recruitment is ongoing.AppendixAppendix 1Table 1Assessment scheduleBaseline assessmentFirst follow-up (4th week)Second follow-up (8th week)Third follow-up (12th week)ADAS-CogVVVVCantonese MMSEVVVVn-back test performanceVVVVDelay recallVVVVLogical memoryVVVVDigit and Visual Span testsVVVVCategory Verbal Fluency TestVVVVTrail-making testVVVVNeuropsychiatric InventoryVVVVAdverse event checklistVVVV
ADAS-Cog Alzheimer’s Disease Assessment Scale – Cognitive Subscale, MMSE Mini-mental State ExaminationAppendix 2Fig. 1Cognitive training paradigms (3 second trials – 20 trials per block for 20 blocks)AbbreviationsADAlzheimer’s diseaseADAS-CogAlzheimer’s Disease Assessment Scale – Cognitive SubscaleCCControl cognitive trainingChiCTRChinese Clinical Trials RegistryCONSORTConsolidated Standards of Reporting TrialsDCS-CCtDCS-control cognitive trainingDCS-WMtDCS-working memory trainingDLPFCdorsal lateral prefrontal cortexDMNdefault mode networkDSM-5Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th editionEEGelectroencephalogramfMRIfunctional magnetic resonance imagingICH-GCPGood Clinical Practice guidelines of the International Conference on HarmonizationMCImild cognitive impairmentMoCAMontreal Cognitive AssessmentNPINeuropsychiatric InventoryRCTrandomized controlled trialtDCStranscranial direct current stimulationWHOWorld Health OrganizationWMworking memoryWM-CDSham tDCS-working memoryCompeting interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionCWL is the overall study principal investigator and responsible for overall project design, data analysis, monitoring of recruitment and intervention. LS and DW are responsible for development of the computer-based cognitive training program, supervision of logistics of this part of intervention, extraction of data and assisted in analysis. PWC contributed in the recruitment and writing of the study protocol. SMC, DPM, WCC and STC participated in monitoring of recruitment and intervention. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.This study received a grant from the General Research Fund for 2014/15 in Hong Kong (Ref: 14108214).References1.PrinceMJacksonJWorld Alzheimer Report 20092009LondonAlzheimer’s Disease International2.World Health Organization and Alzheimer’s Disease InternationalDementia: a public health priority, World Health Organization20123.HerreraCChambonCMichelBFPabanVAlescio-LautierBPositive effects of computer-based cognitive training in adults with mild cognitive impairmentNeuropsychologia20125018718110.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2012.04.012225257054.LeeGYYipCCYuECManDWEvaluation of a computer-assisted errorless learning-based memory training program for patients with early Alzheimer’s disease in Hong Kong: a pilot studyClin Interv Aging2013862333237666385.WolinskyFDVander WegMWHowrenMBJonesMPDotsonMMA randomized controlled trial of cognitive training using a visual speed of processing intervention in middle aged and older adultsPLoS ONE20138e6162410.1371/journal.pone.0061624236505016.Bahar-FuchsAClareLWoodsBCognitive training and cognitive rehabilitation for mild to moderate Alzheimer’s disease and vascular dementiaCochrane Database Syst Rev20136CD003260237405357.ZinkeKZeintlMEschenAHerzogCKliegelMPotentials and limits of plasticity induced by working memory training in old-old ageGerontology201258798710.1159/000324240214303588.RudebeckSRBorDOrmondAO’ReillyJXLeeACA potential spatial working memory training task to improve both episodic memory and fluid intelligencePLoS ONE20127e5043110.1371/journal.pone.0050431232097409.LilienthalLTamezESheltonJTMyersonJHaleSDual n-back training increases the capacity of the focus of attentionPsychon Bull Rev2013201354110.3758/s13423-012-0335-62318450610.HeinzelSSchulteSOnkenJDuongQLRiemerTGHeinzAWorking memory training improvements and gains in non-trained cognitive tasks in young and older adultsNeuropsychol Dev Cogn B Aging Neuropsychol Cogn2014211467310.1080/13825585.2013.7903382363907011.ThompsonTWWaskomMLGarelKLCardenas-IniguezCReynoldsGOWinterRFailure of working memory training to enhance cognition or intelligencePLoS ONE20138e6361410.1371/journal.pone.00636142371745312.HicksKLFriedDEHambrickDZKaneMJEngleRWNo evidence of intelligence improvement after working memory training: a randomized, placebo-controlled studyJ Exp Psychol Gen20131423597910.1037/a00290822270871713.RabeyJMDobronevskyEAichenbaumSGonenOMartonRGKhaigrekhtMRepetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation combined with cognitive training is a safe and effective modality for the treatment of Alzheimer’s disease: a randomized, double-blind studyJ Neural Transm2013120813910.1007/s00702-012-0902-z2307672314.BoggioPSFerrucciRMameliFMartinsDMartinsOVergariMProlonged visual memory enhancement after direct current stimulation in Alzheimer’s diseaseBrain Stimul201252233010.1016/j.brs.2011.06.0062184028815.JavadiAHChengPTranscranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) enhances reconsolidation of long-term memoryBrain Stimul201366687410.1016/j.brs.2012.10.0072313770216.StaggCJLinRLMezueMSegerdahlAKongYXieJWidespread modulation of cerebral perfusion induced during and after transcranial direct current stimulation applied to the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortexJ Neurosci201333114253110.1523/JNEUROSCI.3887-12.20132384351417.MeinzerMLindenbergRAntonenkoDFlaischTFlöelAAnodal transcranial direct current stimulation temporarily reverses age-associated cognitive decline and functional brain activity changesJ Neurosci20133312470810.1523/JNEUROSCI.5743-12.20132388495118.NitscheMAMuller-DahlhausFPaulusWZiemannUThe pharmacology of neuroplasticity induced by non-invasive brain stimulation: building models for the clinical use of CNS active drugsJ Physiol201259046416210.1113/jphysiol.2012.2329752286901419.PilatoFProficePRanieriFCaponeFDi IorioRFlorioLSynaptic plasticity in neurodegenerative diseases evaluated and modulated by in vivo neurophysiological techniquesMol Neurobiol2012465637110.1007/s12035-012-8302-92282118720.LamLCLeeJSChungJCLauAWooJKwokTCA randomized controlled trial to examine the effectiveness of case management model for community dwelling older persons with mild dementia in Hong KongInt J Geriatr Psychiatry20102539540210.1002/gps.23521960645521.CampbellMFitzpatrickRHainesAKinmonthALSandercockPSpiegelhalterDFramework for design and evaluation of complex interventions to improve healthBMJ2000321694610.1136/bmj.321.7262.6941098778022.AmLCTamCWLuiVWChanWCChanSSChiuHFScreening of mild cognitive impairment in Chinese older adults – a multistage validation of the Chinese abbreviated mild cognitive impairment testNeuroepidemiology20083061210.1159/0001133001820429123.KirchnerWKAge differences in short-term retention of rapidly changing informationJ Exp Psychol195855352810.1037/h00436881353931724.ChengSTChowPKSongYQYuECChanACLeeTMMental and physical activities delay cognitive decline in older persons with dementiaAm J Geriatr Psychiatry201422637410.1016/j.jagp.2013.01.0602358275025.American Psychological AssociationDiagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5)201326.KuoMFPaulusWNitscheMATherapeutic effects of non-invasive brain stimulation with direct currents (tDCS) in neuropsychiatric diseasesNeuroImage201485Pt 39486010.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.05.1172374796227.VicklandVMcDonnellGWernerJDraperBLowLFBrodatyHA computer model of dementia prevalence in Australia: foreseeing outcomes of delaying dementia onset, slowing disease progression, and eradicating dementia typesDement Geriatr Cogn Disord2010291233010.1159/00027243620145398
