<?xml version="1.0"?>
TrialsTrialsTrials1745-6215BioMed CentralLondon5445390196410.1186/s13063-017-1964-xStudy ProtocolOpen-label versus double-blind placebo treatment in irritable bowel syndrome: study protocol for a randomized controlled trialhttp://orcid.org/0000-0002-6746-1958BallouSarahsballou@bidmc.harvard.edu1KaptchukTed J.23HirschWilliamwhirsch@bidmc.harvard.edu1NeeJudyjnee@bidmc.harvard.edu1IturrinoJohannajiturrin@bidmc.harvard.edu1HallKathryn T.khall0@bwh.harvard.edu24KelleyJohn M.jkelley@endicott.edu25ChengVivianvcheng@bidmc.harvard.edu1KirschIrvingirvkirsch@gmail.com2JacobsonEriceric_jacobson@hms.harvard.edu3ConboyLisalisa_conboy@hms.harvard.edu26LemboAnthonyalembo@bidmc.harvard.edu12DavisRoger B.rdavis@bidmc.harvard.edu2610000 0000 9011 8547grid.239395.7Department of Medicine, Division of Gastroenterology, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, 330 Brookline Avenue, Boston, MA 02215 USA 20000 0000 9011 8547grid.239395.7Program in Placebo Studies, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center/Harvard Medical School, 330 Brookline Avenue, Boston, MA 02215 USA 3000000041936754Xgrid.38142.3cDepartment of Global Health and Social Medicine Harvard Medical School, 641 Huntington Avenue, Boston, MA 02115 USA 40000 0004 0378 8294grid.62560.37Division of Preventive Medicine, Brigham and Women’s Hospital/Harvard Medical School, 900 Commonwealth Avenue, Boston, MA 02215 USA 50000 0000 9546 2582grid.454545.1Department of Psychology, Endicott College, 376 Hale Street, Beverly, MA 01915 USA 60000 0000 9011 8547grid.239395.7Department of Medicine, Division of General Medicine and Primary Care, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, 330 Brookline Avenue, Boston, MA 02215 USA 2552017255201720171823412120172942017© The Author(s). 2017
Open AccessThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundPlacebo medications, by definition, are composed of inactive ingredients that have no physiological effect on symptoms. Nonetheless, administration of placebo in randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and in clinical settings has been demonstrated to have significant impact on many physical and psychological complaints. Until recently, conventional wisdom has suggested that patients must believe that placebo pills actually contain (or, at least, might possibly contain) active medication in order to elicit a response to placebo. However, several recent RCTs, including patients with irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), chronic low back pain, and episodic migraine, have demonstrated that individuals receiving open-label placebo (OLP) can still experience symptomatic improvement and benefit from honestly described placebo treatment.Methods and designThis paper describes an innovative multidisciplinary trial design (n = 280) that attempts to replicate and expand upon an earlier IBS OLP study. The current study will compare OLP to double-blind placebo (DBP) administration which is made possible by including a nested, double-blind RCT comparing DBP and peppermint oil. The study also examines possible genetic and psychological predictors of OLP and seeks to better understand participants’ experiences with OLP and DBP through a series of extensive interviews with a randomly selected subgroup.DiscussionOLP treatment is a novel strategy for ethically harnessing placebo effects. It has potential to re-frame theories of placebo and to influence how physicians can optimize watch-and-wait strategies for common, subjective symptoms. The current study aims to dramatically expand what we know about OLP by comparing, for the first time, OLP and DBP administration. Adopting a unique, multidisciplinary approach, the study also explores genetic, psychological and experiential dimensions of OLP. The paper ends with an extensive discussion of the “culture” of the trial as well as potential mechanisms of OLP and ethical implications.Trial registrationClinicalTrials.gov, identifier: NCT02802241. Registered on 14 June 2016.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13063-017-1964-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.KeywordsPlacebo effectsOpen-label placeboIrritable bowel syndromeResearch methodsMulti-disciplinary modelsPeppermint oilhttp://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000062National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney DiseasesT32DK007760BallouSarahhttp://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100008460National Center for Complementary and Integrative HealthR01AT008573R01AT008573KaptchukTed J.LemboAnthonyissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2017<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec13" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods/design</title><p>Below we describe the specific methods used to test whether there are differences in outcomes between OLP treatment, DBP treatment, and NTC. Recruitment began in July, 2016 and is expected to be complete in 2019 yielding a sample of 280 participants randomized to four arms. See Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> for a detailed timeline of the study which accords with the Standard Protocol Items: Recommendations for Interventional Trials (SPIRIT) figure (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Schedule of enrollment, interventions, and assessments</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13063_2017_1964_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><sec id="Sec14"><title>Subject selection</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Inclusion/exclusion criteria</title><p>Detailed inclusion and exclusion criteria are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. We diagnose IBS based on physician interview using the Rome IV criteria published in 2016 which has demonstrated good specificity and sensitivity for IBS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The Rome IV criteria require recurrent abdominal pain, starting at least 6 months previously, and occurring at least 1 day/week in the last 3 months, associated with at least two of the following three features: [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] related to defecation; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] associated with change in frequency of stool; and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] associated with a change in form (consistency) of stool. Participants who meet criteria for IBS and who report at least moderate symptom severity at baseline visit (determined by a score of <underline>&gt;</underline>175 on the Irritable Bowel Severity Scoring System) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] are eligible for the study.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria used to determine eligibility for participation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>Inclusion</td></tr><tr><td>1. Provide signed and dated informed consent and understand the nature of the study sufficiently to allow completion of all study assessments</td></tr><tr><td>2. Be ambulatory, community dwelling, 18 to 80 years, inclusive</td></tr><tr><td>3. Meet Rome IV diagnostic criteria for IBS</td></tr><tr><td>4. Have IBS of at least moderate severity, i.e., have a score on the IBS-SSS of <underline>&gt;</underline>175 (0–500) at the baseline visit*</td></tr><tr><td>5. If the patient is on medications which affect the gastrointestinal tract or visceral sensation (e.g., tricyclic antidepressants, fiber, antispasmodics, etc.), they must be on a stable dose for at least 1 month prior to entering the study and for the duration of the study*</td></tr><tr><td>*Participants will be allowed to rescreen once if they do not meet inclusion criteria #4 or #5 at the initial screening visit</td></tr><tr><td>Exclusion</td></tr><tr><td>1. Self-reported pregnancy or planned pregnancy within the next 2 months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Have an established diagnosis of any concomitant bowel disturbance that would interfere with the assessment of efficacy or safety in the study (e.g., Hirschsprung’s disease, diverticulitis, colonic ischemia)</td></tr><tr><td>3. Report warning symptoms (e.g., rectal bleeding, weight loss &gt;10%, iron deficiency anemia, etc.) otherwise not explained</td></tr><tr><td>4. Have undergone previous abdominal surgery to the intestines (with the exception of uncomplicated appendectomy, cholecystectomy, hysterectomy, or polypectomy <underline>&gt;</underline>6 months prior to enrollment)</td></tr><tr><td>5. Have a history of drug, excluding nicotine or caffeine, or alcohol abuse within 2 years of entry into the study</td></tr><tr><td>6. Exhibit abnormalities on physical examination, unless judged to be clinically insignificant by the investigator. Such cases will be noted</td></tr><tr><td>7. Current, within the past 30 days, therapeutic use of enteric-coated peppermint oil for the treatment of IBS</td></tr><tr><td>8. Known or suspected peppermint or soybean oil allergy</td></tr><tr><td>9. Severe acid reflux (&gt;3 episodes of heartburn or regurgitation per day on average over a week)</td></tr><tr><td>10. Inability to speak or read English</td></tr><tr><td>11. Unable or unwilling to cooperate with the study protocol or considered by the investigator to be unsuitable for the study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>IBS</italic> irritable bowel syndrome, <italic>IBS-SSS</italic> Irritable Bowel Syndrome Severity Scoring System</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Participants are allowed to continue any IBS medications as long as they have been on stable doses for at least 30 days prior to entering the study and agree not to change medications or dosages during the trial. Any nonpharmacological treatments for IBS (e.g., meditation, dietary regime, etc.) are also allowed as long as they are on a stable pattern/behavior for at least 30 days prior to entering the study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Study interventions</title><p>The study involves four groups as follows: (1) no-treatment control (NTC) (<italic>n</italic> ≈ 80); (2) open-label placebo (OLP) (<italic>n</italic> ≈ 80); (3) double-blind placebo (DBP) (<italic>n</italic> ≈ 80); and (4) double-blind peppermint oil (<italic>n</italic> ≈ 40). See Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Because the nested peppermint oil comparison is a secondary aim, arising from necessary inclusion of peppermint oil in order to test DBP, we chose to randomize fewer participants into this arm in order to increase power for the primary comparison of OLP, DBP, and NTC.</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>The pills: placebo and peppermint oil softgels</title><p>Three of the four study groups are administered either a placebo (<italic>n</italic> = 160) or peppermint-oil softgel (<italic>n</italic> = 40). The OLP and DBP pills are identical to each other and both are matched to the peppermint oil. In the peppermint oil group, 0.2 mL-dose peppermint oil softgels are used (Pepogest™; Boca Raton, FL, USA). In the placebo groups, treatment is supplied as 0.2 mL soybean oil in order to match the peppermint oil softgels in appearance (manufactured by SoftGel Technologies Inc; Los Angeles, CA, USA). Participants in the peppermint oil and placebo groups receive identical instructions to take one softgel three times per day, approximately 30 min before meal times. The bottle of pills is labeled as “Open Label Placebo Capsule” in the OLP arm and as “Placebo or Peppermint Oil Capsule” in the double-blind arm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>The setting: interactions with clinicians and study staff</title><p>We notify potential participants about the study via (1) mailed postcards, (2) flyers posted in greater Boston, and (3) physician referrals. Participants are first introduced to the study (in person or by phone) by trained study staff. This initial interaction provides a transparent description of the aims of the study and outlines the four groups into which participants might be enrolled. During this first encounter, OLP is introduced as a “novel, mind-body intervention” and the rationale for the study is briefly discussed.</p><p>During study visits, clinicians are instructed to be warm, empathic, natural, and truthful about the design and methods of the study with all patients. Although patients are informed of the design of the study during the first contact with the recruiters, physicians give all patients a detailed overview of the study during visit 1. After introducing the study and answering any questions, the physician opens a randomization envelope and informs patients of their assignment to either the OLP group, the double-blind group, or the NTC group. In the OLP group, the physician is aware of assignment, as they would be in clinical practice. Just as in a standard double-blind RCT, neither the participants or the study staff are aware of which blinded group (peppermint oil or placebo) is assigned in the double-blind condition. After randomization, participants are given a semiscripted description of their group assignment (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This semiscripted interaction lasts approximately 20–25 min (including informed consent) for all patients in all study groups. The script for the OLP group is similar to our previous OLP study and the script for the double-blind and NTC are similar to what would happen in a typical RCT. The physician makes every effort to assure equal time, attention, encouragement, and patient-physician relationship for every arm of the study. The study time with research staff/physicians totals approximately 1 h. Including the time needed to complete study questionnaires the entire first visit takes approximately 1.5 h.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Core components of scripted interactions between study clinicians and study participants in each arm</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>Open-label placebo</td></tr><tr><td>Interaction is geared toward making participants comfortable taking open-label placebo and reducing negative feelings about placebo. Specifically, patients will be told the following four points:</td></tr><tr><td>1. In clinical trials, IBS patients treated with placebos often improve nearly as much as patients on active medication</td></tr><tr><td>2. In order to reduce concern that that any placebo effect a participant might experience is “all in the head,” classical conditioning (“like Pavlov’s dogs”) will be suggested as a possible mechanism to explain how such self-healing can happen automatically</td></tr><tr><td>3. To suspend disbelief and encourage an open mind about the effectiveness of the treatment, patients will be told that positive expectations may be helpful, but it is normal to have doubts about open-label placebo. We can understand why patients might think the study is unusual</td></tr><tr><td>4. To encourage adherence, patients will be told that it is most important to take the pills faithfully. Research shows that patients who are more adherent – even to placebo – improve more than those who are less adherent</td></tr><tr><td>5. Participants are provided with reassurance that they may not notice changes right away. They are informed that some people respond to placebo “gradually” and others respond “quickly” and that this varies across individuals</td></tr><tr><td>Double-blind placebo and double-blind peppermint oil</td></tr><tr><td>1. Provide rationale for doing a double-blind experiment and the principle of equipoise</td></tr><tr><td>2. Provide a rationale for why peppermint oil might be effective: “Peppermint oil has been used for many years to ‘soothe’ the GI tract and is known to reduce contractions or spasms in the GI tract”</td></tr><tr><td>3. Explain that peppermint oil in IBS has never been tested in the USA</td></tr><tr><td>4. Provide a rationale for why placebo might be effective: “In early clinical trials IBS patients treated with placebos often improve nearly as much as patients on active medication”</td></tr><tr><td>5. Participants are provided with reassurance that they may not notice changes right away. They are informed that some people respond to placebo “gradually” and others respond “quickly” and that this varies across individuals</td></tr><tr><td>No-treatment control</td></tr><tr><td>1<italic>.</italic> Explain the importance of this research to develop effective treatments for IBS</td></tr><tr><td>2. Explain that it is critical to measure the normal waxing and waning of IBS symptoms in the no-treatment control group in order to understand the placebo and peppermint effects detected in the other arms of the study</td></tr><tr><td>3. Highlight the importance of not changing anything that they are regularly doing for the IBS during the trial</td></tr><tr><td>4. Explain that the study physician will provide some specific suggestions and options at the end of the trial</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>GI</italic> gastrointestinal, <italic>IBS</italic> irritable bowel syndrome</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>At each follow-up visit, patients in OLP and DBP arms are asked to bring in any remaining pills that they may have so that a blinded assessor can count the pills in order to track compliance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Culture of the trial</title><p>The general context and ambiance of a pharmaceutical RCT is not usually described in protocols. Most researchers assume that these details are less important than the nuts and bolts of the implementation. Given that placebo effects are ultimately the result of the entire context of a clinical interaction we want to share some of the following description of the culture of the current trial.</p><p>First, we believe that absolute honesty is critical. Placebos still conjure the idea of deception. In all interactions and discussions with participants, our team tries to be comfortably transparent. Participants may be suspicious of placebo research and we want to avoid this whenever possible. Second, we do not pressure participants to believe or expect that open-label treatment will work. Obviously, we would not be doing a RCT if we thought it was absolutely certain, and more importantly, our team has its own doubts (regardless of our earlier study). Research suggests that patients are rational and are commonly uncertain of their expected outcomes of participation in trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Importantly, our hospital is a tertiary facility and our patients have usually seen multiple physicians for IBS who have given them positive expectations that have been false. They have undergone many episodes of therapeutic failure. Therefore, we do not suppress or deny uncertainty. And no pressure is ever applied to patient’s experience. Our motto about taking placebos could be described as: “let what happens, happen” and we often say this to patients.</p><p>Another specific contextual point unique to this OLP study is that it has both OLP and a potential active drug (peppermint oil). In our experience, patients are not unlike health care providers in that when offered a choice, they want a “real” drug. Like society at large, there is a prevailing belief that compared to a drug, placebos are a sort of consolation prize or, more colloquially, the “booby prize.” In our advertisements, we speak of a novel-mind body intervention that harnesses placebo effects. We want patients to be open to placebo effects and we try to avoid the possibility that initially advertising peppermint oil will make people think that the placebo is the less important intervention. When potential participants call, we explain the entire trial transparently and we clearly explain that we include peppermint in the trial in order to compare OLP and DBP and because preliminary results suggest that it may be beneficial for IBS. During the intake, we make it clear that evidence exists that peppermint oil may be helpful.</p><p>As will be discussed below, the mechanisms of OLP are not yet understood. Given this, our trial emphasizes that behaving naturally, respectfully and considerately is critical. Following what we tell our patients, our team assumes that the active ingredient is “automatic” (or at least very hard to describe scientifically or psychologically at this point) and involves the sum and/or interaction of many factors, including the words, nonverbal communication, symbols, rituals, and behaviors involved from the first advertisement notice to the screening call to the intake procedures and all visits.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Study timeline</title><p>In all of the study groups, participants attend three in-person visits over the course of 6 weeks. In study visit 1, participants provide informed consent, complete questionnaires, meet with a study clinician, and are randomized into study groups. In visit 2 (3 weeks post randomization) and visit 3 (6 weeks post randomization), participants complete questionnaires and meet briefly with a study clinician. Visits 1 and 3 also include a blood draw (20 mL each visit), see section titled “Genetic screening” below for additional details.</p><p>Additionally, 42 patients will be randomly selected to participate in the nested qualitative study and will undergo a detailed interview with a medical anthropologist or sociologist upon completion of their final study visit.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Measures</title><p>Measures were chosen to increase our understanding of the placebo phenomena in this population. All measures are outlined in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. When feasible, we selected continuous rather than dichotomous measures. Our preference for continuous scales is supported by a meta-analysis that compared placebo arms with wait-list controls, and found that studies using continuous variables were more likely to detect significant placebo effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Measures to evaluate symptoms, quality of life, and patient expectancy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Scale</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">Primary outcome measure</td></tr><tr><td>Irritable Bowel Symptom Severity Scale (IBS-SSS)</td><td>This 5-item questionnaire provides a simple way to scale IBS symptoms and the progress of the disease. Items consider pain, distension, bowel dysfunction, and quality of life/global wellbeing. Scores show good reliability and sensitivity to change</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Secondary outcome measures</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Symptom evaluation</td></tr><tr><td>IBS-Adequate Relief</td><td>A single yes/no question makes up this simple global measure of symptom relief in the past week</td></tr><tr><td>IBS-Global Improvement</td><td>A single question provides a measure of improvement in the past week using a 7-point scale</td></tr><tr><td>Daily Symptom Diary</td><td>Questions regarding subject symptoms will be completed daily for the 7-day period prior to visit 2 and visit 3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Quality of life</td></tr><tr><td>Short Form-12 Health Survey (SF-12)</td><td>This 12-item scale measures emotional and physical health and wellbeing</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Psychosocial</td></tr><tr><td>Patient Health Questionnaire-8 (PHQ-8)</td><td>An 8-item scale that is used as a diagnostic and severity measure for depressive disorders in clinical studies</td></tr><tr><td>Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7)</td><td>A 7-item scale that is used as a diagnostic and severity measure for anxiety disorders in clinical practice and research</td></tr><tr><td>Visceral Sensitivity Index</td><td>A 15-item measure of gastrointestinal symptom-specific anxiety</td></tr><tr><td>Pain Catastrophizing Scale</td><td>A scale that measures the tendency to magnify or exaggerate the seriousness of pain sensations</td></tr><tr><td>Five Factor Inventory</td><td>A 60-item instrument that measures the “Big Five” dimensions of personality</td></tr><tr><td>Interpersonal Support Evaluation List</td><td>Designed to measure perceptions of social support among individuals in the general population</td></tr><tr><td>Balanced Inventory of Desirable Reach</td><td>Describes the tendency of respondents to answer questions that will be viewed favorably by others</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Patient experience</td></tr><tr><td>Consultation and Relational Empathy Measure</td><td>Assesses physician empathy and relational skills on 10 ordinal items, which are then summed</td></tr><tr><td>Expectancy Question</td><td>“If I receive placebo/peppermint oil/no additional treatment, I expect my IBS symptoms to be: “(numerical rating scale running from zero “not improved at all” to 100 “completely improved”)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Genetic screening</title><p>Genomic DNA will be extracted from whole blood drawn at visits 1 and 3 using Qiagen Blood kit (Valencia, CA, USA) following the manufacturer's protocol. TaqMan single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) genotyping assays will be purchased from Applied Biosystems, (Foster City, CA, USA). Each visit will test for “placebome markers,” described in detail elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Exploratory analyses will be performed for: the mu-opioid receptor polymorphism (<italic>OPRM1 A118G</italic>), fatty acid amide hydrolase (<italic>FAAH</italic>) polymorphisms <italic>Pro129Thr</italic>, monoamine oxidase gene polymorphisms, and serotonin-related polymorphism <italic>CGTTLPR</italic> and <italic>G-703 T</italic> (polymorphism in the tryptophan hydroxylase-2 (<italic>TPH-2</italic>) gene promoter). COMT and other candidate genotypes will be correlated with response to placebo or active drug treatment. Furthermore, potential correlations of the COMT and other genotypes and patient-disease characteristics, for instance pain experience at baseline, will be examined.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Randomization, stratification, and blinding</title><p>All outcome assessments, at all study points, are performed by blinded research assistants. Patients on OLP are obviously not blinded; patients assigned to DPB or peppermint oil are told that they are in a regular double-blind RCT and are unaware of exact treatment assignment. Patients on the NTC are aware of assignment.</p><p>Randomized treatment assignments were generated by a program written by our biostatistician using SAS statistical software (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC, USA). Treatment assignments are generated using permuted block randomization with randomly varying block sizes. Randomization is done in a 2:2:2:1 ratio (no-treatment control; open-label placebo; double-blind placebo; double-blind peppermint oil) and assignments to one of the four groups are sealed in sequentially numbered opaque envelopes.</p><p>Stratification is based on IBS symptom severity score (&lt;300 and <underline>&gt;</underline>300) and gender, resulting in four strata. Each stratum has a different color randomization envelope and a unique set of randomization ID numbers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Statistical considerations</title><p>Data are recorded and stored via Research Electronic Data Capture (REDCap) as the study is in progress. REDCap is a secure web interface with data checks during data entry and uploading to ensure data quality, and housed on secure severs.</p><sec id="Sec25"><title>Power and sample size</title><p>To calculate power for our primary analyses, we used our previous pilot trial testing OLP in IBS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In that study, the effect size for the difference between OLP and no-treatment on the IBS Symptom Severity Scale was <italic>d</italic> = 0.53. For this study, there will be a total of 280 participants enrolled with 80 participants in the OLP, DBP, and NTC and 40 participants in the double-blind peppermint oil group. Using analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) to control for baseline scores leaves the power for the three-group comparison at 0.94. The comparison of peppermint oil and DBP using an ANCOVA approach provides power of 0.75 to detect an effect size of 0.60, an effect consistent with prior studies of peppermint oil.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Analyses</title><p>For our primary analyses, we will use a modified intention-to-treat analysis including any patient who was randomized and provided a baseline assessment and at least one post-baseline primary outcome assessment.</p><p>To test our primary aim (to determine whether 6 weeks of OLP, DBP, and no-treatment results in different clinical outcomes) we will conduct a one-way analysis of covariance. The covariates in the model will be the baseline IBS-SSS score, and gender. The covariates for the ANCOVA model will include the baseline value of the outcome measure as well as the two randomization stratification factors: symptom severity and gender. Assuming that there is a significant difference between the three groups, Dunnett’s analysis will be used to do pairwise analyses to evaluate specific differences between the groups.</p><p>For our secondary aims, we will use the following analyses: (1) analysis of covariance will be used to determine if double-blind peppermint oil results in greater improvement than DBP in patients with IBS; (2) exploratory analysis and correlation will be used to confirm and expand upon our previous findings regarding a genetic biomarker for the placebo response; (3) multiple regression will be used to test the association between personality traits and placebo outcome after controlling for baseline characteristics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Missing data</title><p>Missing data minimization strategies include patient-retention efforts and a modified intent-to-treat analysis. Each individual patient-reported assessment will be captured electronically at each visit with missing responses prohibited by the electronic system. The modified intention-to-treat analysis will replace missing visit-3 outcome measures with visit-2 results, a last observation carried forward (LOCF) approach. If more than a few participants have missing visit-3 outcomes, we will conduct a sensitivity analysis using multiple imputation procedures to produce a full intention-to-treat analysis.</p></sec></sec></sec>Additional file
Additional file 1:SPIRIT 2013 Checklist. (DOC 121 kb)
AbbreviationsAMAAmerican Medical AssociationcLBPChronic lower back painCOMTCatechol-O-methyltransferaseDBPDouble-blind placebofMRIFunctional magnetic resonance imagingIBSIrritable bowel syndromeIBS-SSSIrritable Bowel Syndrome Severity Scoring SystemNTCNo-treatment controlOLPOpen-label placeboRCTRandomized controlled trial.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13063-017-1964-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.AcknowledgementsNot applicable.FundingThe study is supported by NIH/NCCIH grant # R01AT008573. SB is supported by NIH grant # T32DK007760-17. TJK is supported by NIH/NCCIH grant # 2 K24 AT004095.Availability of data and materialsNot applicable.Authors’ contributionsSB, RD, TK, and AL conceived of writing this paper and participated in creating the first draft. SB, RD, TK, AL, WH, JN, JIM, JK, VC, IK, EJ, LC, and KH contributed to the final draft of the paper. All authors helped to design the study and are currently responsible for implementation of the study. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.Authors’ informationNot applicable.Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Consent for publicationNot applicable.Ethical approval and consent to participateEthical and regulatory approvals were obtained from the Institutional Review Board for the Protection of Human Subjects at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center. All participants give written informed consent. Reference number: 2015P000282Publisher’s NoteSpringer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.References1.KaptchukTJMillerFGPlacebo effects in medicineN Engl J Med201537318910.1056/NEJMp1504023261329382.FinnissDGKaptchukTJMillerFBenedettiFBiological, clinical, and ethical advances of placebo effectsLancet Lond Engl201037597156869510.1016/S0140-6736(09)61706-23.WagerTDAtlasLYThe neuroscience of placebo effects: connecting context, learning and healthNat Rev Neurosci20151674031810.1038/nrn3976260876814.TilburtJCEmanuelEJKaptchukTJCurlinFAMillerFGPrescribing “placebo treatments”: results of national survey of US internists and rheumatologistsBMJ.2008337a193810.1136/bmj.a1938189483465.TempleREllenbergSSPlacebo-controlled trials and active-control trials in the evaluation of new treatments. Part 1: ethical and scientific issuesAnn Intern Med200013364556310.7326/0003-4819-133-6-200009190-00014109759646.BleaseCRBishopFLKaptchukTJInformed consent and clinical trials: where is the placebo effect?BMJ.2017356j46310.1136/bmj.j463281597697.RaicekJEStoneBHKaptchukTJPlacebos in 19th century medicine: a quantitative analysis of the BMJBMJ.2012345e832610.1136/bmj.e8326232496688.KaptchukTJPlacebo studies and ritual theory: a comparative analysis of Navajo, acupuncture and biomedical healingPhilos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci2011366157218495810.1098/rstb.2010.0385215761429.KaptchukTJPowerful placebo: the dark side of the randomised controlled trialLancet Lond Engl199835191171722510.1016/S0140-6736(97)10111-810.KaptchukTJIntentional ignorance: a history of blind assessment and placebo controls in medicineBull Hist Med199872338943310.1353/bhm.1998.0159978044811.BokSThe ethics of giving placebosSci Am19742315172310.1038/scientificamerican1174-17443206012.MeissnerKHöfnerLFässlerMLindeKWidespread use of pure and impure placebo interventions by GPs in GermanyFam Pract2012291798510.1093/fampra/cmr0452180807213.FässlerMMeissnerKSchneiderALindeKFrequency and circumstances of placebo use in clinical practice—a systematic review of empirical studiesBMC Med.201081510.1186/1741-7015-8-152017856114.KermenRHicknerJBrodyHHashamIFamily physicians believe the placebo effect is therapeutic but often use real drugs as placebosFam Med2010429636422092767215.BleaseCCollocaLKaptchukTJAre open-label placebos ethical? Informed consent and ethical equivocationsBioethics20163064071410.1111/bioe.122452684054716.KaptchukTJFriedlanderEKelleyJMSanchezMNKokkotouESingerJPPlacebos without deception: a randomized controlled trial in irritable bowel syndromePloS One2010512e1559110.1371/journal.pone.00155912120351917.Carvalho C, Caetano JM, Cunha L, Rebouta P, Kaptchuk TJ, Kirsch I. Open-label placebo treatment in chronic low back pain: a randomized controlled trial. Pain. 2016;157(12):2766–72.18.Kam-HansenSJakubowskiMKelleyJMKirschIHoaglinDCKaptchukTJAltered placebo and drug labeling changes the outcome of episodic migraine attacksSci Transl Med20146218218ra510.1126/scitranslmed.30061752440194019.SchaeferMHarkeRDenkeCOpen-label placebos improve symptoms in allergic rhinitis: a randomized controlled trialPsychother Psychosom2016856373410.1159/0004472422774443320.KelleyJMKaptchukTJCusinCLipkinSFavaMOpen-label placebo for major depressive disorder: a pilot randomized controlled trialPsychother Psychosom2012815312410.1159/0003370532285475221.SandlerADBodfishJWOpen-label use of placebos in the treatment of ADHD: a pilot studyChild Care Health Dev20083411041010.1111/j.1365-2214.2007.00797.x1817145122.PerlisMGrandnerMZeeJBremerEWhinneryJBarillaHDurability of treatment response to zolpidem with three different maintenance regimens: a preliminary studySleep Med20151691160810.1016/j.sleep.2015.06.0152629879523.AderRMercurioMGWaltonJJamesDDavisMOjhaVConditioned pharmacotherapeutic effects: a preliminary studyPsychosom Med2010722192710.1097/PSY.0b013e3181cbd38b2002883024.SchaferSMCollocaLWagerTDConditioned placebo analgesia persists when subjects know they are receiving a placeboJ Pain Off J Am Pain Soc20151654122010.1016/j.jpain.2014.12.00825.HillsJMAaronsonPIThe mechanism of action of peppermint oil on gastrointestinal smooth muscle. An analysis using patch clamp electrophysiology and isolated tissue pharmacology in rabbit and guinea pigGastroenterology19911011556510.1016/0016-5085(91)90459-X164614226.HawthornMFerranteJLuchowskiERutledgeAWeiXYTriggleDJThe actions of peppermint oil and menthol on calcium channel dependent processes in intestinal, neuronal and cardiac preparationsAliment Pharmacol Ther1988221011810.1111/j.1365-2036.1988.tb00677.x285650227.WechslerMEKelleyJMBoydIOEDutileSMarigowdaGKirschIActive albuterol or placebo, sham acupuncture, or no intervention in asthmaN Engl J Med201136521192610.1056/NEJMoa11033192175190528.SorokinISchatzAWelliverCPlacebo medication and sham surgery responses in benign prostatic hyperplasia treatments: implications for clinical trialsCurr Urol Rep201516107310.1007/s11934-015-0544-42630377529.FreemanEWEnsrudKELarsonJCGuthrieKACarpenterJSJoffeHPlacebo improvement in pharmacologic treatment of menopausal hot flashes: time course, duration, and predictorsPsychosom Med20157721677510.1097/PSY.00000000000001432564775330.QuDZhangZYuXZhaoJQiuFHuangJPsychotropic drugs for the management of cancer-related fatigue: a systematic review and meta-analysisEur J Cancer Care (Engl)2016256970910.1111/ecc.123972649008331.KaptchukTJKelleyJMConboyLADavisRBKerrCEJacobsonEEComponents of placebo effect: randomised controlled trial in patients with irritable bowel syndromeBMJ20083367651999100310.1136/bmj.39524.439618.251839049332.HallKTLemboAJKirschIZiogasDCDouaiherJJensenKBCatechol-O-methyltransferase val158met polymorphism predicts placebo effect in irritable bowel syndromePloS One2012710e4813510.1371/journal.pone.00481352311018933.ScottDJStohlerCSEgnatukCMWangHKoeppeRAZubietaJ-KPlacebo and nocebo effects are defined by opposite opioid and dopaminergic responsesArch Gen Psychiatry20086522203110.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2007.341825026034.De La Fuente-FernándezRStoesslAJThe biochemical bases for reward. Implications for the placebo effectEval Health Prof20022543879810.1177/01632787022380521244908235.KelleyJMLemboAJAblonJSVillanuevaJJConboyLALevyRPatient and practitioner influences on the placebo effect in irritable bowel syndromePsychosom Med20097177899710.1097/PSY.0b013e3181acee121966119536.KaptchukTJShawJKerrCEConboyLAKelleyJMCsordasTJ“Maybe I made up the whole thing”: placebos and patients’ experiences in a randomized controlled trialCult Med Psychiatry.200933338241110.1007/s11013-009-9141-71959797637.KerrCEShawJRConboyLAKelleyJMJacobsonEKaptchukTJPlacebo acupuncture as a form of ritual touch healing: a neurophenomenological modelConscious Cogn20112037849110.1016/j.concog.2010.12.0092139751938.BishopFLJacobsonEEShawJKaptchukTJParticipants’ experiences of being debriefed to placebo allocation in a clinical trialQual Health Res201222811384910.1177/10497323124485442267309439.BishopFLJacobsonEEShawJRKaptchukTJScientific tools, fake treatments, or triggers for psychological healing: how clinical trial participants conceptualise placebosSoc Sci Med20127457677410.1016/j.socscimed.2011.11.0202228528940.FordACMoayyediPLacyBELemboAJSaitoYASchillerLRAmerican College of Gastroenterology monograph on the management of irritable bowel syndrome and chronic idiopathic constipationAm J Gastroenterol2014109 Suppl 1S22610.1038/ajg.2014.1872509114841.Lacy BE, Mearin F, Chang L, Chey WD, Lembo AJ, Simren M, et al. Bowel disorders. Gastroenterology. 2016;150(6):1393–1407. doi:10.1053/j.gastro.2016.02.031.42.FrancisCYMorrisJWhorwellPJThe irritable bowel severity scoring system: a simple method of monitoring irritable bowel syndrome and its progressAliment Pharmacol Ther199711239540210.1046/j.1365-2036.1997.142318000.x914678143.HróbjartssonAGøtzschePCIs the placebo powerless? An analysis of clinical trials comparing placebo with no treatmentN Engl J Med200134421159460210.1056/NEJM2001052434421061137201244.HallKTLoscalzoJKaptchukTJGenetics and the placebo effect: the placebomeTrends Mol Med20152152859410.1016/j.molmed.2015.02.0092588306945.Schafer SM, Colloca L, Wager TD. Placebo-induced decreases in the neurologic pain signature do not always correspond with pain relief. In: Organization of Human Brain Mapping; June 14-18, 2015; Honolulu, Hawaii, USA. 14-18; Abstract #4272 6.46.KirschIResponse expectancy as a determinant of experience and behaviorAm Psychol19854011118920210.1037/0003-066X.40.11.118947.AlbringAWendtLBensonSNissenSYavuzZEnglerHPreserving learned immunosuppressive placebo response: perspectives for clinical applicationClin Pharmacol Ther20149622475510.1038/clpt.2014.752469903248.Stewart-WilliamsSPoddJThe placebo effect: dissolving the expectancy versus conditioning debatePsychol Bull200413023244010.1037/0033-2909.130.2.3241497977549.GeersALMillerFGUnderstanding and translating the knowledge about placebo effects: the contribution of psychologyCurr Opin Psychiatry20142753263110.1097/YCO.00000000000000822504608150.RitterWSussmanEDeaconDCowanNVaughanHGTwo cognitive systems simultaneously prepared for opposite eventsPsychophysiology1999366835810.1111/1469-8986.36608351055459651.BubicAvon CramonDYSchubotzRIPrediction, cognition and the brainFront Hum Neurosci.20104252063185652.JensenKBKaptchukTJKirschIRaicekJLindstromKMBernaCNonconscious activation of placebo and nocebo pain responsesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A201210939159596410.1073/pnas.12020561092301938053.JensenKBKaptchukTJChenXKirschIIngvarMGollubRLA Neural mechanism for nonconscious activation of conditioned placebo and nocebo responsesCereb Cortex N Y N 19912015251039031054.JensenKKirschIOdmalmSKaptchukTJIngvarMClassical conditioning of analgesic and hyperalgesic pain responses without conscious awarenessProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2015112257863710.1073/pnas.15045671122597994055.EavesERNichterMRitenbaughCWays of hoping: navigating the paradox of hope and despair in chronic painCult Med Psychiatry2016401355810.1007/s11013-015-9465-42619478056.HsuCShermanKJEavesERTurnerJACherkinDCCrompDNew perspectives on patient expectations of treatment outcomes: results from qualitative interviews with patients seeking complementary and alternative medicine treatments for chronic low back painBMC Complement Altern Med.20141427610.1186/1472-6882-14-2762507773257.LopezSJSnyderCRPedrottiJHope: many definitions, many measuresPositive psychological assessment: a handbook of models and measures2003WashingtonAmerican Psychological Association9110758.AverillJSundarajanLEliottJHope as rhetoric: cultural narratives of wishing and copingInterdisciplinary perspectives on hope2005New YorkNova1275959.LidstoneSCSchulzerMDinelleKMakESossiVRuthTJEffects of expectation on placebo-induced dopamine release in Parkinson diseaseArch Gen Psychiatry20106788576510.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.882067959360.BergmannJFChassanyOGandiolJDebloisPKanisJASegrestaaJMA randomised clinical trial of the effect of informed consent on the analgesic activity of placebo and naproxen in cancer painClin Trials Metaanal19942914171015018461.FiorilloCDToblerPNSchultzWDiscrete coding of reward probability and uncertainty by dopamine neuronsScience20032995614189890210.1126/science.10773491264948462.KaptchukTJThe placebo effect in alternative medicine: can the performance of a healing ritual have clinical significance?Ann Intern Med2002136118172510.7326/0003-4819-136-11-200206040-000111204413063.ClarkASurfing uncertainty: prediction, action and the embodied mind2016New YorkOxford University Press64.KirschIKirschIResponse expectancy: An introductionHow expectancies shape experience1999WashingtonAmerican Psychological Association31365.Dennett D. Consciousness Explained. Penguin: London; 1993.66.ClarkAMetzingerTEmbodied predictionWindt JM Open Mind 7(1)2015Frankfurt am MainMIND Group67.CostaVDTranVLTurchiJAverbeckBBDopamine modulates novelty seeking behavior during decision makingBehav Neurosci201412855566610.1037/a00371282491132068.Guitart-MasipMBunzeckNStephanKEDolanRJDüzelEContextual novelty changes reward representations in the striatumJ Neurosci Off J Soc Neurosci20103051721610.1523/JNEUROSCI.5331-09.201069.WinnicottDWThrough paediatrics to psycho-analysis: collected papers. 1st Brunner/Mazel ed1992New YorkBrunner/Mazel5070.SechSMMontoyaJDBernierPABarnboymEBrownSGregoryAThe so-called “placebo effect” in benign prostatic hyperplasia treatment trials represents partially a conditional regression to the mean induced by censoringUrology19985122425010.1016/S0090-4295(97)00609-2949570571.GoldenholzDMMossRScottJAuhSTheodoreWHConfusing placebo effect with natural history in epilepsy: a big data approachAnn Neurol20157833293610.1002/ana.244702615009072.HullSCCollocaLAvinsAGordonNPSomkinCPKaptchukTJPatients’ attitudes about the use of placebo treatments: telephone surveyBMJ.2013347f375710.1136/bmj.f37572381996373.BishopFLAizlewoodLAdamsAEMWhen and why placebo-prescribing is acceptable and unacceptable: a focus group study of patients’ viewsPLoS One201497e10182210.1371/journal.pone.01018222500667374.BarnhillAClinical use of placebos: still the physician’s prerogative?Hastings Cent Rep2012423293710.1002/hast.3322627721
