<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front PsycholFront PsycholFront. Psychol.Frontiers in Psychology1664-1078Frontiers Media S.A.492757110.3389/fpsyg.2016.00967PsychologyOriginal ResearchEffects of Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy on Body Awareness in Patients with Chronic Pain and Comorbid Depressionde JongMarasha123†LazarSara W.4†HugKiran56MehlingWolf E.7HölzelBritta K.48SackAlexander T.9PeetersFrenk2AshihHeidi1MischoulonDavid1GardTim41011*1Depression Clinical and Research Program, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical SchoolBoston, MA, USA2Department of Psychiatry and Psychology, School of Mental Health and Neuroscience, Maastricht University Medical CenterMaastricht, Netherlands3MondriaanMaastricht, Netherlands4Department of Psychiatry, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical SchoolBoston, MA, USA5Department of Psychosomatic Medicine, Medical Faculty, Medical Center-University of FreiburgFreiburg, Germany6Division of Clinical Psychology and Psychotherapy, Faculty of Psychology, University of BaselBasel, Switzerland7Department of Family and Community Medicine, Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, University of California, San FranciscoSan Francisco, CA, USA8Department of Neuroradiology, Klinikum rechts der Isar, Technical University of MunichMunich, Germany9Department of Cognitive Neuroscience, Faculty of Psychology and Neuroscience, Maastricht UniversityMaastricht, Netherlands10Institute for Complementary and Integrative Medicine, University Hospital Zurich, University of ZurichZurich, Switzerland11Translational Neuromodeling Unit, Institute for Biomedical Engineering, University of Zurich and Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (ETH)Zurich, SwitzerlandEdited by: Olga Pollatos, University of Ulm, GermanyReviewed by: Takamitsu Watanabe, University College London, UK; Karin Meissner, Ludwig Maximilians University of Munich, Germany*Correspondence: Tim Gard tgard@mgh.harvard.eduThis article was submitted to Consciousness Research, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychology†These authors have contributed equally to this work.30620162016796726720151062016Copyright © 2016 de Jong, Lazar, Hug, Mehling, Hölzel, Sack, Peeters, Ashih, Mischoulon and Gard.2016de Jong, Lazar, Hug, Mehling, Hölzel, Sack, Peeters, Ashih, Mischoulon and GardThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution and reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Body awareness has been proposed as one of the major mechanisms of mindfulness interventions, and it has been shown that chronic pain and depression are associated with decreased levels of body awareness. We investigated the effect of Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy (MBCT) on body awareness in patients with chronic pain and comorbid active depression compared to treatment as usual (TAU; N = 31). Body awareness was measured by a subset of the Multidimensional Assessment of Interoceptive Awareness (MAIA) scales deemed most relevant for the population. These included: Noticing, Not-Distracting, Attention Regulation, Emotional Awareness, and Self-Regulation. In addition, pain catastrophizing was measured by the Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS). These scales had adequate to high internal consistency in the current sample. Depression severity was measured by the Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology—Clinician rated (QIDS-C16). Increases in the MBCT group were significantly greater than in the TAU group on the “Self-Regulation” and “Not Distracting” scales. Furthermore, the positive effect of MBCT on depression severity was mediated by “Not Distracting.” These findings provide preliminary evidence that a mindfulness-based intervention may increase facets of body awareness as assessed with the MAIA in a population of pain patients with depression. Furthermore, they are consistent with a long hypothesized mechanism for mindfulness and emphasize the clinical relevance of body awareness.mindfulness-based cognitive therapymindfulness meditationinteroceptive awarenessbody awarenesspain catastrophizingchronic paindepressionmediationanonymous bequestMind and Life Varela Award<sec xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Participants in this add-on study were part of a larger clinical trial reported elsewhere (de Jong et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">in press</xref>; clinicaltrials.gov id: NCT01473615). Patients were recruited from different outpatient clinics through introduction of the study by their physicians, as well as via web-based advertisements and through several online mailing lists. After phone screening and a subsequent in-person screening visit, eligible participants were offered enrollment and were randomly assigned to treatment as usual (TAU) or TAU plus mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT). English-language literate individuals aged 18 or older were eligible if they (a) had persistent chronic pain for a minimum of 3 months; (b) met the DSM-IV criteria for MDD, Dysthymic Disorder, or Depressive disorder Not Otherwise Specified (NOS); and (c) a score ≥10 on the QIDS-C<sub>16</sub> scale. After initiating the study the cutoff was reduced to a QIDS-C<sub>16</sub> score ≥6 (indicative of at least mild depressive symptoms) to allow more ample recruitment.</p><p>Exclusion criteria were: (a) serious suicide or homicide risk; (b) current or past bipolar disorder, current psychotic symptoms, or a current or past primary psychotic disorder; (c) diagnosis of substance abuse or dependence disorder during the last 3 months; (d) general condition that impedes attendance in group interventions, such as severe personality disorders, cognitive impairment, or tendencies toward physical aggression; (e) severe and unstable medical illness including cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, respiratory, endocrine, neurological, or hematological disease; and (f) significant present meditation practice with more than 3 h of mindfulness, insight, or vipassana meditation per week. Patients were requested to keep their psychological and pharmacological treatment as stable as possible from 8 weeks before the beginning of the study until its conclusion.</p><p>Seventy-one participants were screened, of which 40 were randomized to TAU or MBCT + TAU in a 1:2 ratio (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Participants received $40 for completed study participation and provided written informed consent. The study was approved by the Partners Human Research Committee, Massachusetts General Hospital (protocol 2011-P-001699/1).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Patient flow</bold>. LTFU, lost to follow up; MAIA, Multidimensional Assessment of Interoceptive Awareness; MBCT, Mindfulness Based Cognitive Therapy; PCS, Pain Catastrophizing Scale; QIDS-C, Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptoms-Clinician Rated; TAU, Treatment As Usual.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyg-07-00967-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Measures</title><sec><title>Multidimensional assessment of interoceptive awareness (MAIA)</title><p>The MAIA is a 32-item instrument that assesses body awareness on 6-point Likert-type scales that range from 0 (Never) to 5 (Always). It comprises eight scales, namely Noticing, Not-Distracting, Not-Worrying, Attention Regulation, Emotional Awareness, Self-Regulation, Body Listening, and Trusting (Mehling et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The eight scales have been shown to have adequate to excellent internal-consistency reliabilities, with Cronbach's alphas from 0.66 to 0.87, and above 0.70 for five of the eight scales (Mehling et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Because the current study was an add-on to a larger study, subject burden had to be kept to a minimum. For this reason only the scales deemed most relevant for the specific population were administered, namely Noticing, Not-Distracting, Attention Regulation, Emotional Awareness, and Self-Regulation.</p><p>The Noticing scale assesses the awareness of comfortable, neutral, and uncomfortable body sensations. Not-Distracting refers to not ignoring or distracting oneself from uncomfortable body sensations such as pain. Attention Regulation is the ability to maintain and regulate attention to body sensations, and Emotional Awareness is defined as consciousness of the interrelation of emotions and body sensations. Self-Regulation refers to the ability to control psychological distress by consciously attending to body sensations (Mehling et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The MAIA Not Worrying scale assesses worrying or feeling emotionally distressed in response to uncomfortable body sensations including pain and was not administered, since its items are similar to the Pain Catastrophizing Scale, which was included in the larger study.</p></sec><sec><title>Pain catastrophizing scale (PCS)</title><p>The PCS is a 13-item scale, comprised of three subscales, that measures pain catastrophizing. Pain catastrophizing is defined as “an exaggerated negative mental set brought to bear during (actual or anticipated) painful experience” (Sullivan et al., <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). The PCS total score can range from 0 to 52 and has been shown to have excellent reliability (Cronbach's alpha = 0.87; Sullivan et al., <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Quick inventory of depressive symptomatology—clinician rated (QIDS-C<sub>16</sub>)</title><p>The QIDS-C is a widely used clinician rated instrument to assess depression symptom severity. The instrument is comprised of 16 items, has good psychometric properties, score range from 0 to 27 and is sensitive to changes in depressive severity (Rush et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Trivedi et al., <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Procedure</title><p>Eligible participants were randomly assigned to TAU (control group) or MBCT + TAU (intervention group) in a 1:2 ratio, which allowed the main project to fill the MBCT groups with participants more quickly. An independent researcher not involved in the project generated the randomization sequence in blocks of five (using the sequence generator on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.random.org">www.random.org</ext-link>). In order to assure equal gender distribution in both groups we stratified for gender. The intervention group received an 8-week MBCT group skills program. Interoceptive awareness, pain catastrophizing, and depression were assessed at baseline (week 0), midpoint (week 4), and endpoint (week 8).</p></sec><sec><title>Intervention</title><p>The intervention consisted of an 8-week group skills program with one 2-h mindfulness training session each week and individual exercises for homework practice. It was modeled on the MBCT program developed by Segal et al. (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), which was developed as a program to address recurrent depressive episodes and combines elements of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), such as psycho-education, with experiential mindfulness practices. The program is intended to teach and foster a non-judgmental, accepting attitude toward one's internal, and external experience. For the current study the original program was adapted to our specific population by modifying the psychoeducation and CBT elements to a depressed CP population. This included psycho-education linking CP, negative thoughts, negative emotions, and depressive behaviors such as withdrawal; identifying automatic thoughts related to CP; and paying attention to behavioral elements such as pacing of activities. We also included meditations that specifically focused on cultivating mindfulness in relationship to CP. The MBCT program was led by two instructors, an experienced licensed independent clinical social worker (LICSW) and a fellow in psychology and was provided free of charge. Subjects that were assigned to TAU were waitlisted and offered the MBCT treatment after completion of the study. TAU included all regular visits with the pain physician, psychiatrist, psychotherapist and prescribed pain and/or antidepressant medications.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Differences in patient characteristics at baseline were assessed by performing independent-samples <italic>t</italic>-tests for continuous variables and Chi-square tests for categorical variables. To evaluate internal consistency/reliability, Cronbach's alphas were assessed. Inter-scale correlations were obtained for the MAIA scales and the PCS total score based on the data of all subjects at baseline. The effects of intervention/group (MBCT + TAU vs. TAU) and time (baseline vs. endpoint) on the dependent variables body awareness and pain catastrophizing were assessed by conducting repeated measures analysis of variance (rmANOVA), with time as repeated measure, treatment group as between-subjects factor, and MAIA scales and PCS as dependent variables. Assumptions of normality and homogeneity were met. Paired samples <italic>t</italic>-tests were conducted to compare baseline and endpoint scores on the MAIA scales and the PCS within each group. As a measure of effect size, Cohen's d was calculated for each pre-post change. Analyses were conducted according to a modified intention-to-treat (ITT) principle with the last observation carried forward (LOCF). When endpoint measures were missing, midpoint measures were imputed, and if midpoint data were missing, baseline data were used. Only participants who attended at least four of the eight classes were included in the analyses.</p><p>The main study, to which this study was added on, revealed a significant effect of MBCT (group by time interaction) on depression as measured with the Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology-Clinician rated (QIDS-C<sub>16</sub>) (de Jong et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">in press</xref>). To explore if and how this effects is mediated by the MAIA, a multiple mediator model was tested. The model comprised group (MBCT + TAU vs. TAU) as independent variable, depression measured at week 8 as dependent variable and MAIA scales (measured at week 8) that revealed significant group by time interactions, as mediators. Depression and respective MAIA scales measured at baseline (week 0) were included as covariates. Mediation analyses were conducted with a macro by Preacher and Hayes (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) that implements a bootstrapping procedure to create confidence intervals for partial and total indirect effects. For mediation analyses only participants who participated in at least 4 classes and who had week 0 and week 8 data available were included in the analyses and 10,000 bootstrap iterations were used. All analyses were conducted with SPSS 21 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).</p></sec></sec>This study was funded by an anonymous bequest to the DCRP, and the Mind and Life Francisco J. Varela (Grant 2010-01-010) to TG. We would like to thank Narayan Brach for his help with Red Cap, Jim Doorley, Rosemary Walker, and Thomas Calahan for logistics, Laurie Rhoades for teaching the MBCT program, Ronald Kulich, Karsten Kueppenbender, and Egilius Spiering for patient recruitment and Lee Baer, and Alisabet J. Clain, for assistance with data base conversion and general statistical questions, and Elizabeth Hoge, Willoughby Britton, Jonathan Alpert, and Maurizio Fava for advice. We also would like to thank all participants for their efforts.ReferencesArchJ. J.CraskeM. G. (2006). Mechanisms of mindfulness: emotion regulation following a focused breathing induction. Behav. Res. Ther.
44, 1849–1858. 10.1016/j.brat.2005.12.00716460668BaerR. A. (2003). Mindfulness training as a clinical intervention: a conceptual and empirical review. Clin. Psychol.
10, 125–143. 10.1093/clipsy.bpg015BairM. J.RobinsonR. L.KatonW.KroenkeK. (2003). Depression and pain comorbidity: a literature review. Arch. Intern. Med.
163, 2433–2445. 10.1001/archinte.163.20.243314609780BaumeisterR. F.BratslavskyE.MuravenM.TiceD. M. (1998). Ego depletion: is the active self a limited resource?
J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.
74, 1252. 10.1037/0022-3514.74.5.12529599441BishopS. R.LauM.ShapiroS.CarlsonL.AndersonN. D.CarmodyJ. (2004). Mindfulness: a proposed operational definition. Clin. Psychol.
11, 230–241. 10.1093/clipsy.bph077BodenM. T.IronsJ. G.FeldnerM. T.BujarskiS.Bonn-MillerM. O. (2015). An investigation of relations among quality of life and individual facets of emotional awareness and mindfulness. Mindfulness
6, 700–707. 10.1007/s12671-014-0308-0BornemannB.HerbertB. M.MehlingW. E.SingerT. (2015). Differential changes in self-reported aspects of interoceptive awareness through three months of contemplative training. Front. Psychol.
5:1504
10.3389/fpsyg.2014.01504BornemannB.SingerT. (2015). Taking time to get in touch with our body: heart beat perception accuracy increases linearly over nine months of contemplative training, in International Convention of Psychological Science (Amsterdam).BroderickP. C. (2005). Mindfulness and coping with dysphoric mood: contrasts with rumination and distraction. Cognit. Ther. Res.
29, 501–510. 10.1007/s10608-005-3888-0CassidyE. L.AthertonR. J.RobertsonN.WalshD. A.GillettR. (2012). Mindfulness, functioning and catastrophizing after multidisciplinary pain management for chronic low back pain. Pain
153, 644–650. 10.1016/j.pain.2011.11.02722240149CraigA. D. (2003). A new view of pain as a homeostatic emotion. Trends Neurosci.
26, 303–307. 12798599DanielssonL.PapouliasI.PeterssonE.-L.CarlssonJ.WaernM. (2014). Exercise or basic body awareness therapy as add-on treatment for major depression: a controlled study. J. Affect. Disord.
168, 98–106. 10.1016/j.jad.2014.06.04925043321DayM. A.ThornB. E.WardL. C.RubinN.HickmanS. D.ScoginF.. (2014). Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for the treatment of headache pain: a pilot study. Clin. J. Pain
30, 152–161. 10.1097/AJP.0b013e318287a1dc23446085de BoerM. J.SteinhagenH. E.VersteegenG. J.StruysM. M. R. F.SandermanR. (2014). Mindfulness, acceptance and catastrophizing in chronic pain. PLoS ONE
9:e87445. 10.1371/journal.pone.008744524489915de JongM.PeetersF.GardT.AshihH.DoorleyJ.WalkerR. (in press). A randomized controlled pilot study on mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for unipolar depression in patients with chronic pain. J. Clin. Psychiatry.DunnB. D.DalgleishT.LawrenceA. D.OgilvieA. D. (2007). The accuracy of self-monitoring and its relationship to self-focused attention in dysphoria and clinical depression. J. Abnorm. Psychol.
116, 1–15. 10.1037/0021-843X.116.1.117324012EhlersA.BreuerP. (1992). Increased cardiac awareness in panic disorder. J. Abnorm. Psychol.
101, 371–382. 10.1037/0021-843X.101.3.3711500594EhlersA.BreuerP. (1996). How good are patients with panic disorder at perceiving their heartbeats?
Biol. Psychol.
42, 165–182. 8770377FarbN.DaubenmierJ. J.PriceC. J.GardT.KerrC.DunnB.. (2015). Interoception, contemplative practice, and health. Front. Psychol.
6:763. 10.3389/fpsyg.2015.0076326106345FarbN. A.AndersonA. K.MaybergH.BeanJ.McKeonD.SegalZ. V. (2010). Minding one's emotions: mindfulness training alters the neural expression of sadness. Emotion
10, 25–33. 10.1037/a001715120141299FarbN. A.SegalZ. V.AndersonA. K. (2013). Mindfulness meditation training alters cortical representations of interoceptive attention. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
8, 15–26. 10.1093/scan/nss06622689216FoxK. C.ZakarauskasP.DixonM.EllamilM.ThompsonE.ChristoffK. (2012). Meditation experience predicts introspective accuracy. PLoS ONE
7:e45370. 10.1371/journal.pone.004537023049790GardT.HölzelB. K.SackA. T.HempelH.LazarS. W.VaitlD.. (2012). Pain attenuation through mindfulness is associated with decreased cognitive control and increased sensory processing in the brain. Cereb. Cortex
22, 2692–2702. 10.1093/cercor/bhr35222172578GarlandE. L.GaylordS. A.PalssonO.FaurotK.MannJ. D.WhiteheadW. E. (2012). Therapeutic mechanisms of a mindfulness-based treatment for IBS: effects on visceral sensitivity, catastrophizing, and affective processing of pain sensations. J. Behav. Med.
35, 591–602. 10.1007/s10865-011-9391-z22161025GoldmanR. N.GreenbergL. S.PosA. E. (2005). Depth of emotional experience and outcome. Psychother. Res.
15, 248–260. 10.1080/1050330051233138518822011154GoyalM.SinghS.SibingaE. M.GouldN. F.Rowland-SeymourA.SharmaR.. (2014). Meditation programs for psychological stress and well-being: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Intern. Med.
174, 357–368. 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.1301824395196HadjistavropoulosH. D.HadjistavropoulosT.QuineA. (2000). Health anxiety moderates the effects of distraction versus attention to pain. Behav. Res. Ther.
38, 425–438. 10.1016/S0005-7967(99)00044-310816903HayesA. F. (2013). Introduction to Mediation, Moderation, and Conditional Process Analysis. New York, NY: The Guilford Press.HayesS. C.WilsonK. G.GiffordE. V.FolletteV. M.StrosahlK. (1996). Experiential avoidance and behavioral disorders: a functional dimensional approach to diagnosis and treatment. J. Consult. Clin. Psychol.
64, 1152. 8991302HerbertB. M.PollatosO.SchandryR. (2007). Interoceptive sensitivity and emotion processing: an EEG study. Int. J. Psychophysiol.
65, 214–227. 10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2007.04.00717543405HofmannS. G.SawyerA. T.WittA. A.OhD. (2010). The effect of mindfulness-based therapy on anxiety and depression: a meta-analytic review. J. Consult. Clin. Psychol.
78, 169–183. 10.1037/a001855520350028HogeE. A.BuiE.MarquesL.MetcalfC. A.MorrisL. K.RobinaughD. J.. (2013). Randomized controlled trial of mindfulness meditation for generalized anxiety disorder: effects on anxiety and stress reactivity. J. Clin. Psychiatry
74, 786–792. 10.4088/JCP.12m0808323541163HölzelB. K.LazarS. W.GardT.Schuman-OlivierZ.VagoD. R.OttU. (2011). How does mindfulness meditation work? Proposing mechanisms of action from a conceptual and neural perspective. Pers. Psychol. Sci.
6, 537–559. 10.1177/174569161141967126168376HölzelB. K.OttU.GardT.HempelH.WeygandtM.MorgenK.. (2008). Investigation of mindfulness meditation practitioners with voxel-based morphometry. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
3, 55–61. 10.1093/scan/nsm03819015095HuffzigerS.KuehnerC. (2009). Rumination, distraction, and mindful self-focus in depressed patients. Behav. Res. Ther.
47, 224–230. 10.1016/j.brat.2008.12.00519166993HyettM. P.BreakspearM. J.FristonK. J.GuoC. C.ParkerG. B. (2015). Disrupted effective connectivity of cortical systems supporting attention and interoception in melancholia. JAMA Psychiatry
72, 350–358. 10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.249025692565JainS.ShapiroS.SwanickS.RoeschS.MillsP.BellI.. (2007). A randomized controlled trial of mindfulness meditation versus relaxation training: effects on distress, positive states of mind, rumination, and distraction. Ann. Behav. Med.
33, 11–21. 10.1207/s15324796abm3301_217291166JamesW. (1984). What is an emotion?
Mind
9, 188–205. 26834811JohnstonN. E.AtlasL. Y.WagerT. D. (2012). Opposing effects of expectancy and somatic focus on pain. PLoS ONE
7:e38854. 10.1371/journal.pone.003885422723896Kabat-ZinnJ. (1990). Full Catastrophe Living: Using the Wisdom of Your Body and Your Mind to Face Stress, Pain and Illness. New York, NY: Delta.Kabat-ZinnJ.LipworthL.BurneyR. (1985). The clinical use of mindfulness meditation for the self-regulation of chronic pain. J. Behav. Med.
8, 163–190. 10.1007/BF008455193897551KazdinA. E. (2007). Mediators and mechanisms of change in psychotherapy research. Annu. Rev. Clin. Psychol.
3, 1–27. 10.1146/annurev.clinpsy.3.022806.09143217716046KhalsaS. S.RudraufD.DamasioA. R.DavidsonR. J.LutzA.TranelD. (2008). Interoceptive awareness in experienced meditators. Psychophysiology
45, 671–677. 10.1111/j.1469-8986.2008.00666.x18503485KingstonJ.ChadwickP.MeronD.SkinnerT. C. (2007). A pilot randomized control trial investigating the effect of mindfulness practice on pain tolerance, psychological well-being, and physiological activity. J. Psychosom. Res.
62, 297–300. 10.1016/j.jpsychores.2006.10.00717324679LazarS. W.KerrC. E.WassermanR. H.GrayJ. R.GreveD. N.TreadwayM. T.. (2005). Meditation experience is associated with increased cortical thickness. Neuroreport
16, 1893–1897. 10.1097/01.wnr.0000186598.66243.1916272874MarchandW. R. (2012). Mindfulness-based stress reduction, mindfulness-based cognitive therapy, and Zen meditation for depression, anxiety, pain, and psychological distress. J. Psychiatr. Pract.
18, 233–252. 10.1097/01.pra.0000416014.53215.8622805898MathesonK.AnismanH. (2003). Systems of coping associated with dysphoria, anxiety and depressive illness: a multivariate profile perspective. Stress
6, 223–234. 10.1080/1025389031000159448713129815MehlingW. E.DaubenmierJ.PriceC. J.AcreeM.BartmessE.StewartA. L. (2013). Self-reported interoceptive awareness in primary care patients with past or current low back pain. J. Pain Res.
6, 403–418. 10.2147/JPR.S4241823766657MehlingW. E.GopisettyV.DaubenmierJ.PriceC. J.HechtF. M.StewartA. (2009). Body awareness: construct and self-report measures. PLoS ONE
4:e5614. 10.1371/journal.pone.000561419440300MehlingW. E.PriceC. J.DaubenmierJ.MikeA.BartmessE.StewartA. (2014). Body awareness and the practice of yoga or meditation in 435 primary care patients with past or current low back pain. J. Altern. Complement. Med.
20, A63–A64. 10.1089/acm.2014.5165.abstract27150263MehlingW. E.PriceC.DaubenmierJ. J.AcreeM.BartmessE.StewartA. (2012). The multidimensional assessment of interoceptive awareness (MAIA). PLoS ONE
7:e48230. 10.1371/journal.pone.004823023133619MelloniM.SedenoL.CoutoB.ReynosoM.GelorminiC.FavaloroR.. (2013). Preliminary evidence about the effects of meditation on interoceptive sensitivity and social cognition. Behav. Brain Funct.
9:47. 10.1186/1744-9081-9-4724365106MichalakJ.BurgJ.HeidenreichT. (2012). Don't forget your body: mindfulness, embodiment, and the treatment of depression. Mindfulness
3, 190–199. 10.1007/s12671-012-0107-4MichalakJ.TrojeN. F.HeidenreichT. (2010). Embodied effects of mindfulness-based cognitive therapy. J. Psychosom. Res.
68, 312–313. 10.1016/j.jpsychores.2010.01.00420159220MichalakJ.TrojeN.HeidenreichT. (2011). The effects of mindfulness-based cognitive therapy on depressive gait patterns. J. Cogni. Behav. Psychother.
11, 13–27.MuravenM.BaumeisterR. F. (2000). Self-regulation and depletion of limited resources: does self-control resemble a muscle?
Psychol. Bull.
126:247. 10.1037/0033-2909.126.2.24710748642NielsenL.KaszniakA. W. (2006). Awareness of subtle emotional feelings: a comparison of long-term meditators and nonmeditators. Emotion
6, 392. 10.1037/1528-3542.6.3.39216938081ParkinL.MorganR.RosselliA.HowardM.SheppardA.EvansD. (2014). Exploring the relationship between mindfulness and cardiac perception. Mindfulness
5, 298–313. 10.1007/s12671-012-0181-7PeresM. F.LucchettiG. (2010). Coping strategies in chronic pain. Curr. Pain Headache Rep.
14, 331–338. 10.1007/s11916-010-0137-320680705PhillipotP.SegalZ. (2009). Mindfulness based psychological interventions: developing emotional awareness for better being. J. Conscious. Stud.
16, 10–12.PietJ.HougaardE. (2011). The effect of mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for prevention of relapse in recurrent major depressive disorder: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
31, 1032–1040. 10.1016/j.cpr.2011.05.00221802618PollatosO.Traut-MattauschE.SchandryR. (2009). Differential effects of anxiety and depression on interoceptive accuracy. Depress. Anxiety
26, 167–173. 10.1002/da.2050419152366PreacherK. J.HayesA. F. (2008). Asymptotic and resampling strategies for assessing and comparing indirect effects in multiple mediator models. Behav. Res. Methods
40, 879. 10.3758/BRM.40.3.87918697684PrinsB.DecuypereA.Van DammeS. (2014). Effects of mindfulness and distraction on pain depend upon individual differences in pain catastrophizing: an experimental study. Eur. J. Pain
18, 1307–1315. 10.1002/j.1532-2149.2014.491.x24677437ReidK. J.HarkerJ.BalaM. M.TruyersC.KellenE.BekkeringG. E.. (2011). Epidemiology of chronic non-cancer pain in Europe: narrative review of prevalence, pain treatments and pain impact. Curr. Med. Res. Opin.
27, 449–462. 10.1185/03007995.2010.54581321194394ReidM. C.BarryL. C.KernsR. D.DuongB. D.ConcatoJ. (2002). Coping strategies and their associations with levels of disability or pain, among older veterans receiving primary care. J. Clin. Epidemiol.
55, 629. 10.1016/s0895-4356(02)00420-115817018RileyB. (2014). Experiential avoidance mediates the association between thought suppression and mindfulness with problem gambling. J. Gambl. Stud.
30, 163–171. 10.1007/s10899-012-9342-923108594RushA. J.TrivediM. H.IbrahimH. M.CarmodyT. J.ArnowB.KleinD. N.. (2003). The 16-item quick inventory of depressive symptomatology (QIDS), clinician rating (QIDS-C), and self-report (QIDS-SR): a psychometric evaluation in patients with chronic major depression. Biol. Psychiatry
54, 573–583. 10.1016/S0006-3223(02)01866-812946886SchutzeR.ReesC.PreeceM.SchutzeM. (2010). Low mindfulness predicts pain catastrophizing in a fear-avoidance model of chronic pain. Pain
148, 120–127. 10.1016/j.pain.2009.10.03019944534SegalZ. V.WilliamsJ. M. G.TeasdaleJ. D. (2013). Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy for Depression. New York, NY: The Guilford Press.SipeW. E.EisendrathS. J. (2012). Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy: theory and practice. Can. J. Psychiatry
57, 63–69. 10.1177/07067437120570020222340145SullivanM. J. L.ThornB.HaythornthwaiteJ. A.KeefeF.MartinM.BradleyL. A.. (2001). Theoretical perspectives on the relation between catastrophizing and pain. Clin. J. Pain
17, 52–64. 10.1097/00002508-200103000-0000811289089SzeJ. A.GyurakA.YuanJ. W.LevensonR. W. (2010). Coherence between emotional experience and physiology: does body awareness training have an impact?
Emotion
10, 803. 10.1037/a002014621058842TrivediM. H.RushA.IbrahimH.CarmodyT.BiggsM.SuppesT.. (2004). The inventory of depressive symptomatology, clinician rating (IDS-C) and self-report (IDS-SR), and the quick inventory of depressive symptomatology, clinician rating (QIDS-C) and self-report (QIDS-SR) in public sector patients with mood disorders: a psychometric evaluation. Psychol. Med.
34, 73–82. 10.1017/S003329170300110714971628TunksE. R. (2008). Epidemiology of chronic pain with psychological comorbidity: prevalence, risk, course, and prognosis. Can. J. Psychiatry
53, 224–234. 10.1177/07067437080530040318478825TurkD. C.WilsonH. D.CahanaA. (2011). Treatment of chronic non-cancer pain. Lancet
377, 2226–2235. 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60402-921704872VagoD. R.SilbersweigD. A. (2012). Self-awareness, self-regulation, and self-transcendence (S-ART): a framework for understanding the neurobiological mechanisms of mindfulness. Front. Hum. Neurosci.
6:296. 10.3389/fnhum.2012.0029623112770van Der VeldenA. M.KuykenW.WattarU.CraneC.PallesenK. J.DahlgaardJ.. (2015). A systematic review of mechanisms of change in mindfulness-based cognitive therapy in the treatment of recurrent major depressive disorder. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
37, 26–39. 10.1016/j.cpr.2015.02.00125748559VeehofM. M.OskamM. J.SchreursK. M.BohlmeijerE. T. (2011). Acceptance-based interventions for the treatment of chronic pain: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Pain
152, 533–542. 10.1016/j.pain.2010.11.00221251756VohsK. D.BaumeisterR. F. (2011). Handbook of Self-Regulation: Research, Theory, and Applications. New York, NY: The Guilford Press.WilliamsJ. M. G. (2010). Mindfulness and psychological process. Emotion
10, 1–7. 10.1037/a001836020141295WilliamsV.CiarrochiJ.DeaneF. P. (2010). On being mindful, emotionally aware, and more resilient: longitudinal pilot study of police recruits. Aust. Psychol.
45, 274–282. 10.1080/00050060903573197
