<?xml version="1.0"?>
Children (Basel)Children (Basel)childrenChildren2227-9067MDPI492872310.3390/children1020134children-01-00134ReviewAcupuncture for Pediatric PainGolianuBrenda1*YehAnn Ming2BrooksMeredith31Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Medicine, Pediatric Anesthesiology, Stanford University, 300 Pasteur Dr. Stanford, CA 94304, USA2Pediatric Gastroenterology, Stanford University, 750 Welch Road, Suite 116, Palo Alto CA 94304, USA; E-Mail: annming@stanford.edu3Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Medicine, Pediatric Anesthesiology, Stanford University, 300 Pasteur Dr. Stanford, CA 94304, USA; E-Mail: mrbrooks@stanford.edu*Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: bgolianu@stanford.edu; Tel.: +1-650-725-5847; Fax: +1-650-725-8544.21820149201412134148076201414720140782014© 2014 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.2014This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/).Chronic pain is a growing problem in children, with prevalence as high as 30.8%. Acupuncture has been found to be useful in many chronic pain conditions, and may be of clinical value in a multidisciplinary treatment program. The basic principles of acupuncture are reviewed, as well as studies exploring basic mechanisms of acupuncture and clinical efficacy. Conditions commonly treated in the pediatric pain clinic, including headache, abdominal pain, fibromyalgia, juvenile arthritis, complex regional pain syndrome, cancer pain, as well as perioperative pain studies are reviewed and discussed. Areas in need of further research are identified, and procedural aspects of acupuncture practice and safety studies are reviewed. Acupuncture can be an effective adjuvant in the care of pediatric patients with painful conditions, both in a chronic and an acute setting. Further studies, including randomized controlled trials, as well as trials of comparative effectiveness are needed.acupuncturepediatricpainintegrative medicinereviewacupressurelaser acupuncture1. IntroductionChronic pain is a growing problem in children with prevalence as high as 30.8% in some epidemiological studies [1]. The predominant types of pain include headache (60.8%), abdominal pain (43.3%), limb (33.6%), and back (30.2%), and pain symptoms have been found to be associated with many lifestyle restrictions including sleep problems, inability to pursue hobbies, school absences, and inability to meet with friends. Pediatric pain clinics offer many integrative and complementary services including biofeedback (33%), acupuncture (24%), massage (20%), gratitude journals (16%), yoga and tai chi (8%) [2]. In other studies of pediatric headache conducted in Italy and Germany, Complementary Alternative Medicine (CAM) therapies were utilized by 76% and 75.7% of patients respectively [3,4]. Thus, a thorough understanding of the basis and efficacy of these therapies is warranted to help our patients better navigate the extensive selection of therapies, as well as integrate them with conventional medical treatment strategies.2. Physiology of Chronic PainThe physiology of chronic pain has evolved from a direct stimulus response model to one of an integrated complex neural network response. Following tissue injury, there is an immediate release of local inflammatory mediators, including prostaglandins, histamine, bradykinin and other factors, which lead to a localized tissue response, consisting of localized swelling, pain, and edema. Furthermore, they sensitize the primary neurons such that a subsequent stimulus is perceived as even more painful. The development of chronic pain involves long term potentiation of peripheral nerves, molecular changes in the spinal cord and central nervous system, [5] as well as alteration in how various areas of the mid brain and limbic system, including structures such as insula, prefrontal cortex, anterior cingulate, thalamus, often termed the “pain matrix”, connect to one another. These changes can be observed using functional MRI studies. Improvement in pain is often correlated with the return of normalized connectivity in these areas [6,7].3. Acupuncture: Introduction, Mechanisms of Action, and Clinical Research3.1. IntroductionAcupuncture has been practiced in China for at least 3000 years. The basic principles of acupuncture revolve around the concept of “Qi”, or energy of the body. When this energy is not flowing correctly, it is believed to lead to illness and disease. In the traditional setting acupuncture is frequently utilized as a preventative therapy or an intervention early in the course of illness.In the pediatric population,, standard medical therapies for chronic pain conditions often carry a significant side effect profile. Side effects of frequently used pharmacological agents for chronic pain include sedation, dizziness, tolerance, nausea, constipation, as well as depression and suicidal ideation. As a result, many parents and children are especially interested in trying acupuncture and other CAM therapies due to their relatively low risk profile.3.2. Acupuncture Mechanisms of ActionA challenging area of research has involved understanding the mechanisms of acupuncture action and how it relates to pain. Although much research has been performed in the last several decades and many basic scientific studies have outlined various physiologic pathways which are activated by acupuncture, a complete synthesis of the mechanism of action of acupuncture is still elusive [8]. Many areas of active research can be identified, and within each hundreds of studies are found, however we will mention three theories that are particularly noteworthy regarding the mechanisms of action of acupuncture: molecular mechanisms, physiologic changes found at acupuncture point locations, and central nervous system changes in brain connectivity. Principal among the molecular studies is the work of JS Han and colleagues, who over several decades explored how acupuncture stimulated the release of endogenous endorphins [9]. One of their most significant findings is that low frequency (2–10 Hz) electrical stimulation of acupuncture points leads to increased endorphin release, while high frequency stimulation (100 Hz) leads to increased dynorphin release. Other studies describe the local changes found at acupuncture points, including connective tissue changes, and changes in electrical resistance at acupoints. For example, Langevin identified changes in connective tissue that occur with the physical act of needle placement [10], while Anh et al. explored the changes in skin resistance at distal acupuncture points and found that changes in these responses correlated with clinical response in adolescent girls with pelvic pain [11].A number of fMRI studies have shown changes in brain blood flow following acupuncture treatment, and normalization of activity in areas of the limbic system, as well as areas of the “pain matrix” [12,13,14]. An excellent review of acupuncture basic mechanisms was performed by Wang et al. [15].3.3. Challenges in Acupuncture Clinical ResearchIn 1997, the NIH conducted a Consensus meeting, where it was determined that sufficient evidence was present to conclude that acupuncture is effective for a number of conditions including nausea and vomiting related to chemotherapy, adult postoperative pain and postoperative dental pain. Additional promising indications included tennis elbow, dysmenorrhea, stroke rehabilitation, and the treatment of addiction [16]. Since that time many additional studies have supported the use of acupuncture in a number of types of painful conditions [17,18].Some studies, such as the back pain trial in Germany, showed an improvement in both the active and the sham acupuncture arms as compared to standard care, suggesting that some of the acupuncture effect may not depend on the specificity of the points utilized [19]. There is significant controversy in the acupuncture literature about how this matter should be interpreted, as the sham controls in many studies have shown clinical efficacy. One explanation is that since we do not know the exact mechanisms of pain relief of acupuncture, the sham controls, which involve active needle placement in alternate locations, are themselves having a therapeutic benefit. Secondly, the active acupuncture treatment that is performed as part of an RCT may have limitations, as it does not allow individualization of treatment, a necessary ingredient of acupuncture therapy. Thus the finding in many studies that active acupuncture and sham acupuncture appear to both be efficacious remains an interpretive challenge in current acupuncture research, and until this phenomenon is better understood and an appropriate, therapeutically inactive but believable sham treatment can be designed, there has been a call for different types of studies, such as comparative effectiveness trials, which compare the acupuncture therapy against standard therapies, to continue to inform clinical practice [20]. MacPherson et al., in a meta-analysis of published studies, determined that positive trials were associated with more needles and more frequent treatments, suggesting that dosing of acupuncture may also be important [21].4. Pediatric PainAcupuncture can be a useful adjuvant in the care of pediatric patients with painful conditions, both in the chronic and acute setting. In a study on the feasibility of acupuncture/hypnosis intervention, 33 children were offered acupuncture together with a hypnosis session while needles were in place. Treatments were highly acceptable (only 2 patients refused). Both parents and children reported decrease in pain (4.38 (p &lt; 0.0001)), and improvement in function (2.62 (p = 0.014)) [22]. Lin et al. investigated the efficacy of acupuncture for children and adolescents with chronic pain. Fifty-three patients between 2 and 18 years of age, with a variety of painful conditions underwent pain assessment before and after acupuncture treatment. The average duration of pain improvement was 3 days, suggesting that continued acupuncture was needed for longer term improvement [23].Conditions commonly treated in pediatric pain, including headache, abdominal pain, fibromyalgia, juvenile arthritis, complex regional pain syndrome, cancer pain, as well as perioperative pain studies will be discussed. Due to the paucity of acupuncture research in the pediatric literature, adult studies will also be reviewed in each section, as they often serve as the clinical basis for the development of treatment regimens. Lastly, areas in need of further research of acupuncture in children will be identified. 4.1. Procedure Consent, Acceptance and Safety of Acupuncture4.1.1. The Procedure of AcupunctureInformed consent is obtained from the parents prior to initiation of acupuncture treatment. The type of acupuncture is explained to both the parent and child, along with possible complications, which may include bleeding, infection, or increased pain. More serious complications have occurred (see below) and may be related to needling technique or patient condition. A refusal of the parent or child to receive acupuncture should be a contraindication. Pediatric patients often require more gentle introduction to the needling process, to allow them to grow more accustomed to the idea, trust the practitioner, and observe for themselves that the needles usually do not cause excessive discomfort. Lin et al. showed that while 53% of children were initially apprehensive of acupuncture needles, following their first needle 64% felt it did not hurt, and furthermore would recommend it to someone else.. Acupuncture treatment will usually consist of a series of treatments, usually 6–10, to determine if acupuncture intervention is helpful for the patient’s condition. In a study by Kemper of adolescents receiving acupuncture for their pain, 67% reported the therapy as pleasant, and 70% reported that it had helped their pain [24]. Children were moderately receptive to acupuncture therapy for their chronic pain symptoms [25]. Parental experience with acupuncture, regardless of its perceived efficacy, appears to play in a role in parents’ consideration of acupuncture for their child [26]. Parental stress was found to decrease along with child discomfort following acupuncture therapy for the child [27]. 4.1.2. Acupuncture SafetyIn an excellent review of the safety of acupuncture in the pediatric population, Adams et al. screened a total of 9537 references, and identified 37 studies in the international literature that satisfied criteria for inclusion. Described complications included infection, and 1 case each of cardiac rupture, pneumothorax, and other effects, likely related to direct needle organ penetration. Additional mild adverse effects included pain, bruising, and worsening of symptoms. The study concluded that acupuncture is safe when performed by appropriately trained practitioners [28]. Yates et al. showed that non-invasive electrical stimulation at acupuncture points during a routine heel stick was well tolerated in healthy neonates [29].4.1.3. HeadacheIn the adult literature, several studies examine acupuncture as a prophylactic treatment. Allais et al. performed a randomized trial of 160 women migraine sufferers who received weekly acupuncture for 2 months, followed by monthly acupuncture for an additional 4 months. Decreased headache severity, as well as decreased medication usage, was statistically significant at all time points analyzed [30]. Diener et al. performed a large multicentre randomized study of 443 patients randomized into three groups—verum acupuncture, sham acupuncture (termed New Western acupuncture by the researchers), and standard medical care. Following 10 weekly acupuncture treatments, headache frequency and severity was measured at 26 weeks after baseline. Although the results were statistically significant, the effect size may have been diminished by the long time lapse between last acupuncture treatment and pain assessment [31]. In another study of migraine sufferers, the study intervention was delivered in a standard clinical format, without randomization. Study results showed that acupuncture had a measurable clinical effect, which was greater than that seen in a randomized format [32]. Finally two large Cochrane Collaboration Reviews concluded that although it appeared that specific point selection was not as important as had previously thought, acupuncture should be considered as a treatment option for patients needing prophylactic treatment for migraine or tension headaches [33,34].In the pediatric population, a randomized trial of 22 children with migraine showed in the true acupuncture group the migraine frequency decreased from 9.3 (±1.6) to 1.4 (±0.6), and intensity decreased from 8.7 (±0.4) to 7.8 (±0.6) following 10 weekly sessions [35]. Gottschling et al. used a non-invasive technique, laser acupuncture, in a randomized trial of 43 children with either migraine or tension type headache. The mean number of headaches per month decreased by 6.4 days in the treatment group, and by 1.0 day in the placebo group (p &lt; 0.001). Secondary outcomes of headache severity were likewise decreased, and were statistically significant at all time points [36]. Further studies are needed exploring the use of acupuncture as a prophylactic agent in the pediatric population, as well as studies which combine the use of a low dose prophylactic medication together with acupuncture. 4.1.4. Abdominal PainAbdominal pain can be due to a multitude of diagnoses, and a full review of these is beyond the scope of this work. We will first review the available adult literature on the use of acupuncture in the management of pain related to irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), a functional disorder characterized by chronic or recurrent abdominal pain or discomfort which is associated with disturbed bowel function, and feelings of abdominal distention and bloating [37]. Chao et al. performed a meta-analysis of 6 randomized placebo controlled studies [38]. Although five of the studies did not show statistically significant improvement, the one positive study in the group was a relatively large study [39], and thus the overall meta-analysis provided support for the use of acupuncture. A Cochrane review of acupuncture for IBS showed no benefit from acupuncture as compared to credible sham controlled therapies, however a comparative effectiveness trial of acupuncture compared to two antispasmodics (pinaverium bromide and trimebutin maleate) showed acupuncture as more effective than these standard therapies for IBS [40]. In a pediatric trial on children with intermittent abdominal pain that compared hand acupuncture to no treatment, hand acupuncture was shown to be effective [41]. As the trial was not blinded, however, the results are difficult to interpret. Further studies are needed to delineate whether there is clinical benefit of acupuncture in this condition, the necessary dose or frequency and duration of acupuncture treatment required, as well as possible mechanisms of action.4.1.5. Pediatric FibromyalgiaPediatric fibromyalgia is a poorly understood condition that affects 1%–6% of populations studied, and includes symptoms of general fatigue, disordered sleep, severe myofascial pain, and abdominal dysregulation [42]. The mechanisms of fibromyalgia pain are not fully understood, but may include genetic, anatomic, metabolic and psychosocial factors [43]. Acupuncture was found to change cortical responses to painful stimuli in fibromyalgia patients, suggesting a complex inhibitory modulation may be active in the central nervous system in fibromyalgia patients [44].In the adult population, acupuncture studies have demonstrated that acupuncture may be a significant adjunct in the care of fibromyalgia patients, and is superior to standard care alone [45]. It is noted however that sham acupuncture likewise appeared more effective than standard care, making it difficult to determine the specificity of the acupuncture needle placement in this study. Although acupuncture is routinely offered and utilized as a CAM therapy in pediatric pain clinics by patients with fibromyalgia, to date there have been no randomized controlled studies in the pediatric population [46]. Future acupuncture research in children with fibromyalgia should examine its benefits, comparative effectiveness, mechanism of action and necessary dose.4.1.6. Acupuncture for Juvenile ArthritisChildren with juvenile idiopathic arthritis (JIA) and other rheumatological conditions utilize CAM therapies regularly, with frequencies between 34% and 92% [47]. Factors associated with CAM use include longer disease duration, presence of more than one illness, previous CAM use by parents themselves, and parents’ perception that medications are not helping [48,49]. In adults, Berman et al., in a landmark randomized controlled study of osteoarthritis, found that the true acupuncture group experienced a greater improvement in WOMAC function at 8 weeks than the sham acupuncture group [50]; however, a subsequent meta-analysis of nine studies showed short-term benefits compared to sham, and clinically relevant benefits relative to wait-list control [51]. Zanette et al. studied 40 adults on a stable medication regimen with uncontrolled rheumatoid arthritis in a randomized controlled study. There was significant improvement in patient and physician global assessment and in physician assessment of disease activity in the acupuncture group, however the primary outcome of 20% improvement in ACR criteria was not statistically significant [52]. There are no studies in the literature evaluating the effect of acupuncture on juvenile arthritis. Studies are needed to explore the efficacy of acupuncture in pediatric rheumatological conditions.4.1.7. Pelvic PainAcupuncture has been shown to be effective in pain related to dysmenorrhea in multiple adult randomized clinical trials. Kiran et al. showed that acupuncture was as effective as NSAIDS in a small, randomized trial [53]. A Cochrane review concluded that acupuncture may be effective for dymenorrhea, however more studies were needed [54]. A study of acupressure in adolescents with dysmenorrhea showed a decrease in pain in the experimental group that was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.002) compared to the sham acupressure group [55]. Sham acupressure also had some effect of improved analgesia, however, thus a third control of standard care or other relatively inert control would have been beneficial and may have shown an even greater clinical significance. In a small randomized sham controlled pediatric study on pelvic pain due to endometriosis, Wayne et al. showed that participants experienced a 4.8 (SD 2.4) point reduction on a 11 point scale after 4 weeks, which differed significantly from the control group who experienced an average reduction of 1.4 (SD2.1) (p = 0.004). Reduction in pain persisted 6 months after intervention; however, after 4 weeks the differences were not clinically significant, suggesting continued acupuncture may be needed for a more prolonged therapeutic effect [56]. Further research is needed in pediatric patients with pelvic pain focusing on comparative effectiveness with standard treatments, dose efficacy and mechanism of action.4.1.8. Complex Regional Pain SyndromeLittle information exists regarding the treatment of Complex Regional Pain Syndrome (CRPS) with acupuncture. Several case reports in adult military personnel showed benefits in shoulder and hand CRPS following scalp acupuncture [57]. An adult case study involving laser acupuncture and small subcutaneous needles also proved to be effective [58]. In children, one case study describes the use of electrical stimulation at acupuncture points, while another describes the use of acupuncture in three pediatric patients leading to clinical improvement [59,60]. Further studies in children with complex regional pain syndrome, including scalp acupuncture, electrical stimulation and other specific protocols are needed to delineate whether there is measurable and reproducible benefit.4.1.9. Acupuncture for Cancer PainThe management of cancer pain presents a complex challenge for the oncologist and the pain practitioner. Pain may be due to acute tissue invasion, inflammation, bone pain, neuropathic pain, or a combination of causes [61]. In addition, cancer patients suffer from other chemotherapeutic side effects including nausea and vomiting. CAM therapies are frequently utilized by this population. A prevalence study of CAM use in children and adolescents with cancer in Germany found that 29% of children and 36% of adolescents used CAM therapies. Reasons for using CAM included strengthening the immune system, reduction of therapy-related side effects, and desire to increase healing chances [62]. Acupuncture was used by 12% of children and 17% of adolescents. In a randomized trial of acupuncture to alleviate chemotherapy related nausea and vomiting due to highly emetogenic chemotherapy, the need for rescue anti-emetics was significantly lower in the acupuncture group than in the control group (p &lt; 0.001) [63]. Episodes of vomiting were likewise lower in the treatment group (p = 0.01). Acupuncture was found to be safe in patients with thrombocytopenia due to chemotherapy [64]. 4.1.10. Acupuncture for Acute PainTwo studies have explored the use of acupuncture in the treatment of acute post-operative pain in pediatric patients. Wu et al. reported a case series of 20 pediatric patients, aged 7 months to 18 years, who had undergone various surgeries [65]. Acupuncture was performed in the post-operative period. Pain scores declined immediately following acupuncture, as well as at 24 hours after acupuncture was performed. The acupuncture was well tolerated, and 85% of parents reported they would pay for acupuncture “out of pocket” if not covered by insurance. This study was not controlled, however. Lin et al. performed a randomized trial examining pain and delirium in pediatric patients following tympanostomy surgery [66]. Sixty children were randomized to acupuncture or sham acupuncture following induction of anesthesia. Statistical differences in pain scores were observed in post anesthesia care unit at each five minute time point. Median pain scores were between 2 and 4 points lower than the sham acupuncture group. Postoperative agitation was also decreased, and showed statistical significance at all time points. Additional studies are needed to explore the magnitude of the clinical effect of various acupuncture treatments, duration of action, as well as post-operative opioid use and surgical recovery time.4.1.11. Acupuncture for Delirium, Agitation, Withdrawal and Emotional ConditionsSeveral studies exist on the use of acupuncture on post-traumatic stress disorder. Hollifield et al. found that acupuncture was as effective as cognitive behavioral therapy, and Zhang et al. found that acupoint stimulation together with cognitive behavioral therapy was more effective than cognitive behavioral therapy alone [67,68]. To date, no studies have been identified examining the efficacy of acupuncture in children with post traumatic stress disorder. Several studies specifically address the effect of acupuncture interventions on withdrawal and agitation in children. Wang et al. found that acupressure reduced anxiety in children undergoing anesthesia [69]. Kundu et al. performed a retrospective review of pediatric patients who had postoperative agitation on a previous anesthetic, and received acupuncture with a subsequent anesthetic [70]. 10 patients (83%) did not exhibit symptoms of agitation, while 2 (17%) exhibited milder symptoms but were able to communicate their distress. In a study of neonates with Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome (NAS), the addition of auricular acupressure beads did not result in a different clinical course, though there was a suggestive trend toward less pharmacological support in the acupressure group [71].4.1.12. Non-Invasive Transcutaneous Electrical Acupoint Stimulation (TEAS)As some pediatric patients, as well as some adults, may have a fear of needles, the use of transcutaneous electric acupoint stimulation (TEAS) may provide an alternative to conventional acupuncture treatments. The effectiveness of TENS may be mediated by alpha 2A adrenergic receptors [72]. A number of studies suggest that such stimulation may be clinically effective. Wang et al. showed that TEAS reduced intraoperative remifentanil consumption and alleviated post-operative side effects following sinusotomy [73]. TEAS was also applied by Kabalak for the management of postoperative vomiting following tonsillectomy in children in a randomized study [74]. In another randomized double blinded perioperative study, TEAS was applied at the start of surgery in patients undergoing pediatric cardiac surgery [75]. Duration of ventilation, and length of stay in ICU were significantly lower in the active treatment group. In addition, cardiac troponin, a measure of damaged cardiac tissue, was significantly lower in the active treatment group. As TEAS is a non-invasive technique, it has significant promise as a potential treatment in children.4.1.13. Non-Invasive Laser AcupunctureLaser acupuncture may also be utilized in the clinic for management of pain and discomfort in the pediatric patient. In addition to the headache study as mentioned above by Gottschling et al., others have demonstrated clinical utility. Ferreira et al. described a case report of improved trismus as a sequelae of medulobastoma in a child [76]. Other non-invasive therapies offered in pediatric pain clinics include moxibustion, cupping and acupressure magnets [77].4.2. Cost-Effectiveness of Acupuncture TherapyThis is a relatively new area of research, however, an National Health Service (NHS) analysis of low back pain studied in 239 patients, with 159 randomized to acupuncture and 80 to usual care, found that the addition of acupuncture to standard care led to improved pain both immediately after the treatments as well as at 24 months. Though the cost of delivering acupuncture in addition to standard care was an increase of expenditure, this cost was more than balanced by a reduction in lost days of work, and decreased medical spending in other areas including hospitalization, general practitioner or other outpatient visits. This suggests an overall societal benefit to supporting the provision of acupuncture services [77]. Further research is needed examining the cost-effectiveness of acupuncture in children in relation to lost parental work days, cost of medications, and other therapeutic interventions.5. ConclusionsAcupuncture techniques, both invasive and noninvasive, can be an important adjuvant in the care of the pediatric patient with chronic pain. Acupuncture should be performed by a trained professional, and should be incorporated in a multidisciplinary program of treatment, after appropriate workup has been performed. The evidence suggests that it is a safe and cost-effective treatment modality for pediatric pain. Further research is needed regarding the specific and non-specific effects of acupuncture, as well as mechanisms of action, dosing and frequency related to various painful conditions in pediatric patients.AcknowledgmentsThe authors wish to thank their respective Departments for continued support and encouragement in the investigation of the efficacy and mechanisms of action of acupuncture therapy. Author ContributionsBrenda Golianu contributed to the writing and editing of the manuscript. Ann Ming Yeh contributed to the writing and editing of the manuscript. Meredith Brooks contributed to the writing and editing of the manuscript.Conflicts of InterestThe authors declare no conflict of interest.References1.
Roth-IsigkeitA.ThyenU.StovenH.SchwarzenbergerJ.SchmuckerP.
Pain among children and adolescents: Restrictions in daily living and triggering factors
Pediatrics
2005
2
e152
e162
156874232.
YoungL.KemperK.J.
Integrative care for pediatric patients with pain
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2013
19
627
632
10.1089/acm.2012.0368
234481203.
Dallara LiberaD.ColomboB.PavanG.ComiG.
Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) use in an Italian cohort of pediatric headache patients: The tip of the iceberg
Neurol. Sci.
2014
35
145
148
248678524.
SchetzekS.HeinenF.KruseS.BorggraefeI.BonfertM.GaulC.GottschlingS.EbingerF.
Headache in children: Update on complementary treatments
Neuropediatrics
2013
44
25
33
233155555.
BasbaumA.I.BautistaD.M.ScherrerG.JuliusD.
Cellular and molecular mechanisms of pain
Cell
2009
139
267
284
198370316.
WoolfC.J.
Pain: Metabolites, mambas and mutations
Lancet Neurol.
2013
12
18
19
10.1016/S1474-4422(12)70287-9
232378967.
BalikiM.N.PetreB.TorbeyS.HerrmannK.M.HuangL.SchnitzerT.J.FieldsH.L.ApkarianA.V.
Corticostriatal functional connectivity predicts transition to chronic back pain
Nat. Neurosci.
2012
15
1117
1119
227510388.
NapadowV.AnhA.LonghurstJ.LaoL.Stener-VictorinE.HarrisR.LangevinH.M.
The status and future of acupuncture mechanism research
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2008
14
861
869
188034959.
HanJ.S.
Acupuncture: Neuropeptide release produced by electrical stimulation of different frequencies
Trends Neurosci.
2003
26
17
22
1249585810.
LangevinH.M.BouffardN.A.ChurchillD.L.BadgerG.J.
Connective tissue fibroblast response to acupuncture: Dose-dependent effect of bidirectional needle rotation
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2007
13
355
360
10.1089/acm.2007.6351
1748013711.
AhnA.C.SchnyerR.ConboyL.LauferM.R.WayneP.M.
Electrodermal measures of jing-well points and their clinical relevance in endometriosis-related chronic pelvic pain
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2009
15
1293
1305
10.1089/acm.2008.0597
1995813212.
HuiK.K.S.LiuJ.MarinaO.NapadowV.HaselgroveC.KwongK.K.KennedyD.M.MakrisN.
The integrated response of the human cerebro-cerebellar and limbic systems to acupuncture stimulation at ST36 as evidenced by fMRI
NeuroImage
2005
27
479
496
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.04.037
1604614613.
DhondR.P.YehC.ParkK.KettnerN.NapadowV.
Acupuncture modulates resting state connectivity in default and sensorimotor brain networks
Pain
2008
136
407
418
1833700914.
NapadowV.KettnerN.LiuJ.LiM.KwongK.K.VangelM.MakrisN.AudetteJ.HuiK.K.
Hypothalamus and amygdala response to acupuncture stimuli in carpal tunnel syndrome
Pain
2007
130
254
266
1724006615.
WangS.M.KainZ.N.WhiteP.
Acupuncture Analgesia: I. The scientific basis
Anesthesia Analgesia
2008
106
602
610
1822732216.
NIH consensus conference: Acupuncture
JAMA
1998
280
1518
1524
10.1213/ane.0b013e318160644d
9809733
WangS.M.HarrisR.E.LinY.C.GanT.J.
Acupuncture in 21st century anesthesia: Is there a needle in the haystack?
Anesthesia Analgesia
2013
116
1356
1359
10.1213/ane.0b013e318160644d
2370907517.
WangS.M.KainZ.N.WhiteP.
Acupuncture analgesia: II. Clinical considerations
Anesthesia Analgesia
2008
106
611
621
10.1213/ane.0b013e318160644d
1822732318.
HaakeM.MullerH.H.BrittingerC.
German acupuncture trials (GERAC) for chronic low back pain
Arch. Intern. Med.
2007
167
1892
1898
1789331119.
LangevinH.M.WayneP.M.MacPhersonH.SchnyerR.MilleyM.R.NapadowV.LaoL.ParkJ.HarrisR.E.CohenM.
Paradoxes in acupuncture research: strategies for moving forward
J. Evid. Based Complementary Altern. Med.
2011
10.1155/2011/180805
20.
MacPhersonH.MaschinoA.C.LewithG.FosterN.E.WittC.VickersA.J.
Characteristics of acupuncture treatment associated with outcome: An individual patient meta-analysis of 17,922 patients with chronic pain in randomized controlled trials
PLoS ONE
2013
10.1371/journal.pone.0077438
21.
ZeltzerL.K.TsaoJ.C.I.StellingC.PowersM.WaterhouseM.
A phase I study on the feasibility and acceptability of an acupuncture/hypnosis intervention for chronic pediatric pain
J. Pain Symptom Manage.
2002
24
437
446
10.1016/S0885-3924(02)00506-7
1250521322.
LinY.BioteauA.B.LeeA.C.
Acupuncture for the management of pediatric pain
Acupuncture Med.
2003
14
45
46
23.
KemperK.J.SarahR.Silver-HighfieldE.XiarhosE.BarnesL.BerdeC.
On pins and needles? Pediatric pain patients’ experience with acupuncture
Pediatrics
2000
105
941
947
1074235124.
GoldJ.I.NicolauC.D.BelmontK.A.KatzA.R.BenaronD.M.YuW.
Pediatric Acupunct
2009
6
429
439
25.
Jastrowski ManoK.E.DaviesH.
Parental attitudes toward acupuncture in a community sample
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2009
15
661
668
10.1089/acm.2008.0449
1948970526.
MeyerR.M.L.BarberB.A.KobyleckaM.GoldJ.I.
Examining the association between parental stress related to child illness and child pain across acupuncture treatments
Med. Acupunct.
2014
26
23
30
10.1089/acu.2013.1008
27.
AdamsD.ChengF.JouH.AungS.YasuiY.VohraS.
The safety of pediatric acupuncture: A systematic review
Pediatrics
2011
128
e1575
e1587
10.1542/peds.2011-1091
2210607328.
YatesC.C.MitchellA.LoweL.M.LeeA.HallR.W.
Safety of noninvasive electrical stimulation of acupuncture points during a routine neonatal heel stick
Med. Acupunct.
2013
25
285
290
10.1089/acu.2012.0952
2476117829.
AllaisG.de LorenzoC.QuiricoP.AirolaG.TolardoG.ManaO.BenedettoC.
Acupuncture in the prophylactic treatment of migraine without aura: a comparison with flumarizine
Headache
2002
42
855
861
1239061030.
DienerH.C.KronfeldK.BoewingG.LungenhausenM.MaierC.MolsbergerA.TegenthoffM.TrampischH.J.ZenzM.MeinertR.
Efficacy of acupuncture for the prophylaxis of migraine: a multicentre randomized controlled clinical trial
Lancet Neurol.
2006
5
310
316
10.1016/S1474-4422(06)70382-9
1654574731.
LindeK.StrengA.HoppeA.WeidenhammerW.WagenpfeilS.MelchartD.
Randomized trial vs. observational study of acupuncture for migraine found that patient characteristics differed but outcomes were similar
J. Clin. Epidemiol.
2007
60
280
287
10.1016/j.jclinepi.2006.06.014
1729202232.
LindeK.AllaisG.BrinkhausB.ManheimerE.VickersA.WhiteA.R.
Acupuncture for migraine prophylaxis
Cochrane Lib.
2009
10.1002/14651858.CD001218
33.
LindeK.AllaisG.BrinkhausB.ManheimerE.VickersA.WhiteA.R.
Acupuncture for tension-type headache
Cochrane Lib.
2009
10.1002/14651858.CD007587
34.
PintovS.LahatE.AlsteinM.VogelA.BargJ.
Acupuncture and the opioid system: Implications in management of migraine
Pediatr. Neurol.
1997
17
129
133
10.1016/S0887-8994(97)00086-6
936729235.
GottschlingS.MeyerS.GribovaI.DistlerL.BerrangJ.GortnerL.GrafN.ShamdeenM.G.
Laser acupuncture in children with headache: A double-blind, randomized, bicenter, placebo-controlled trial
Pain
2008
137
405
412
1802231836.
LongstrethG.F.ThompsonW.G.CheyW.D.HoughtonL.A.MearinR.SpillerR.C.
Functional bowel disorders
Gastroenterology
2006
130
1480
1491
1667856137.
ChaoG.Q.ZhangS.
Effectiveness of acupuncture to treat irritable bowel syndrome: A meta-analysis
World J. Gastroenterol.
2014
20
1871
1877
10.3748/wjg.v20.i7.1871
2458766538.
MacphersonH.TilbrookH.BlandJ.M.BloorK.BrabynS.CoxH.Kang’ombeA.R.ManM.S.StuardiT.TorgersonD.
Acupuncture for irritable bowel syndrome: primary care based pragmatic randomized controlled trial
BMC Gastroenterol.
2012
12
150
2309537639.
ManheimerE.ChengK.WielandL.S.MinL.S.ShenX.BermanB.H.LaoL.
Acupuncture for treatment of irritable bowel syndrome
Cochrane Lib.
2012
10.1002/14651858.CD005111.pub3.review
40.
HongY.
The effects of hand-acupuncture therapy on intermittent abdominal pain in children
Taehan Kanho Hakhoe Chi
2005
35
487
93
1602750041.
BuskilaD.AblinJ.
Pediatric fibromyalgia
Rheumatismo
2012
64
230
237
42.
AnthonyK.K.ShanbergL.E.
Juvenile primary fibromyalgia syndrome
Curr. Rheumatology Rep.
2001
3
165
171
10.1007/s11926-001-0012-7
43.
TommasoM.DelussiM.RicciK.D’AngeloG.
Abdominal acupuncture changes cortical responses to nociceptive stimuli in fibromyalgia patients
CNS Neurosci. Ther.
2014
20
565
567
10.1111/cns.12280
2483674144.
CaoH.J.LiX.HanM.LiuJ.
Acupuncture stimulation for fibromyalgia: A systematic review of randomized controlled trials
J. Evid. Based Complementary Altern. Med.
2013
10.1155/2013/362831
45.
TsaoJ.C.I.MeldrumM.KimS.C.JacobM.C.ZeltzerL.K.
Treatment preferences for CAM in Children with Chronic Pain
Electron. Centralised Aircr. Monit.
2007
4
367
374
46.
ToupinA.K.WaljiR.
The state of research on complementary and alternative medicine in pediatric rheumatology
Rheumatic Dis. Clin. N. Am.
2011
37
85
94
10.1016/j.rdc.2010.11.011
47.
HagenL.E.SchneiderR.StephensD.ModrusanD.FeldmanB.M.
Use of complementary and alternative medicine by pediatric rheumatology patients
Arthritis Rheumatol.
2003
49
3
6
10.1002/art.10931
48.
AprilK.T.EhrmannF.D.ZunzuneguiM.V.DescarreauxM.MallesonP.DuffyC.M.
Longitudinal analysis of complementary and alternative health care use in children with juvenile idiopathic arthritis
Complement. Ther. Med.
2009
17
208
215
10.1016/j.ctim.2009.03.003
1963254849.
BermanB.M.LaoL.X.LangenbergP.LeeW.L.GilpinA.M.HochbergM.C.
Effectiveness of acupuncture as adjunctive therapy in osteoarthritis of the knee
Ann. Internal Med.
2004
141
901
910
10.7326/0003-4819-141-12-200412210-00006
1561148750.
ManheimerE.LindeK.LaoL.X.BouterL.M.BermanB.M.
Meta-analysis: Acupuncture for osteoarthritis of the knee
Ann. Internal Med.
2007
146
868
877
10.7326/0003-4819-146-12-200706190-00008
1757700651.
ZanetteS. de A.BornI.G.BrenolJ.C.XavierR.M.
A pilot study of acupuncture as adjunctive treatment of rheumatoid arthritis
Clin. Rheumatol.
2008
27
627
635
10.1007/s10067-007-0759-y
1798991852.
KiranG.GumusalanY.EkerbicerH.C.KiranH.CoskunA.ArikanD.C.
A randomized pilot study of acupuncture treatment for primary dysmenorrhea
Eur. J. Obstetrics Gynecology Reproductive Biol.
2013
169
292
295
10.1016/j.ejogrb.2013.02.016
53.
SmithC.A.ZhuX.HeL.SongJ.
Acupuncture for primary dymenorrhoea
Cochrane Rev.
2011
10.1002/14651858.CD007854.pub2
54.
YehM.L.HungY.L.ChenH.H.WangY.J.
Auricular acupressure for pain relief in adolescents with dysmenorrhoea: A placebo controlled study
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2013
19
313
318
10.1089/acm.2011.0665
2313094355.
WayneP.M.KerrC.E.SchnyerR.N.LegedzaA.T.Savetsky-GermanJ.ShieldsM.H.BuringJ.E.DavisR.B.ConboyL.A.HighfieldE.
Japanese-style acupuncture for endometriosis-related pelvic pain in adolescents and young women: results of a randomized sham-controlled trial
J. Pediatr. Adolescent Gynecol.
2008
212
47
57
56.
HommerD.H.
Chinese scalp acupuncture relieves pain and restores function in complex regional pain syndrome
Mil. Med.
2012
177
1231
1234
10.7205/MILMED-D-12-00193
2311345457.
SpragueM.ChangJ.C.
Integrative approach focusing on acupuncture in the treatment of chronic complex regional pain syndrome
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2011
17
67
70
10.1089/acm.2010.0088
2120813058.
LeoK.C.
Use of electrical stimulation at acupuncture points for the treatment of reflex sympathetic dystrophy in a child: A case report
J. Phys. Thermophys.
1983
63
957
959
59.
KellyA.
Treatment of reflex sympathetic dystrophy in 3 pediatric patients using 7 external dragons
J. Med. Acup.
2004
15
29
30
60.
FalkS.DickensonA.H.
Pain and nociception: Mechanisms of cancer-induced bone pain
J. Clin. Oncol.
2014
32
1647
1654
10.1200/JCO.2013.51.7219
2479946961.
GottschlingS.MeyerS.LanglerA.ScharifiG.EbingerF.GronwaldB.
Differences in use of complementary and alternative medicine between children and adolescents with cancer in Germany: A population based survey
Pediatr. Blood Cancer
2014
61
488
492
10.1002/pbc.24769
2403886462.
GottschlingS.ReindlT.K.MeyerS.BerrangJ.HenzeG.GraeberS.OngM.F.GrafN.
Acupuncture to alleviate chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in pediatric oncology—a randomized multicenter crossover pilot trial
Klin. Padiatr.
2008
220
365
370
1894967263.
LadasE.J.RooneyD.TarominaK.NdaoD.H.KellyK.M.
The safety of acupuncture in children and adolescents with cancer therapy-related thrombocytopenia
Supportive Care Cancer
2010
18
1487
1490
64.
WuS.SapruA.StewartM.A.MiletM.J.HudesM.LivermoreL.F.FloriH.R.
Using acupuncture for acute pain in hospitalized children
Pediatr. Crit. Care Med.
2009
10
291
296
1930780865.
LinY.C.TassoneR.F.JahngS.RahbarR.HolzmanR.S.ZurakowskiD.SethnaN.
Acupuncture management of pain and emergence agitation in children after bilateral myringotomy and tympanostomy tube insertion
Pediatr. Anesthesia
2009
19
1096
1101
10.1111/j.1460-9592.2009.03129.x
66.
HollifieldM.Sinclair-LianN.WarnerT.D.HammerschlagR.
Acupuncture for posttraumatic stress disorder: A randomized controlled pilot trial
J. Nerv. Mental Dis.
2007
195
504
513
10.1097/NMD.0b013e31803044f8
67.
ZhangY.FengB.XieJ.P.XuF.Z.ChenJ.
Clinical study on treatment of the earthquake-caused post-traumatic stress disorder by cognitive-behavior therapy and acupoint stimulation
J. Trad. Chin. Med.
2011
31
60
63
68.
WangS.M.EscaleraS.LinE.C.MaranetsI.KainZ.N.
Extra-1 acupressure for children undergoing anesthesia
Anesthesia Analgesia
2008
107
811
816
10.1213/ane.0b013e3181804441
1871388969.
KunduA.JimenezN.LynnA.
Acupuncture therapy for prevention of emergence delirium in children undergoing general anesthesia
Med. Acupunct.
2008
20
151
154
10.1089/acu.2008.0615
70.
SchwartzL.XiaoR.BrownE.R.SommersE.
Auricular acupressure augmentation of standard medical management of the neonatal Narcotic Abstinence Syndrome
Med. Acupunct.
2011
23
175
186
71.
KingE.W.AudetteK.AthmanG.A.NguyenH.O.SlukaK.A.FairbanksC.A.
Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation activates peripherally located alpha-2A adrenergic receptors
Pain
2005
115
364
373
1591116372.
WangH.XieY.ZhangQ.XuN.ZhongH.DongH.LiuL.JiangT.WangQ.XiongL.
Transcutaneous electric acupoint stimulation reduced intra-operative remifentanil consumption and alleviates postoperative side-effects in patients undergoing sinusotomy: A prospective, randomized, placebo-controlled trial
Br. J. Anaesthesia
2014
112
1075
1082
10.1093/bja/aeu001
73.
KabalakA.A.AkcayM.AkcayF.GogusK.
Transcutaneous electrical acupoint stimulation versus ondansetron in the prevention of postoperative vomiting following pediatric tonsillectomy
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
2005
11
407
413
10.1089/acm.2005.11.407
1599222374.
NiX.XieY.WangQ.ZhongH.ChenM.WangF.XiongL.
Cardioprotective effect of transcutaneous electric acupoint stimulation in the pediatric cardiac patients: a randomized controlled clinical trial
Pediatr. Anesthesia
2012
22
805
811
10.1111/j.1460-9592.2012.03822.x
75.
ChiH.ZhouW.X.WuY.Y.ChenT.Y.GeW.YuanL.ShenW.D.ZhouJ.
Electroacupuncture intervention combined with general anesthesia for 80 cases of heart valve replacement surgery under cardiopulmonary bypass
Zhen Ci Yan Jiu
2013
39
1
6
2468410376.
FerreiraD.C.DeRossiA.TorresC.P.GaloR.Paula-SilvaF.W.QueirozA.M.
Effect of laser acupuncture and auricular acupressure in a child with trismus as a sequel of medulloblastoma
Acupunct. Med.
2013
32
190
193
2438454177.
ThomasK.H.MacPhersonH.RatcliffeJ.ThorpeL.BrazierJ.CampbellM.FitterM.RomanM.
Longer term clinical and economic benefits of offering acupuncture care to patients with chronic low back pain
Health Technol. Assess.
2005
9
1
109

