<?xml version="1.0"?>
Schizophr Res TreatmentSchizophr Res TreatmentSPRTSchizophrenia Research and Treatment2090-20852090-2093Hindawi Publishing Corporation34206012296644710.1155/2012/815315Review ArticleNeurocognitive and Social Cognitive Approaches for Improving Functional Outcome in Early Psychosis: Theoretical Considerations and Current State of EvidenceBartholomeuszCali F.
1
*AllottKelly
2
1Melbourne Neuropsychiatry Centre, Department of Psychiatry, National Neuroscience Facility, The University of Melbourne, Level 2-3 Alan Gilbert Building, 161 Barry Street, Carlton South, VIC 3053, Australia2Orygen Youth Health Research Centre, Centre for Youth Mental Health, The University of Melbourne, Locked Bag 10, Parkville, VIC 3052, Australia*Cali F. Bartholomeusz: barc@unimelb.edu.auAcademic Editor: César González-Blanch20125420122012815315151020112512012Copyright © 2012 C. F. Bartholomeusz and K. Allott.2012This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Improving functional outcome, in addition to alleviating psychotic symptoms, is now a major treatment objective in schizophrenia research. Given the large body of evidence suggesting pharmacological treatments generally have minimal effects on indices of functioning, research has turned to psychosocial rehabilitation programs. Among these, neurocognitive and social cognitive interventions are at the forefront of this field and are argued to target core deficits inherent to the schizophrenia illness. However, to date, research trials have primarily focused on chronic schizophrenia populations, neglecting the early psychosis groups who are often as severely impaired in social and occupational functioning. This theoretical paper will outline the rationale for investigating adjunctive cognitive-based interventions in the early phases of psychotic illness, critically examine the current approach strategies used in these interventions, and assess the evidence supporting certain training programs for improving functional outcome in early psychosis. Potential pathways for future research will be discussed.1. IntroductionThe field of schizophrenia research and treatment is in a transitional phase, shifting from a focus on outcomes that are measured by symptomatic remission and basic illness management to an all-encompassing outlook on real-world functional recovery [1, 2]. This is an exciting time for researchers and consumers, as the improvement in social, occupational, and personally challenging activities that impact the individual's day-to-day living are now primary research objectives. In this research era it is also widely acknowledged that the early phase of a psychotic illness, known as the “critical period,” is the most crucial in terms of limiting or even preventing the development of disability, with maximal levels of disability reached within the first 5 years after illness onset [3]. The first onset of psychosis typically occurs between the age of 18 and 24 [4], although prodromal symptoms are often detectable in the adolescent years [5]. There is a paucity of research that has focused investigation on the “functional” outcome of this early psychosis cohort. A systematic review of 37 early detection/intervention studies in first-episode psychosis (FEP) found that 42% of patients had “good” illness outcomes as opposed to 27% who had “poor” outcomes at an average of 3-year follow-up [6]. However, outcome was predominantly defined by hospital readmission or change in symptom severity, with only 4 of the 37 studies reporting functional recovery. Another review, which specifically focused on social, role/occupational, and community functioning, found long-term functional outcome to be poor for a substantial proportion of FEP patients [7]. Furthermore, two randomized controlled trials (RCTs) of intensive therapy, involving multidisciplinary teams offering a mixture of cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT), family therapy, vocational interventions, and social skills training, failed to find significant changes in the size of patients' social network [8, 9] or the amount of contact with existing friends [8]. In addition, although the latter study found more patients in the intensive therapy group (49%) to have spent at least 6 months in educational/vocational activities, a large percentage of patients who were considerably impaired in their role functioning at the 18-month follow-up remained. Overall, findings support early intervention strategies as key to the treatment and prevention of psychotic disorders, which has shown significant benefits over more traditional approaches [10]. However, this biopsychosocial approach [11] is largely ineffective for the treatment of social impairment, highlighting the need for innovative intervention strategies targeting functional outcome.This paper will examine the evidence and potential for neurocognitive and social cognitive interventions in addressing the issue of functional recovery in early psychosis. With the impetus that cognitive deficits are at the core of schizophrenia [12], this paper will only include interventions that have a neurocognitive or social cognitive target; thus, interventions that focus primarily on changing behaviour, such as social skills training (SST) and cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT), will not be addressed here (for review of other interventions see [13]). For this review, the term “neurocognition” will be used to refer to elementary cognitive abilities (e.g., memory, attention, etc.) and remediation/therapies that are neurocognitive based. “Social cognition” which encompasses the perception, interpretation, and processing of social information, will refer to purely social cognitive abilities, primarily, emotion perception (recognition of facial and vocal affect); social perception and social knowledge (the ability to detect and comprehend social cues with respect to social context); Theory of Mind (ToM; the mental capacity to infer one's own and others' mental states); attributional style (tendencies in explaining the cause of events, i.e. to the self, others or the environment) [14]. The term “cognition” will be used to encompass both neurocognition and social cognition. We will first provide a rationale for focusing on cognition by drawing on evidence supporting the neurodevelopmental hypothesis and the link between cognition and functional outcome. This paper will then highlight the differences in the theoretical underpinnings of the available interventions, in addition to reviewing original research that has tested the effects of such interventions on functional outcome in FEP or ultra high-risk (UHR) of psychosis samples. Discussion surrounding future pathways for achieving real-world improvements in social and occupational functioning will be provided, within the context of the early phase of illness.2. Why Focus on Cognitive-Based Interventions?3. Background of Cognitive Intervention Programs in SchizophreniaCognitive remediation is the most common form of the cognitive-based interventions used in schizophrenia and has recently been defined as “a behavioural training based intervention that aims to improve cognitive processes (attention, memory, executive function, social cognition or metacognition) with the goal of durability and generalization” [72, page 1]. This definition implies that although dysfunction in cognition, including social cognition, is the intervention target, improved and sustained functioning in the real world is the desired outcome [73]. It should be noted that, although social cognition is included in the above definition, the majority of cognitive remediation programs to date have predominantly targeted neurocognitive processes. The approaches used in cognitive remediation are highly variable, but a clear common element is repeated practice in exercises requiring effortful “thinking skills.” The majority of programs also involve a trained facilitator (see [74] for exception). However, the frequency and duration of training sessions is inconsistent, as is whether the intervention is delivered one-on-one or involves a group-based component.Numerous systematic reviews of neurocognitive remediation have been published, but the first quantitative meta-analysis (26 studies) to examine the effects of neurocognitive remediation on functional outcome found a small-to-medium mean ES of 0.36, which was only slightly lower than the improvement found in neurocognitive function (mean ES 0.41) [75]. Interestingly, the effect of neurocognitive remediation on functioning was significantly moderated by whether or not adjunctive psychosocial rehabilitation, such as vocational programs or SST, was provided, with the finding that provision of psychosocial rehabilitation led to significant improvements in social functioning (mean ES 0.47). In comparison, studies of neurocognitive remediation alone produced a meagre mean ES of 0.05. These findings were broadly replicated in an updated meta-analysis that included 40 RCTs, although the effect sizes were slightly larger [72]. The mechanism for this “synergistic” effect is hypothesised to be the improved neurocognitive functioning produced by neurocognitive remediation enhancing the capacity to learn new skills, which in turn leads to increased benefit from psychiatric rehabilitation [75]. However, this hypothesis requires further empirical investigation, such as examination of whether change in cognition is associated with change in functioning.Because social cognitive neuropsychiatric research is in its infancy, social cognitive interventions are considered to be a relatively new line of treatment for improving social functioning. The primary goal of such interventions is to enhance social cognitive abilities, which as mentioned earlier, are considered to be largely independent constructs to neurocognitive processes. Social cognitive interventions typically employ a model that is bidirectional and flexible, where social cognitive processes, emotions, and actions are addressed in unison or in parallel, as opposed to a pure bottom-up information-processing framework characteristic of some neurocognitive interventions. Due to the limited research into social cognitive interventions, fewer reviews have been conducted. The most commanding review to date is a recent meta-analysis of 19 controlled trials of social cognitive training in established schizophrenia [76]. A large mean ES (0.78) was found for observer-rated indices of functional outcome (6 of the 19 studies), which in contrast to the neurocognition meta-analyses was larger than most of the ESs found for specific domains of social cognition. This finding is impressive given that the social cognitive interventions reviewed led to generalised improvements in functioning mostly in the absence of adjunctive psychosocial interventions. It has been suggested that the mediating role of social cognition between neurocognition and functional outcome implies that social cognition is more proximal to real-world functioning. Thus, targeting social cognition may produce greater effects on functioning than neurocognition [77].Given that this paper is focused specifically on early psychosis, it is important to explore whether age or stage of illness may be a key moderator of outcome in trials of cognitive remediation. With respect to participant age as a moderator, the existing research is equivocal. The McGurk et al. [75] meta-analysis found that older patients (aged 38–50 years) benefited more from neurocognitive remediation in terms of functioning (mean ES 0.55) than younger patients (aged 15–37 years; mean ES 0.18). However, it should be noted that the younger patient group included a wide age range and likely included patients with a long duration of illness. The more recent meta-analysis by Wykes et al. [72] found that age did not moderate outcome, but it was unclear as to whether this included functional outcome. Conversely, the Kurtz and Richardson [76] meta-analysis found that age was negatively correlated with functional (and symptomatic) outcome, such that younger patients (youngest mean age was 25 years) benefited more from social cognition training than older patients, although exact age ranges were not stated. Some studies have suggested that illness stage (e.g., first-versus multiple-episode) or duration of illness affects responses to cognitive remediation, but again findings are mixed. Longer illness duration is associated with poorer response to neurocognitive remediation [78–82], but better response to social cognitive remediation [76]. Despite the majority of studies to date having recruited patients with longstanding psychotic disorders, evidence from neuroimaging and behavioural research discussed earlier suggests that intervening in the early stages of psychosis may provide greater potential for recovery to premorbid levels, when individuals are less removed from their original functional trajectories.4. Current Approaches for Treating Cognitive DeficitsHaving briefly reviewed the evidence for cognitive remediation in schizophrenia, the paper will now turn to describing the specific approaches used and their theoretical underpinnings.5. Effects of Neurocognitive Interventions on Functional Outcome in Early Psychosis6. Effects of Social Cognitive Interventions on Functional Outcome in Early PsychosisDue to the more recent inception of social cognition in the field of schizophrenia research, no published literature to date has investigated a social cognitive intervention program in a UHR or FEP cohort. Despite this, the meta-analysis of chronic schizophrenia studies mentioned earlier provides very promising findings [76]. We will briefly review the available interventions that have been trialed in established schizophrenia, with reference to their impact on functional outcome and applicability in early psychosis.Social Cognition and Interaction Training (SCIT), developed by Penn et al. [130], is probably the most evidence-based stand-alone social cognitive intervention currently available. SCIT is a manualised 20-week (1 session/week) group-based intervention targeting multiple aspects of social cognition. SCIT employs a range of approaches including behavioural learning (and at times strategy coaching), metacognitive training, role-play, and exposure therapy techniques. There are three phases: (1) emotion training, which focuses on defining emotions, emotion mimicry, and understanding paranoia, (2) figuring out situations, which focuses on distinguishing facts from guesses, jumping to conclusions, and understanding bad events, and (3) integration, which encourages participants to “check it out” or apply their newly acquired social cognitive skills to personal real-life situations. A small trial that compared SCIT (n = 18) to a coping skills group (n = 10; which focused on problem-solving, symptom management, and relapse prevention) found SCIT to be significantly more effective at improving performance on measures of social and emotion perception, ToM, and attributional style [111]. Aggressive behaviour, patient's need for closure, and social relationships also improved with SCIT. Moreover, social functioning (as assessed with the Social Functioning Scales: engagement and interpersonal [131]) improved significantly, independent of changes in psychopathology. A more recent trial of SCIT in an outpatient setting has yielded similar positive results [132]. These successful trials led to the integration of the SCIT program into standard clinical practice within mental health services around New York [133]. Given the SCIT model emphasizes that performance varies as a function of the personal relevance and emotional tone of the social context and ultimately aims to improve day-to-day living, our research team has adapted SCIT to be suitable for young people with emerging psychosis. A pilot study in a FEP sample is currently underway.Emotion and ToM Imitation Training (ETIT) [134] is one of the other few social cognition interventions that have been found to enhance functional outcome. This is a 12-week group-based program, involving participants imitating emotional facial expressions in the mirror, tracking eye-gaze of others, and observing pictures of art, sketches, and comic strips depicting social scenarios with the aim of enhancing the ability to infer mental states of others and attribution of intentions. ETIT stems from the mirror neuron theory of imitation [135], thus relies heavily on the mimicry approach, but also uses coaching and role-play techniques. A small RCT found that schizophrenia patients in the ETIT group (n = 16) improved significantly on multiple aspects of social cognition, but also on a global measure of personal and social functioning, in comparison to individuals in a problem solving skills training group (n = 17) [134]. To our knowledge no follow-up studies or trials in an early psychosis population have been published.There are several other targeted and broad-based social cognitive interventions that have been developed and trialed in schizophrenia, but to date most have conducted limited assessment of functional outcome. However, as found by Kurtz and Richardson [76], significant effects on functioning are emerging. One of the programs available for possible use in FEP samples is Social Cognition Enhancement Training (SCET) developed by Kwon [136] and modified by Choi and Kwon [137]. This is a 6-month (36 session) group-based program consisting of three phases (elementary, middle, and advanced), each with 12 sessions. The use of cartoon stories is a central feature of SCET, which aid in the learning of social cue perception, context appraisal, and social knowledge. Additional techniques used are psychoeducation, behavioural learning approaches, and exposure to social situations via group work. Other programs include MCT (described earlier) and a similar intervention devised by Roncone et al. [138], Training of Affect Recognition (TAR) [139], and Ekman's Micro-Expression Training Tool (METT) [140], but comprehensive studies are lacking, even in established schizophrenia [76]. Nevertheless, these interventions and various techniques may still hold potential for enhancing social and other areas of functioning. However, larger studies that include functioning as a primary outcome across different illness stages are required before any inferences can be made.7. Conclusions and Future DirectionsThe literature is clearly lacking in the area of early psychosis, with only four studies having trialed a cognitive intervention, and these were primarily focused on neurocognition as opposed social cognition. With respect to functional outcome, the most successful of these appeared to be CET. However, as discussed, the CET trial had significant limitations. These included the control group being unmatched for nonspecific treatment effects and raters not being blind to group allocation, making it difficult to draw firm conclusions regarding the potency of specific aspects of the intervention (i.e., neurocognitive versus social cognitive remediation). Furthermore, participants were not representative of traditional early psychosis samples.Our review revealed that there are currently no published data available on the efficacy of an exclusive social cognitive intervention in an early psychosis sample. This is noteworthy, given that the behavioural evidence, discussed earlier, and the quantitative review revealing larger effects of social cognitive training on functioning relative to reviews of cognitive remediation in established schizophrenia [76], points towards social cognition as having a greater impact on functional outcome than neurocognition.In summary, it is presently impossible to make any definitive conclusions regarding the usefulness of cognitive-based interventions in the treatment of functional disability for this early illness population.While there is evidence that cognitive interventions lead to significant moderate improvements in specific cognitive abilities for individuals with established schizophrenia, residual cognitive deficits often remain [72, 75]. It has been previously suggested that there may be a ceiling to the effects of cognitive remediation at least when delivered in isolation [92]. At present, it is unclear how much improvement in cognition is enough to lead to significant functional improvements, whether stand-alone cognitive interventions are sufficient, or even whether improvement in cognition is essential for functional recovery. Furthermore, it is entirely possible that psychosocial programs that only target functioning may improve cognition, in the absence of a program specifically aimed at treating cognitive deficits [141]. These points open a number of important avenues for future research, with the overarching question being how do we optimize functional outcome?Starting with evidence from neurocognitive interventions, the schizophrenia literature indicates that neurocognitive remediation combined with psychosocial rehabilitation is far superior with respect to functional outcome than when cognitive remediation is delivered alone [72, 75], yet apart from the Ueland and Rund [124] study, no other trials combining psychosocial with cognitive approaches have been completed in early psychosis, although at least two others are currently underway [142, 143]. One RCT proposes to combine Multifamily Group Psychoeducation with neurocognitive remediation using the PSSCogRehab computer program (drill and practice approach), with the primary outcome being relapse rates. Secondary outcomes include functioning in social, vocational, and activities of daily living domains and quality of life in patients with recent-onset psychosis [143]. Another RCT (NEUROCOM study) will recruit FEP patients and randomize them to receive a combination of cognitive training with a comprehensive psychosocial program (OPUS) or OPUS alone, with the primary outcome being everyday functional capacity [142]. In this study the cognitive training will comprise a combination of computer-assisted drill-and-practice exercises and strategy coaching as well as teaching compensatory strategies (e.g., calendar use). The outcomes of these studies will be very informative.Despite the lack of early psychosis research into the combined intervention approach, Integrated Psychological Therapy (IPT) [144] has been extensively investigated in established schizophrenia and warrants discussion. IPT is a manualised group-based intervention that aims to ameliorate cognitive impairment and social behavioural deficits, with the ultimate goal of improving social competence [145]. It involves 30–60 min sessions three times per week for 3 months and comprises 5 hierarchically arranged subprograms targeting cognitive differentiation, social perception, verbal communication, social skills, and interpersonal problem solving. Meta-analysis of 30 IPT studies (7 of which were RCTs) showed that IPT compared to a control condition or TAU was more effective for enhancing neurocognition (mean ES 0.41), psychosocial functioning (mean ES 0.31), and psychopathology (mean 0.31) [146]. The largest effect was on neurocognition, which is not surprising given IPT is heavily focused on this domain. Not only do the findings support the combined approach as putatively superior to stand-alone interventions, but further implicate the importance of early intervention, given that duration of illness was the only negative predictor on the global therapy outcome of IPT.One question that cannot be answered from these combination studies is whether targeting neurocognition or social cognition will be more fruitful regarding functional outcome, and furthermore, which approach strategies/techniques or combination of techniques are likely to have the biggest impact on functioning. We suggest that social cognitive interventions, which typically rely on approaches such as metacognitive learning, didactic teaching and exposure techniques via group-based therapy, hold promise for producing robust effects on functional outcome, but to reiterate they are yet to be trialed in early psychosis. Furthermore, while some neurocognitive approaches have been trialed in early psychosis, others have not. For example, evidence suggests that compensatory approaches may play an important role in maximizing functional recovery, and indeed, large effects (&gt;0.80) have been found in individual studies of chronic schizophrenia populations [89, 91, 147]. Head-to-head studies of the various cognitive interventions are required to tease out the most effective techniques.A recent elegant study by Horan and colleagues [77] attempted to address this. After trialing a modified version of SCIT [148], Horan et al. developed the Social Cognitive Skills Training (SCST) program comprising 24 sessions. This program is similar to SCIT in that it targets emotional processing, social perception, attributional bias and mentalising skills with the primary aim of enabling participants to become more proficient in social interacting. Schizophrenia outpatients were randomized to receive either SCST (n = 16), computerized neurocognitive remediation (n = 19; exercises developed by PositScience), standard skills training (n = 19), or a hybrid of SCST and neurocognitive remediation (n = 14) [77]. Groups were matched for session number and time with the therapist. This was the first study to directly examine the effects of combining a social cognitive with a neurocognitive intervention and is also the first study to conduct a well-controlled head-to-head comparison of neurocognitive versus social cognitive remediation. The SCST was more successful in treating deficits in facial affect recognition, when compared to the neurocognitive remediation and standard skills training groups, as well as emotion management, when compared to the neurocognitive remediation and the hybrid groups. The hybrid group, in comparison to the three other groups, improved significantly on the measure of attributional bias. For other social cognitive and neurocognitive measures there were general improvements, but these did not differ between treatment groups. There were no significant improvements on the measures of functional outcome in any group, although a positive trend was observed for both the SCST and the neurocognitive remediation groups on a measure of social competence. The findings suggest SCST as a stand-alone treatment can enhance emotion processing, but functioning was unaffected. However, group numbers were small, and authors suggested that integration sessions conducted within the community may lead to better skill retention and generalisation, but this requires further investigation. It should also be noted that the neurocognitive remediation program was a prototype and appeared to use only the drill and practice approach without utilizing complimentary techniques such as strategy coaching. Furthermore, participants were compensated for attending training sessions, making it difficult to determine the true participant acceptability of the different approaches.While Horan et al. [77] provide evidence to support the SCST as a successful stand-alone intervention for treating emotional processing deficits, the finding that the hybrid intervention had a significant effect on attributional bias also suggests a combined approach may be useful. This line of work warrants further research, especially given that the hybrid training was matched in number of hours to the other interventions, meaning the amount of time spent on social cognitive training was half that of the SCST group and similarly for the neurocognitive component. However, to reiterate, functioning, which is the outcome of primary interest, was not significantly affected by either the SCST alone or the combined approach. The results from the CET trial [126–128], an intervention that encompasses both neurocognitive and social cognitive training, add further weight to the idea that a combined/hybrid approach appears complimentary and may work synergistically to enhance social and occupational functioning.Finally, coming back to the neurodevelopmental hypothesis and biological basis of schizophrenia, it would be advantageous for future clinical trials to utilise modern brain imaging techniques not only to explore the origins of cognitive impairment but to evaluate the effects of intervention programs on the illness at its source. Indeed, Eack and colleagues [149] found CET to have a neuroprotective effect against grey matter volume reductions and that CET was a significant mediator between grey matter volume changes in the parahippocampus, fusiform gyrus, and amygdala and improved cognitive performance. Normalization of brain activation [150] and serum brain-derived neurotrophic factor [151] have also been demonstrated in chronic schizophrenia following neurocognitive remediation.In conclusion, given the evidence for debilitating cognitive and functional difficulties occurring at or even before onset of psychosis and the clear relationship between these two constructs, we argue that the maximal benefits of cognitive remediation are likely to occur early in the course of illness, even in the putative prodromal phase. This is based on the premise that the “ceiling” for potential recovery may be higher in early psychosis due to ongoing neurodevelopment in this phase of life. Needless to say there is a great deal more research to be done in this area; however, preliminary findings suggest there are a number of potential avenues that may alleviate functional impairments of young people with psychotic disorders.AcknowledgmentsDr. C. F. Bartholomeusz and Dr. K. Allott are each supported by a National Health and Medical Research Council Australian-based Clinical Research Fellowship (567042 and 628884, resp.). 1BuchananRWDavisMGoffDA summary of the FDA-NIMH-MATRICS workshop on clinical trial design for neurocognitive drugs for schizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin2005311519158884222HarveyPDBellackASToward a terminology for functional recovery in schizophrenia: is functional remission a viable concept?Schizophrenia Bulletin2009352300306191266343BirchwoodMToddPJacksonCEarly intervention in psychosis: the critical period hypothesisBritish Journal of Psychiatry19981723353594JablenskyAEpidemiology of schizophrenia: the global burden of disease and disabilityEuropean Archives of Psychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience20002506274285111539625YungARPhillipsLJYuenHPPsychosis prediction: 12-Month follow up of a high-risk (“prodromal”) groupSchizophrenia Research20036012132125051356MenezesNMArenovichTZipurskyRBA systematic review of longitudinal outcome studies of first-episode psychosisPsychological Medicine2006361013491362167566897MallaAPayneJFirst-episode psychosis: psychopathology, quality of life, and functional outcomeSchizophrenia Bulletin2005313650671160065938GaretyPACraigTKJDunnGSpecialised care for early psychosis: symptoms, social functioning and patient satisfaction—randomised controlled trialBritish Journal of Psychiatry20061883745163880689ThorupAPetersenLJeppesenPIntegrated treatment ameliorates negative symptoms in first episode psychosis—results from the Danish OPUS trialSchizophrenia Research2005791951051612290910KillackeyEYungAREffectiveness of early intervention in psychosisCurrent Opinion in Psychiatry20072021211251727890811McGorryPDEdwardsJMihalopoulosCHarriganSMJacksonHJEPPIC: an evolving system of early detection and optimal managementSchizophrenia Bulletin1996222305326878228812BilderRMThe neuropsychology of schizophrenia circa 2009Neuropsychology Review20091932772791968081613BartholomeuszCFKillackeyEThompsonARitsnerMInterventions targeting social and vocational dysfunction in individuals with a schizophrenia spectrum disorderHandbook of Schizophrenia Spectrum Disorders20113New York, NY, USASpringer14CoutureSMPennDLRobertsDLThe functional significance of social cognition in schizophrenia: a reviewSchizophrenia bulletin200632S44S631691688915BlakemoreSJDevelopment of the social brain during adolescenceQuarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology2008611404916PausTMapping brain maturation and cognitive development during adolescenceTrends in Cognitive Sciences20059260681566809817GogtayNGieddJNLuskLDynamic mapping of human cortical development during childhood through early adulthoodProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America200410121817481791514838118SteinbergLCognitive and affective development in adolescenceTrends in Cognitive Sciences20059269741566809919SteinbergLMorrisASAdolescent developmentAnnual Review of Psychology2001528311020PausTKeshavanMGieddJNWhy do many psychiatric disorders emerge during adolescence?Nature Reviews Neuroscience20089129479571900219121Australian Bureau of StatisticsNational survey of mental health and wellbeing: summary of results2007Sydney, AustraliaAustralain Bureau of Statistics,22MorganVWaterreusAJablenskyAPeople living with psychotic illness 2010: report on the second Australian national survey2011Canberra, AustraliaDepartment of Health and Aging23PantelisCYücelMBoraENeurobiological markers of illness onset in psychosis and schizophrenia: the search for a moving targetNeuropsychology Review20091933853981972809824Mesholam-GatelyRIGiulianoAJGoffKPFaraoneSVSeidmanLJNeurocognition in first-episode Schizophrenia: a meta-analytic reviewNeuropsychology20092333153361941344625DickinsonDRaglandJDGoldJMGurRCGeneral and specific cognitive deficits in schizophrenia: Goliath defeats David?Biological Psychiatry20086498238271847208926BozikasVPAndreouCLongitudinal studies of cognition in first episode psychosis: a systematic review of the literatureAustralian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry2011452931082132003327BrewerWJWoodSJPhillipsLJGeneralized and specific cognitive performance in clinical high-risk cohorts: a review highlighting potential vulnerability markers for psychosisSchizophrenia Bulletin20063235385551678275928CorrellCUHauserMAutherAMCornblattBAResearch in people with psychosis risk syndrome: a review of the current evidence and future directionsJournal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry and Allied Disciplines201051439043129Fusar-PoliPPerezJBroomeMNeurofunctional correlates of vulnerability to psychosis: a systematic review and meta-analysisNeuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews20073144654841722319430AddingtonJSaeediHAddingtonDFacial affect recognition: a mediator between cognitive and social functioning in psychosis?Schizophrenia Research2006851–31421501667838831EdwardsJPattisonPEJacksonHJWalesRJFacial affect and affective prosody recognition in first-episode schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research2001482-32352531129537732PinkhamAEPennDLPerkinsDOGrahamKASiegelMEmotion perception and social skill over the course of psychosis: a comparison of individuals “at-risk” for psychosis and individuals with early and chronic schizophrenia spectrum illnessCognitive Neuropsychiatry20071231982121745390133AmmingerGPSchaferMRPapageorgiouKEmotion recognition in individuals at clinical high-risk for SchizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin. In press34GreenMFBeardenCECannonTDSocial cognition in Schizophrenia, Part 1: performance across phase of illnessSchizophrenia Bulletin. In press35BertrandMCSuttonHAchimAMMallaAKLepageMSocial cognitive impairments in first episode psychosisSchizophrenia Research2007951–31241331763026136MontreuilTBodnarMBertrandMCMallaAKJooberRLepageMSocial cognitive markers of short-term clinical outcome in first-episode psychosisClinical Schizophrenia and Related Psychoses2010421051142064363337InoueYYamadaKHiranoMImpairment of theory of mind in patients in remission following first episode of schizophreniaEuropean Archives of Psychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience200625653263281692704038KettleJWLO’Brien-SimpsonLAllenNBImpaired theory of mind in first-episode schizophrenia: comparison with community, university and depressed controlsSchizophrenia Research2008991–3961021815544739KoelkebeckKPedersenASuslowTKueppersKAAroltVOhrmannPTheory of Mind in first-episode schizophrenia patients: correlations with cognition and personality traitsSchizophrenia Research20101191–31151232006068640KrstevHJacksonHMaudeDAn investigation of attributional style in first-episode psychosisBritish Journal of Clinical Psychology19993821811941038959941AnSKKangJIParkJYKimKRLeeSYLeeEAttribution bias in ultra-high risk for psychosis and first-episode schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research20101181–354612017184942ThompsonADBartholomeuszCYungARSocial cognition deficits and the 'ultra high risk' for psychosis population: a review of literatureEarly Intervention in Psychiatry2011531922022172642243AddingtonJPennDWoodsSWAddingtonDPerkinsDOFacial affect recognition in individuals at clinical high risk for psychosisBritish Journal of Psychiatry2008192167681817451444SchloegelhoferMSchaeferMPapageorgiouKEmotion recognition in individuals at Ultra High Risk for psychosisSchizophrenia Bulletin200686S94S9545van RijnSAlemanAde SonnevilleLMisattribution of facial expressions of emotion in adolescents at increased risk of psychosis: the role of inhibitory controlPsychological Medicine2011414995082050766946ChungYSKangDHShinNYYooSYKwonJSDeficit of theory of mind in individuals at ultra-high-risk for schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research2008991–31111181809637147CoutureSMPennDLAddingtonJWoodsSWPerkinsDOAssessment of social judgments and complex mental states in the early phases of psychosisSchizophrenia Research20081001–32372411825527348BlakemoreSJThe social brain in adolescenceNature Reviews Neuroscience2008942672771835439949PantelisCVelakoulisDWoodSJNeuroimaging and emerging psychotic disorders: the Melbourne ultra-high risk studiesInternational Review of Psychiatry200719437338150JungWHJangJHByunMSAnSKKwonJSStructural brain alterations in individuals at ultra-high risk for psychosis: a review of magnetic resonance imaging studies and future directionsJournal of Korean Medical Science20102512170017092116528251SeiferthNYPaulyKKellermannTNeuronal correlates of facial emotion discrimination in early onset schizophreniaNeuropsychopharmacology20093424774871858087452SeiferthNYPaulyKHabelUIncreased neural response related to neutral faces in individuals at risk for psychosisNeuroImage20084012892971818734253BrüneMÖzgürdalSAnsorgeNAn fMRI study of "theory of mind" in at-risk states of psychosis: comparison with manifest schizophrenia and healthy controlsNeuroImage20115513293372114723554BoksmanKThébergeJWilliamsonPA 4.0-T fMRI study of brain connectivity during word fluency in first-episode schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research2005752-32472631588551755WoodwardNDWaldieBRogersBTibboPSeresPPurdonSEAbnormal prefrontal cortical activity and connectivity during response selection in first episode psychosis, chronic schizophrenia, and unaffected siblings of individuals with schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research20091091–31821901917905056LuckDBuchyLCzechowskaYFronto-temporal disconnectivity and clinical short-term outcome in first episode psychosis: a DTI-tractography studyJournal of Psychiatric Research20114533693772070819857CrossleyNAMechelliAFusar-PoliPSuperior temporal lobe dysfunction and frontotemporal dysconnectivity in subjects at risk of psychosis and in first-episode psychosisHuman Brain Mapping20093012412941371953021958GreenMFKernRSBraffDLMintzJNeurocognitive deficits and functional outcome in schizophrenia: are we measuring the “right stuff”?Schizophrenia Bulletin20002611191361075567359FettAKJViechtbauerWDominguezMDGPennDLvan OsJKrabbendamLThe relationship between neurocognition and social cognition with functional outcomes in schizophrenia: a meta-analysisNeuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews20113535735882062016360AllottKLiuPProffittTMKillackeyECognition at illness onset as a predictor of later functional outcome in early psychosis: systematic review and methodological critiqueSchizophrenia Research20111252212352111157761BellMTsangHWHGreigTCBrysonGJNeurocognition, social cognition, perceived social discomfort, and vocational outcomes in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin20093547387471824505862BrüneMEmotion recognition, “theory of mind,” and social behavior in schizophreniaPsychiatry Research20051332-31351471574099063PinkhamAEPennDLNeurocognitive and social cognitive predictors of interpersonal skill in schizophreniaPsychiatry Research20061432-31671781685975464AllenDNStraussGPDonohueBvan KammenDPFactor analytic support for social cognition as a separable cognitive domain in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research2007931–33253331749892765WilliamsLMWhitfordTJFlynnGGeneral and social cognition in first episode schizophrenia: identification of separable factors and prediction of functional outcome using the IntegNeuro test batterySchizophrenia Research2008991–31821911805368866AddingtonJGirardTAChristensenBKAddingtonDSocial cognition mediates illness-related and cognitive influences on social function in patients with schizophrenia-spectrum disordersJournal of Psychiatry and Neuroscience201035149542004024667SergiMJRassovskyYNuechterleinKHGreenMFSocial perception as a mediator of the influence of early visual processing on functional status in schizophreniaAmerican Journal of Psychiatry200616334484541651386668VauthRRüschNWirtzMCorriganPWDoes social cognition influence the relation between neurocognitive deficits and vocational functioning in schizophrenia?Psychiatry Research200412821551651548895869BrekkeJKayDDLeeKSGreenMFBiosocial pathways to functional outcome in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research2005802-32132251613785970AddingtonJSaeediHAddingtonDInfluence of social perception and social knowledge on cognitive and social functioning in early psychosisBritish Journal of Psychiatry20061893733781701266271HoranWPGreenMFDegrootMSocial cognition in Schizophrenia, Part 2: 12-month stability and prediction of functional outcome in first-episode patientsSchizophrenia Bulletin. In press72WykesTHuddyVCellardCMcGurkSRCzoborPA meta-analysis of cognitive remediation for schizophrenia: methodology and effect sizesAmerican Journal of Psychiatry201116854724852140646173MedaliaAChoiJCognitive remediation in schizophreniaNeuropsychology Review20091933533641944461474FisherMHollandCMerzenichMMVinogradovSUsing neuroplasticity-based auditory training to improve verbal memory in schizophreniaAmerican Journal of Psychiatry200916678058111944818775McGurkSRTwamleyEWSitzerDIMcHugoGJMueserKTA meta-analysis of cognitive remediation in schizophreniaAmerican Journal of Psychiatry200716412179118021805623376KurtzMMRichardsonCLSocial cognitive training for schizophrenia: a meta-analytic investigation of controlled researchSchizophrenia Bulletin. In press77HoranWPKernRSTrippCEfficacy and specificity of social cognitive skills training for outpatients with psychotic disordersJournal of Psychiatric Research2011458111311222137716878RoderVMuellerDRMueserKTBrennerHDIntegrated psychological therapy (IPT) for schizophrenia: is it effective?Schizophrenia bulletin200632S81S931691688879RauchensteinerSKawohlWOzgurdalSTest-performance after cognitive training in persons at risk mental state of schizophrenia and patients with schizophreniaPsychiatry Research20111853343392049354080McGurkSRMueserKTResponse to cognitive rehabilitation in older versus younger persons with severe mental illnessAmerican Journal of Psychiatric Rehabilitation20081119010581WykesTReederCLandauSMatthiassonPHaworthEHutchinsonCDoes age matter? Effects of cognitive rehabilitation across the age spanSchizophrenia Research20091132-32522581952440982HogartyGEFlesherSUlrichRCognitive enhancement therapy for schizophrenia: effects of a 2-year randomized trial on cognition and behaviorArchives of General Psychiatry20046198668761535176583GreenMFCognitive remediation in schizophrenia: is it time yet?American Journal of Psychiatry19931502178187842206884FisherMHollandCSubramaniamKVinogradovSNeuroplasticity-based cognitive training in schizophrenia: an interim report on the effects 6 months laterSchizophrenia Bulletin20103648698791926992485MedaliaAFreilichBThe Neuropsychological Educational Approach to Cognitive Remediation (NEAR) model: practice principles and outcome studiesAmerican Journal of Psychiatric Rehabilitation200811212314386TwamleyEWJesteDVBellackASA review of cognitive training in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin20032923593821455251087WykesTReederCCognitive Remediation Therapy for Schizophrenia: Theory and Practice2005London, UKRoutledge88DelahuntyAMoriceRA training programme for the remediation of cognitive deficits in schizophrenia1993Albury, AustraliaDepartment of Health89TwamleyEWSavlaGNZurhellenCHHeatonRKJesteDVDevelopment and pilot testing of a novel compensatory cognitive training intervention for people with psychosisAmerican Journal of Psychiatric Rehabilitation20081121441631919866490PijnenborgGHMWithaarFKEvansJJVan Den BoschRJBrouwerWHSMS text messages as a prosthetic aid in the cognitive rehabilitation of schizophreniaRehabilitation Psychology200752223624091VelliganDIBow-ThomasCCHuntzingerCRandomized controlled trial of the use of compensatory strategies to enhance adaptive functioning in outpatients with schizophreniaAmerican Journal of Psychiatry20001578131713231091079792BellackASGoldJMBuchananRWCognitive rehabilitation for schizophrenia: problems, prospects, and strategiesSchizophrenia Bulletin19992522572741041673093VelliganDIRitchJLMaplesNJCognitive Adaptation Training: The Use of Compensatory Strategies in the Psychosocial Rehabilitation of Patients with Schizophrenia20102nd editionSan Antonio, Tex, USAUTHSC, Department of Psychiatry94TwamleyEWBurtonCZVellaLCompensatory cognitive training for psychosis: who benefits? who stays in treatment?Schizophrenia Bulletin201137supplement 2S55S622186004895VelliganDIKernRSGoldJMCognitive rehabilitation for schizophrenia and the putative role of motivation and expectanciesSchizophrenia Bulletin20063234744851664142496KernRSGreenMFMintzJLibermanRPDoes “errorless learning” compensate for neurocognitive impairments in the work rehabilitation of persons with schizophrenia?Psychological Medicine20033334334421270166497PopeJWKernRSAn "errorful" learning deficit in schizophrenia?Journal of Clinical and Experimental Neuropsychology20062811011101644897998O’CarrollRERussellHHLawrieSMJohnstoneECErrorless learning and the cognitive rehabilitation of memory-impaired schizophrenic patientsPsychological Medicine19992911051121007729899KernRSGreenMFMitchellSKopelowiczAMintzJLibermanRPExtensions of errorless learning for social problem-solving deficits in schizophreniaAmerican Journal of Psychiatry2005162351351915741468100KernRSLibermanRPBeckerDRDrakeRESugarCAGreenMFErrorless learning for training individuals with schizophrenia at a community mental health setting providing work experienceSchizophrenia Bulletin200935480781518326529101SilversteinSMBridging the gap between extrinsic and intrinsic motivation in the cognitive remediation of schizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin201036594995620064900102KrabbendamLAlemanACognitive rehabilitation in schizophrenia: a quantitative analysis of controlled studiesPsychopharmacology20031693-437638212545330103BellMBrysonGGreigTCorcoranCWexlerBENeurocognitive enhancement therapy with work therapy: effects on neuropsychological test performanceArchives of General Psychiatry200158876376811483142104McGurkSRMueserKTPascarisACognitive training and supported employment for persons with severe mental illness: one-year results from a randomized controlled trialSchizophrenia Bulletin200531489890916079391105SilversteinSMSpauldingWDMendittoAAAttention shaping: a reward-based learning method to enhance skills training outcomes in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin200935122223218212327106WykesTReederCWilliamsCCornerJRiceCEverittBAre the effects of cognitive remediation therapy (CRT) durable? Results from an exploratory trial in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research2003612-316317412729868107DavisLWLysakerPHCognitive behavioral therapy and functional and metacognitive outcomes in schizophrenia: a single case studyCognitive and Behavioral Practice2005124468478108MoritzSBurlonMWoodwardTSMetacognitive Skills Training for Patients with Schizophrenia (MCT). Version 3.22005Hamburg, GermanyVanHam Campus Press109KorenDSeidmanLJGoldsmithMHarveyPDReal-world cognitive—and metacognitive—dysfunction in schizophrenia: a new approach for measuring (and remediating) more ‘right stuff’Schizophrenia Bulletin200632231032616397202110BellackASBrownCHThomas-LohrmanSPsychometric characteristics of role-play assessments of social skill in schizophreniaBehavior Therapy200637433935217071212111CombsDRAdamsSDPennDLRobertsDTiegreenJStemPSocial Cognition and Interaction Training (SCIT) for inpatients with schizophrenia spectrum disorders: preliminary findingsSchizophrenia Research2007911–311211617293083112CarrLIacoboniMDubeautMCMazziottaJCLenziGLNeural mechanisms of empathy in humans: a relay from neural systems for imitation to limbic areasProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America200310095497550212682281113ObermanLMRamachandranVSThe simulating social mind: the role of the mirror neuron system and simulation in the social and communicative deficits of autism spectrum disordersPsychological Bulletin2007133231032717338602114SinghJSHopeDACognitive-behavioral approaches to the treatment of social anxiety disorderIsrael Journal of Psychiatry and Related Sciences2009461626919728574115WolpeJThe Practice of Behaviour Therapy19692nd editionNew York, NY, USAPergamon116PonniahKHollonSDEmpirically supported psychological interventions for social phobia in adults: a qualitative review of randomized controlled trialsPsychological Medicine200838131417640438117PonniahKHollonSDEmpirically supported psychological interventions for social phobia in adults: a qualitative review of randomized controlled trialsPsychological Medicine200838131417640438118RobertsDPennDCombsDSocial Cognition and Interaction Training (SCIT) Treatment Manual2010119HogartyGEGreenwaldDPCognitive Enhancement Therapy: The Training Manual2006Pittsburgh, Pa, USAUniversity of Pittsburgh Medical Center120VinogradovSLoewyRFisherMNeuroplasticity-based cognitive training in early psychosis (Abstract)Biological Psychiatry201067S188S189121LinAWoodSJNelsonBNeurocognitive predictors of functional outcome two to 13 years after identification as ultra-high risk for psychosisSchizophrenia Research201113211721763109122NiendamTABeardenCEJohnsonJKNeurocognitive performance and functional disability in the psychosis prodromeSchizophrenia Research200684110011116563699123UelandTRundBRA controlled randomized treatment study: the effects of a cognitive remediation program on adolescents with early onset psychosisActa Psychiatrica Scandinavica20041091707414674961124UelandTRundBRCognitive remediation for adolescents with early onset psychosis: a 1-year follow-up studyActa Psychiatrica Scandinavica2005111319320115701103125WykesTNewtonELandauSRiceCThompsonNFrangouSCognitive remediation therapy (CRT) for young early onset patients with schizophrenia: an exploratory randomized controlled trialSchizophrenia Research2007941–322123017524620126EackSMGreenwaldDPHogartySSCognitive enhancement therapy for early-course schizophrenia: effects of a two-year randomized controlled trialPsychiatric Services200960111468147619880464127EackSMHogartyGEGreenwaldDPHogartySSKeshavanMSEffects of cognitive enhancement therapy on employment outcomes in early schizophrenia: results from a 2-year randomized trialResearch on Social Work Practice2011211324223885163128EackSMGreenwaldDPHogartySSKeshavanMSOne-year durability of the effects of cognitive enhancement therapy on functional outcome in early schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research20101201–321021620472402129WykesTSpauldingWDThinking about the future cognitive remediation therapy-what works and could we do better?Schizophrenia Bulletin201137supplement 2S80S9021860051130PennDLRobertsDLCombsDSterneAThe development of the social cognition and interaction training program for schizophrenia spectrum disordersPsychiatric Services200758444945117412842131BirchwoodMSmithJCochraneRWettonSCopestakeSThe Social Functioning Scale. The development and validation of a new scale of social adjustment for use in family intervention programmes with schizophrenic patientsBritish Journal of Psychiatry19901578538592289094132RobertsDLPennDLSocial cognition and interaction training (SCIT) for outpatients with schizophrenia: a preliminary studyPsychiatry Research20091662-314114719272654133RobertsDLPennDLLabateDMargolisSASterneATransportability and feasibility of Social Cognition and Interaction Training (SCIT) in community settingsBehavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapy2010381354719857363134MazzaMLucciGPacittiFCould schizophrenic subjects improve their social cognition abilities only with observation and imitation of social situations?Neuropsychological Rehabilitation201020567570320714969135GalleseVMirror neurons, embodied simulation, and the neural basis of social identificationPsychoanalytic Dialogues2009195519536136KwonJHSocial Cognition Enhancement Rehabilitation Program2003Seoul, KoreaHakjisa137ChoiKHKwonJHSocial cognition enhancement training for schizophrenia: a preliminary randomized controlled trialCommunity Mental Health Journal200642217718716732472138RonconeRMazzaMFrangouIRehabilitation of theory of mind deficit in schizophrenia: a pilot study of metacognitive strategies in group treatmentNeuropsychological Rehabilitation2004144421435139WölwerWFrommannNHalfmannSPiaszekAStreitMGaebelWRemediation of impairments in facial affect recognition in schizophrenia: efficacy and specificity of a new training programSchizophrenia Research2005802-329530316125367140RussellTAGreenMJSimpsonIColtheartMRemediation of facial emotion perception in schizophrenia: concomitant changes in visual attentionSchizophrenia Research20081031–324825618565733141BioDSGattazWFVocational rehabilitation improves cognition and negative symptoms in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Research20111261–326526920800453142VesteragerLChristensenTTOlsenBBCognitive training plus a comprehensive psychosocial programme (OPUS) versus the comprehensive psychosocial programme alone for patients with first-episode schizophrenia (the NEUROCOM trial): a study protocol for a centrally randomised, observer-blinded multi-centre clinical trialTrials201112, article 35143BreitbordeNJKMorenoFAMai-DixonNMultifamily group psychoeducation and cognitive remediation for first-episode psychosis: a randomized controlled trialBMC Psychiatry201111, article 9144BrennerHDThe treatment of basic psychological dysfunctions from a systemic point of viewBritish Journal of Psychiatry198915557483145BrennerHDHodelBRoderVCorriganPTreatment of cognitive dysfunctions and behavioral deficits in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin199218121261553495146RoderVMuellerDRMueserKTBrennerHDIntegrated psychological therapy (IPT) for schizophrenia: is it effective?Schizophrenia bulletin200632supplement1S819316916888147VelliganDIDiamondPMMintzJThe use of individually tailored environmental supports to improve medication adherence and outcomes in schizophreniaSchizophrenia Bulletin200834348349317932089148HoranWPKernRSShokat-FadaiKSergiMJWynnJKGreenMFSocial cognitive skills training in schizophrenia: an initial efficacy study of stabilized outpatientsSchizophrenia Research20091071475418930378149EackSMHogartyGEChoRYNeuroprotective effects of cognitive enhancement therapy against gray matter loss in early schizophrenia: results from a 2-year randomized controlled trialArchives of General Psychiatry201067767468220439824150WexlerBEAndersonMFulbrightRKGoreJCPreliminary evidence of improved verbal working memory performance and normalization of task-related frontal lobe activation in schizophrenia following cognitive exercisesAmerican Journal of Psychiatry2000157101694169711007730151VinogradovSFisherMHollandCShellyWWolkowitzOMellonSHIs serum brain-derived neurotrophic factor a biomarker for cognitive enhancement in schizophrenia?Biological Psychiatry200966654955319368899
