<?xml version="1.0"?>
PLoS OnePLoS ONEplosplosonePLoS ONE1932-6203Public Library of ScienceSan Francisco, CA USA538307010.1371/journal.pone.0175107PONE-D-16-21864Research ArticleResearch and Analysis MethodsMathematical and Statistical TechniquesStatistical MethodsMeta-AnalysisPhysical SciencesMathematicsStatistics (Mathematics)Statistical MethodsMeta-AnalysisBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceCognitive ScienceCognitionBiology and Life SciencesPsychologyEmotionsAnxietySocial SciencesPsychologyEmotionsAnxietyComputer and Information SciencesComputer NetworksInternetMedicine and Health SciencesMental Health and PsychiatryMood DisordersDepressionBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceCognitive ScienceCognitive PsychologyAttentionBiology and Life SciencesPsychologyCognitive PsychologyAttentionSocial SciencesPsychologyCognitive PsychologyAttentionMedicine and Health SciencesMental Health and PsychiatryNeuropsychiatric DisordersAnxiety DisordersMedicine and Health SciencesMental Health and PsychiatryNeurosesAnxiety DisordersBiology and Life SciencesBehaviorEffects of cognitive bias modification on social anxiety: A meta-analysisEffects of cognitive bias modification on social anxiety: A meta-analysisLiuHaining123LiXianwen4HanBuxin13*LiuXiaoqian131Key Lab of Mental Health, Institute of Psychology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China2Psychology Department of Chengde Medical University, Chengde, China3University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China4School of Nursing, Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, ChinaEbmeierKlausEditorUniversity of Oxford, UNITED KINGDOMCompeting Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceptualization: HL.Data curation: HL.Formal analysis: HL Xianwen Li.Funding acquisition: BH.Investigation: Xiaoqian Liu.Methodology: HL Xianwen Li.Project administration: BH.Resources: Xiaoqian Liu.Supervision: BH.Validation: HL.Visualization: Xianwen Li.Writing – original draft: HL.Writing – review &amp; editing: BH.
* E-mail: hanbx@psych.ac.cn6420172017124e017510731520162132017© 2017 Liu et al2017Liu et alThis is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.BackgroundCognitive bias modification (CBM), a set of techniques for modifying bias in information processing—is considered a novel intervention for social anxiety disorder (SAD), which has drawn considerable interest from researchers. However, the effects of CBM on SAD are not consistent. Some studies have demonstrated significant positive effects compared to control groups, while others have found no such effects.AimsWe conducted a meta-analysis aimed at quantitatively assessing the effects of CBM on SAD at post-test.MethodThrough a systematic literature search by two independent raters, 34 articles (36 randomized studies) including 2,550 participants were identified. A multilevel modeling approach was employed to assess the effects of CBM on SAD, and to explore the potentially crucial procedures and sample characteristics that enhance the effectiveness of benign training.ResultsIn general, there were small but significant effects of CBM on the primary symptoms of SAD (g = 0.17), cognitive bias (CB) toward threat (g = 0.32), and reactivity in stressful situations (g = 0.25), but non-significant effects on secondary symptoms. However, the interpretation modification program was more effective than was attentional bias modification in reducing SAD primary symptoms and negative CB. Laboratory training procedures produced larger primary symptom reductions compared to Internet-based training, whereas the percentage of contingency and feedback about training performance boosted cognitive effects only. Finally, the following groups were more likely to benefit from CBM: younger participants (primary symptoms and cognitive effects), women (primary symptom effects), and samples with stronger CB (stressor effects). The quality of the randomized controlled trials was less than desirable, as there was some indication of publication bias in our study.ConclusionsCurrent findings broadly supported cognitive theories of SAD that consider a bidirectional or mutually reinforcing relationship between symptoms and CBs. However, the small therapeutic effect observed here indicates that it is necessary to develop more reliable and efficient CBM interventions that are specific to SAD.Scientific Foundation of the Key Lab of Mental Health, Institute of Psychology, Chinese Academy of SciencesKLMH2014K02HanBuxinNational Social Science FoundationMajor Project, 16ZDA233LiuHainingThis work was supported by the Scientific Foundation of the Key Lab of Mental Health, Institute of Psychology, Chinese Academy of Sciences under Grant KLMH2014K02 and the National Social Science Foundation (Major Project, 16ZDA233). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.Data AvailabilityAll relevant data from the published studies are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. We obtained all data from third parties (i.e., the original researchers of these studies). However, others can request these data from the relevant researchers listed in Table 1 of this manuscript. Contact information can be retrieved from their own papers.Data AvailabilityAll relevant data from the published studies are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. We obtained all data from third parties (i.e., the original researchers of these studies). However, others can request these data from the relevant researchers listed in Table 1 of this manuscript. Contact information can be retrieved from their own papers.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec007"><title>Method</title><sec id="sec008"><title>Identification and selection of studies</title><p>With strict adherence to the PRISMA guidelines [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], the first and second authors searched the literature independently (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0175107.s001">S1 Table</xref>). Records were identified by searching multiple literature databases (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0175107.s003">S1 Text</xref>), including ISI Web of Science, PubMed, PsycInfo, EMBASE and the Cochrane Collaboration's register of controlled trials, through December 2015. The following combinations of keywords were used in this search: “cognitive bias modification,” “attention* bias modification,” “interpret* bias modification,” “attention* training,” “bias experimental manipulation,” and “bias training” paired with “social phobi*”or “social anxi*” (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0175107.s003">S1 Text</xref>). There were no language restrictions. The references within the most recent reviews on CBM for social anxiety disorders were also systematically searched [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0175107.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Unpublished studies were not included.</p><p>A total of 1,944 records were identified (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0175107.g001">Fig 1</xref> for details). After removal of duplicated records, the titles and abstracts of the remaining articles were screened. After eliminating obviously irrelevant publications, 56 potentially relevant articles were retained and their full texts were reviewed for incorporation into the meta-analysis. Studies were included in the review if: (a) a randomized controlled trial (RCT) was used; (b) the therapeutic effect of CBM was isolated and not merged with other treatments; (c) the study was designed specifically to manipulate CB for the purpose of alleviating SAD symptoms and emotional susceptibility among patients with SAD or in subclinical populations; (d) at least one control group was included (i.e., a placebo control); (e) social-anxiety-relevant symptoms (i.e., SAD symptoms, such as self-reported reactivity in stressful situations or clinician-administered symptom assessment) were assessed at least once after training; (f) positive or negative emotionally relevant stimuli were used as training stimuli (i.e., strongly valenced words, facial expressions); and (g) sufficient data were available to compute ESs.</p><fig id="pone.0175107.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0175107.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>The PRISMA flow diagram of study selection [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0175107.g001"/></fig><p>Some studies included two or even more control groups (i.e., attend threat, the sham intervention, or waiting-list groups) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0175107.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. We selected the group that was closest to the placebo condition (i.e., sham intervention group) to calculate ESs, as this was the most common approach used for control groups in CBM studies. Two studies used a four-groups design, including two experimental and two control groups, to examine the effectiveness of CBM [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0175107.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In addition, one study reported a six-group design—three experimental and three control groups [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. For such studies, only the data sets that were related to the standard CBM and control conditions were extracted. Finally, with regard to findings for extended samples [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0175107.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] based on original studies [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0175107.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], we only chose the datasets reported in the original studies [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], as these offered more information about possible moderators.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Quality assessment and data abstraction</title><p>We used the risk of bias assessment tool formulated by the Cochrane Collaboration [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] to evaluate the methodological quality of the studies included in the meta-analysis. Five criteria from this tool were chosen to examine sources of bias in RCTs: (1) generation of adequate random allocation sequence, (2) allocation concealment prior to assignment, (3) blinding of participants to information about the allocated intervention, (4) blinding of outcome assessors to information about the allocated intervention, and (5) dealing with incomplete outcome data. The last criterion was met if there were no missing data or the missing data were managed using an intent-to-treat approach. The quality assessment of the studies was implemented by two independent authors (Liu and Li). Conflicting opinions were resolved via discussion; if this did not resolve the conflict, the authors sought the advice of the senior author (Han).</p><p>Information about following characteristics of the included studies was collected (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0175107.t001">Table 1</xref>):</p><table-wrap id="pone.0175107.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0175107.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Selective characteristics of included studies.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0175107.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0175107.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical status of participant</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%—total Female</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-total sessions</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of training materials</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training setting</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bias</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feedback (y/n)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stressor (y/n)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measures</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amir, et al. (2008) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI–S, Spatial cueing task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amir, et al. (2009) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI–II, HAM–D, LSAS, SPAI, STAI–T, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amir, et al. (2010) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / threat</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI, Spatial cueing task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amir &amp; Taylor (2012) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / threat</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI-II, LSAS, SPAI, STAI-T, WSAP</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asnaani et al. (2014) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smiling faces / checkerboards</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI-II, IPSM, LSAS, SPIN, STAI-S</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beard &amp; Amir, (2008) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI-II,SPAI-SP, STAI-T, WSAP</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beard, et al. (2011) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral + benign interpretation / threat</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+I</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSAS</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boettcher, et al. (2012) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces/neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI, LSAS, SIAS, SPS, Spatial cueing task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boettcher, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive words / threat /neutral + happy faces / disgust / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAI, LSAS, MADRS, QOLI, SPS, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bunnell, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BARS, BDI, BSPS, CGI, IST, LSAS, SPAI, UCT</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carlbring, et al. (2012) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAI, LSAS, SIAS, SPS, SPSQ</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carleton, et al. (2015) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threat words / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab/Internet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CES-D, SIPS, STAI-T</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Voogd, et al. (2014) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive faces / negative</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCADS</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enock, et al., (2014) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">429</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threat faces /neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smartphone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DASS, LSAS, PSWQ, SIAS, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heeren, et al. (2011) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces/neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BASA, VAS, Spatial cueing task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heeren, et al. (2012) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive faces / threat</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BASA, FNE, LSAS, SCR, SUDS, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heeren, et al. (2015) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces /neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BASA, SUDS, Spatial cueing task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hoppitt, et al. (2014) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FNE, PANAS, STAI-S, STAI-T, Dot-probe task, ambiguous social scenarios</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Julian, et al. (2012) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI-S, Spatial cueing task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khalili-Torghabeh, et al. (2014) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FNE, SADS, ambiguous social scenarios</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Klumpp &amp; Amir, (2010) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–22</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI-S</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li, et al. (2008) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive faces / negative</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FNE, SIAS, SPS, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maoz, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angry faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSAS, STAI-S, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McNally, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / happy</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DASS, LSAS, PRCS, SPRS, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murphy, et al. (2007) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI-S,ambiguous social scenarios</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neubauer, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI, LSAS, SIAS, SPS, Dot-probe task</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nowalcowski, et al. (2015) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSP, SPIN, ambiguous social scenarios</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rapee, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social words / neutral</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DASS, SIAS, SPS, STAI-S</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schmidt, et al. (2009) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disgust faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI, BSPS, LSAS, SPAI, STAI–T</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sportel, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive faces or words / neutral / threat benign + interpretation</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A+I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCADS</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taylor &amp; Amir (2012) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive faces / neutral</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI-S</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vassilopoulos, et al. (2009) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / negative</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDI, SASC, ambiguous social scenarios</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vassilopoulos, et al. (2013) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unselected</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / negative</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="justify" style="background-color:#CCCCCC" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDI, SASC, ambiguous social scenarios</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vassilopoulos &amp; Brouzos (2015) [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subclinical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign interpretation / negative</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDI, SASC, ambiguous social scenarios</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Notes. DSM-IV = Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders; SAD = Social Anxiety Disorder; SP = Social Phobia; A = attentional bias; BDI-II = Beck Depression Inventory-II; HAM-D = Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression; LSAS = Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale; SPAI = Social Phobia and Anxiety Inventory; STAI-S/STAI-T = State-Trait Anxiety Inventory-State/State-Trait Anxiety Inventory-Trait; I = interpretation bias; WSAP = word–sentence association paradigm; SPAI-SP = Social Phobia and Anxiety Inventory—Social Phobia subscale; SIAS = Social Interaction Anxiety Scale; SPS = Social Phobia Scale; BAI = Beck Anxiety Inventory; MADRS = Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale; QOLI = Quality of Life Inventory; BARS = Behavioral Avoidance Rating Scale; BSPS = Brief Social Phobia Scale; CGI = Clinical Global Impression of Improvement; IST = Impromptu Speech Task; UCT = Unstructured Conversation Task; SPSQ = Social Phobia Screening Questionnaire; CES-D = Centre for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale; SIPS = Social Interaction Phobia Scale; RCADS = The Revised Child Anxiety and Depression Scale; DASS = Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale; PSQW = Penn State Worry Questionnaire; BASA = Behavioral Assessment of Speech Anxiety; VAS = Visual Subclinical scales; SUDS = Subjective Units of Discomfort Scale; FNE = Fear of Negative Evaluation; SCR = skin conductance reactivity; PANAS = Positive and Negative Affect Schedule; SADS = Social Avoidance and Distress Scale; PRCS = Personal Report of Confidence as a Speaker; SPRS = Social Performance Rating Scale; PSP = Perception of Speech Performance; SPIN = Social Phobia Inventory; CDI = Children’s depression inventory; SASC = Social anxiety scale for children; AA = AAT Approach Bias; IPSM = Interpersonal Sensitivity Measurement</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><italic>Publication information</italic>: including identification information (author and year of publication), and the journal impact factor (through Web of Science) at the time of publication;</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Characteristics of the study sample</italic>: including source (clinical/subclinical), number of participants across different conditions, percentage of women per study, and seriousness of primary and secondary symptoms of social anxiety (i.e., the Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale or Beck Depression Inventory score at baseline);</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Characteristics of the CBM procedure</italic>: including treatment dose (total number of sessions), type of training materials (i.e., type of threaten and non-threaten cues), training setting (laboratory, internet, or smartphone), type of bias intervention (i.e., ABM or CBM-I), the presence of a stressful task during the training program (yes or no), feedback on accuracy when the tasks were solved (yes or no), and the percentage of trials in the CBM condition in which cues were valid.</p></list-item></list><p>The outcome measures were classified into four categories (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0175107.s002">S2 Table</xref>): (1) self-reported primary social anxiety symptoms at post-test; (2) negative CB at post-test; (3) reactivity in stressful situations (i.e., speech challenge); (4) secondary social anxiety symptoms, both self-reported and clinician-rated, at post-test (i.e., depression and general distress).</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Data analysis</title><p>For each between-group comparison, the ES (Cohen’s <italic>d</italic>) was calculated to indicate the differences between the CBM intervention and a control group at post-training. The ESs were calculated by subtracting the mean value of the CBM group from the mean value of the comparison group (at post-training), and dividing by the pooled standard deviations of both groups. Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> values of 0.2, 0.5, and 0.8 are considered small, medium, and large ESs, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Because some studies had small sample sizes, the corrected ES coefficient—Hedges’ g—was applied [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. This can be interpreted like Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</p><p>We calculated the pooled mean ESs using Comprehensive Meta-Analysis (CMA; version 2.2.064 for Windows). As there were a number of measurements used to assess the symptoms, we classified the outcome measures as follows: SAD primary symptoms, CB, reactivity in stressful situations, and secondary symptoms (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0175107.s002">S2 Table</xref>). When a study included several instruments measuring the same outcome, an average ES was calculated. When calculating averages, we weighted ESs by their sample size. If the studies did not report the means and standard deviations, we used the other statistics recommended by CMA 2.0, such as <italic>t</italic> values, sample sizes, and precise <italic>p</italic> values from independent groups. Additionally, we emailed the authors to inquire prudently whether there were any related unpublished data.</p><p>We also aimed to investigate how the baseline (i.e., before training) CB influenced the therapeutic benefits yielded by CBM to SAD symptoms, CB, and reactivity in stressful situations. Thus, we imputed a third data set of ESs and coded them as positive values to reflect a larger baseline CB in the CBM group relative to the control group. Only ESs for post-test and post-challenge were reported. Follow-up data were not considered because the duration differed considerably and participants in some studies underwent treatment while others did not. ESs were computed with random-effects models, which assume the observed estimates of treatment effects vary within-study (as with fixed-effects models) as well as between-studies, because this method is generally considered more conservative [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p><p>Homogeneity of ESs was tested using the <italic>Q</italic>-statistic and the <italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>-statistic [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. A significant <italic>Q</italic>-statistic suggests that there is true heterogeneity in ESs exceeding the random error. The <italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> quantifies the degree of heterogeneity in percentages, with higher values indicating higher heterogeneity. A value of 0% is regarded as no heterogeneity, while those of 25%, 50%, and 75% indicate low, moderate, and high heterogeneity, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. When investigating categorical moderators, not only the heterogeneity within each group (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>w</italic></sub>) but also the heterogeneity between groups (<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub>) were evaluated. Significant between-group heterogeneity indicated that the moderators were significant.</p><p>Publication bias was examined using two methods: visually observing the funnel plots for the main outcome classification, and employing the trim and fill procedure of Duval–Tweedie to obtain a corrected ES [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Outliers were defined as an ES of ≥2.5 standard deviations (<italic>SD</italic>) above or below the average ES estimate in each dataset [<xref rid="pone.0175107.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The robustness of the findings was assessed using sensitivity analyses, which involved comparing results when including and excluding outliers.</p><p>Categorical moderators were tested with subgroup analyses using a mixed-effects model. In this model, we investigated pooled studies within subgroups using a random-effects model, whereas significant differences between subgroups were examined using a fixed-effects model. If there were less than three studies within a subgroup, it was not reported. For continuous moderators, unrestricted maximum likelihood meta-regression analyses were conducted.</p></sec></sec>We want to thank Tongqi Wei of the National Science Library of the Chinese Academy of Sciences for helping us devise the search strategy.References1National Collaborating Centre for Mental Health. Social anxiety disorder: recognition, assessment and treatment. British Psychological Society, 2013.2SteinmanSA and TeachmanBA. Modifying interpretations among individuals high in anxiety sensitivity. J Anxiety Disord. 2010; 24(1): 71–8. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2009.08.008
197477973SteinMB and SteinDJ, Social anxiety disorder. The Lancet. 2008; 371(9618): 1115–25.4EatonNR, KeyesKM, KruegerRF, BalsisS, SkodoAEl, MarkonKE
et al
An invariant dimensional liability model of gender differences in mental disorder prevalence: evidence from a national sample. J Abnorm Psychol. 2012; 121(1): 282–8. doi: 10.1037/a0024780
218429585SchneierF, GoldmarkJ. Social Anxiety Disorder, in Anxiety Disorders and Gender. Springer
2015; 49–67. http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-13060-6_3.6XuY, SchneierF, HeimbergRG, PrincisvalleK, LiebowitzMR, WangS, et al
Gender differences in social anxiety disorder: Results from the national epidemiologic sample on alcohol and related conditions. J Anxiety Disord. 2012; 26(1): 12–9. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2011.08.006
219033587KatzelnickDJ, KobakKA, DeLeireT, HenkHJ, GreistJH, DavidsonJR, et al
Impact of generalized social anxiety disorder in managed care. AM J PSYCHIAT, 2014.8CramerP. Understanding Defense Mechanisms. Psychodynamic Psychiatry. 2015; 43(4): 523–52. doi: 10.1521/pdps.2015.43.4.523
265834399LeichsenringF, BeutelM, LeibingE. Psychodynamic psychotherapy for social phobia: a treatment manual based on supportive-expressive therapy. Bulletin of the Menninger Clinic. 2007; 71(1): 56–84. doi: 10.1521/bumc.2007.71.1.56
1748467010KeefeJR, McCarthyKS, DingerU, Zilcha-ManoS, BarberJP. A meta-analytic review of psychodynamic therapies for anxiety disorders. Clin Psychol Rev. 2014; 34(4): 309–23. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2014.03.004
2478689711AngélicoAP, CrippaJAdS, LoureiroSR. Social anxiety disorder and social skills: A critical review of the literature. International Journal of Behavioral Consultation and Therapy. 2013; 7(4): 16–23.12EpkinsCC, HecklerDR. Integrating etiological models of social anxiety and depression in youth: Evidence for a cumulative interpersonal risk model. Clin Child Fam Psych. 2011; 14(4): 329–76.13HeerenA, LangeWG, PhilippotP, WongQJ. Biased cognitions and social anxiety: building a global framework for integrating cognitive, behavioral, and neural processes. Front Hum Neurosci. 2014; 8: 538
doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2014.00538
2510098014HofmannSG. Cognitive factors that maintain social anxiety disorder: A comprehensive model and its treatment implications. Cogn Behav Ther. 2007; 36(4): 193–209. doi: 10.1080/16506070701421313
1804994515LeMoultJ, JoormannJ. Attention and memory biases in social anxiety disorder: The role of comorbid depression. Cogn Behav Ther. 2012; 36(1): 47–57.16MorrisonAS, HeimbergRG. Social anxiety and social anxiety disorder. Annu Rev Clin Psychol. 2013; 9: 249–74. doi: 10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-050212-185631
2353748517Van BockstaeleB, VerschuereB, TibboelH, De HouwerJ, CrombezG, KosterEH. A review of current evidence for the causal impact of attentional bias on fear and anxiety. Psychol Bull. 2014; 140(3): 682–721. doi: 10.1037/a0034834
2418841818HirschCR, MathewsA. A cognitive model of pathological worry. Behav Res Ther. 2012; 50(10): 636–46. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2012.06.007
2286354119MoserJS, HuppertJD, FoaEB, SimonsRF. Interpretation of ambiguous social scenarios in social phobia and depression: evidence from event-related brain potentials. Biol Psychol. 2012; 89(2): 387–97. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsycho.2011.12.001
2217844320MacLeodC, RutherfordE, CampbellL, EbsworthyG, HolkerL. Selective attention and emotional vulnerability: Assessing the causal basis of their association through the experimental manipulation of attentional bias. J Abnorm Psychol. 2002; 111(1): 107–23. 1186616521BeardC, AmirN. A multi-session interpretation modification program: changes in interpretation and social anxiety symptoms. Behav Res Ther. 2008; 46, 1135–41. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2008.05.012
1867540022RinckM, TelliS, KampmannIL, WoudML, KerstholtM, Te VelthuisS, et al
Training approach-avoidance of smiling faces affects emotional vulnerability in socially anxious individuals. Front Hum Neurosci. 2013; 7: 481
doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2013.00481
2397086223AmirN, BeardC, TaylorCT, KlumppH, EliasJ, BumsM, et al
Attention Training in Individuals With Generalized Social Phobia: A Randomized Controlled Trial. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2009; 77(5): 961–73. doi: 10.1037/a0016685
1980357524AmirN, TaylorCT. Interpretation Training in Individuals With Generalized Social Anxiety Disorder: A Randomized Controlled Trial. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2012; 80(3): 497–511. doi: 10.1037/a0026928
2225085125BeardC, WeisbergRB, AmirN. Combined cognitive bias modification treatment for social anxiety disorder: a pilot trial. Depress Anxiety. 2011; 28, 981–8. doi: 10.1002/da.20873
2189870526HeerenA, ReeseHE, McNallyRJ, PhilippotP. Attention training toward and away from threat in social phobia: Effects on subjective, behavioral, and physiological measures of anxiety. Behav Res Ther. 2012; 50(1): 30–9. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2011.10.005
2205528027EnockPM, HofmannSG, McNallyRJ. Attention bias modification training via smartphone to reduce social anxiety: A randomized, controlled multi-session experiment. Cognit Ther Res. 2014; 38, 200–16.28KlumppH, AmirN. Preliminary study of attention training to threat and neutral faces on anxious reactivity to a social stressor in social anxiety. Cognit Ther Res. 2010; 34(3): 263–71.29AsnaaniA, RinckM, BeckerE, HofmannSG. The Effects of Approach-Avoidance Modification on Social Anxiety Disorder: A Pilot Study. Cognit Ther Res. 2014; 38(2): 226–38. doi: 10.1007/s10608-013-9580-x
2465983230BoettcherJ, LeekL, MatsonL, HolmesEA, BrowningM, MacLeodC, et al
Internet-Based Attention Bias Modification for Social Anxiety: A Randomised Controlled Comparison of Training towards Negative and Training Towards Positive Cues. PloS one. 2013; 8(9): e71760
doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0071760
2409863031BunnellBE, BeidelDC, MesaF. A Randomized Trial of Attention Training for Generalized Social Phobia: Does Attention Training Change Social Behavior?
Behav Ther. 2013; 44(4): 662–73. doi: 10.1016/j.beth.2013.04.010
2409479132McNallyR, EnockP, TsaiC, TousianM. Attention bias modification for reducing speech anxiety. Behav Res Ther. 2013; 51(12): 882–8. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2013.10.001
2421133933HeerenA, MogoașeC, PhilippotP, McNallyRJ. Attention bias modification for social anxiety: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Psychol Rev. 2015; 40: 76–90. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2015.06.001
2608031434CristeaIA, KokRN, CuijpersP. Efficacy of cognitive bias modification interventions in anxiety and depression: meta-analysis. Br J Psychiatry. 2015; 206(1): 7–16. doi: 10.1192/bjp.bp.114.146761
2556148635HallionLS, RuscioAM. A meta-analysis of the effect of cognitive bias modification on anxiety and depression. Psychol Bull. 2011; 137(6): 940–58. doi: 10.1037/a0024355
2172839936Menne-LothmannC, ViechtbauerW, HöhnP, KasanovaZ, HallerSP, DrukkerM, et al
How to boost positive interpretations? A meta-analysis of the effectiveness of cognitive bias modification for interpretation. PloS one. 2014; 9(6): e100925
doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0100925
2496823437MogoaşeC, DavidD, KosterEH. Clinical efficacy of attentional bias modification procedures: An updated meta-analysis. J Clin Psychol. 2014; 70(12): 1133–57. doi: 10.1002/jclp.22081
2465282338MoherD, LiberatiA, TetzlaffJ, AltmanDG. Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. Ann Intern Med. 2010;8(5):336–41.39MobiniS, ReynoldsS, MackintoshB. Clinical implications of cognitive bias modification for interpretative biases in social anxiety: An integrative literature review. Cognit Ther Res. 2013; 37(1): 173–82.40HeerenA, LievensL, PhilippotP. How does attention training work in social phobia: Disengagement from threat or re-engagement to non-threat?
J Anxiety Disord. 2011; 25(8): 1108–15. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2011.08.001
2190753941JulianK, BeardC, SchmidtNB, PowersMB, SmitsJA. Attention training to reduce attention bias and social stressor reactivity: an attempt to replicate and extend previous findings. Behav Res Ther. 2012; 50, 350–8. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2012.02.015
2246602242BoettcherJ, LeekL, MatsonL, HolmesEA, BrowningM, MacLeodC, et al
Internet-based attention bias modification for social anxiety: a randomised controlled comparison of training towards negative and training towards positive cues. PLoS One. 2013; 8(9): e71760
doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0071760
2409863043AmirN, TaylorCT, DonohueMC. Predictors of response to an attention modification program in generalized social phobia. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2011; 79 (4): 533–41. doi: 10.1037/a0023808
2170713444KuckertzJ, GildebrantE, LiliequistB, KarlstromP, VaepplingC, BodlundO, et al
Moderation and mediation of the effect of attention training in social anxiety disorder. Behav Res Ther. 2014; 53: 30–40. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2013.12.003
2437398445CarlbringP, ApelstrandM, SehlinH, AmirN, RousseauA, HofmannSG, et al
Internet-delivered attention bias modification training in individuals with social anxiety disorder--a double blind randomized controlled trial. BMC psychiatry. 2012; 12(1): 66.2273188946HigginsJP, AltmanDG, GøtzschePC, JüniP, MoherD, OxmanAD, et al
The Cochrane Collaboration’s tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials. Bmj. 2011; 343: d5928
doi: 10.1136/bmj.d5928
2200821747CohenJ. Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, 1988.48HedgesC, OlkinI. Statistical techniques for meta-analysis. Academic Press, 1985.49RileyRD, HigginsJP, DeeksJJ. Interpretation of random effects meta-analyses. Bmj. 2011; 342: d549
doi: 10.1136/bmj.d549
2131079450CooperH, HedgesLV, ValentineJC. The handbook of research synthesis and meta-analysis. Russell Sage Foundation, 2009.51HigginsJP, ThompsonSG. Quantifying heterogeneity in a meta-analysis. Statistics in medicine. 2002; 21(11): 1539–58. doi: 10.1002/sim.1186
1211191952DuvalS. TweedieR. Trim and fill: a simple funnel-plot–based method of testing and adjusting for publication bias in meta-analysis. Biometrics. 2000; 56(2): 455–63. 1087730453LipseyMW, WilsonDB. Practical meta-analysis. Sage Publications, Inc, 2001.54AmirN, WeberG, BeardC, BomyeaJ, TaylorCT. The effect of a single-session attention modification program on response to a public-speaking challenge in socially anxious individuals. J Abnorm Psychol. 2008; 117, 860–8. doi: 10.1037/a0013445
1902523255AmirN, BomyeaJ, BeardC. The effect of single-session interpretation modification on attention bias in socially anxious individuals. J Anxiety Disord. 2010; 24, 178–82. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2009.10.005
1992644256BoettcherJ, BergerT, RennebergB. Internet-based attention training for social anxiety: A randomized controlled trial. Cognit Ther Res. 2012; 36(5): 522–36.57CarletonRN, SapachMJNT, OrietC, DuranceauS, LixLM, ThibodeauMA, et al
A randomized controlled trial of attention modification for social anxiety disorder. J Anxiety Disord. 2015; 33: 35–44. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2015.03.011
2604705958De VoogdEL, WiersRW, PrinsPJM, SaleminkE. Visual search attentional bias modification reduced social phobia in adolescents. Journal of Behav Ther and Experimental Psychiatry. 2014; 45(2): 252–9.59HeerenA, LievensL, PhilippotP. How does attention training work in social phobia: disengagement from threat or re-engagement to non-threat?
J Anxiety Disord. 2011; 25(8): 1108–15. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2011.08.001
2190753960HeerenA, MogoaşeC, McNallyRJ, SchmitzA, PhilippotP. Does attention bias modification improve attentional control? A double-blind randomized experiment with individuals with social anxiety disorder. J Anxiety Disord. 2015; 29: 35–42. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2014.10.007
2546588561HoppittL, Illingworth JosephineL, MacLeodC, HampshireA, Dunn BarnabyD, MackintoshB. Modifying social anxiety related to a real-life stressor using online Cognitive Bias Modification for interpretation. Behav Res Ther. 2014; 52: 45–52. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2013.10.008
2431728162Khalili-TorghabehS, FadardiJS, MackintoshB, ReynoldsS, MobiniS. Effects of a multi-session Cognitive Bias Modification program on interpretative biases and social anxiety symptoms in a sample of Iranian socially-anxious students. J Exp Psychopathol. 2014; 5(4): 514–27.63LiS, TanJ, QianM, LiuX. Continual training of attentional bias in social anxiety. Behav Res Ther. 2008; 46: 905–12. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2008.04.005
1853830564MaozK, AbendR, FoxNA, PineDS, Bar-HaimY. Subliminal attention bias modification training in socially anxious individuals. Front Hum Neurosci. 2013; 7: 389
doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2013.00389
2388813865MurphyR, HirschCR, MathewsA, SmithK, ClarkDM. Facilitating a benign interpretation bias in a high socially anxious population. Behav Res Ther. 2007; 45(7): 1517–29. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2007.01.007
1734997066NeubauerK, AuerM, MurrayE, PetermannF, Helbig-LangS, GerlachAL. Internet-delivered attention modification training as a treatment for social phobia: a randomized controlled trial. Behav Res Ther. 2013; 51: 87–97. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2012.10.006
2326211667NowalcowskiME, AntonyMM, KoernerN. Modifying interpretation biases: Effects on symptomatology, behavior, and physiological reactivity in social anxiety. Journal of Behav Ther and Experimental Psychiatry. 2015; 49: 44–52.68RapeeRM, MacLeodC, CarpenterL, GastonJE, FreiJ, PetersL, et al
Integrating cognitive bias modification into a standard cognitive behavioural treatment package for social phobia: a randomized controlled trial. Behav Res Ther. 2013; 51(4–5): 207–15. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2013.01.005
2343512169SchmidtNB, RicheyJA, BucknerJD, TimpanoKR. Attention training for generalized social anxiety disorder. J Abnorm Psychol. 2009; 118, 5–14. doi: 10.1037/a0013643
1922230970SportelBE, HulluEd, JongPJ, NautaMH. Cognitive Bias Modification versus CBT in Reducing Adolescent Social Anxiety: A Randomized Controlled Trial. PLoS One. 2013; 8(5): e64355
doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0064355
2369120371TaylorCT, AmirN. Modifying automatic approach action tendencies in individuals with elevated social anxiety symptoms. Behav Res Ther. 2012; 50(9): 529–36. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2012.05.004
2272864572VassilopoulosSP, BanerjeeR, PrantzalouC. Experimental modification of interpretation bias in socially anxious children: Changes in interpretation, anticipated interpersonal anxiety, and social anxiety symptoms. Behav Res Ther. 2009; 47(12): 1085–9. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2009.07.018
1967929973VassilopoulosSP, MoberlyNJ, ZisimatouG. Experimentally modifying interpretations for positive and negative social scenarios in children: a preliminary investigation. Behav Cogn Psychoth. 2013; 41: 103–16.74VassilopoulosSP, BrouzosA. Cognitive bias modification of interpretations in children: Processing information about ambiguous social events in a duo. J Child Fam Stud. 2016; 25(1): 299–307.75KimbrelNA. A model of the development and maintenance of generalized social phobia. Clin Psychol Rev. 2008; 28(4): 592–612. A model of the development and maintenance of generalized social phobia. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2007.08.003
1795928876KimbrelNA, Nelson-GrayRO, MitchellJT. BIS, BAS, and bias: The role of personality and cognitive bias in social anxiety. Pers Indiv Differ. 2012; 52(3): 395–400.77ClarkDM, WellsA. A cognitive model of social phobia social phobia:Diagnosis, assessment, and treatment. Guilford Press
1995: 69–93.78MellingsTM, AldenLE. Cognitive processes in social anxiety: The effects of self-focus, rumination and anticipatory processing. Behav Res Ther. 2000; 38(3): 243–57. 1066515879RapeeRM, HeimbergRG. A cognitive-behavioral model of anxiety in social phobia. Behav Res Ther. 1997; 35(8): 741–56. 925651780ClarkDM, McManusF. Information processing in social phobia. Biol Psychiat. 2002; 51(1): 92–100. 1180123481ClarkePJF, NotebaertL, MacLeodC. Absence of evidence or evidence of absence: reflecting on therapeutic implementations of attentional bias modification[J]. BMC psychiatry, 2014, 14(1): 1–6.82Mayo-WilsonE, DiasS, MavranezouliI, KewK, ClarkDM, AdesA, et al
Psychological and pharmacological interventions for social anxiety disorder in adults: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Lancet Psychiat. 2014; 1(5): 368–76.83MansellW. Core processes of psychopathology and recovery:“Does the Dodo bird effect have wings?”. Clin Psychol Rev. 2011; 31(2): 189–92. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2010.06.009
2062466484ButlerE, MobiniS, RapeeRM, MackintoshB, ReynoldsSA. Enhanced effects of combined cognitive bias modification and computerised cognitive behaviour therapy on social anxiety. Cogent Psychology. 2015; 2(1): 1011905.85WilliamsAD, BlackwellSE, HolmesEA, AndrewsG. Positive imagery cognitive bias modification (CBM) and internet-based cognitive behavioural therapy (iCBT) versus control CBM and iCBT for depression: study protocol for a parallel-group randomised controlled trial. BMJ Open. 2013; 3(10): e004049
doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004049
2417194186BeckAT, ClarkDA. An information processing model of anxiety: Automatic and strategic processes. Behav Res Ther. 1997; 35(1): 49–58. 900904387BeardC, WeisbergRB, PrimackJ. Socially anxious primary care patients' attitudes toward cognitive bias modification (CBM): a qualitative study. Behav Cogn Psychother. 2012; 40(5): 618–33. doi: 10.1017/S1352465811000671
2212702288MacLeodC, ClarkePJF. The attentional bias modification approach to anxiety intervention. Clinical Psychological Science. 2015; 3(1): 58–78.89EmmelkampPMG. Attention bias modification: the Emperor's new suit?
BMC Med. 2012; 10(1): 63.2273199090ClarkePJ, BrowningM, HammondG, NotebaertL, MacLeodC. The causal role of the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in the modification of attentional bias: evidence from transcranial direct current stimulation. Biol Psychiatry. 2014; 76(12): 946–52. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.03.003
2469011391FoxE, MackintoshB, HolmesEA. Travellers’ tales in cognitive bias modification research: A commentary on the special issue. Cognit Ther Res. 2014; 38(2): 239–47.92CuijpersP, SmitF, BohlmeijerE, HollonSD, AnderssonG. Efficacy of cognitive–behavioural therapy and other psychological treatments for adult depression: meta-analytic study of publication bias. Brit J Psychiat. 2010; 196(3): 173–8. doi: 10.1192/bjp.bp.109.066001
2019453693BeardC, SawyerAT, HofmannSG. Efficacy of attention bias modification using threat and appetitive stimuli: A meta-analytic review. Behav Ther. 2012; 43(4): 724–40. doi: 10.1016/j.beth.2012.01.002
2304677694HakamataY, LissekS, Bar-HaimY, BrittonJC, FoxNA, LeibenluftE, et al
Attention bias modification treatment: a meta-analysis toward the establishment of novel treatment for anxiety. Biol Psychiatry. 2010; 68(11): 982–90. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2010.07.021
2088797795HertelPT, MathewsA. Cognitive Bias Modification: Past Perspectives, Current Findings, and Future Applications. Perspect Psychol Sci. 2011; 6(6): 521–36. doi: 10.1177/1745691611421205
2616837596StewartSH, TaylorS, BakerJM. Gender differences in dimensions of anxiety sensitivity. J Anxiety Disord. 1997; 11(2): 179–200. 916834197CannonMF, WeemsCF. Cognitive biases in childhood anxiety disorders: Do interpretive and judgment biases distinguish anxious youth from their non-anxious peers?
J Anxiety Disord. 2010; 24(7): 751–8. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2010.05.008
2055442698KeoghE, HamidR, HamidS, ElleryD. Investigating the effect of anxiety sensitivity, gender and negative interpretative bias on the perception of chest pain. Pain. 2004; 111(1): 209–17.1532782599ZhaoX, ZhangP, ChenL, ZhouR. Gender differences in the relationship between attentional bias to threat and social anxiety in adolescents. Pers Indiv Differ. 2014; 71, 108–12.100SassSM, HellerW, StewartJL, SiltonRL, EdgarJC, FisherJE, et al
Time course of attentional bias in anxiety: emotion and gender specificity. Psychophysiology. 2010; 47(2): 247–59. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8986.2009.00926.x
19863758101TurkCL, HeimbergRG, OrsilloSM, HoltCS, GitowA, StreetLL, et al
An investigation of gender differences in social phobia. J Anxiety Disord. 1998; 12(3): 209–23. 9653680102SalthouseTA. When does age-related cognitive decline begin?
Neurobiol Aging. 2009; 30(4): 507–14. doi: 10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2008.09.023
19231028103MozolicJL, LongAB, MorganAR, Rawley-PayneM, LaurientiPJ. A cognitive training intervention improves modality-specific attention in a randomized controlled trial of healthy older adults. Neurobiol Aging. 2011; 32(4): 655–68. doi: 10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2009.04.013
19428142104OpitzPC, RauchLC, TerryDP, UrryHL. Prefrontal mediation of age differences in cognitive reappraisal. Neurobiol Aging. 2012; 33(4): 645–55. doi: 10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2010.06.004
20674090105BraverTS, BarchDM, KeysBA, CarterCS, CohenJD, KayeJA, et al
Context processing in older adults: evidence for a theory relating cognitive control to neurobiology in healthy aging. J Exp Psychol Gen. 2001; 130(4): 746–63. 11757878106IoannidisJP. Effect of the statistical significance of results on the time to completion and publication of randomized efficacy trials. Jama. 1998; 279(4): 281–6. 9450711107SternJM, SimesRJ. Publication bias: evidence of delayed publication in a cohort study of clinical research projects. Bmj. 1997; 315(7109): 640–5. http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.315.7109.640. 9310565108EggerM, SmithGD. Bias in location and selection of studies. Bmj. 1998; 316(7124): 61–6. 9451274109CortinaJM. Apples and oranges (and pears, oh my!): The search for moderators in meta-analysis. Organ Res Methods. 2003; 6(4): 415–39.110WiersCE,WiersRW, Imaging the neural effects of cognitive bias modification training, NeuroImage (2016); http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.07.041.111HirschCR, ClarkDM, MathewsA. Imagery and interpretations in social phobia: Support for the combined cognitive biases hypothesis. Behav Ther. 2006; 37(3): 223–36. Imagery and interpretations in social phobia: Support for the combined cognitive biases hypothesis. doi: 10.1016/j.beth.2006.02.001
16942974112HofmannSG, AsnaaniA, HintonDE. Cultural aspects in social anxiety and social anxiety disorder. Depress Anxiety. 2010; 27(12): 1117–27. doi: 10.1002/da.20759
21132847113WoodySR, MiaoS, Kellman-McFarlaneK. Cultural differences in social anxiety: A meta-analysis of Asian and European heritage samples. Asian Am J Psychol. 2015; 6(1): 47–55.
