<?xml version="1.0"?>
Glob Adv Health MedGlob Adv Health MedgahmjGlobal Advances in Health and Medicine2164-957X2164-9561Global Advances in Health and Medicine465478026665044gahmj.2015.012.suppl10.7453/gahmj.2015.012.supplReview ArticleDistant Healing Intention Therapies: An Overview of the Scientific EvidenceRadinDeanPhDInstitute of Noetic Sciences, Petaluma, California (Dr Radin)SchlitzMarilynPhDCalifornia Pacific Medical Center Research Institute, San Francisco, California (Dr Schlitz)BaurChristopherSamueli Institute, Alexandria, Virginia (Mr Baur)Correspondence Dean Radin, PhD dradin@noetic.org112015011120154SupplBiofield Science and Healing: Toward a Transdisciplinary Approach6771© 2015 GAHM LLC.2015This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial- No Derivative 3.0 License, which permits rights to copy, distribute and transmit the work for noncommercial purposes only, provided the original work is properly cited.This article provides a broad overview of “distant healing intention” (DHI) therapies, ie, intentional healing modalities claimed to transcend the usual constraints of distance through space or time. We provide a summary of previous reviews and meta-analyses that have explored a diverse array of DHI modalities, outcome measures, and experimental protocols. While some significant experimental effects have been observed, the evidence to date does not yet provide confidence in its clinical efficacy. The purported “nonlocal” nature of DHI raises significant methodological and theoretical challenges. We recommend several avenues for improving future research.Key WordsDistant healing intentionDHInonlocalprayerDisclosures The authors completed the ICMJE Form for Potential Conflicts of Interest and had no conflicts to disclose.THEORETICAL AND OTHER CONSIDERATIONSThe preponderance of evidence for DHI effects in simple living systems and for intercessory prayer is at best suggestive of its effectiveness to alter outcomes. But the proof-of-principle offered by DMILS experiments more clearly indicates the existence of genuine interactions between distant people. This presents us with an evidence-based enigma worthy of serious consideration. However, for many researchers, the mere concept of distant healing continues to elicit significant resistance for two main reasons. The first is based on the assumption that “action at a distance” is impossible because it violates one or more physical or biological laws.8,41 The second is founded on the neuroscience-based assumption that the mind is identical to the brain, in which case it does not make sense to propose that the brain activity we call “healing intention” can interact with anything outside of the brain's own body.42,43The first critique was a game-ender for many decades, but today, the “nonlocal” connections of quantum entanglement have been convincingly demonstrated,20,44–46 establishing that instant physical correlations over macroscopic distances, as well as connections that transcend time, are no longer startling theoretical possibilities but empirical facts. The second critique is predicated on the assumption that subjective mental activity (ie, conscious awareness) somehow mechanically arises out of brain activity in spite of the fact that no one has any idea how this can occur. According to Ralph Adolphs, PhD, writing about the unsolved problems of neuroscience in a 2015 issue of Trends in Cognitive Science, one key problem is “How and why does conscious experience arise?”47 Adolphs ranks this as a problem that may never be solved, to which we might clarify that the word never is predicated on the assumption that existing frameworks for understanding the mind-brain relationship are sacrosanct. But if the brain and mind are in fact not identical, as DHI and similar consciousness-related anomalies suggest,16,48 then new possibilities arise where the mind may be able to interact with the world in ways that the brain cannot. Obviously this does not answer the second critique in a fully adequate way, but it does remind us that “impossibilities” are embedded within a context. Sometimes shifting one's perspective allows us to rethink the unthinkable.Beyond the theoretical challenges to understanding how DHI may work, we are faced with a host of epistemological challenges. Traditional selection strategies for dependent and independent variables assume that influences are localized, real-time, and explicitly sourced. None of these assumptions may hold for DHI phenomena. Defining the “when” and “where” of intentional effects and their actual source can be exceedingly difficult because anyone involved in a DHI experiment is unavoidably “entangled” with the healing process. For example, Leibovici studied patients with bloodstream infections whom were prayed for retroactively, meaning years after they were first hospitalized.49 The question explored in that study was whether DHI would be effective not only with spatial distance between the healers and patients but also with temporal distance. Results demonstrated that patients who received “retroactive” intercessory prayer had statistically significantly shorter hospital duration stays and duration of fevers compared to a control group that did not receive the retroactive prayer. From a conventional perspective, that outcome is outrageous, explainable only as a joke or a statistical fluke. But if DHI is in fact a genuine nonlocal phenomenon, then this sort of outcome may be mind-boggling, but it is also permissible.50To help identify the “when” and “where” of DHI effects, as well as the role of investigators' and patients' expectations in potentially modulating these effects, future studies should consider designs where healing spans a range of spatial and temporal distances and where independent teams are led by investigators holding a variety of expectations and beliefs about the possibility of nonlocal influences. To study whether DHI may be better understood in conventional causal terms or via more holistic or even acausal concepts, protocols could be devised that examine dose effects, where the “dose” of intention or attention must be carefully defined and measured. That is, 20 minutes of DHI applied to a patient should not be considered double the dose of 10 minutes because attention invariably wanders. And given that both spatial and temporal distance may not be constraining factors with DHI effects, dose might be better measured in terms of meaning or motivation rather than amount of time.Because DHI research often attracts hypercritical scrutiny, we recommend that prior to conducting future studies, a comprehensive description of the planned protocol is publicly registered and/or sent to an independent third party. Pre-registration is a growing trend in psychological and medical research to counter problems associated with “questionable research practices,” including selective reporting and post-hoc analyses, and as such it seems especially apropos for DHI research.51 Finally, investigators from orthodox fields who become interested in studying DHI phenomena may assume that the phenomena are simple and easily shoehorned into standard designs; in so doing, they are likely to fall into conceptual traps that specialists have learned to recognize. To avoid this, we recommend that specialists in DHI experimental designs and practices be consulted to ensure that the instruments used to study the phenomena are appropriate for the job.AcknowledgmentsThe authors thank Stefan Schmidt and Alan Pierce for their assistance in preparing this manuscript. In memory of Bernard Grad and William Braud, who inspired much of this work.REFERENCES1.DosseyLHealing words : the power of prayer and the practice of medicine. 1st ed.
San Francisco, Calif.: HarperSanFrancisco; 1993.2.Halifax-GrofJ
Hex Death. In: AngoffABarthD, eds. Proceedings of an International Conference on Parapsychology and Anthropology, 1973
New York: Parapsychology Foundation, Inc; 1974:59–79.3.SchlitzMRadinDIMalleBFSchmidtSUttsJYountGL
Distant healing intention: definitions and evolving guidelines for laboratory studies. Alternative therapies in health and medicine.
2003;9((3 Suppl)):A31–43.127764634.TargE
Evaluating distant healing: a research review. Alternative therapies in health and medicine. 11
1997;3(6):74–78.5.SchlitzMBraudW
Distant intentionality and healing: assessing the evidence. Altern Ther Health Med.
1997;3(6):62–73.93754316.BarnesPMPowell-GrinerEMcFannKNahinRL
Complementary and alternative medicine use among adults: United States, 2002. Adv Data.
2004
5
27;(343):1–19.151887337.AstinJAHarknessEErnstE
The efficacy of “distant healing”: A systematic review of randomized trials. Annals Internal Med.
2000;132:903–910.8.SloanRRamakrishnanR
The MANTRA II study. Lancet.
2005(366):1769–70.162982089.AccardiLRegoliM
Non-locality and quantum theory: new experimental evidence. In: TombesiPHirotaO, eds. Quantum communication, computing, and measurement 3.
New York: Kluwer; 2001:313–23.10.BaarsBJEdelmanDB
Consciousness, biology and quantum hypotheses. Phys Life Rev.
2012;9(3):285–94.2292583911.MelkikhAVKhrennikovA
Nontrivial quantum and quantum-like effects in biosystems: Unsolved questions and paradoxes. Prog Biophys Mol Biol.
2015
11;119(2):137–61.2616064412.SchmidtSSchneiderRUttsJWalachH
Distant intentionality and the feeling of being stared at: two meta-analyses. Br J Psychol.
2004;95(Pt 2):235–47.1514230413.SchmidtS
Can we help just by good intentions? A meta-analysis of experiments on distant intention effects. J Altern Complement Med.
2012;18(6):529–33.2278433914.BoschHSteinkampFBollerE
Examining psychokinesis: the interaction of human intention with random number generators—a meta-analysis. Psychol Bull.
2006;132(4):497.1682216215.RadinDNelsonRDobynsYHoutkooperJ
Reexamining psychokinesis: comment on Bösch, Steinkamp, and Boller (2006). Psychol Bull.
2006;132(4):529-32; discussion 533–7.1682216416.StormLTressoldiPEDi RisioL
Meta-analysis of free-response studies, 1992-2008: assessing the noise reduction model in parapsychology. Psychol Bull.
7
2010;136(4):471–85.2056516417.
BraudW, ed Allobiofeedback: immediate feedback for a psychokinetic influence upon another person's physiology
1977
RollWG, ed. Research in parapsychology.18.RadinDTaylorRBraudW
Remote mental influence of human electrodermal activity: A pilot replication. Eur J Parapsychol.
1995;11:19–34.19.RadinDI
Event-related electroencephalographic correlations between isolated human subjects. J Altern Complement Med.
2004;10(2):315–23.1516541220.RadinDI
Entangled minds. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster; 2006.21.BunnellT
The effect of “healing with intent” on pepsin enzyme activity. J Sci Explor.
1999;13(2):139–48.22.
BarryJ
General and comparative study of the psychokinetic effect on a fungus culture. J Parapsychol.
1968.23.GradB
A telekinetic effect on yeast activity. J Parapsychol.
1965;29:285–6.24.HaraldssonEThorsteinssonT
Psychokinetic effects on yeast: an exploratory experiment. Vol 1972: Scarecrow Press Metuchen, NJ; 1973:20–21.25.
NashCB
Psychokinetic control of bacterial growth. J Soc Psychical Res.
1982.26.BengstonWEKrinsleyD
The effect of the “laying on of hands” on transplanted breast cancer in mice. J Sci Explor.
2000;14(3):353–64.27.
BraudWG
Distant mental influence of rate of hemolysis of human red blood cells. J Am Soc Psychical Res.
1990.28.GronowiczGAJhaveriAClarkeLWAronowMSSmithTH
Therapeutic touch stimulates the proliferation of human cells in culture. J Altern Complement Med.
4
2008;14(3):233–9.1837057929.MagerJMooreDBendlDWongBRachlinKYountG
Evaluating biofield treatments in a cell culture model of oxidative stress. Explore (NY).
Jul-Aug
2007;3(4):386–90.1768125930.SnelFHolP
Psychokinesis experiments in casein induced amyloidosis of the hamster. JParapsychol
1983;5(1):51–76.31.SolfvinJ
Psi expectancy effects in psychic healing studies with malarial mice. Eur J Parapsychol.
1982;4(2):160–97.32.WatkinsGKWatkinsAM
Possible PK influence on the resuscitation of anesthetized mice. J Parapsychol.
1971;35(4):257–72.33.
SchlitzM
PK on living systems-further studies with anesthetized mice. Paper presented at Parapsychological Association convention; abstracted in Journal of Parapsychology, 1982.34.RoeCCharmaineSRoxburghE
Two meta-analyses of noncontact healing studies. Explore.
2014;11(1):11–23.2545744235.JonasWB
The middle way: realistic randomized controlled trials for the evaluation of spiritual healing. J Altern Complement Med.
2001;7(1):5–7.1124693636.CrawfordCCSparberAGJonasWB
A systematic review of the quality of research on hands-on and distance healing: clinical and laboratory studies. Altern Ther Health Med.
2003;9(3 Suppl):A96–104.1277646837.SoPSJiangYQinY
Touch therapies for pain relief in adults. Cochrane Database Syst Rev.
2008
10
8;(4):CD006535.1884372038.RobertsLAhmedIHallSDavisonA
Intercessory prayer for the alleviation of ill health. Cochrane Database Syst Rev.
2009
4
15;(2):CD000368.1937055739.BensonHDusekJASherwoodJB, 
Study of the Therapeutic Effects of Intercessory Prayer (STEP) in cardiac bypass patients: a multicenter randomized trial of uncertainty and certainty of receiving intercessory prayer. Am Heart J.
2006;151(4):934–42.1656956740.KrucoffMWCraterSWGallupD, 
Music, imagery, touch, and prayer as adjuncts to interventional cardiac care: the Monitoring and Actualisation of Noetic Trainings (MANTRA) II randomised study. Lancet.
7
16-22
2005;366(9481):211–7.1602351141.LederD
“Spooky actions at a distance”: physics, psi, and distant healing. J Altern Complement Med.
10
2005;11(5):923–30.1629692842.CrickF
The astonishing hypothesis : the scientific search for the soul. New York: Scribner; Maxwell Macmillan International; 1994.43.EdelmanS
Computing the mind: how the mind really works. New York: Oxford University Press; 2008.44.KwiatPGBarraza-LopezSStefanovAGisinN
Experimental entanglement distillation and ‘hidden' non-locality. Nature.
2001;409(6823):1014–7.1123400445.FuwaMTakedaSZwierzMWisemanHMFurusawaA
Experimental proof of nonlocal wavefunction collapse for a single particle using homodyne measurements. Nat Commun.
2015;6:6665.2580107146.TeoCAraujoMQuintinoMT, 
Realistic loophole-free Bell test with atom-photon entanglement. Nat Commun.
2013;4:2104.2382086547.AdolphsR
The unsolved problems of neuroscience. Trends Cogn Sci.
4
2015;19(4):173–5.2570368948.RadinDI
Supernormal. New York: Random House; 2013.49.LeiboviciL
Effects of remote, retroactive intercessory prayer on outcomes in patients with bloodstream infection: randomised controlled trial. BMJ.
2001;323(7327):1450–1.1175134950.BraudW
Wellness implications of retroactive intentional influence: exploring an outrageous hypothesis. Altern Ther Health Med.
2000;6(1):37–48.1063182151.VandenbrouckeJP
Preregistration: when shall we start the real discussion?
Eur J Public Health.
8
2015;25(4):555–6.2613882052.OmuraY
Impression on observing psychic surgery and healing in Brazil which appear to incorporate (+) qi gong energy &amp; the use of acupuncture points. Acupunct Electrother Res.
1997;22(1):17–33.918891353.BengstonWF
Methodological difficulties involving control groups in healing research: parallels between laying on of hands for the treatment of induced mammary cancers in mice to research in homeopathy. J Altern Complement Med.
4
2004;10(2):227–8.1516540154.BengstonWFMogaM
Resonance, placebo effects, and Type II errors: some implications from healing research for experimental methods. J Altern Complement Med.
4
2007;13(3):317–27.17480130
