<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front Hum NeurosciFront Hum NeurosciFront. Hum. Neurosci.Frontiers in Human Neuroscience1662-5161Frontiers Media S.A.348880010.3389/fnhum.2012.00295NeuroscienceOriginal ResearchRandomized Controlled Trial of Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction Versus Aerobic Exercise: Effects on the Self-Referential Brain Network in Social Anxiety DisorderGoldinPhilippe1*ZivMichal1JazaieriHooria1GrossJames J.11Department of Psychology, Stanford UniversityStanford, CA, USAEdited by: Amishi P. Jha, University of Miami, USAReviewed by: Lawrence W. Barsalou, Emory University, USA; Norman Farb, Baycrest, Canada*Correspondence: Philippe Goldin, Department of Psychology, Stanford University, Jordan Hall, Building 420, Stanford, CA 94305-2130, USA. e-mail: pgoldin@stanford.edu0511201220126295241201205102012Copyright © 2012 Goldin, Ziv, Jazaieri and Gross.2012This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in other forums, provided the original authors and source are credited and subject to any copyright notices concerning any third-party graphics etc.Background: Social anxiety disorder (SAD) is characterized by distorted self-views. The goal of this study was to examine whether mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) alters behavioral and brain measures of negative and positive self-views. Methods: Fifty-six adult patients with generalized SAD were randomly assigned to MBSR or a comparison aerobic exercise (AE) program. A self-referential encoding task was administered at baseline and post-intervention to examine changes in behavioral and neural responses in the self-referential brain network during functional magnetic resonance imaging. Patients were cued to decide whether positive and negative social trait adjectives were self-descriptive or in upper case font. Results: Behaviorally, compared to AE, MBSR produced greater decreases in negative self-views, and equivalent increases in positive self-views. Neurally, during negative self versus case, compared to AE, MBSR led to increased brain responses in the posterior cingulate cortex (PCC). There were no differential changes for positive self versus case. Secondary analyses showed that changes in endorsement of negative and positive self-views were associated with decreased social anxiety symptom severity for MBSR, but not AE. Additionally, MBSR-related increases in dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (DMPFC) activity during negative self-view versus case were associated with decreased social anxiety related disability and increased mindfulness. Analysis of neural temporal dynamics revealed MBSR-related changes in the timing of neural responses in the DMPFC and PCC for negative self-view versus case. Conclusion: These findings suggest that MBSR attenuates maladaptive habitual self-views by facilitating automatic (i.e., uninstructed) recruitment of cognitive and attention regulation neural networks. This highlights potentially important links between self-referential and cognitive-attention regulation systems and suggests that MBSR may enhance more adaptive social self-referential processes in patients with SAD.social anxietyself-viewmindfulnessfMRIexercisebrainselfmeditationIntroductionSelf-views can powerfully influence how a person thinks, feels, and behaves, particularly in social contexts. The relationship of self-views to social functioning is especially salient in the clinical context of social anxiety disorder (SAD). Cognitive models of social anxiety (Clark and Wells, 1995) suggest that distorted self-views, specifically, regarding the self as socially awkward, inadequate, or flawed are an essential feature of SAD. Recent conceptualizations highlight distorted social self-views as the core problem in SAD (Moscovitch, 2009). These models suggest that maladaptive social self-reflective processes are implicated in cognitively biased evaluations of self which generate negative emotions, disrupt emotion regulation, and interfere with social self-efficacy and performance (Spurr and Stopa, 2002).Meta-analyses of neuroimaging studies of self-referential processing in healthy adults have identified a set of three cortical midline brain regions that comprise the self-referential network (SRN), including the ventromedial prefrontal cortex (VMPFC), dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (DMPFC), and posterior cingulate cortex/precuneus (hereafter abbreviated as PCC; Figure 1; Northoff et al., 2006, 2011). To induce activation in the SRN, studies have used judgments of visually presented trait adjectives (Kelley et al., 2002), aurally presented statements (Johnson et al., 2002), or mental reflection on self-traits (Kjaer et al., 2002). Most studies have used tasks that require making a rapid judgment of whether or not a specific trait applies to oneself. Specifically, neural activity in the VMPFC has been shown to be related to ratings of self-relatedness (Phan et al., 2004; de Greck et al., 2008). Activation of the DMPFC and PCC has been observed during self-endorsement of positive and negative traits in healthy adults (Fossati et al., 2003).Figure 1Self-referential network from Northoff et al. (2006).Neuroimaging studies of self-referential processing have begun to investigate abnormal patterns of SRN activity in a variety of clinical samples, however, results are mixed. In patients with major depressive disorder, fMRI investigations have reported elevated VMPFC activation during event-related task designs which is thought to be associated with more automatic alerting to self-relevant information, as well as elevated transient DMPFC activation during block task designs which may represent more strategic evaluation (Lemogne et al., 2012). In patients with SAD, fMRI investigations have observed SRN activation during self-referential processing of trait adjectives, as well as brain regions implicated in language, memory, affective, and visual processing during social trait self-endorsement (Goldin et al., 2009a), and decreased VMPFC response for first (versus second) person self-referential statements which were associated with increased social anxiety symptom severity (Blair et al., 2011). However, there are no randomized controlled trials (RCT) that have compared the impact of different psychosocial interventions on SRN activity in patients with SAD. Conducting such RCTs may provide stronger evidence for the function and modulation of the SRN in clinical samples.One especially intriguing psychosocial intervention that directly cultivates non-identification with self-views is mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR; Kabat-Zinn, 1990). Meta-analyses of MBSR training in healthy adults have shown reliable reductions in symptoms of anxiety, stress, and ruminative thinking (Chiesa and Serretti, 2009). Among patients with anxiety disorders, meta-analysis indicates robust reduction of anxiety, and depression symptoms (Vøllestad et al., 2012). An important fMRI study of self-reference in a non-clinical sample of adults found that for the contrast of experiential (versus narrative) self-focus MBSR resulted in brain response decreases in anterior VMPFC and DMPFC regions and increases in a right lateralized network including dorsolateral and ventrolateral PFC, insular cortex, supramarginal gyrus, angular gyrus, inferior parietal lobule suggesting suppression of conceptual narrative self-processing, and enhancement of viscerosomatic processing and present-moment focused attention (Farb et al., 2007). Inferences from this study are limited because brain responses were measured only at post-MBSR. In the few studies of patients with SAD, there are preliminary positive results for MBSR training, including reduction of clinical symptoms and increased well-being (Koszycki et al., 2007; Jazaieri et al., 2012). Proposed mechanisms of MBSR include modulation of attention regulation, body awareness, emotion regulation, and self-views (Hölzel et al., 2011). Thus, MBSR is expected to decrease grasping at conceptual self-views (instantiated in the SRN and language brain networks) and to increase present-moment experiential modes of self-processing (instantiated in viscerosomatic networks). The impact of MBSR on the SRN in clinical populations, however, is not yet understood.In patients with SAD, MBSR has been shown to modulate attention regulation, emotion regulation, and self-views (Goldin et al., 2009a, 2012; Goldin and Gross, 2010). Neurally, during self-referential processing in patients with SAD, MBSR has been shown to decrease neural responses in brain regions related to self-referential and language processing for positive self-views, and increase responses in brain regions linked to attention engagement and regulation for negative self-views (Goldin et al., 2009a). This study also reported associations of pre-to-post-MBSR increases in attention engagement related parietal brain regions and decreases in anxiety symptoms. However, important caveats of these studies include a small sample size, participant self-selection, and no active comparison intervention. Thus, the implementation of a RCT with two active and dose matched stress reduction programs should support stronger inferences about the effects of MBSR on self-views.In addition to modulation of brain response magnitude, there is growing evidence of abnormal neural temporal dynamics during social cognition and emotion regulation in patients with SAD (Campbell et al., 2007; Goldin et al., 2009b). One study has reported MBSR-related changes in neural temporal dynamics of emotional reactivity to negative self-views in adults with SAD (Goldin and Gross, 2010). Currently, nothing is known about how MBSR impacts the neural temporal dynamics of brain responses within the SRN. Analysis of neural temporal dynamics might elucidate the effects of MBSR on other cognitive processes that come online in patients with SAD when engaging to self-referential processing, such as shifts in attention regulation and cognitive regulation of emotional reactivity to self-views.Considered together, these changes suggest that MBSR likely modulates multiple cognitive processes. MBSR is hypothesized to increase the ability to decenter from habitual patterns of reactivity. However, in the case of adults with SAD, MBSR may have more specific effects such as modifying some of the core cognitive biases (e.g., distorted self-views, maladaptive attention, and emotional processing, deficient cognitive regulation) that are fundamental features of social anxiety.The goal of the present study was to investigate the differential effects of MBSR versus an active control condition [aerobic exercise (AE) stress reduction] on the neural bases of self-referential processing in patients with generalized SAD in the context of a RCT. MBSR cultivates a non-judgmental, pliable present-moment awareness that decreases habitual patterns of evaluation and reactivity, and increases psychological flexibility. In patients with SAD, MBSR is associated with reduced symptoms of anxiety, depression and self-deprecation, and increased quality of life and functionality (Koszycki et al., 2007). A recent review suggests that the brain-based mechanisms underlying MBSR include attention regulation, body awareness, emotion regulation, and changes in the self-views (Hölzel et al., 2011). Few studies, however, have investigated these proposed brain-based mechanisms in the context of a RCT. To do this, we choose AE as a control condition for several reasons. Like MBSR, AE has been shown to improve both physical and mental health (Penedo and Dahn, 2005), especially symptoms of stress, depression, and anxiety (Petruzzello et al., 1991; Stich, 1998; Ströhle, 2009) in clinical samples of mixed anxiety (e.g., Merom et al., 2007), panic disorder (e.g., Broocks et al., 1998; Dratcu, 2001), and generalized anxiety disorder (e.g., Steptoe et al., 1989; McEntee and Halgin, 1999). As implemented in this study, we matched the amount of individual and group practice for MBSR and AE. Presently, there are no studies describing the impact of AE on self-views in patients with SAD.We conducted a RCT in which we obtained behavioral and neural measures of self-views during an fMRI assessment in patients with generalized SAD before and after MBSR or AE. For behavioral responses, we expected that, compared to AE, MBSR would result in self-endorsement of more adaptive self-views, namely, greater decreases in negative and greater increases in positive self-views. For neural responses, based on prior studies that reported reduction in cortical midline brain region responses during experiential (versus narrative) self-focus (Farb et al., 2007) and during self-referential processing in patients with SAD (Goldin et al., 2009a), we expected that, compared to AE, MBSR would result in greater reductions during negative and positive self-referential processing in the VMPFC and DMPFC. Based on previous reports of MBSR-related increased activity in parietal cortex regions associated with attention engagement and regulation in general (Farb et al., 2007; Hölzel et al., 2011) and specifically in patients with SAD (Goldin et al., 2009a; Goldin and Gross, 2010), we expected that, compared to AE, MBSR would result in greater increases in PCC during negative and positive self-referential processing. In secondary analyses, we examined whether MBSR and AE-related changes in behavioral and brain responses related to changes in clinical symptoms and mindfulness, and how MBSR impacted the neural temporal dynamics in the three SRN brain regions.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Participants were unmedicated patients seeking treatment for SAD who met DSM-IV (American Psychiatric Association, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1994</xref>) criteria for generalized SAD. Of 316 individuals assessed for eligibility, 260 were excluded (173 for not meeting study criteria, 66 for other reasons, and 21 declined to participate). The remaining 56 participants were randomly assigned to either MBSR (<italic>n</italic> = 31) or AE (<italic>n</italic> = 25; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Groups did not differ in gender, age, ethnicity, or education (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). fMRI assessments at both baseline and post-intervention were available for 24 MBSR and 18 AE participants.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Consolidated standards of reporting trials diagram for randomized controlled trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) versus aerobic exercise (AE)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-06-00295-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Demographic characteristics at baseline for patients randomized to mindfulness-based stress reduction versus aerobic exercise</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBSR</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AE</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>-Test</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 31</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 25</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">or χ<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (61.3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (40%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup> = 2.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (<italic>M</italic> years ± SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.87 ± 8.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.88 ± 7.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> = 0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup> = 0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (41.9%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (40%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (45.2%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (44%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.7%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiracial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.2%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (12%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (<italic>M</italic> years ± SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.40 ± 2.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.84 ± 2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> = 0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current axis-I comorbidity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup> = 4.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (32%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (32%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major depressive disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (24%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dysthymia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (12%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific phobia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panic disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agoraphobia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obsessive-compulsive disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Past axis-I comorbidity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup> = 1.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major depressive disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (29%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dysthymia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panic disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obsessive-compulsive disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substance abuse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eating disorder</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Past psychotherapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (48%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (36%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup> = 1.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Past pharmacotherapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (23%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (20%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup> = 1.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAF (<italic>M</italic> ± SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.36 ± 5.87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.38 ± 4.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> = 1.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGI (<italic>M</italic> ± SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93 ± 1.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22 ± 0.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> = 1.33</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic><italic>n</italic>, Sample size, <italic>M</italic>, mean; SD, standard deviation; GAF, global assessment of functioning; CGI, clinical global impression</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Patients passed an MR safety screen and had to be medication and psychotherapy-free for at least 6 months with no history of medical disorders or head trauma. Patients had to have a primary diagnosis of generalized SAD and no evidence of thought disorders, bipolar depression, alcohol, or drug dependence. Patients were not permitted to be currently in any form of pharmacological or psychological treatment. Patients were excluded if they had previously completed an MBSR course or if they had a regular meditation practice or AE regime (defined as three or more times per week, for more than 2 months). Patients randomized to MBSR and AE did not differ in current or past Axis-I comorbidity, current Global Assessment of Functioning or Clinical Global Impression, and past psychotherapy or past pharmacotherapy (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Procedure</title><p>Patients were recruited through web-based community listings and referrals from mental health providers. After passing a telephone screening, potential participants were administered the ADIS-IV-L (Di Nardo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">1994</xref>) by a clinical psychologist. We enrolled patients with a principal diagnosis of generalized SAD operationalized as (a) moderate or higher severity (≥4 on a scale of 0–8) on the ADIS-IV-L Clinician’s Severity Rating for SAD and (b) social fear for five or more distinct social or performance situations in the SAD section. Patients were randomly assigned to MBSR or AE using a biased coin randomization procedure (Efron, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">1971</xref>) which entails higher probability of allocation to the group with fewer participants. This method controls for potential confounds encountered when a greater number of participants are assigned at specific time points during a trial to one of two interventions. Patients were administered self-report clinical and fMRI scanning assessments before and after MBSR and AE. All participants provided informed consent in accordance with the Stanford University Human Subjects Committee and federal guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction</title><p>Mindfulness-based stress reduction consisted of eight, weekly 2.5 h group classes, a 1-day meditation retreat, and daily home practice. Patients were trained in formal meditation, informal practice, and Hatha yoga. Daily logs were collected each week to measure group and individual meditation and yoga practice. Patients attended MBSR courses offered by seven different teachers in eight healthcare settings throughout the San Francisco Bay Area. Instructors had an average of 15.7 years (SD = 4.1 years, range = 10–20 years) of MBSR teaching experience.</p></sec><sec><title>Aerobic exercise</title><p>To match the individual and group components of MSBR, participants in the 8-week AE intervention were provided a 2-month gym membership and were required to complete weekly at least two individual AE sessions and one group AE session (other than meditation or yoga).</p></sec><sec><title>Self-referential encoding task</title><p>The self-referential encoding task (SRET; Derry and Kuiper, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">1981</xref>) is considered an information processing measure of self-schema. Stimuli consisted of 25 positive and 25 negative social trait adjectives from the Affective Norms of Emotion Words database (Bradley and Lang, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">1999</xref>), balanced (all <italic>p</italic>s &gt; 0.51) on word frequency (positive adjectives = 40.5, negative adjectives = 33.6) and number of letters (positive adjectives = 6.9, negative adjectives = 7.2), as well as on arousal (positive adjectives = 5.54, negative adjectives = 5.43 on a scale of 1 = low to 9 = high using) and valence (deviation from neutral: positive adjectives = 2.66, negative adjectives = 2.58 on a scale of 1 = most negative, 5 = neutral, 9 = most positive) based on the nine-point Self-Assessment Manikin rating system (Lang, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">1980</xref>).</p><p>The SRET was 5 min and 39 s in length. Each adjective was presented twice, once in each of two conditions. The self-referential condition assessed self-focused social-evaluative processing. Case identification was used as a comparison condition to control for reading negative and positive adjectives while determining whether the word consisted of upper or lower case letters. Each of the four trial types (two conditions by two valences) included five blocks. Each block consisted of fixation, question (either “Describes ME?” or “UPPER case?”), and five adjectives of the same valence presented one at a time for 3 s each (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Trial structure for self-referential encoding task</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-06-00295-g003"/></fig><p>Stimulus order included a pseudo-random block sequence with no more than two blocks of the same condition in a row and a random sequence of words and upper/lower case within each block. Patients pressed buttons to indicate whether or not a word was self-descriptive or in uppercase letters.</p></sec><sec><title>Measures of clinical symptoms and mindfulness</title><p>To measure severity of social anxiety symptoms, we used the 24-item <italic>Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale-Self-Report</italic> (LSAS-SR; Liebowitz, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">1987</xref>; Fresco et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">2001</xref>), which consists of questions that assess social interaction situations (11 items) and performance situations (13 items). A four-point Likert-type scale is used for ratings of fear and of avoidance, with a range from 0 (<italic>none</italic> and <italic>never</italic>, respectively) to 3 (<italic>severe</italic> and <italic>usually</italic>, respectively) for situations during the past week. Ratings are summed for a total LSAS-SR score (range = 0–144). The LSAS-SR has reliability and construct validity (Rytwinski et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">2009</xref>) and its internal consistency (Cronbach’s alpha) for this study was 0.90 in MBSR and 0.90 in AE.</p><p>To measure social anxiety related disability, we administered the <italic>Sheehan Disability Scale</italic> (SDS; Sheehan, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">1983</xref>) which measures work, social life, and family life impairment as a function of SAD and comorbid conditions, and has demonstrated good internal consistency and validity (Hambrick et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2004</xref>), and its internal consistency in this study was 0.68 in MBSR and 0.68 in AE.</p><p>To measure mindfulness, we used the <italic>Kentucky Inventory of Mindfulness Skills</italic> (FFMQ; Baer, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2003</xref>). It is a 39-item self-report measure which measures mindfulness, and includes four components: observing, describing, acting with awareness, and accepting without judgment. Items are rated on a five-point Likert scale. The instrument has good internal consistency and validity (Baer et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2004</xref>), and its internal consistency in this study was 0.76 in MBSR and 0.85 in AE.</p><p>To measure the potential confound of social desirability, we administered the 10-item <italic>Marlowe–Crowne Social Desirability Scale</italic> (MCSDS; Crowne and Marlowe, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">1960</xref>). The instrument consists of true-false items with four reverse coded items, with higher scores reflecting a greater tendency to give a socially desirable response. It has shown adequate internal consistency and reliability (Crino et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1983</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>fMRI acquisition</title><p>Imaging was performed on a General Electric 3 T Signa magnet using a custom-built quadrature “dome” elliptical bird cage head coil and a T2*-weighted gradient echo spiral-in/out pulse sequence that used blood oxygenation level-dependent (BOLD) contrast. Head movement was minimized using a bite bar and padding. During a single run, 226 volumes (each consisting of 22 sequential axial slices) were obtained (TR = 1500 ms, TE = 30 ms, flip angle = 60, FOV = 22 cm, frequency encoding = 64, voxel = 3.438 mm × 4.5 mm). A high-resolution anatomical scan was acquired using a fast spin-echo spoiled grass pulse sequence (voxel = 0.85942 mm × 1.2 mm; FOV = 22 cm, frequency encoding = 256).</p></sec><sec><title>fMRI data preprocessing</title><p>Analysis of functional neuroimages (AFNI) software (Cox, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1996</xref>) was used for preprocessing and statistical analysis. Preprocessing included an analysis of potential outliers, volume registration to a base image, motion correction, 4 mm<sup>3</sup> isotropic Gaussian spatial smoothing, high-pass filtering (0.011 Hz), linear detrending, and conversion into percentage change in each voxel. No volumes demonstrated motion in the <italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, or <italic>z</italic> directions in excess of ±0.8 mm. There was no stimulus-correlated motion, as assessed by correlations between condition-specific reference functions and <italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, <italic>z</italic> motion correction parameters (all <italic>p</italic>s &gt; 0.48).</p></sec><sec><title>fMRI statistical analysis</title><p>Multiple-regression was implemented with AFNI 3dDeconvolve and included baseline parameters to remove mean, linear, and quadratic trends, and motion-related variance in the BOLD signal. Regressors for the negative self, negative case, positive self, and positive case were convolved with the gamma variate model (Cohen, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1997</xref>) of the hemodynamic response function. Functional MRI BOLD signal intensity was computed as percentage of signal change [(MR signal per voxel per time point/mean MR signal in that voxel for the entire functional run) × 100]. Brain maps were converted to Talairach atlas space (Talairach and Tournoux, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">1988</xref>) and second-level group statistical parametric maps were produced according to a random-effects model.</p><p>Repeated-measures analysis of variance with planned follow-up <italic>t</italic>-tests was conducted to examine average BOLD responses in masks for each of the three cortical midline SRN regions (VMPFC, DMPFC, and PCC). The <italic>a priori</italic> rectangular region-of-interest masks were defined by a meta-analysis of 27 neuroimaging studies (Northoff et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">2006</xref>). The Talairach coordinates of the boundaries of the three rectangular masks are: VMPFC <italic>x</italic> = −12 to 8, <italic>y</italic> = 38–60, <italic>z</italic> = −7 to 21, DMPFC: <italic>x</italic> = −14 to 12, <italic>y</italic> = −11 to 31, <italic>z</italic> = 37–61, and PCC: <italic>x</italic> = −14 to 8, <italic>y</italic> = −74 to −48, <italic>z</italic> = 10–52.</p><p>For the examination of pre-to-post-intervention changes in the temporal dynamics in each region we used repeated-measures ANOVA with the Greenhouse–Geisser correction for potential violations of sphericity in the time course of 10 time points (or 15 s per trial).</p><p>We also conducted whole-brain <italic>t</italic>-tests to examine within-group changes pre-to-post-MBSR and AE, separately, on negative and positive self-views. We used AlphaSim, a Monte Carlo simulation bootstrapping program in the AFNI library, to protect against false positive cluster detection (Forman et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">1995</xref>). The program determined that a voxel-wise <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 threshold and cluster volume threshold of ≤213 mm<sup>3</sup> (4 voxels × 3.438 mm × 4.5 mm) provided protection against false positive cluster detection at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></sec></sec>ResultsClinical responsesAs shown in Table 2, both MBSR and AE yielded significant reductions in social anxiety symptom severity (LSAS-SR; ts &gt; 4.05, ps &lt; 0.001), SAD-related disability (SDS; ts &gt; 2.29, ps &lt; 0.05), and increases in mindfulness (KIMS; ts &gt; 2.26, ps &lt; 0.05). However, there were no between-group differences in pre-to-post change (all ps &gt; 0.34). A full account of the treatment-related self-reported changes in clinical and well-being measures has been published elsewhere (Jazaieri et al., 2012).Table 2Self-endorsement and clinical variables.MBSR n = 31AE n = 25Mean ± SDMean ± SDLIEBOWITZ SOCIAL ANXIETY SCALE-SELF-REPORTPre87.3 ± 20.690.1 ± 17.1Post56.7 ± 19.061.4 ± 28.6SHEEHAN DISABILITY SCALEPre17.8 ± 7.118.0 ± 6.8Post9.2 ± 3.813.5 ± 8.5KENTUCKY INVENTORY OF MINDFULNESS SKILLSPre110.9 ± 12.9110.9 ± 14.9Post126.5 ± 13.2117.5 ± 14.6NEGATIVE SELF-ENDORSEMENTPre66.8 ± 18.465.3 ± 18.7Post33.6 ± 22.049.8 ± 27.0POSITIVE SELF-ENDORSEMENTPre32.3 ± 16.735.5 ± 20.3Post50.7 ± 28.146.2 ± 20.0To rule out the possibility of a social desirability response bias on self-report measures, we examined the relationship of the MCSDS and the clinical variables listed in Table 2. We found no relationship (rs: −0.20 to +0.11, all ps &gt; 0.09) between the MCSDS and baseline SRET negative self-endorsement, SRET positive self-endorsement, social anxiety symptom severity (LSAS), SAD-related disability (SDS), and mindfulness skills (Kentucky Inventory of Mindfulness Skills). There was also no relationship between the MC and the same measures at post-intervention (rs: −0.08 to 0.21, all ps &gt; 0.21).Behavioral responsesFor self-endorsement of negative social traits, a 2 Group (MBSR, AE) × 2 Time (pre, post) repeated-measures ANOVA yielded no main effect of group (p &gt; 0.25), a main effect of time (F = 46.31, p &lt; 0.0001, ηp2 = 0.63), and an interaction of group by time (F = 4.50, p &lt; 0.05, ηp2 = 0.14). Follow-up paired t-tests showed decreases in negative self-endorsement from pre-to-post-MBSR (change = −33.2, t = 5.72, p &lt; 0.001, ηp2 = 0.70) and AE (change = −15.5, t = 3.84, p &lt; 0.002, ηp2 = 0.53). Compared to AE, MBSR led to greater decreases in negative self-endorsement (t = 2.10, p &lt; 0.05, ηp2 = 0.16; Figure 4; Table 2).Figure 4Blood oxygenation level-dependent signal at baseline for negative self versus case and positive self versus case for all patients with SAD. T-maps were thresholded at t &gt; 3.65, voxel-wise p &lt; 0.001 and cluster volume &gt;6 voxels in order to obtain a cluster-wise p &lt; 0.05. *p &lt; 0.05; error bars = SEM.For self-endorsement of positive social traits, a 2 Group × 2 Time repeated-measures ANOVA yielded no main effect of group (p &gt; 0.84), a main effect of time (F1,28 = 25.75, p &lt; 0.001, ηp2 = 0.49), and no interaction of group by time (p &gt; 0.33). Follow-up paired t-tests revealed increases in positive self-endorsement from pre-to-post-MBSR (change = 18.4, t = 4.14, p &lt; 0.001, ηp2 = 0.51) and AE (change = 10.7, t = 3.02, p &lt; 0.01, ηp2 = 0.41) that were not statistically different (t = 0.97, p &gt; 0.34).Brain responsesManipulation checkTo confirm that the SRET task induced activation of the cortical midline SRN, we examined BOLD responses for negative and positive self-views, separately, across all patients at baseline. There was evidence of robust activations in VMPFC, DMPFC, and PCC regions for the contrasts of negative self versus case and positive self versus case (Figure 5).Figure 5Pre-to-post change in self-endorsement of negative and positive self-views.Treatment-related changes in the self-referential networkWe conducted a 2 Group (MBSR, AE) × 2 Time (pre, post) repeated-measures ANOVA of BOLD responses in each of the three SRN a priori ROIs (DMPFC, VMPFC, PCC) for the contrasts of negative self (versus case) and positive self (versus case), separately.Negative self-viewFor the DMPFC, there were no main effects of time (p &gt; 0.14) or group (p &gt; 0.89), but there was a significant interaction of group by time (F = 8.87, p &lt; 0.005, ηp2 = 0.18). Follow-up paired t-tests showed no significant change in BOLD signal from pre-to-post-MBSR (change = 0.03, p &gt; 0.29, ηp2 = 0.4) and a decrease from pre-to-post-AE (change = −0.10, t = 3.62, p = 0.002, ηp2 = 0.45; Figure 6). For the VMPFC, there were no main or interaction effects (all ps &gt; 0.35). For the PCC, there were no main effects of time (p &gt; 0.82) or group (p &gt; 0.17), and a significant interaction of group by time (F = 6.29, p &lt; 0.05, ηp2 = 0.13). Follow-up t-tests showed an increase from pre-to-post-MBSR (change = 0.09, t = 2.16, p &lt; 0.05, ηp2 = 0.16) and no significant change in AE (change = −0.07, p &gt; 0.15, ηp2 = 0.12).Figure 6Blood oxygenation level-dependent signal in the three self-referential network brain regions pre- and post-mindfulness-based stress reduction and aerobic exercise in patients with social anxiety disorder for positive self versus case and negative self versus case (A) Dorsomedial Prefrontal Cortex. (B) Ventromedial Prefrontal Cortex. (C) Posterior Cingulate Cortex. *p &lt; 0.05; error bars = SEM.Positive self-viewThere were no main or interaction effects (all ps &gt; 0.10) in the VMPFC, DMPFC, and PCC.Secondary analysesWe examined whether MBSR and AE-related changes in behavioral and brain responses were related to changes in clinical symptoms and mindfulness, and also tested how MBSR impacted the neural temporal dynamics in the three SRN brain regions for the contrast of negative self versus case. For completeness, we also report the within-group effects of MBSR and AE, separately, on whole-brain responses for negative and positive self-referential processing.Association of behavioral responses and clinical symptomsFor behavioral responses, decrease in self-endorsement of negative self-views was associated with decrease in social anxiety symptom severity (LSAS-SR) from pre-to-post-MBSR (r = 0.85, p &lt; 0.001), but not AE (r = 0.00, p &gt; 0.99; Zdiff = 2.48, p = 0.013). Increase in self-endorsement of positive self-views was associated with decrease in social anxiety symptom severity from pre-to-post-MBSR (r = −0.94, p &lt; 0.001), but not from pre-to-post-AE (r = −0.11, p &gt; 0.73; Zdiff = 3.25, p = 0.001). There was no relationship with mindfulness (KIMS).Association of brain responses and clinical symptoms/mindfulnessFor the contrast of self-endorsement of negative self (versus case), increases in DMPFC activity were associated with (a) decreased social anxiety related disability (SDS) from pre-to-post-MBSR (r = −0.58, p &lt; 0.05; Figure A1 in Appendix) and AE (r = −0.63, p &lt; 0.05) and (b) increased mindfulness (KIMS) in MBSR (r = 0.60, p &lt; 0.05; Figure A2 in Appendix), but not in AE (r = 0.35, p &gt; 0.43; Zdiff = 0.80, p &gt; 0.42). For the contrast of self-endorsement of positive self (versus case), decreases in DMPFC activity were associated with increased mindfulness (KIMS) in MBSR (r = −0.53, p &lt; 0.05; Figure A3 in Appendix) but not in AE (r = 0.21, p &gt; 0.65; Zdiff = 1.98, p &lt; 0.05).Neural temporal dynamicsFor the contrast of negative self (versus case) in the MBSR group, we conducted a 2 Group (MBSR, AE) × 2 Time (pre, post) × 10 TRs (ten 1.5 s TRs or brain volume acquisitions) repeated-measures ANOVA with Greenhouse–Geisser correction on BOLD responses for each of the three SRN brain regions.In the DMPFC, there was not a three-way interaction (p &gt; 0.18). However, there was a group by time interaction (F = 8.87, p &lt; 0.005, ηp2 = 0.18; Figure 7). Paired t-tests comparing BOLD response at each time point in the 15-s blocks showed significant increases from pre-to-post-MBSR in the middle of the 15-s blocks and significant decreases from pre-to-post-AE in the early and later segments of blocks.Figure 7Blood oxygen level-dependent signal time series in the (A) dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (DMPFC) and (B) posterior cingulate cortex (PCC) across each 15 s block for the contrast of negative self-view versus case pre- and post-MSBR and AE. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01; error bars = SEM.In the VMPFC, there were no three- or two-way interactions (all ps &gt; 0.35).In the PCC, there was not a three-way interaction (p &gt; 0.08). However, there was an interaction of group by time (F = 6.29, p &lt; 0.05, ηp2 = 0.13). Paired t-tests comparing BOLD response at each time point in the 15-s blocks again showed significant increases from pre-to-post-MBSR in the middle of the 15-s blocks and significant decreases from pre-to-post-AE in the early segment of blocks.Treatment-related changes in whole-brainFor MBSR, a paired t-test yielded pre-to-post BOLD signal increases for negative self (versus case) in ventromedial, left ventrolateral, and bilateral dorsolateral PFC, PCC/precuneus, left inferior parietal lobule, and left posterior superior temporal gyrus (Table A1 in Appendix). The contrast of positive self (versus case) yielded BOLD signal increases in anterior and posterior ventromedial, dorsomedial, right ventrolateral, and left anterior dorsolateral PFC, as well as subcortical uncus. For AE, a paired t-test revealed no significant pre-to-post BOLD signal increases for negative self (versus case), and increased responses in only the left mid-insula for positive self (versus case Table A2 in Appendix).Conflict of Interest StatementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.This work was supported by the National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine Institutes of Health awarded to James Gross (Grant AT003644).AppendixTable A1Pre-to-post-mindfulness-based stress reduction changes in BOLD responses for negative and positive self versus case.Brain regionsBAxyz%Vol mm3t-TestMBSR post versuspreNegative self &gt; caseFRONTAL LOBESRostromedial PFC10−3 62 80.169573.56Caudomedial PFC107 52 −20.124263.21L middle frontal gyrus8−38 35 500.229043.15R middle frontal gyrus831 31 460.1212233.29L Ventrolateral PFC47−38 31 −20.1410113.47TEMPORAL LOBESL superior temporal gyrus22−69 −13 10.152134.18PARIETAL LOBESPCC/precuneus31/70 −61 290.1012773.62L inferior parietal lobule40−45 −61 460.214263.66Negative case &gt; selfNonePositive self &gt; caseFRONTAL LOBESRostromedial PFC100 62 120.188514.64Dorsomedial PFC83 52 500.413723.46L rostral superior frontal gyrus9−17 52 290.083193.65Caudal rectal gyrus257 4 −160.243193.55R ventrolateral PFC4658 31 120.142133.36SUBCORTICALL uncus28−31 4 −190.083193.15Positive case &gt; selfNoneItalicized brain regions are located within the Northoff defined self-referential cortical midline network. xyz = Talairach coordinates for peak of cluster, % = BOLD percent signal change for contrast, t-value threshold ≥3.10, voxel p &lt; 0.005, minimum cluster volume threshold &gt;213 mm3 (4 voxels × 3.438 mm × 4.5 mm), cluster-wise p &lt; 0.01. BA, Brodmann area; BOLD, blood oxygen level-dependent; L, left; MFG, middle frontal gyrus; PCC, posterior cingulate cortex; PFC, prefrontal cortex; R, right; SAD, social anxiety disorder; Vol, volume.Table A2Pre-to-post aerobic exercise changes in BOLD responses for negative and positive self versus case.Brain regionsBAxyz%Vol mm3t-TestAE post versuspreNegative self &gt; caseNoneNegative case &gt; selfFRONTAL LOBESDorsal medial PFC80 25 43−0.17479−3.64Medial PFC90 49 15−0.14213−3.34Rostral anterior cingulate243 27 1−0.17479−3.59L ventral lateral PFC47−31 25 −2−0.10319−4.66L ventral lateral PFC47−48 31 −9−0.27213−3.27R inferior frontal gyrus4541 21 12−0.10213−4.17PARIETAL LOBESR lateral precuneus728 −41 43−0.14266−3.39OCCIPITAL LOBESR lingual gyrus183 −79 −9−0.20798−4.68L lingual gyrus18−7 −65 5−0.11532−3.28L lingual gyrus18−3 −79 −6−0.19213−4.16SUBCORTICALR caudate3 1 12−0.17745−3.40R caudate14 11 5−0.12479−4.84R caudate17 −10 22−0.09213−3.71R thalamus14 −10 1−0.10426−4.76Negative case &gt; selfNonePositive self &gt; caseL insula13−31 −10 150.072133.65Positive case &gt; selfNoneItalicized brain regions are located within the Northoff defined self-referential cortical midline network. xyz = Talairach coordinates for peak of cluster, % = BOLD percent signal change for contrast, t-value threshold ≥3.10, voxel p &lt; 0.005, minimum cluster volume threshold &gt;213 mm3 (4 voxels × 3.438 mm × 4.5 mm), cluster-wise p &lt; 0.01. BA, Brodmann area; BOLD, blood oxygen level-dependent; L, left; PFC, prefrontal cortex; R, right; SAD, social anxiety disorder; Vol, volume.Figure A1Association of pre-to-post-MBSR changes in DMPFC during negative self versus case and social anxiety related disability.Figure A2Association of pre-to-post-MBSR changes in DMPFC during negative self versus case and mindfulness skills.Figure A3Association of pre-to-post-MBSR changes in DMPFC during positive self versus case and mindfulness skills.ReferencesAmerican Psychiatric Association. (1994). Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders. Washington, DC: American Psychiatric AssociationBaerR. A. (2003). Mindfulness training as a clinical intervention: a conceptual and empirical review. Clin. Psychol.10, 125–14310.1093/clipsy.bpg015BaerR. A.SmithG. T.AllenK. B. (2004). Assessment of mindfulness by self-report: the Kentucky inventory of mindfulness skills. Assessment
11, 191–20610.1177/107319110426802915358875BlairK. S.GeraciM.OteroM.MajesticC.OdenheimerS.JacobsM. (2011). Atypical modulation of medial prefrontal cortex to self-referential comments in generalized social phobia. Psychiatry Res.
193, 38–4510.1016/j.pscychresns.2010.12.01621601433BradleyM. M.LangP. J. (1999). Affective Norms for English Words (ANEW) Technical Manual and Affective Ratings. Gainsville, FL: Center for Research in Psychophysiology, University of FloridaBroocksA.BandelowB.PekrunG.GeorgeA.MeyerT.BartmannU. (1998). Comparison of aerobic exercise, clomipramine, and placebo in the treatment of panic disorder. Am. J. Psychiatry
155, 603–6099585709CampbellD. W.SareenJ.PaulusM. P.GoldinP. R.SteinM. B.ReissJ. P. (2007). Time-varying amygdala response to emotional faces in generalized social phobia. Biol. Psychiatry
62, 455–46310.1016/j.biopsych.2006.09.01717188251CavannaA. E.TrimbleM. R. (2006). The precuneus: a review of its functional anatomy and behavioural correlates. Brain
129, 564–58310.1093/brain/awl00416399806ChiesaA.SerrettiA. (2009). Mindfulness-based stress reduction for stress management in healthy people: a review and meta-analysis. J. Altern. Complement. Med.
15, 593–600010.1089/acm.2008.049519432513ClarkD. M.WellsA. (1995). A Cognitive Model of Social Phobia. New York, NY: Guilford PressCohenM. S. (1997). Parametric analysis of fMRI data using linear systems methods. Neuroimage
6, 93–10310.1006/nimg.1997.02789299383CoxR. W. (1996). AFNI: software for analysis and visualization of functional magnetic resonance neuroimages. Comput. Biomed. Res.
29, 162–17310.1006/cbmr.1996.00148812068CrinoM. D.SvobodaM.RubenfeldS.WhiteM. C. (1983). Data on the Marlowe-Crowne and Edwards social desirability scales. Psychol. Rep.
53, 963–96810.2466/pr0.1983.53.3.963CrowneD.MarloweD. (1960). A new scale of social desirability independent of psychopathology. J. Consult. Psychol.
24, 349–35410.1037/h004735813813058de GreckM.RotteM.PausR.MoritzD.ThiemannR.ProeschU. (2008). Is our self based on reward? Self-relatedness recruits neural activity in the reward system. Neuroimage
39, 2066–207510.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.11.00618155927DerryP. A.KuiperN. A. (1981). Schematic processing and self-reference in clinical depression. J. Abnorm. Psychol.
90, 286–29710.1037/0021-843X.90.4.2867264058Di NardoP. A.BrownT. A.BarlowD. H. (1994). Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for DSM-IV: Lifetime Version (ADIS-IV-L). San Antonio, TX: Psychological CorporationDratcuL. (2001). Physical exercise: an adjunctive treatment for panic disorder?
Eur. Psychiatry
16, 372–37410.1016/S0924-9338(01)00593-411686132EfronB. (1971). Forcing a sequential experiment to be balanced. Biometrika
58, 40310.1093/biomet/58.3.403FanJ.McCandlissB. D.FossellaJ.FlombaumJ. I.PosnerM. I. (2005). The activation of attentional networks. Neuroimage
26, 47110.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.02.00415907304FarbN. A. S.SegalZ. V.MaybergH.BeanJ.McKeonD.FatimaZ. (2007). Attending to the present: mindfulness meditation reveals distinct neural modes of self-reference. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
2, 313–32210.1093/scan/nsm03018985137FormanS. D.CohenJ. D.FitzgeraldM.EddyW. F.MintunM. A.NollD. C. (1995). Improved assessment of significant activation in functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI): use of a cluster-size threshold. Magn. Reson. Med.
33, 636–64710.1002/mrm.19103305087596267FossatiP.HevenorS. J.GrahamS. J.GradyC.KeightleyM. L.CraikF. (2003). In search of the emotional self: an FMRI study using positive and negative emotional words. Am. J. Psychiatry
160, 1938–194510.1176/appi.ajp.160.11.193814594739FrescoD. M.ColesM. E.HeimbergR. G.LiebowitzM. R.HamiS.SteinM. B. (2001). The Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale: a comparison of the psychometric properties of self-report and clinician-administered formats. Psychol. Med.
31, 1025–103510.1017/S003329170100405611513370FrescoD. M.MooreM. T.van DulmenM. H. M.SegalZ. V.MaS. H.TeasdaleJ. D. (2007). Initial psychometric properties of the experiences questionnaire: validation of a self-report measure of decentering. Behav. Ther.
38, 234–24610.1016/j.beth.2006.08.00317697849GarlandE.GaylordS.ParkJ. (2009). The role of mindfulness in positive reappraisal. Explore (NY)
5, 37–4410.1016/j.explore.2008.10.00119114262GoldinP.RamelW.GrossJ. J. (2009a). Mindfulness meditation training and self referential processing in social anxiety disorder: behavioral and neural effects. J. Cogn. Psychother.
23, 242–25710.1891/0889-8391.23.3.242GoldinP. R.Manber-BallT.WernerK.HeimbergR.GrossJ. J. (2009b). Neural mechanisms of cognitive reappraisal of negative self-beliefs in social anxiety disorder. Biol. Psychiatry
66, 1091–109910.1016/j.biopsych.2009.07.01419717138GoldinP.ZivM.JazaieriH.HahnK.GrossJ. (2012). MBSR vs aerobic exercise in social anxiety: fMRI of emotion regulation of negative self-beliefs. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci. [Epub ahead of print].22586252GoldinP. R.GrossJ. J. (2010). Effects of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) on emotion regulation in social anxiety disorder. Emotion
10, 83–9110.1037/a001844120141305HambrickJ. P.TurkC. L.HeimbergR. G.SchneierF. R.LiebowitzM. R. (2004). Psychometric properties of disability measures among patients with social anxiety disorder. J. Anxiety Disord.
18, 82510.1016/j.janxdis.2003.10.00415474855HerringM. P.JacobM. L.SuvegC.DishmanR. K.O’ConnorP. J. (2012). Feasibility of exercise training for the short-term treatment of generalized anxiety disorder: a randomized controlled trial. Psychother. Psychosom.
81, 21–2810.1159/00032789822116310HölzelB. K.LazarS. W.GardT.Schuman-OlivierZ.VagoD. R.OttU. (2011). How does mindfulness meditation work? Proposing mechanisms of action from a conceptual and neural perspective. Perspect. Psychol. Sci.
6, 537–55910.1177/1745691611419671JazaieriH.GoldinP. R.WernerK.ZivM.GrossJ. J. (2012). A randomized trial of MBSR versus aerobic exercise for social anxiety disorder. J. Clin. Psychol.
68, 715–73110.1002/jclp.21863JohnsonS. C.BaxterL. C.WilderL. S.PipeJ. G.HeisermanJ. E.PrigatanoG. P. (2002). Neural correlates of self-reflection. Brain
125, 1808–181410.1093/brain/awf18112135971Kabat-ZinnJ. (1990). Full Catastrophe Living: Using the Wisdom of Your Body and Mind to Face Stress, Pain, and Illness. New York, NY: Dell PublishingKelleyW. M.MacraeC. L.WylandC. L.CaglarS.InatiS.HeathertonT. F. (2002). Finding the self? An event-related fMRI study. J. Cogn. Neurosci.
14, 785–79410.1162/0898929026013867212167262KjaerT. W.NowakM.LouH. C. (2002). Reflective self-awareness and conscious states: PET evidence for a common midline parietofrontal core. Neuroimage
17, 1080–108610.1006/nimg.2002.123012377180KoszyckiD.BengerM.ShlikJ.BradwejnJ. (2007). Randomized trial of a meditation-based stress reduction program and cognitive behavior therapy in generalized social anxiety disorder. Behav. Res. Ther.
45, 2518–252610.1016/j.brat.2007.04.01117572382LangP. J. (1980). “Behavioral treatment and bio-behavioral assessment: computer applications,” in Technology in Mental Health Care Delivery, eds SidowskiJ. B.JohnsonJ. H.WilliamsT. A. (Norwood: Ablex Publishing), 119–137LemogneC.DelaveauP.FretonM.GuionnetS.FossatiP. (2012). Medial prefrontal cortex and the self in major depression. J. Affect. Disord.
136, e1–e1110.1016/j.jad.2011.11.04121185083LiebowitzM. R. (1987). Social phobia. Mod. Probl. Pharmacopsychiatry
22, 141–1732885745MarguliesD. S.VincentJ. L.KellyC.LohmannG.UddinL. Q.BiswalB. B. (2009). Precuneus shares intrinsic functional architecture in humans and monkeys. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
106, 20069–2007419903877MartinS. D.MartinE.RaiS. S.RichardsonM. A.RoyallR. (2001). Brain blood flow changes in depressed patients treated with interpersonal psychotherapy or venlafaxine hydrochloride: preliminary findings. Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
58, 641–64810.1001/archpsyc.58.7.64111448369McEnteeD. J.HalginR. P. (1999). Cognitive group therapy and aerobic exercise in the treatment of anxiety. J. College Stud. Psychother.
13, 39–58MeromD.PhongsavanP.WagnerR.CheyT.MarnaneC.SteelZ. (2007). Promoting walking as an adjunct intervention to group cognitive behavioral therapy for anxiety disorders: a pilot group randomized trial. J. Anxiety Disord.
22, 959–96810.1016/j.janxdis.2007.09.01017988832MoscovitchD. A. (2009). What is the core fear in social phobia? A new model to facilitate individualized case conceptualization and treatment. Cogn. Behav. Pract.
16, 123–13410.1016/j.cbpra.2008.12.001NorthoffG.BermpohlF. (2004). Cortical midline structures and the self. Trends Cogn. Sci. (Regul. Ed.)
8, 102–10710.1016/j.tics.2004.01.00415301749NorthoffG.HeinzelA.de GreckM.BermpohlF.DobrowolnyH.PankseppJ. (2006). Self-referential processing in our brain-A meta-analysis of imaging studies on the self. Neuroimage
31, 440–45710.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.12.00216466680NorthoffG.QinP.FeinbergT. E. (2011). Brain imaging of the self – conceptual, anatomical and methodological issues. Conscious. Cogn.
20, 52–6310.1016/j.concog.2010.09.01120932778NorthoffG.SchneiderF.RotteM.MatthiaeC.TempelmannC.WiebkingC. (2009). Differential parametric modulation of self-relatedness and emotions in different brain regions. Hum. Brain Mapp.
30, 369–38210.1002/hbm.2051018064583OchsnerK. N.GrossJ. J. (2005). The cognitive control of emotion. Trends Cogn. Sci. (Regul. Ed.)
9, 242–24910.1016/j.tics.2005.06.00415866151PenedoF. J.DahnJ. R. (2005). Exercise and well-being: a review of mental and physical health benefits associated with physical activity. Curr. Opin. Psychiatry
18, 189–19310.1097/00001504-200503000-0001316639173PetruzzelloS. J.LandersA. C.HatfieldB. D.KubitzK. A.SalazarW. (1991). A meta-analysis on the anxiety-reducing effect of acute and chronic exercise: outcomes and mechanisms. Sports Med.
11, 143–18210.2165/00007256-199111030-000021828608PfeiferJ. H.PeakeS. J. (2012). Self-development: integrating cognitive, socioemotional, and neuroimaging perspectives. Dev. Cogn. Neurosci.
2, 55–6910.1016/j.dcn.2011.07.01222682728PhanK. L.TaylorS. F.WelshR. C.HoS. H.BrittonJ. C.LiberzonI. (2004). Neural correlates of individual ratings of emotional salience: a trial-related fMRI study. Neuroimage
21, 768–78010.1016/j.neuroimage.2003.09.07214980580RamelW.GoldinP. R.CarmonaP. E.McQuaidJ. R. (2004). The effects of mindfulness meditation on cognitive processes and affect in patients with past depression. Cognit. Ther. Res.
28, 43310.1023/B:COTR.0000045557.15923.96RytwinskiN. K.FrescoD. M.HeimbergR. G.ColesM. E.LiebowitzM. R.CissellS. (2009). Screening for social anxiety disorder with the self-report version of the Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale. Depress. Anxiety
26, 34–3810.1002/da.2050318781659SamsonA. C.MeisenzahlE.ScheuereckerJ.RoseE.SchoepfV.WiesmannM. (2011). Brain activation predicts treatment improvement in patients with major depressive disorder. J. Psychiatr. Res.
45, 1214–122221477817SchmitzT. W.JohnsonS. C. (2007). Relevance to self: a brief review and framework of neural systems underlying appraisal. Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
31, 585–59610.1016/j.neubiorev.2006.12.00317418416SchneiderM.DebbanéM.LagioiaA.SalomonR.D’ArgembeauA.EliezS. (2012). Comparing the neural bases of self-referential processing in typically developing and 22q11.2 adolescents. Dev. Cogn. Neurosci.
2, 277–28910.1016/j.dcn.2011.12.00422483077SegalZ. V.WilliamsJ. M. G.TeasdaleJ. D. (2002). Mindfulness Based Cognitive Therapy for Depression: A New Approach to Preventing Relapse. New York: Guildford PressSheehanD. V. (1983). The Anxiety Disease. New York: ScribnerSpurrJ. M.StopaL. (2002). Self-focused attention in social phobia and social anxiety. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
22, 947–97510.1016/S0272-7358(02)00107-112238248SteptoeA.EdwardsS.MosesJ.MathewsA. (1989). The effects of exercise training on mood and perceived coping ability in anxious adults from the general population. J. Psychosom. Res.
33, 537–54710.1016/0022-3999(89)90061-52795526StichF. A. (1998). A meta-analysis of physical exercise as a treatment for symptoms of anxiety adults from the general population. Psychosom. Res.
33, 537–547StröhleA. (2009). Physical activity, exercise, depression and anxiety disorders. J. Neural Transm.
116, 777–78410.1007/s00702-008-0092-x18726137TalairachJ.TournouxP. (1988). Co-Planar Stereotaxic Atlas of the Human Brain. New York: Thiemevan der MeerL.CostafredaS.AlemanA.DavidA. S. (2010). Self-reflection and the brain: a theoretical review and meta-analysis of neuroimaging studies with implications for schizophrenia. Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
34, 935–94610.1016/j.neubiorev.2009.12.00420015455VøllestadJ.NielsenM. B.NielsenG. H. (2012). Mindfulness- and acceptance-based interventions for anxiety disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Br. J. Clin. Psychol.
51, 239–26010.1111/j.2044-8260.2011.02024.x22803933
