<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC PsychiatryBMC PsychiatryBMC Psychiatry1471-244XBioMed CentralLondon45337622626545256910.1186/s12888-015-0569-8Study ProtocolThe effects of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation in obese females with binge eating disorder: a protocol for a double-blinded, randomized, sham-controlled trialhttp://orcid.org/0000-0001-6687-8738MaranhãoMara Fernandesmara.proata@gmail.com1EstellaNara Mendesnaramendes@post.harvard.edu1CuryMaria Elisa Gisbertm.elisa@clinicapsico.com.br1AmigoVeruska Lastoriaveruskalastoria@uol.com.br1PicassoClarissa Mollineroclarissalli@gmail.com1BerberianArthurArthur.berberian@gmail.com2CampbellIainIain.campbell@kcl.ac.uk3SchmidtUlrikeulrike.schmidt@kcl.ac.uk3ClaudinoAngélica Medeirosaclaudino@unifesp.br11Eating Disorder Unit, Psychiatry Department, Universidade Federal de São Paulo (UNIFESP), R. Borges Lagoa, 570, 7th floor, CEP 04038–020, São Paulo, SP Brazil 2Laboratory Integrative Neuroscience (LiNC), Psychiatric Department, Universidade Federal de São Paulo (UNIFESP), R. Pedro de Toledo, 669, 3rd floor, CEP 04039–032, São Paulo, SP Brazil 3Section of Eating Disorder, Institute of Psychiatry, King’s College London, Denmark Hill, SE5 8AF, London, UK 1282015128201520151519412620151672015© Maranhão et al. 2015This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundBinge eating disorder is a new category in DSM-5 and highly associated with higher body mass index. The neural mechanisms that underlie binge eating are of great interest in order to improve treatment interventions. Brain mechanisms underlying drug and food craving are suggested to be similar: for example, both are reported to be associated with increased neural activity in the orbitofrontal and anterior cingulate cortex, and a diminished regulatory influence from lateral prefrontal circuits. Several studies have begun to assess the potential benefits of brain stimulation in reducing craving and addictive behaviors. Data from a study of a one-off session of transcranial magnetic stimulation in healthy women identified as strong cravers and of individuals with bulimic-type eating disorders, reported a reduction in food craving and binge eating episodes. This provides support for a more extensive investigation of the potential therapeutic benefits of transcranial magnetic stimulation. Lastly, brain imaging studies and a dimensional approach, will improve understanding of the neural correlates of the disorders and of the mode of action of transcranial magnetic stimulation.Methods/DesignSixty eligible obese females, with binge eating disorder, will be randomly allocated to receive 20 sessions of transcranial magnetic stimulation intervention (n = 30) or the sham transcranial magnetic stimulation intervention (n = 30) scattered 3 days/week. Thirty eligible controls will complete the baseline assessment. The primary outcome (number of binge eating episodes) will be assed at each treatment sessions, and 8 weeks after intervention completion (follow-up). It is hypothesized that mean weekly binge-eating episodes will be reduced in the intervention group, compared to the sham group, and that the effect will be maintained at follow-up.DiscussionDespite the severity associated with Binge Eating Disorder, there are limited treatment options. This study is an important step in the development of more effective treatments. Importantly, the study is the first to investigating binge eating disorder using a dimensional approach, by looking at the different aspects of the disorder, such as behavioral factors, biological factors, brain circuits and chemistry.Trial registrationClinical Trials NCT02180984. Registered in July 2014.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12888-015-0569-8) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.KeywordsBinge eating disorderTranscranial magnetic stimulationNeuroimagingHormonesEating disordersObesityControl inhibitionEating disordersFAPESP, Foundation for the Support of Research in the State of Sao Paulo2014/04258-5ClaudinoAngélica MedeirosCNP-Q, National Council for Scientific and Technological Development448058/2014-6ClaudinoAngélica Medeirosissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2015<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec7" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Overview and study design</title><p>This is a two-arm, double-blinded, randomized controlled trial (RCT). Sixty obese patients diagnosed with BED will be assigned to either: 1) a 20-session treatment protocol of real rTMS, or 2) a 20-session treatment protocol of sham rTMS. Participants will be evaluated for outcome measures before and after the intervention, with a follow up visit 8 weeks after the end of treatment. In addition, a control group comprising 30 female individuals with no lifetime diagnosis of ED (15 obese individuals without a diagnosis of BED and 15 normal weight healthy individuals) will be recruited and enrolled for baseline comparison (biomarkers, neuropsychological and neuroimaging evaluation). The trial design and study flow are shown graphically in Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, in line with the SPIRIT 2013 Statement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A summary of the study design and participants flow during the study</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12888_2015_569_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e838"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Consort 2010 Flow Diagram</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12888_2015_569_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e847"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Participants</title><p>The study will be conducted at a specialized outpatient program for eating disorders (ED) of the Federal University of São Paulo (UNIFESP), Brazil. Participants will be females seeking treatment for their ED or referred by their clinical care providers. Recruitment will also include individuals attending online advertisement, study flyers, and newsletters.</p><p>All participants will be informed about the study and asked to sign the informed consent term before any procedure is conducted. Study intervention will be completed in approximately 7 weeks.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Enrollment</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Inclusion criteria for randomization</title><p>Participants are eligible for randomization if they fulfill the following inclusion criteria:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Meet DSM-5 criteria for BED.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Age between 18 to 55 years old.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Right-handed and able to write, read, and understand all elements of the study.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Females.</p></list-item><list-item><p>BMI ≥ 35 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and body weight ≤ 150 kg.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Laboratory blood tests (fasting glucose, fasting glucose/insulin ratio, complete blood count, TSH and T4) within normal range at study enrollment. In order to exclude participants with diabetes, fasting glucose levels under 126 mg/dl will be accepted.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Inclusion criteria for controls</title><p>Control participants are eligible if:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>BMI between 19 and 24.99 kg/m<sup>2</sup> for normal weight controls and BMI ≥ 35 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (and less than 150 kg) for obese controls.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Normal menstrual cycle (every 21–35 days) for the past 6 months.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Age between 18 to 55 years old.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Right-handed and able to write, read, and understand all elements of the study.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Females.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Laboratory blood tests (fasting glucose, fasting glucose/insulin ratio, complete blood count, TSH and T4) within normal range at study enrollment.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>History of head or eye injury or epilepsy.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Body metallic implants, pacemaker, claustrophobia and any other contraindication to fMRI or rTMS.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Current use of psychotropic drugs (except for antidepressants on a stable dose for at least one month).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Current use of any anti-obesity drug (e.g. sibutramine, orlistat) and medications that are known to reduce weight, such as Liraglutide and Topiramate (three months washout period for any medication).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Pregnant or breastfeeding.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Diabetes Mellitus diagnosis.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Major psychiatric disorder requiring immediate treatment (e.g. Schizophrenia, Bipolar Disorder).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Substance dependence (smokers of less than 5 cigarettes/day will be included).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Individuals currently receiving any psychological therapy for ED.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cushing’s and Turner’s syndrome.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>*Control participants will be excluded if they meet psychiatric disorder criteria based on the MINI International Neuropsychiatric Interview 7.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Withdrawal criteria</title><p>Participants will be withdrawn from the study if they: i) become pregnant; ii) experience any adverse event which the study investigator specifies as an indicator that it is no longer safe for the individual to participate; iii) initiate the use of any medication described as an exclusion criteria; iv) develop psychotic or manic symptoms, or v) failure to complete three consecutive rTMS sessions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Intervention</title><p>Following assessment, participants eligible for the study will undergo a preliminary fMRI, followed by 20 sessions of neuronavigated rTMS, one session per day, 3 days/week over approximately 7 weeks. Focal rTMS will be performed using a Neurosoft device and a ‘figure of eight’ coil. Brainscience Neuronavigation will be used to guide the placement of the coil to the target PFC region using a template MRI for all participants. The coil will be placed at a 45° angle to the mid-sagittal line to induce a posterior to anterior current in the underlying neural tissue. For the real treatment condition, stimulation will target the left DLPFC at 110 % of the resting motor threshold. Each session of 10 Hz stimulation will apply 1000 pulses to the left hemisphere, with a duty cycle of 5 s on and 55 s off, for a total stimulation time of 20 min. Sham rTMS treatment will be administered with the same TMS methodology used for real intervention, except for the fact that in the sham condition there is no actual magnetic stimulation. In order to mimic the cutaneous sensation and muscle twitching of rTMS without stimulating the brain, focal electrical stimulation will be used as a sham rTMS condition. To ensure treatment adherence, if rTMS sessions are missed, replacement sessions will be schedule within a week.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Measures</title><p>Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1 describes the study measures and timeframe in details.</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>Diagnosis and eligibility measures</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Anthropometric measures</title><p>Height and weight will be measured in triplicate using a stadiometer and a scale. Participants will be backwards and in a hospital gown. Hip-waist circumference and ratio will be measured in triplicate also.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Laboratory blood examination</title><p>Fasting blood samples will be obtained for a complete blood count, fasting glucose levels, fasting glucose/insulin ratio, TSH, and free thyroxine (T4). A urine pregnancy test will be collected if pregnant condition is possible (women in fertile age and not using a reliable contraceptive method).</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Diagnostic interviews</title><p>Psychiatric diagnosis will be assessed with The Structured Clinical Interview (MINI 7.0). The interview comprises modules representing different groups of psychiatric disorders. In order to confirm BED diagnosis (DSM-5) and collect further information on ED psychopathology, The Eating Disorder Examination (EDE 17.0D) will also be applied. The EDE is a semi-structured diagnostic interview and the gold-standard instrument used in the diagnosis of eating disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. It has four subscales of symptoms severity (shape, weight and eating concern and dietary restrain) and a global score. In addition the number of binge eating episodes and days during the past month (or 28 days) is carefully assessed during the interview. Trained professionals will be conducting these interviews.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>TMS/fMRI safety questionnaires</title><p>These questionnaires will be administered in order to rule out potential contraindications to TMS intervention and/or fMRI exams, such as, history of epilepsy, metal implanted devices, brain or eye injury, pregnancy, stroke, etc.).</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Clinical measures</title><p>Medication use and menstrual status will be assessed based on a questionnaire developed by the authors.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Primary outcome measures</title><p>The primary outcomes of this study are: (1) the change in the number of BE episodes before and after study treatment (number of BE episodes at baseline subtracted from the number of BE episodes at the end of treatment), as measured by participants recording of binge episodes in the food diary during the previous 15 days to the baseline visit (first rTMS session, T.3) to the end of treatment visit (T.23); (2) the change in “urge to eat” (craving) as measured in a 10 cm VAS (from T3 to T22).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Secondary outcome measures</title><p>Self report measures<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>A short and modified version (comprising 8 items) of the Food Craving Questionnaire-Trait (FCQ-T) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. The FCQ-T was translated and adapted to Brazilian Portuguese (publication in progress). This instrument investigates various aspects of food cravings across different time periods and situations.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Binge Eating Scale (BES) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. BE severity will be examined using the BES, which is composed of 16 items and has been translated and validated to Portuguese Change in the total mean score from the baseline visit (T.3) to the end-of treatment evaluation (T.23) and 8-week follow up (T.24) will be compared between the two randomized groups.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Three Eating Factor Questionnaire (TEF-Q) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. The reduced 21 item version (TEFQ-R21) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], which has been translated and adapted to Brazilian Portuguese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] will be used. Overall, the questionnaire evaluates the following aspects: eating cognitive restrain, emotional eating and control over eating.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The Loss of Control over Eating Scale (LOCES) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] is an instrument developed to investigate aspects associated with the loss of control over eating. The scale has been translated and validated to Brazilian Portuguese (publication in progress).</p></list-item><list-item><p>UPPS Impulsive Behavior Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] was originally developed with five factors and later reduced to four factors and 45-items [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. These factors were divided as: a) urgency, tendency to experience strong impulses, b) lack of premeditation, tendency not to think about the consequences of an act before engaging in it, c) lack of perseverance, lack of the ability to stay focused on a task that can be boring or difficult, and d) sensation seeking, tendency to search for activities that are exciting, and openness to try new experiences. The scale is also available in Brazilian Portuguese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS-21) is a 21-item self-report scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] developed to measure the negative emotional states of depression, anxiety and stress during the past week. Each item is rated using a 4-point severity/frequency scale according to the corresponding statement. DASS-21 is available in Brazilian Portuguese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Food diary. Participants will be instructed to register complete food intake in a food diary for seven consecutive days before the T.3, T.23 and T.24 visits, and to record BE episodes for 15 consecutive days before the same time points (T.3, T.23 and T.24).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Body Shape Questionnaire (BSQ-34). The questionnaire has been validated in patients with eating disorders and includes assessments of body image. The questions related to body shape perception and range from 1 to 6. Higher scores on these scales indicate greater psychopathology. The questionnaire has been translated and validated to Brazilian Portuguese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>The 12-item Short Form Health Survey (SF-12). This questionnaire measures health-related quality of life, subdivided in two scales – Physical Health Component Summary scales (PCS) and Mental Health Component Summary scales (MCS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. It has been translated into Brazilian Portuguese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>].</p></list-item></list></p><p>Anthropometric measures will be completed as previously described.</p><sec id="FPar6"><title>Biomarkers</title><p>Blood serum levels of reactive-C protein, BDNF, adiponectin, TNF-Alpha, IL-6, IL-10, leptin, ghrelin, PYY<sub>3–36</sub>, estradiol and progesterone will be measured in order to analyze changes in inflammatory response, hormones and neurotrophic factors.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Cognitive evaluation</title><p>The evaluation will include seven cognitive tests investigating executive functions such as, working memory, control inhibition and decision-making, as described in details in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2.</p></sec><sec id="FPar8"><title>Neuroimaging</title><p>Neuroimaging scans will be performed on a 3 T Magneton Trio Tim System (Siemens, Germany) scanner. Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scans will be acquired for the whole brain structure (T1-weighted, 1 mm resolution). Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) scans for resting state (no task) will be acquired to investigate functional connectivity. T2-weighted echo-planar images (EPI) depicting blood oxygen level dependent (BOLD) contrast will be acquired during the Stroop Word Color Task (SWCT). The SWCT is widely used as an index of attention and executive control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. The task requires the ability to actively inhibit a learned response in favor of a more voluntary (and difficult) response. A SWCT block-design of three conditions (control/congruent, neutral and incongruent) will be used during the fMRI. Neuroimaging allows for a deeper understanding of brain structures, patterns and activation. The fMRI exam and the SWCT will be used as tools to investigate brain areas involved in automatic inhibitory responses during the SWCT. Further, the SWCT allows the investigation of differences in activation patterns and connectivity in the PFC during the task [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>].</p><p>Food Challenge Task (FCT): The task was used and described in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The FCT requires participants to watch a film clip (2 min.) followed by exposure of food (10 min.), in order to stimulate craving. The current study will only use the film clip to stimulate craving; there will be no food exposure. Participants will also complete the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) of “urge to eat”, “hunger”, “tension” and “mood” and a short and modified version (comprising 5 items) of the Food Craving Questionnaire-State (FCQ-S) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], which was translated to Brazilian Portuguese and is in the process of validation. The FCQ-S investigates aspects of food craving in real time. In addition, salivary cortisol samples will be collected along with the FCT to examine potential impact of stress (exposure to food cues).</p></sec><sec id="FPar9"><title>rTMS tolerability and safety</title><p>Participants will be provided with a monitoring record and instructed to record any experience of adverse events during the rTMS treatment. The monitoring record will be reviewed before each rTMS session. Tolerability will be based on the number of adverse events reported (grouped per side effect type) and number of dropouts due to adverse events or other reasons. Safety will be measured based on the occurrence of serious adverse events, such as seizures (reported as rare in rTMS studies).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Sample size and statistical analysis</title><p>To detect the change in craving and BE frequency before and after treatment intervention, the following parameters were used to estimate sample size: effect size <italic>f</italic> = 0.31 (supposed to be small), alpha error probability =0.05, power = (1-β error probability) = 0.8, number of groups = 2, number of measurements through the follow-up = 3 and correlation among repeated measurements = 0.5.</p><p>Statistical Inferences: Two different types of analyses will be used to evaluate the effectiveness of the rTMS. The first (and standard) method is intention-to-treat (ITT) that assumes that every patient allocated to be intervention actually received it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. The other paradigm, CACE estimation method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>] will take into account the compliance status (patient’s adherence to the rTMS).The compliance status is defined here as at least one of 20 session of rTMS; CACE estimation, therefore, provides a realistic effect under non-adherence phenomenon being estimated based on the structural equation modeling. Underlying both paradigms, it will be used growth modeling, which examines the development of individuals on one more outcome variables over the time. In growth modeling (on contrary of repeated ANOVAS), random effects are used to capture individual differences in development. The corrected significance level (Bonferroni) to be adopted due to 32 outcomes will be 0,0015. Such procedure will be carried to avoid false discovered rate due to multiple comparisons. All the statistical inference will be done via Mplus 7.0. In addition, careful fMRI image acquisition and processing will be completed and analyzed taking into consideration the limitations of fMRI studies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Randomization</title><p>A simple randomization will be conducted with a 1:1 allocation. A randomization sequence list will be created using the website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.random.org">www.random.org</ext-link>, which offers true random numbers; such randomness comes from atmospheric noise, which for many purposes is better than the pseudo-random number algorithms typically used in computer program. Participants will be randomly assigned following simple randomization sequence to one of the two treatments. Group 1 for active rTMS and group 2 for sham rTMS. Patient allocation will be blinded to all participants and study staff, in exception to the professionals providing the rTMS treatment and one doctorate student, responsible for allocation concealment. The allocation sequence will be concealed and sequentially numbered in dark, sealed and stapled envelopes and locked in a key protected cabinet file. Allocation implementation will occur pre-intervention and between the T.2 and T.3 visits.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Ethical review and trial registration</title><p>The protocol has been reviewed and approved by Research Ethics Committee UNIFESP/EPM in São Paulo, Brazil (registration number: 26164614.7.0000.5505). It is registered in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link> (trial ID: NCT02180984).</p></sec></sec>Additional files
Additional file 1: Table S1.A summary of instruments and measures completed at each study time point. (PDF 75 kb)
Additional file 2: Table S2.Cognitive evaluation: A short description of cognitive tests used for evaluation. (PDF 52 kb)
AbbreviationsANAnorexia NervosaANOVASAnalysis of variancesBEBinge eatingBEDBinge eating disorderBDNFBrain derived neurotrophic factorBNBulimia NervosaBESBinge eating scaleBMIBody mass indexCACEComplier average causal effectCBTCognitive Behavior TherapyDLPFCDorsolateral pre-frontal cortexDSMDiagnostic Statistical ManualEDEating DisorderEDNOSEating disorder not otherwise specifiedFCTFood challenge TaskFCQ-SFood craving questionnaire stateFCQ-TFood craving questionnaire traitfMRIFunctional Magnetic Resonance ImageHPAHypothalamic-pituitary-adrenalHzHertzIFGInferior frontal gyrusITTIntent to treatLOCESLoss of control over eating scalePFCPre frontal cortexPYYPeptide tyrosine tyrosinerTMSrepetitive transcranial magnetic stimulationRCTRandomized clinical trialRDoCResearch Domain CriteriaTMSTranscranial magnetic stimulationVASVisual analogue scaleVMPFCVentromedial prefrontal cortex.Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsMFM, NME and AMC wrote the first draft of the paper and study protocol. MEGC, CMP and AB wrote the first draft of neurocognitive protocol. NME wrote the first draft of the neuroimaging protocol. MFM wrote the TMS protocol. VL, IC, US and AMC all critically read the protocol, revised and wrote the methods/analysis. All authors participated in the design of this project and approved the final manuscript.AcknowledgementsThis work is supported in part by the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientifico e Tecnologico - MCTI/CNPQ Universal 14/2014 grant (N° 448058/2014-6) and São Paulo Research Foundation - FAPESP (N° 2014/04258-5) Nara Mendes Estella, Mara Fernandes Maranhão and Maria Elisa Cury are all scholarship students from Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nivel Superior - CAPES. The agencies are all based on peer-reviewed grant and scholarship approval.References1.American Psychological AssociationDiagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders20135Arlington, VAAmerican Psychiatric Publishing2.American Psychiatric AssociationDiagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders20004Washington, DCAmerican Psychiatric Association3.DarbyAHayPMondJQuirkFButtnerPKennedyLThe rising prevalence of comorbid obesity and eating disorder behaviors from 1995 to 2005Int J Eat Disord200942210410810.1002/eat.20601189497674.AghTKovacsGPawaskarMSupinaDInotaiAVokoZEpidemiology, health-related quality of life and economic burden of binge eating disorder: a systematic literature reviewEat Weight Disord201520110.1007/s40519-014-0173-9255718855.PalavrasMAKaioGHMari JdeJClaudinoAMA review of Latin American studies on binge eating disorderRevista brasileira de psiquiatria201133Suppl 1S8110810.1590/S1516-44462011000500007218453376.PopeHGJrLalondeJKPindyckLJWalshTBulikCMCrowSJMcElroySLRosenthalNHudsonJIBinge eating disorder: a stable syndromeAm J Psychiatry2006163122181218310.1176/ajp.2006.163.12.2181171511727.TiricoPPStefanoSCBlaySLQualidade de vida e transtornos alimentares: uma revisão sistemáticaCad Saúde Pública201026343144910.1590/S0102-311X2010000300002204640638.WilsonGTWilfleyDEAgrasWSBrysonSWPsychological treatments of binge eating disorderArchives of general psychiatry20106719410110.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.170200482279.WilfleyDEWelchRRSteinRISpurrellEBCohenLRSaelensBEDounchisJZFrankMAWisemanCVMattGEA randomized comparison of group cognitive-behavioral therapy and group interpersonal psychotherapy for the treatment of overweight individuals with binge-eating disorderArchives of general psychiatry200259871372110.1001/archpsyc.59.8.7131215064710.VocksSTuschen-CaffierBPietrowskyRRustenbachSJKerstingAHerpertzSMeta-analysis of the effectiveness of psychological and pharmacological treatments for binge eating disorderInt J Eat Disord20104332052171940202811.StefanoSCBacaltchukJBlaySLAppolinarioJCAntidepressants in short-term treatment of binge eating disorder: systematic review and meta-analysisEat Behav20089212913610.1016/j.eatbeh.2007.03.0061832959012.ReasDLGriloCMReview and meta-analysis of pharmacotherapy for binge-eating disorderObesity (Silver Spring)20081692024203810.1038/oby.2008.3331918632713.KramerCKLeitaoCBPintoLCCananiLHAzevedoMJGrossJLEfficacy and safety of topiramate on weight loss: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trialsObes Rev2011125e33834710.1111/j.1467-789X.2010.00846.x2143898914.CuthbertBNInselTRToward new approaches to psychotic disorders: the NIMH Research Domain Criteria projectSchizophr Bull20103661061106210.1093/schbul/sbq1082092996915.GearhardtANWhiteMAPotenzaMNBinge eating disorder and food addictionCurr Drug Abuse Rev20114320120710.2174/18744737111040302012199969516.VolkowNDWangGJFowlerJSTomasiDBalerRFood and drug reward: overlapping circuits in human obesity and addictionCurr Top Behav Neurosci20121112410.1007/7854_2011_1692201610917.MarcusMDWildesJEObesity: is it a mental disorder?Int J Eat Disord200942873975310.1002/eat.207251961001518.FuhrerDZyssetSStumvollMBrain activity in hunger and satiety: an exploratory visually stimulated FMRI studyObesity (Silver Spring)200816594595010.1038/oby.2008.331829274719.VolkowNDWangGJBalerRDReward, dopamine and the control of food intake: implications for obesityTrends Cogn Sci2011151374610.1016/j.tics.2010.11.0012110947720.RobbinsTWGillanCMSmithDGde WitSErscheKDNeurocognitive endophenotypes of impulsivity and compulsivity: towards dimensional psychiatryTrends Cogn Sci2012161819110.1016/j.tics.2011.11.0092215501421.HareTACamererCFRangelASelf-control in decision-making involves modulation of the vmPFC valuation systemScience2009324592764664810.1126/science.11684501940720422.Lo SauroCRavaldiCCabrasPLFaravelliCRiccaVStress, hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis and eating disordersNeuropsychobiology20085739511510.1159/0001389121855251123.Illan-GomezFGonzalvez-OrtegaMOrea-SolerIAlcaraz-TafallaMSAragon-AlonsoAPascual-DiazMPerez-ParedesMLozano-AlmelaMLObesity and inflammation: change in adiponectin, C-reactive protein, tumour necrosis factor-alpha and interleukin-6 after bariatric surgeryObes Surg201222695095510.1007/s11695-012-0643-y2252759224.Guerre-MilloMAdiponectin: an updateDiabetes Metab2008341121810.1016/j.diabet.2007.08.0021806903025.WangXGeAChengMGuoFZhaoMZhouXLiuLYangNIncreased hypothalamic inflammation associated with the susceptibility to obesity in rats exposed to high-fat dietExp Diabetes Res201220128472462284427126.WalkerAJKimYPriceJBKaleRPMcGillivrayJABerkMTyeSJStress, inflammation, and cellular vulnerability during early stages of affective disorders: biomarker strategies and opportunities for prevention and interventionFront Psychiatry201453410.3389/fpsyt.2014.000342478278927.Rosas-VargasHMartinez-EzquerroJDBienvenuTBrain-derived neurotrophic factor, food intake regulation, and obesityArch Med Res201142648249410.1016/j.arcmed.2011.09.0052194538928.RiosMFanGFeketeCKellyJBatesBKuehnRLechanRMJaenischRConditional deletion of brain-derived neurotrophic factor in the postnatal brain leads to obesity and hyperactivityMol Endocrinol200115101748175710.1210/mend.15.10.07061157920729.EdlerCLipsonSFKeelPKOvarian hormones and binge eating in bulimia nervosaPsychol Med200737113114110.1017/S00332917060089561703820630.MisraMTsaiPAndersonEJHubbardJLGallagherKSoykaLAMillerKKHerzogDBKlibanskiANutrient intake in community-dwelling adolescent girls with anorexia nervosa and in healthy adolescentsAm J Clin Nutr20068446987061702369431.MisraMKatzmanDKEstellaNMEddyKTWeigelTGoldsteinMAMillerKKKlibanskiAImpact of physiologic estrogen replacement on anxiety symptoms, body shape perception, and eating attitudes in adolescent girls with anorexia nervosa: data from a randomized controlled trialJ Clin Psychiatry2013748e76577110.4088/JCP.13m083652402151732.StraubRHThe complex role of estrogens in inflammationEndocr Rev200728552157410.1210/er.2007-00011764094833.MobbsOIglesiasKGolayAVan der LindenMCognitive deficits in obese persons with and without binge eating disorder. Investigation using a mental flexibility taskAppetite201157126327110.1016/j.appet.2011.04.0232160025534.DavisCPatteKCurtisCReidCImmediate pleasures and future consequences. A neuropsychological study of binge eating and obesityAppetite201054120821310.1016/j.appet.2009.11.0021989651535.SvaldiJBrandMTuschen-CaffierBDecision-making impairments in women with binge eating disorderAppetite2010541849210.1016/j.appet.2009.09.0101978270836.DuchesneMMattosPAppolinarioJCde FreitasSRCoutinhoGSantosCCoutinhoWAssessment of executive functions in obese individuals with binge eating disorderRevista brasileira de psiquiatria201032438138810.1590/S1516-444620100004000112130825937.GaliotoRSpitznagelMBStrainGDevlinMCohenRPaulRCrosbyRDMitchellJEGunstadJCognitive function in morbidly obese individuals with and without binge eating disorderComprehensive psychiatry201253549049510.1016/j.comppsych.2011.09.0022203631738.BalodisIMMolinaNDKoberHWorhunskyPDWhiteMARajitaSGriloCMPotenzaMNDivergent neural substrates of inhibitory control in binge eating disorder relative to other manifestations of obesityObesity (Silver Spring)201321236737710.1002/oby.200682340482039.StraussEShermanESpreenOA compendium of neuropsychological tests : administration, norms, and commentary2006Oxford, New YorkOxford University Press40.Tana MG, Montin E, Cerutti S, Bianchi AM. Exploring cortical attentional system by using fMRI during a Continuous Perfomance Test. Computational intelligence and neuroscience 2010:329213. doi: 10.1155/2010/329213.41.GuseBFalkaiPWobrockTCognitive effects of high-frequency repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation: a systematic reviewJ Neural Transm2010117110512210.1007/s00702-009-0333-71985978242.Demirtas-TatlidedeAVahabzadeh-HaghAMPascual-LeoneACan noninvasive brain stimulation enhance cognition in neuropsychiatric disorders?Neuropharmacology20136456657810.1016/j.neuropharm.2012.06.0202274994543.ZanardiniRGazzoliAVentrigliaMPerezJBignottiSRossiniPMGennarelliMBocchio-ChiavettoLEffect of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation on serum brain derived neurotrophic factor in drug resistant depressed patientsJournal of affective disorders2006911838610.1016/j.jad.2005.12.0291644870144.NyffelerTWurtzPPflugshauptTvon WartburgRLuthiMHessCWMuriRMOne-Hertz transcranial magnetic stimulation over the frontal eye field induces lasting inhibition of saccade triggeringNeuroreport200617327327510.1097/01.wnr.0000199468.39659.bf1646259645.UherRYoganathanDMoggAErantiSVTreasureJCampbellICMcLoughlinDMSchmidtUEffect of left prefrontal repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation on food cravingBiol Psychiatry2005581084084210.1016/j.biopsych.2005.05.0431608485546.WalpothMHoertnaglCMangweth-MatzekBKemmlerGHinterholzlJConcaAHausmannARepetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation in bulimia nervosa: preliminary results of a single-centre, randomised, double-blind, sham-controlled trial in female outpatientsPsychother Psychosom2008771576010.1159/0001100611808720947.Van den EyndeFClaudinoAMMoggAHorrellLStahlDRibeiroWUherRCampbellISchmidtURepetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation reduces cue-induced food craving in bulimic disordersBiol Psychiatry201067879379510.1016/j.biopsych.2009.11.0232006010548.DownarJSankarAGiacobbePWoodsideBColtonPUnanticipated rapid remission of refractory bulimia nervosa, during high-dose repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation of the dorsomedial prefrontal cortex: a case reportFront Psychiatry201233010.3389/fpsyt.2012.000302252982249.BaczynskiTPde Aquino ChaimCHNazarBPCartaMGArias-CarrionOSilvaACMachadoSNardiAEHigh-frequency rTMS to treat refractory binge eating disorder and comorbid depression: a case reportCNS Neurol Disord Drug Targets201413577177510.2174/18715273136661403071548232460672050.JanicakPGNahasZLisanbySHSolvasonHBSampsonSMMcDonaldWMMarangellLBRosenquistPMcCallWVKimballJDurability of clinical benefit with transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) in the treatment of pharmacoresistant major depression: assessment of relapse during a 6-month, multisite, open-label studyBrain stimulation20103418719910.1016/j.brs.2010.07.0032096544751.O'ReardonJPBlumnerKHPeshekADPradillaRRPimientoPCLong-term maintenance therapy for major depressive disorder with rTMSJ Clin Psychiatry200566121524152810.4088/JCP.v66n12051640115252.MiniussiCRuzzoliMTranscranial stimulation and cognitionHandbook of clinical neurology201311673975010.1016/B978-0-444-53497-2.00056-52411293553.MullerMBToschiNKresseAEPostAKeckMELong-term repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation increases the expression of brain-derived neurotrophic factor and cholecystokinin mRNA, but not neuropeptide tyrosine mRNA in specific areas of rat brainNeuropsychopharmacology200023220521510.1016/S0893-133X(00)00099-31088284754.BaekenCDe RaedtRLeymanLSchiettecatteJPoppeKKaufmanLHaesMVanderhasseltMAAnckaertED'HaenenHThe impact of one session of HF-rTMS on salivary cortisol in healthy female subjectsWorld J Biol Psychiatry2009104 Pt 258659010.1080/156229707015603511788616855.EversSHengstKPecuchPWThe impact of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation on pituitary hormone levels and cortisol in healthy subjectsJournal of affective disorders2001661838810.1016/S0165-0327(00)00289-51153253756.ChanAWTetzlaffJMAltmanDGLaupacisAGotzschePCKrleza-JericKHrobjartssonAMannHDickersinKBerlinJASPIRIT 2013 statement: defining standard protocol items for clinical trialsAnn Intern Med2013158320020710.7326/0003-4819-158-3-201302050-005832329595757.SheehanDLecrubierYHarnett-SheehanKJanavsJWeillerEBonaraLKeskinerASchinkaJSheehanMDunbarGReliability and Validity of the M.I.N.I. International Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I.): According to the SCID-PEuropean Psychiatry19971223224110.1016/S0924-9338(97)83297-X58.C.G. FCognitive Behavior Therapy and Eating Disorders2008NYGuilford Press59.Cepeda-BenitoAGleavesDHWilliamsTLErathSAThe development and validation of the state and trait food-cravings questionnairesBehavior Therapy20003115117310.1016/S0005-7894(00)80009-X60.FreitasSLopesCCoutinhoWAppolinarioJTradução e adaptação para o português da Escala de Compulsão Alimentar PeriódicaRevista brasileira de psiquiatria200123421522010.1590/S1516-4446200100040000861.StunkardAJMessickSThe three-factor eating questionnaire to measure dietary restraint, disinhibition and hungerJ Psychosom Res1985291718310.1016/0022-3999(85)90010-8398148062.CappelleriJCBushmakinAGGerberRALeidyNKSextonCCLoweMRKarlssonJPsychometric analysis of the three-factor eating questionnaire-R21: results from a large diverse sample of obese and non-obese participantsInt J Obes (Lond)200933661162010.1038/ijo.2009.741939902163.NatacciLCFerreira JuniorMThe three factor eating questionnaire - R21: tradução para o português e aplicação em mulheres brasileirasRevista de Nutrição201124338339410.1590/S1415-5273201100030000264.LatnerJDMondJMKellyMCHaynesSNHayPJThe loss of control over eating scale: development and psychometric evaluationInt J Eat Disord201447664765910.1002/eat.222962486235165.WhitesideSPLynamDRThe five factor model and impulsivity: using a structural model of personality to understand impulsivityPersonality and Individual Differences200130466968910.1016/S0191-8869(00)00064-766.WhitesideSPLynamDRMillerJDReynoldsSKValidation of the UPPS impulsive behaviour scale: a four-factor model of impulsivityEuropean Journal of Personality200519755957410.1002/per.55667.NogueiraCYSCarvalhoAMGauerGTavaresNSantosRMMGinaniGRiveroTSMoraesPHPWhitesideSHMalloy-DinizLFTranslation and adaptation of impulsive behavior scale (UPPS) to the Brazilian populationClinical Neuropsychiatry2013102798568.LovibondSHLovibondPFManual for the depression anxiety stress scales19952SydneyPsychology Foundation69.VignolaRCTucciAMAdaptation and validation of the depression, anxiety and stress scale (DASS) to Brazilian PortugueseJournal of affective disorders201415510410910.1016/j.jad.2013.10.0312423887170.Di PietroMSilveiraDXInternal validity, dimensionality and performance of the Body Shape Questionnaire in a group of Brazilian college studentsRev Bras Psiquiatr2009311212410.1590/S1516-444620080050000171903071871.WareJJrKosinskiMKellerSDA 12-Item Short-Form Health Survey: construction of scales and preliminary tests of reliability and validityMed Care199634322023310.1097/00005650-199603000-00003862804272.SilveiraMFAlmeidaJCFreireRSHaikalDSMartinsAE[Psychometric properties of the quality of life assessment instrument: 12-item health survey (SF-12)]Cien Saude Colet20131871923193110.1590/S1413-812320130007000072382789673.StroopJRStudies of interference in serial verbal reactionsJ Exp Psychology19351864366210.1037/h005465174.HartSJGreenSRCaspMBelgerAEmotional priming effects during Stroop task performanceNeuroImage20104932662267010.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.0761988377275.CampbellMKElbourneDRAltmanDGCONSORT statement: extension to cluster randomised trialsBMJ2004328744170270810.1136/bmj.328.7441.7021503124676.AngristJDImbensGWRubinDBIdentification of causal effects using instrumental variablesJournal of the American statistical Association19969143444445510.1080/01621459.1996.1047690277.JoBMuthénBNew developments and techniques in structural equation modelingModeling of intervention effects with noncompliance: A latent variable approach for randomized trials20015787
