<?xml version="1.0"?>
PLoS OnePLoS ONEplosplosonePLoS ONE1932-6203Public Library of ScienceSan Francisco, CA USA557326810.1371/journal.pone.0183349PONE-D-17-19220Research ArticleBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceCognitive ScienceCognitive PsychologyLanguageBiology and Life SciencesPsychologyCognitive PsychologyLanguageSocial SciencesPsychologyCognitive PsychologyLanguageMedicine and Health SciencesOtorhinolaryngologyLaryngologySpeech-Language PathologySpeech TherapyMedicine and Health SciencesNeurologyCerebrovascular DiseasesStrokeMedicine and Health SciencesVascular MedicineStrokeResearch and Analysis MethodsMathematical and Statistical TechniquesStatistical MethodsMeta-AnalysisPhysical SciencesMathematicsStatistics (Mathematics)Statistical MethodsMeta-AnalysisResearch and Analysis MethodsDatabase and Informatics MethodsDatabase SearchingMedicine and Health SciencesClinical MedicineClinical TrialsRandomized Controlled TrialsMedicine and Health SciencesPharmacologyDrug Research and DevelopmentClinical TrialsRandomized Controlled TrialsResearch and Analysis MethodsClinical TrialsRandomized Controlled TrialsBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceCellular NeuroscienceNeuronal PlasticityResearch and Analysis MethodsDatabase and Informatics MethodsConstraint-induced aphasia therapy in post-stroke aphasia rehabilitation: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trialsConstraint-induced aphasia therapy in post-stroke aphasia rehabilitation: A systematic reviewZhangJiaqiConceptualizationFormal analysisInvestigationSoftwareWriting – original draftWriting – review &amp; editing1YuJiadanData curationInvestigationMethodology2BaoYongConceptualizationSoftwareWriting – review &amp; editing3XieQingSupervisionWriting – original draftWriting – review &amp; editing4XuYangInvestigationSoftware2ZhangJunmeiSupervisionWriting – review &amp; editing5http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5783-3693WangPuConceptualizationMethodologyWriting – review &amp; editing4*1
Master of Science in Neurological Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China2
School of Rehabilitation Sciences, West China School of Medicine, Sichuan University, Sichuan, China3
Ruijin Rehabilitation Hospital of Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai, China4
Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Ruijin Hospital, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai, China5
Department of Physical Education, Wuhan University of Technology, Wuhan, ChinaYuanTifeiEditorNanjing Normal University, CHINACompeting Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.* E-mail: wangpu_03@126.com28820172017128e01833492052017282017© 2017 Zhang et al2017Zhang et alThis is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.BackgroundConstraint-induced aphasia therapy (CIAT) has been widely used in post-stroke aphasia rehabilitation. An increasing number of clinical controlled trials have investigated the efficacy of the CIAT for the post-stroke aphasia.PurposeTo systematically review the randomized controlled trials (RCTs) concerning the effect of the CIAT in post-stroke patients with aphasia, and to identify the useful components of CIAT in post-stroke aphasia rehabilitation.MethodsA computerized database search was performed through five databases (Pubmed, EMbase, Medline, ScienceDirect and Cochrane library). Cochrane handbook domains were used to evaluate the methodological quality of the included RCTs.ResultsEight RCTs qualified in the inclusion criteria. Inconsistent results were found in comparing the CIAT with conventional therapies without any component from the CIAT based on the results of three RCTs. Five RCTs showed that the CIAT performed equally well as other intensive aphasia therapies, in terms of improving language performance. One RCT showed that therapies embedded with social interaction were likely to enhance the efficacy of the CIAT.ConclusionCIAT may be useful for improving chronic post-stroke aphasia, however, limited evidence to support its superiority to other aphasia therapies. Massed practice is likely to be a useful component of CIAT, while the role of “constraint” is needed to be further explored. CIAT embedded with social interaction may gain more benefits.The authors received no specific funding for this work.Data AvailabilityThe data for meta-analyses can be found in the part of figures.Data AvailabilityThe data for meta-analyses can be found in the part of figures.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec007"><title>Methods</title><p>Five computerized databases, including PubMed (via website), EMBASE (via Ovid), the Cochrane library (via Ovid), Medline (via Ovid) and ScienceDirect (via website), were searched for studies published from 2001 up to 18<sup>th</sup> January 2017. The keywords used for identifying CIAT were: CIAT, use-dependent learning, constraint induced aphasia therapy, constraint induced language therapy, ILAT and intensive language action therapy. The keywords used for identifying stroke included stroke, hemiplegia, hemiparesis, hemiplegic, cerebrovascular accident, CVA. First author read all identifies titles and excluded the obviously irrelevant papers. Papers were included if: (1) RCTs, or the first phase of RCTs with a cross-over design was also included in the present review; (2) patients had a diagnosis of stroke/cerebrovascular accident (CVA); (3) CIAT, modified CIAT, or ILAT [<xref rid="pone.0183349.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] was applied in the study, compared with a control group, including different forms of CIAT, other speech therapy programs or the nonintervention control; Papers were excluded if: (1) quasi-RCTs, non-randomized controlled studies, pre-post design studies or case reports; (2) the CIAT group received additional intervention focus on aphasia (e.g. medicine); (3) study did not explore the useful components of CIAT (constraint, massed practice, shaping, social interaction or others). (4) papers were not published in English. The reference list from previous reviews and included RCTs was assessed for relevant records. Two of the authors read through the potentially relevant full-text independently. Disagreements were resolved by consensus discussion between the two assessors.</p><sec id="sec008"><title>Outcome measures</title><p>Primary outcomes were the severity of aphasia (e.g. Western aphasia battery—aphasia quotient, WAB-AQ) and language performances (e.g. Aachen aphasia test, AAT), including total scores and subscale scores if applicable. Secondary outcomes included the subjective experience of language performance (e.g. Communicative activity log, CAL), functional communication and any activity related to language functions.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Data extraction and quality assessment</title><p>The quality of RCTs was evaluated based on Cochrane handbook domains [<xref rid="pone.0183349.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]: (1) random sequence generation, (2) allocation concealment, (3) blinding of researchers (4) blinding of participants, (5) blinding of outcome assessors, (6) drop-out and exclusion and (7) intention to treat analysis. Two authors assessed each article independently. Disagreements were resolved by consensus discussion with the third author.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Data analysis</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using RevMan 5.3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ims.cochrane.org/revman">http://ims.cochrane.org/revman</ext-link>). Mean and standard deviations for each outcome were extracted for each group and pooled to obtain mean difference (MD) and 95% confidence intervals (CI). Heterogeneity was examined using I<sup>2</sup> statistic. Studies with an I<sup>2</sup> of 25% to 50% were considered to have low heterogeneity, I<sup>2</sup> of values of 50% to 75%, and ˃ 75% were considered indicative of moderate and high level of heterogeneity, respectively. Fixed-effect models were used to combine studies if I<sup>2</sup> test was not significant (<italic>P</italic> for heterogeneity&lt;0.1). Otherwise, random effect models were used. <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered indicative of a statistically significant between-group difference. Publication bias was investigated with funnel plots if more than 10 studies were included in the meta-analysis [<xref rid="pone.0183349.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. If there is not available data or varying outcomes used in different studies, a descriptive analysis would be conducted.</p></sec></sec>LimitationsSome limitations could be noted in this review. Firstly, a frim conclusion was unable to be drawn based on the small number of heterogeneous RCTs. Secondly, we can only try to explore the effect from high-intensity (massed practice), constraint and social interaction, however, for other important principles, such as the shaping, could not be well-explained based on currently available literature. Thirdly, we only included the published English language papers. Some unpublished articles, or papers published in other languages might be ignored in this review, which may result in language bias.References1BalardinJB, MiottoEC. A review of Constraint-Induced Therapy applied to aphasia rehabilitation in stroke patients. Dement Neuropsychol. 2009; 3: 275–282.2FangY, ChenX, LiH, LinJ, HuangR, ZengJ. A study on additional early physiotherapy after stroke and factors affecting functional recovery. Clin Rehabil. 2003; 17(6): 608–617. doi: 10.1191/0269215503cr655oa
129717053LeeH, LeeY, ChoiH, PyunSB. Community Integration and Quality of Life in Aphasia after Stroke. Yonsei Med J. 2015; 56(6): 1694–1702. doi: 10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1694
264466564BoehmeAK, Martin-SchildS, MarshallRS, LazarRM. Effect of aphasia on acute stroke outcomes. Neurology. 2016; 87(22): 2348–2354. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000003297
277658645KoleckM, GanaK, LucotC, DarrigrandB, MazauxJM, GlizeB. Quality of life in aphasic patients 1 year after a first stroke. Qual Life Res. 2017; 26(1): 45–54. doi: 10.1007/s11136-016-1361-z
274058716BerthierML, PulvermullerF, DavilaG, CasaresNG, GutierrezA. Drug therapy of post-stroke aphasia: a review of current evidence. Neuropsychol Rev. 2011; 21(3): 302–317. doi: 10.1007/s11065-011-9177-7
218453547BradyMC, KellyH, GodwinJ, EnderbyP, CampbellP. Speech and language therapy for aphasia following stroke. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016(6): Cd000425
doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD000425.pub4
272453108Mei TohSF, FongKNK. Systematic Review on the Effectiveness of Mirror Therapy in Training Upper Limb Hemiparesis after Stroke. HKJOT. 2012; 22(2): 84–95.9HungGKN, LiCTL, YiuAM, FongKNK. Systematic Review: Effectiveness of Mirror Therapy for Lower Extremity Post-Stroke. HKJOT. 2015; 26: 51–59.10ChenW, YeQ, JiX, ZhangS, YangX, ZhouQ, et al
Mirror neuron system based therapy for aphasia rehabilitation. Front Psychol. 2015; 6: 1665
doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2015.01665
2657904611RosbergenIC, GrimleyRS, HaywardKS, WalkerKC, RowleyD, CampbellAM, et al
Embedding an enriched environment in an acute stroke unit increases activity in people with stroke: a controlled before-after pilot study. Clin Rehabil. 2017: 269215517705181.12YuK, WuY, ZhangQ, XieH, LiuG, GuoZ, et al
Enriched environment induces angiogenesis and improves neural function outcomes in rat stroke model. J Neurol Sci. 2014; 347(1–2): 275–280. doi: 10.1016/j.jns.2014.10.022
2545530013NoriseC, HamiltonRH. Non-invasive Brain Stimulation in the Treatment of Post-stroke and Neurodegenerative Aphasia: Parallels, Differences, and Lessons Learned. Front Hum Neurosci. 2016; 10: 675
doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2016.00675
2816790414MorrisDM, CragoJE, DelucaSC, PidikitiRD, TaubE. Constraint-induced movement therapy for moter recovery after stroke. NeuroRehabilitation. 1997; 9(1): 29–43. doi: 10.3233/NRE-1997-9104
2452608915ThraneG, FriborgO, AnkeA, IndredavikB. A meta-analysis of constraint-induced movement therapy after stroke. J Rehabil Med. 2014; 46(9): 833–842. doi: 10.2340/16501977-1859
2518234116BangDH, ShinWS, ChoiHS. Effects of modified constraint-induced movement therapy combined with trunk restraint in chronic stroke: A double-blinded randomized controlled pilot trial. NeuroRehabilitation. 2015; 37(1): 131–137. doi: 10.3233/NRE-151245
2640969817LeungDP, NgAK, FongKN. Effect of small group treatment of the modified constraint induced movement therapy for clients with chronic stroke in a community setting. Hum Mov Sci. 2009; 28(6): 798–808. doi: 10.1016/j.humov.2009.04.006
1983747318MeinzerM, ElbertT, DjundjaD, TaubE, RockstrohB. Extending the Constraint-Induced Movement Therapy (CIMT) approach to cognitive functions: Constraint-Induced Aphasia Therapy (CIAT) of chronic aphasia. NeuroRehabilitation. 2007; 22(4): 311–318. 1797162219PulvermullerF, NeiningerB, ElbertT, MohrB, RockstrohB, KoebbelP, et al
Constraint-induced therapy of chronic aphasia after stroke. Stroke. 2001; 32(7): 1621–1626. 1144121020HamiltonRH, ChrysikouEG, CoslettB. Mechanisms of aphasia recovery after stroke and the role of noninvasive brain stimulation. Brain Lang. 2011; 118(1–2): 40–50. doi: 10.1016/j.bandl.2011.02.005
2145942721PulvermullerF, HaukO, ZohselK, NeiningerB, MohrB. Therapy-related reorganization of language in both hemispheres of patients with chronic aphasia. Neuroimage. 2005; 28(2): 481–489. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.06.038
1609917622BreierJI, JuranekJ, MaherLM, SchmadekeS, MenD, PapanicolaouAC. Behavioral and neurophysiologic response to therapy for chronic aphasia. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2009; 90(12): 2026–2033. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2009.08.144
1996916423MohrB, MacGregorLJ, DifrancescoS, HarringtonK, PulvermullerF, ShtyrovY. Hemispheric contributions to language reorganisation: An MEG study of neuroplasticity in chronic post stroke aphasia. Neuropsychologia. 2016; 93(Pt B): 413–424. doi: 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2016.04.006
2706306124KurlandJ, PulvermullerF, SilvaN, BurkeK, AndrianopoulosM. Constrained versus unconstrained intensive language therapy in two individuals with chronic, moderate-to-severe aphasia and apraxia of speech: behavioral and fMRI outcomes. Am J Speech Lang Pathol. 2012; 21(2): S65–87. doi: 10.1044/1058-0360(2012/11-0113)
2229440925MohrB, DifrancescoS, HarringtonK, EvansS, PulvermullerF. Changes of right-hemispheric activation after constraint-induced, intensive language action therapy in chronic aphasia: fMRI evidence from auditory semantic processing. Front Hum Neurosci. 2014; 8: 919
doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2014.00919
2545272126MeinzerM, RodriguezAD, Gonzalez RothiLJ. First decade of research on constrained-induced treatment approaches for aphasia rehabilitation. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2012; 93(1 Suppl): S35–45. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2011.06.040
2220218927WoldagH, VoigtN, BleyM, HummelsheimH. Constraint-Induced Aphasia Therapy in the Acute Stage: What Is the Key Factor for Efficacy? A Randomized Controlled Study. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2017; 31(1): 72–80. doi: 10.1177/1545968316662707
2750667728StahlB, MohrB, DreyerFR, LuccheseG, PulvermullerF. Using language for social interaction: Communication mechanisms promote recovery from chronic non-fluent aphasia. Cortex. 2016; 85: 90–99. doi: 10.1016/j.cortex.2016.09.021
2784226929SzaflarskiJP, BallAL, VannestJ, DietzAR, AllendorferJB, MartinAN, et al
Constraint-Induced Aphasia Therapy for Treatment of Chronic Post-Stroke Aphasia: A Randomized, Blinded, Controlled Pilot Trial. Med Sci Monit. 2015; 21: 2861–2869. doi: 10.12659/MSM.894291
2639919230WilssensI, VandenborreD, van DunK, VerhoevenJ, Visch-BrinkE, MarienP. Constraint-induced aphasia therapy versus intensive semantic treatment in fluent aphasia. Am J Speech Lang Pathol. 2015; 24(2): 281–294. doi: 10.1044/2015_AJSLP-14-0018
2576560231SickertA, AndersLC, MunteTF, SailerM. Constraint-induced aphasia therapy following sub-acute stroke: a single-blind, randomised clinical trial of a modified therapy schedule. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2014; 85(1): 51–55. doi: 10.1136/jnnp-2012-304297
2382883432MaherLM, KendallD, SwearenginJA, RodriguezA, LeonSA, PingelK, et al
A pilot study of use-dependent learning in the context of Constraint Induced Language Therapy. J Int Neuropsychol Soc. 2006; 12(6): 843–852. doi: 10.1017/S1355617706061029
1706444733MeinzerM, DjundjaD, BarthelG, ElbertT, RockstrohB. Long-term stability of improved language functions in chronic aphasia after constraint-induced aphasia therapy. Stroke. 2005; 36(7): 1462–1466. doi: 10.1161/01.STR.0000169941.29831.2a
1594727934KristensenLF, SteensigI, PedersenAD, PedersenAR, NielsenJF. Constraint-induced aphasia therapy in subacute neurorehabilitation. Aphasiology. 2015; 29(10): 1152–1163.35CicconeN, WestD, CreamA, CartwrightJ, RaiT, GrangerA, et al
Constraint-induced aphasia therapy (CIAT): a randomised controlled trial in very early stroke rehabilitation. Aphasiology. 2016; 30(5): 566–584.36NickelsL, OsborneA. Constraint Induced Aphasia Therapy: Volunteer-led, unconstrained and less intense delivery can be effective. NeuroRehabilitation. 2016; 39(1): 97–109. doi: 10.3233/NRE-161341
2734136437RoseML. Releasing the constraints on aphasia therapy: the positive impact of gesture and multimodality treatments. Am J Speech Lang Pathol. 2013; 22(2): S227–239. doi: 10.1044/1058-0360(2012/12-0091)
2369589938DignamJ, CoplandD, McKinnonE, BurfeinP, O'BrienK, FarrellA, et al
Intensive Versus Distributed Aphasia Therapy: A Nonrandomized, Parallel-Group, Dosage-Controlled Study. Stroke. 2015; 46(8): 2206–2211. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.009522
2610611439DifrancescoS, PulvermüllerF, MohrB. Intensive language-action therapy (ILAT): The methods. Aphasiology. 2012; 26(11): 1317–1351.40HigginsJPT, GreenS (editors). Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 5.1.0 [updated March 2011]. The Cochrane Collaboration, 2011 Available from www.cochrane-handbook.org.41MeinzerM, StreiftauS, RockstrohB. Intensive language training in the rehabilitation of chronic aphasia: efficient training by laypersons. J Int Neuropsychol Soc. 2007; 13(5): 846–853. doi: 10.1017/S1355617707071111
1769741642KurlandJ, StanekEJ3rd, StokesP, LiM, AndrianopoulosM. Intensive Language Action Therapy in Chronic Aphasia: A Randomized Clinical Trial Examining Guidance by Constraint. Am J Speech Lang Pathol. 2016; 25(4S): S798–S812. doi: 10.1044/2016_AJSLP-15-0135
2799795443JohnsonML, TaubE, HarperLH, WadeJT, BowmanMH, Bishop-McKayS, et al
An enhanced protocol for constraint-induced aphasia therapy II: a case series. Am J Speech Lang Pathol. 2014; 23(1): 60–72. doi: 10.1044/1058-0360(2013/12-0168)
2401869844KavianS, KhatoonabadiAR, AnsariNN, SaadatiM, ShaygannejadV. A Single-subject Study to Examine the Effects of Constrained-induced Aphasia Therapy on Naming Deficit. Int J Prev Med. 2014; 5(6): 782–786. 2501369945SzaflarskiJP, BallA, GretherS, Al-FwaressF, GriffithNM, Neils-StrunjasJ, et al
Constraint-induced aphasia therapy stimulates language recovery in patients with chronic aphasia after ischemic stroke. Med Sci Monit. 2008; 14(5): Cr243–250. 1844354746CherneyLR, PattersonJP, RaymerA, FrymarkT, SchoolingT. Evidence-based systematic review: effects of intensity of treatment and constraint-induced language therapy for individuals with stroke-induced aphasia. J Speech Lang Hear Res. 2008; 51(5): 1282–1299. doi: 10.1044/1092-4388(2008/07-0206)
1881248947DignamJK, RodriguezAD, CoplandDA. Evidence for Intensive Aphasia Therapy: Consideration of Theories From Neuroscience and Cognitive Psychology. PM R. 2016; 8(3): 254–267. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2015.06.010
2610753948MozeikoJ, CoelhoCA, MyersEB. The role of intensity in constraint-induced language therapy for people with chronic aphasia. Aphasiology. 2016; 30(4): 339–363.49van de Sandt-KoendermanME, van der MeulenI, RibbersGM. Aphasia rehabilitation: more than treating the language disorder. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2012; 93(1 Suppl): S1–3. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2011.08.037
2211907350FamaME, BaronCR, HatfieldB, TurkeltaubPE. Group therapy as a social context for aphasia recovery: a pilot, observational study in an acute rehabilitation hospital. Top Stroke Rehabil. 2016; 23(4): 276–283. doi: 10.1080/10749357.2016.1155277
27077989
