<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front PsycholFront PsycholFront. Psychol.Frontiers in Psychology1664-1078Frontiers Media S.A.529258010.3389/fpsyg.2017.00141PsychologyReviewA Systematic Review of Associations between Amount of Meditation Practice and Outcomes in Interventions Using the Four Immeasurables MeditationsZengXianglong12ChioFloria H. N.2OeiTian P. S.345LeungFreedom Y. K.2LiuXiangping1*1School of Psychology, Bejing Normal UniversityBeijing, China2Department of Psychology, The Chinese University of Hong KongHong Kong, Hong Kong3School of Psychology, University of QueenslandBrisbane, QLD, Australia4Department of Psychology, James Cook University SingaporeSingapore, Singapore5Department of Psychology, Nanjing UniversityNanjing, ChinaEdited by: Alemka Tomicic, Diego Portales University, ChileReviewed by: Clayton Hoi-Yun McClintock, Columbia University, USA; Giorgio Bertolotti, Fondazione Salvatore Maugeri (IRCCS), Italy*Correspondence: Xiangping Liu lxp599e@163.comThis article was submitted to Psychology for Clinical Settings, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychology06220172017814107920161912017Copyright © 2017 Zeng, Chio, Oei, Leung and Liu.2017Zeng, Chio, Oei, Leung and LiuThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Interventions using the “Four Immeasurables Meditations” (FIM) are effective for various outcomes; however, whether increased meditation practice in these interventions leads to better results has not been well investigated. This systematic review included 22 FIM interventions that reported associations between the amount of meditation practice and its outcomes. Despite the heterogeneity in intervention components and outcome variables, there were generally few significant associations between amount of meditation practice and its outcomes. Specifically, only five studies reported that more than half of the calculated results were significant. In comparison with correlations between total amount of practice and overall outcomes, the short-term influence of meditation practice was evaluated in fewer studies; however, it had a better association with outcomes. More studies are required that address the underlying mechanisms that elucidate how meditation practice leads to outcome changes in daily life. In this study, two promising mechanisms with initial evidence were discussed. This review also summarized common methodological issues including a lack of experimental manipulation and inaccurate measuring of meditation practice.loving-kindness meditationcompassionappreciative joyactive componenttime of practicedose response relationshipBuddhism<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Literature search</title><p>The databases search, which was completed on Feb 23, 2016, included MedlinePlus, ISI Core Journals, PsycInfo, Embase, CINAHL Plus, AMED, and Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials. The search set in the title, abstract, and keywords sections was “immeasurable OR immeasurables OR kindness OR compassion OR compassionate OR [(Appreciating OR Appreciative OR Sympathetic OR Empathic) AND Joy] OR equanimity OR metta OR mudita OR karuna OR upekkha” combined with “Meditat<sup>*</sup> OR Buddhis<sup>*</sup>,” which were adjusted for different databases.</p></sec><sec><title>Selection of studies</title><p>The inclusion criteria were (a) articles published in a peer-reviewed journal in English, (b) empirical studies addressing interventions wherein at least 50% of major practices were FIM, and (c) studies that reported a relationship between the amount of meditation practice and other variables.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction and synthesis</title><p>The first two authors reviewed the titles and abstracts of unduplicated records to identify potential relevant articles for full text review; then, they extracted information about the amount of meditation practice from empirical studies on FIM. The reference lists of identified empirical studies were checked for missing articles. We attempted to contact the authors for unexplained selective reports; however, some researchers had not provided contact information or did not reply.</p></sec></sec>Author contributionsXZ, FL, and XL designed the study. XZ and FC reviewed articles and analyzed the data. XZ and TO wrote the paper. All authors discussed the results and commented on the manuscript.Conflict of interest statementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.We thank two reviewers for their comments and ideas. This study was conducted while XZ was studying at the Chinese University of Hong Kong, and it received support from both Beijing Normal University and the Chinese University of Hong Kong. Dr. Oei is now an Emeritus Professor of UQ and also a visiting Professor of James Cook University, Singapore and Nanjing University, PR China.ReferencesBurgardM.MayC. J. (2010). The effect of positive affect induction via metta meditation on the attentional blink. J. Art. Supp. Null Hypot.
7:8.CarmodyJ.BaerR. A. (2009). How long does a mindfulness-based stress reduction program need to be? A review of class contact hours and effect sizes for psychological distress. J. Clin. Psychol.
65, 627–638. 10.1002/jclp.2055519309694CarsonJ. W.KeefeF. J.LynchT. R.CarsonK. M.GoliV.FrasA. M.. (2005). Loving-kindness meditation for chronic low back pain results from a pilot trial. J. Holistic Nurs.
23, 287–304. 10.1177/089801010527765116049118CohnM. A.FredricksonB. L. (2010). In search of durable positive psychology interventions: predictors and consequences of long-term positive behavior change. J. Posit. Psychol.
5, 355–366. 10.1080/17439760.2010.50888321709728DavidsonR. J.LutzA. (2008). Buddha's brain: neuroplasticity and meditation. IEEE Signal. Process Mag.
25, 176–174. 10.1109/MSP.2008.443187320871742DesbordesG.NegiL. T.PaceT. W.WallaceB. A.RaisonC. L.SchwartzE. L. (2012). Effects of mindful-attention and compassion meditation training on amygdala response to emotional stimuli in an ordinary, non-meditative state. Front. Hum. Neurosci.
6:292. 10.3389/fnhum.2012.0029223125828DoddsS. E.PaceT. W.BellM. L.FieroM.NegiL. T.RaisonC. L.. (2015). Feasibility of Cognitively-Based Compassion Training (CBCT) for breast cancer survivors: a randomized, wait list controlled pilot study. Support. Care Cancer
23, 3599–3608. 10.1007/s00520-015-2888-126275769FredricksonB. L. (2001). The role of positive emotions in positive psychology. Am. Psychol.
56, 218–226. 10.1037/0003-066X.56.3.21811315248FredricksonB. L.CohnM. A.CoffeyK. A.PekJ.FinkelS. M. (2008). Open hearts build lives: positive emotions, induced through loving-kindness meditation, build consequential personal resources. J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.
95, 1045–1062. 10.1037/a001326218954193GalanteJ.GalanteI.BekkersM. J.GallacherJ. (2014). Effect of kindness-based meditation on health and well-being: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Consult. Clin. Psychol.
82, 1101–1114. 10.1037/a003724924979314HofmannS. G.GrossmanP.HintonD. E. (2011). Loving-kindness and compassion meditation: potential for psychological interventions. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
31, 1126–1132. 10.1016/j.cpr.2011.07.00321840289HutchersonC. A.SeppalaE. M.GrossJ. J. (2008). Loving-kindness meditation increases social connectedness. Emotion
8, 720–724. 10.1037/a001323718837623HutchersonC. A.SeppalaE. M.GrossJ. J. (2015). The neural correlates of social connection. Cogn. Affect. Behav. Neurosci.
15, 1–14. 10.3758/s13415-014-0304-924984693JazaieriH.JinpaG. T.McGonigalK.RosenbergE. L.FinkelsteinJ.Simon-ThomasE. (2013). Enhancing compassion: a randomized controlled trial of a compassion cultivation training program. J. Happiness Stud.
14, 1113–1126. 10.1007/s10902-012-9373-zJazaieriH.LeeI. A.McGonigalK.JinpaT.DotyJ. R.GrossJ. J. (2015). A wandering mind is a less caring mind: daily experience sampling during compassion meditation training. J. Posit. Psychol.
11, 37–50. 10.1080/17439760.2015.1025418JazaieriH.McGonigalK.JinpaT.DotyJ. R.GrossJ. J.GoldinP. R. (2014). A randomized controlled trial of compassion cultivation training: effects on mindfulness, affect, and emotion regulation. Motiv. Emot.
38, 23–35. 10.1007/s11031-013-9368-zKangY.GrayJ. R.DovidioJ. F. (2015). The head and the heart: effects of understanding and experiencing loving-kindness on attitudes toward the self and others. Mindfulness
6, 1063–1070. 10.1007/s12671-014-0355-6KlimeckiO. M.LeibergS.LammC.SingerT. (2012). Functional neural plasticity and associated changes in positive affect after compassion training. Cereb. Cortex
23, 1552–1561. 10.1093/cercor/bhs14222661409KlimeckiO. M.LeibergS.RicardM.SingerT. (2013). Differential pattern of functional brain plasticity after compassion and empathy training. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
9, 873–879. 10.1093/scan/nst06023576808KrausS.SearsS. (2009). Measuring the immeasurables: development and initial validation of the Self-Other Four Immeasurables (SOFI) scale based on Buddhist teachings on loving kindness, compassion, joy, and equanimity. Soc. Indic. Res.
92, 169–181. 10.1007/s11205-008-9300-1LeibergS.KlimeckiO.SingerT. (2011). Short-term compassion training increases prosocial behavior in a newly developed prosocial game. PLoS ONE
6:e17798. 10.1371/journal.pone.001779821408020LeppmaM.YoungM. E. (2016). Loving-kindness meditation and empathy: a wellness group intervention for counseling students. J. Couns. Dev.
94, 297–305. 10.1002/jcad.12086LogieK.FrewenP. (2015). Self/other referential processing following mindfulness and loving-kindness meditation. Mindfulness
6, 778–787. 10.1007/s12671-014-0317-zLutzA.GreischarL. L.RawlingsN. B.RicardM.DavidsonR. J. (2004). Long-term meditators self-induce high-amplitude gamma synchrony during mental practice. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
101, 16369–16373. 10.1073/pnas.040740110115534199MascaroJ. S.RillingJ. K.NegiL. T.RaisonC. L. (2012). Compassion meditation enhances empathic accuracy and related neural activity. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
8, 48–55. 10.1093/scan/nss09522956676MascaroJ. S.RillingJ. K.NegiL. T.RaisonC. L (2013). Pre-existing brain function predicts subsequent practice of mindfulness and compassion meditation. Neuroimage
69, 35–42. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.12.02123266748MayC. J.BurgardM.MenaM.AbbasiI.BernhardtN.ClemensS. (2011). Short-term training in loving-kindness meditation produces a state, but not a trait, alteration of attention. Mindfulness
2, 143–153. 10.1007/s12671-011-0053-6NeffK. D.GermerC. K. (2013). A pilot study and randomized controlled trial of the mindful self-compassion program. J. Clin. Psychol.
69, 28–44. 10.1002/jclp.2192323070875PaceT. W.NegiL. T.AdameD. D.ColeS. P.SivilliT. I.BrownT. D.. (2009). Effect of compassion meditation on neuroendocrine, innate immune and behavioral responses to psychosocial stress. Psychoneuroendocrinology
34, 87–98. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.08.01118835662PaceT. W.NegiL. T.Dodson-LavelleB.Ozawa-de SilvaB.ReddyS. D.ColeS. P.. (2013). Engagement with cognitively-based compassion training is associated with reduced salivary C-reactive protein from before to after training in foster care program adolescents. Psychoneuroendocrinology
38, 294–299. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2012.05.01922762896PaceT. W.NegiL. T.SivilliT. I.IssaM. J.ColeS. P.AdameD. D.. (2010). Innate immune, neuroendocrine and behavioral responses to psychosocial stress do not predict subsequent compassion meditation practice time. Psychoneuroendocrinology
35, 310–315. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.06.00819615827RanaN. (2015). Mindfulness and loving-kindness meditation: a potential tool for mental health and subjective well-being. Indian J. Posit. Psychol.
6, 189–196.ReddyS. D.NegiL. T.Dodson-LavelleB.Ozawa-de SilvaB.PaceT. W.ColeS. P. (2013). Cognitive-based compassion training: a promising prevention strategy prevention for at-risk adolescents. J. Child Fam. Stud.
22, 219–230. 10.1007/s10826-012-9571-7ShapiroS. L.BrownK. W.BiegelG. M. (2007). Teaching self-care to caregivers: effects of mindfulness-based stress reduction on the mental health of therapists in training. Train. Educ. Prof. Psychol.
1, 105–115. 10.1037/1931-3918.1.2.105ShoninE.Van GordonW.CompareA.ZangenehM.GriffithsM. D. (2015). Buddhist-derived loving-kindness and compassion meditation for the treatment of psychopathology: a systematic review. Mindfulness
6, 1161–1180. 10.1007/s12671-014-0368-1SujivaV. (2007). Loving-Kindness Meditation. Available online at: http://www.justbegood.net/Downloads/e-books/Meditation%20Loving%20Kindness.pdfSuzukiD. T. (1991). The Zen Doctrine of no Mind: The Significance of the Sutra of Hui-Neng. London; New York, NY: Weiser Books.WallmarkE.SafarzadehK.DaukantaitėD.MadduxR. E. (2013). Promoting altruism through meditation: an 8-week randomized controlled pilot study. Mindfulness
4, 223–234. 10.1007/s12671-012-0115-4WeibelD. T.McClintockA. S.AndersonT. (2016). Does loving-kindness meditation reduce anxiety? Results from a randomized controlled trial. Mindfulness
1–7. 10.1007/s12671-016-0630-9WengH. Y.FoxA. S.ShackmanA. J.StodolaD. E.CaldwellJ. Z. K.OlsonM. C.. (2013). Compassion training alters altruism and neural responses to suffering. Psychol. Sci.
24, 1171–1180. 10.1177/095679761246953723696200WheelerE. A.LenickN. W. (2014). Brief compassion meditation and recall of positive-emotion words. J. Art. Supp. Null Hypot.
11:12.ZengX.ChiuC. P.WangR.OeiT. P.LeungF. Y. (2015). The effect of loving-kindness meditation on positive emotions: a meta-analytic review. Front. Psychol.
6:1693. 10.3389/fpsyg.2015.0169326579061ZengX.ChanV. Y. L.LiuX.OeiT. P. S.LeungF. Y. K. (2017). The four immeasurables meditations: differential effects of appreciative joy and compassion meditations on emotions. Mindfulness. 1–11. 10.1007/s12671-016-0671-0ZengX.LiaoR.ZhangR.OeiT. P.YaoZ.LeungF. Y. (2016). Development of the appreciative joy scale. Mindfulness
1–14. 10.1007/s12671-016-0599-4
