<?xml version="1.0"?>
10161002641507J Pain ReliefJ Pain ReliefJournal of pain &amp; relief2167-0846419329210.4172/2167-0846.S3-001nihpa473986ArticleTranscranial Direct Current Stimulation in Neuropathic PainNgernyamNiran1#JensenMark P2##AuvichayapatNarong3#PunjarukWiyada1#AuvichayapatParadee1#*1Department of Physiology, Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University, Khon Kaen, Thailand2Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, University of Washington, Washington, USA3Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University, Khon Kaen, Thailand*Corresponding author: Dr. Paradee Auvichayapat, MD, Associate Professor of Physiology, Department of Physiology, Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University, Khon Kaen, Thailand, 40002, aparad@kku.ac.th#Member of Noninvasive Brain Stimulation Research Group of Thailand##Consultant to Noninvasive Brain Stimulation Research Group of Thailand1072013214201310102014Suppl 3001Copyright: © 2013 Ngernyam N, et al.2013This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.Neuropathic pain (NP) is one of the most common problems contributing to suffering and disability worldwide. Unfortunately, NP is also largely refractory to treatments, with a large number of patients continuing to report significant pain even when they are receiving recommended medications and physical therapy. Thus, there remains an urgent need for additional effective treatments. In recent years, nonpharmacologic brain stimulation techniques have emerged as potential therapeutic options. Many of these techniques and procedures – such as transcranial magnetic stimulation, spinal cord stimulation, deep brain stimulation, and motor cortical stimulation – have very limited availability, particularly in developing countries. Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) is a noninvasive brain stimulation procedure that has shown promise for effectively treating NP, and also has the potential to be widely available. This review describes tDCS and the tDCS procedures and principles that may be helpful for treating NP. The findings indicate that the analgesic benefits of tDCS can occur both during stimulation and beyond the time of stimulation. The mechanisms of cortical modulation by tDCS may involve various activities in neuronal networks such as increasing glutamine and glutamate under the stimulating electrode, effects on the μ-opioid receptor, and restoration of the defective intracortical inhibition. Additional research is needed to determine (1) the factors that may moderate the efficacy of tDCS, (2) the dose (e.g. number and frequency of treatment sessions) that results in the largest benefits and (3) the long-term effects of tDCS treatment.Transcranial direct current stimulationNeuropathic painNoninvasive brain stimulation<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Material and Method</title><p id="P10">A systematic review was conducted according to a predefined protocol and do not conduct a meta-analysis. Research studies examining the effects and mechanisms of tDCS on NP were identified via Medline database search using the key words “transcranial direct current stimulation and neuropathic pain” and “noninvasive brain stimulation and neuropathic pain” from January 1950 to January 2013. The trial intervention was defined as noninvasive electrical stimulation of the brain using direct currents. The inclusion criteria were: (a) the experimental studies; (b) case studies; (c) trial participants were adult patients with neuropathic or chronic pain (pain &gt;3 mo). The exclusion criteria including: (a) healthy participants who were experimentally exposed to a pain paradigm; (b) studies on patients with primary symptoms other than pain, such as depression, stroke, or Parkinson disease; and (c) studies on surgically implanted brain stimulators, repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation, and electrical stimulation with pulse currents. The outcome of interest was pain severity immediately after intervention as either the primary or secondary outcome parameter, the type of pain measurement tool was not predetermined.</p></sec>AcknowledgementsThe authors wish to thank Prof. Michael A. Nitsche of Department of Clinical Neurophysiology, George-August University; Prof. Tomas Paus of The Rotman Research Institute University of Toronto; Assistant Professor Alexander Rotenberg of The Children Hospital Boston, Harvard University for their guidance and very valuable suggestions.FundingThis research was supported in part by grant number R21 HD058049 from the National Institutes of Health, National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Center for Medical Rehabilitation Research. Niran Ngernyam was supported by a grant from the Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University, Thailand (Grant number I 55229).References1JensenTSBaronRHaanpääMKalsoELoeserJDA new definition of neuropathic painPain201115222042205217645142PaseroCPathophysiology of neuropathic painPain Manag Nurs2004538156448543TothCLanderJWiebeSThe prevalence and impact of chronic pain with neuropathic pain symptoms in the general populationPain Med200910918929195948444JensenMPChodroffMJDworkinRHThe impact of neuropathic pain on health-related quality of life: review and implicationsNeurology20076811781182174204005KerstmanEAhnSBattuSTariqSGraboisMNeuropathic painHandb Clin Neurol2013110175187233126406DworkinRHBackonjaMRowbothamMCAllenRRArgoffCRAdvances in neuropathic pain: diagnosis, mechanisms, and treatment recommendationsArch Neurol20036015241534146237237FlorHCortical reorganisation and chronic pain: implications for rehabilitationJ Rehabil Med20036672128176608WhittJLMasriRPulimoodNSKellerAPathological activity in mediodorsal thalamus of rats with spinal cord injury painJ Neurosci20133339153926234476029SolerMDKumruHPelayoRVidalJTormosJMEffectiveness of transcranial direct current stimulation and visual illusion on neuropathic pain in spinal cord injuryBrain2010133256525772068580610DworkinRHO’ConnorABBackonjaMFarrarJTFinnerupNBPharmacologic management of neuropathic pain: evidence-based recommendationsPain20071322372511792077011GordonDBLoveGPharmacologic management of neuropathic painPain Manag Nurs2004519331564485612MooreRADerrySTaylorRSStraubeSPhillipsCJThe Costs and Consequences of Adequately Managed Chronic Non-Cancer Pain and Chronic Neuropathic PainPain Pract201313VrankenJHMechanisms and treatment of neuropathic painCent Nerv Syst Agents Med Chem2009971782002134014NitscheMACohenLGWassermannEMPrioriALangNTranscranial direct current stimulation: State of the art 2008Brain Stimul200812062232063338615LuedtkeKRushtonAWrightCGeissBJuergensTPTranscranial direct current stimulation for the reduction of clinical and experimentally induced pain: a systematic review and meta-analysisClin J Pain2012284524612256921816CostainRRedfearnJWLippoldOCA controlled trial of the therapeutic effect of polarization of the brain in depressive illnessBr J Psychiatry19641107867991421169517CarneyMWNegative polarisation of the brain in the treatment of manic statesIr J Med Sci19698133135579972618PurpuraDPMcmurtryJGIntracellular activities and evoked potential changes during polarization of motor cortexJ Neurophysiol1965281661851424479319KabakovAYMullerPAPascual-LeoneAJensenFERotenbergAContribution of axonal orientation to pathway-dependent modulation of excitatory transmission by direct current stimulation in isolated rat hippocampusJ Neurophysiol2012107188118892221902820FregniFBoggioPSLimaMCFerreiraMJWagnerTA sham-controlled, phase II trial of transcranial direct current stimulation for the treatment of central pain in traumatic spinal cord injuryPain20061221972091656461821FregniFGimenesRValleACFerreiraMJRochaRRA randomized, sham-controlled, proof of principle study of transcranial direct current stimulation for the treatment of pain in fibromyalgiaArthritis Rheum200654398839981713352922BoggioPSAmancioEJCorreaCFCecilioSValasekCTranscranial DC stimulation coupled with TENS for the treatment of chronic pain: a preliminary studyClin J Pain2009256916951992071823MoriFCodecàCKusayanagiHMonteleoneFButtariFEffects of anodal transcranial direct current stimulation on chronic neuropathic pain in patients with multiple sclerosisJ Pain2010114364422001856724AntalATerneyDKühnlSPaulusWAnodal transcranial direct current stimulation of the motor cortex ameliorates chronic pain and reduces short intracortical inhibitionJ Pain Symptom Manage2010398909032047154925SolerMDKumruHPelayoRVidalJTormosJMEffectiveness of transcranial direct current stimulation and visual illusion on neuropathic pain in spinal cord injuryBrain2010133256525772068580626KumruHSolerDVidalJNavarroXTormosJMThe effects of transcranial direct current stimulation with visual illusion in neuropathic pain due to spinal cord injury: an evoked potentials and quantitative thermal testing studyEur J Pain20131755662261059027NitscheMAPaulusWExcitability changes induced in the human motor cortex by weak transcranial direct current stimulationJ Physiol2000527Pt 36336391099054728AntalANitscheMAPaulusWTranscranial direct current stimulation and the visual cortexBrain Res Bull2006684594631645920329RogalewskiABreitensteinCNitscheMAPaulusWKnechtSTranscranial direct current stimulation disrupts tactile perceptionEur J Neurosci2004203133161524550430KincsesTZAntalANitscheMABártfaiOPaulusWFacilitation of probabilistic classification learning by transcranial direct current stimulation of the prefrontal cortex in the humanNeuropsychologia2004421131171461508131LangNSiebnerHRWardNSLeeLNitscheMAHow does transcranial DC stimulation of the primary motor cortex alter regional neuronal activity in the human brain?Eur J Neurosci2005224955041604550232ClarkVPCoffmanBATrumboMCGasparovicCTranscranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) produces localized and specific alterations in neurochemistry: a 1H magnetic resonance spectroscopy studyNeurosci Lett201150067712168376633LiebetanzDNitscheMATergauFPaulusWPharmacological approach to the mechanisms of transcranial DC-stimulation-induced after-effects of human motor cortex excitabilityBrain2002125223822471224408134NitscheMAFrickeKHenschkeUSchlitterlauALiebetanzDPharmacological modulation of cortical excitability shifts induced by transcranial direct current stimulation in humansJ Physiol20035532933011294922435PortillaASBravoGLMiravalFKVillamarMFSchneiderJCA feasibility study assessing cortical plasticity in chronic neuropathic pain following burn injuryJ Burn Care Res201334e48e522329259536DosSantosMFLoveTMMartikainenIKNascimentoTDFregniFImmediate effects of tDCS on the μ-opioid system of a chronic pain patientFront Psychiatry20123932313000237NitscheMASeeberAFrommannKKleinCCRochfordCModulating parameters of excitability during and after transcranial direct current stimulation of the human motor cortexJ Physiol20055682913031600244138LiebetanzDNitscheMATergauFPaulusWPharmacological approach to the mechanisms of transcranial DC-stimulation-induced after-effects of human motor cortex excitabilityBrain2002125223822471224408139García-LarreaLPeyronRMertensPGrégoireMCLavenneFPositron emission tomography during motor cortex stimulation for pain controlStereotact Funct Neurosurg199768141148971170740García-LarreaLPeyronRMertensPGregoireMCLavenneFElectrical stimulation of motor cortex for pain control: a combined PET-scan and electrophysiological studyPain19998325927310534598Figure 1Transcranial direct current stimulation and 10–20 international electrode placements. A = Nine volts of direct current power supply, B = Stimulating electrode over the left primary motor area, and C = Reference electrode on the right supraorbital area or right shoulder area.Table 1Summary of tDCS in treatment of neuropathic pain [20–26].Topic/authorsStudydesignNumberofSubjectsTreatmentStimulationelectrodepositionReferenceelectrode positionStimulationDurationIntensity(mA)ResultsEffectivedurationAdverseeventsFregni et al. [20]RCT in traumatic spinal cord injury17Anodal and Sham tDCSLeft or right M1Contralateral supraorbital area20 min (5 days)2Significant pain reduction after active tDCS(p&lt;0.05), but not after sham stimulation16 daysMild headache and itching under the electrodesFregni et al. [21]RCT in fibromyalgia32Anodal and Sham tDCSLeft or right M1, DLPFCContralateral supraorbital area20 min (5 days)2Significant pain reduction in M1 than DLPFC and sham (p &lt; 0.0001)3 weeksSleepiness, itching, and headache (similar to sham group)Boggio et al. [22]RCT and cross over study in chronic pain8Active tDCS+active TENS, active tDCS+sham TENS, sham tDCS+shamTENStDCS over M1 TENS at the site of most painContralateral supraorbital area30 min (single stimulation)2Active tDCS+ active TENS induced greater pain reduction than othersN/AN/AMori et al. [23]RCT in chronic pain from multiple sclerosis19Anodal and sham tDCS,M1Contralateral supraorbital area20 min (5 days)2Statistically decrease of pain scores at the end of stimulation4 weeksN/AAntal et al. [24] (2010)RCT in chronic pain214×4 cm2 electrodes size of anodal and sham tDCSM1Contralateral supraorbital area20 min (5 days)1-Pain reduction occurred after the first stimulation(p=0.03)-The maximal pain reduction occure at the 5th stimulation28 daysLight headacheSoler et al. [25]RCT in central pain from spinal cord injury39Anodal tDCS+walking visual illusion, anodal tDCS+ control illusion, sham tDCS+visual illusionM1Contralateral supraorbital area20 min (10 days)2Pain reduction was significant reduced in anodal tDCS+walking visual illusion group than others12 weeksN/AKumru et al. [26]RCT in neuropathic pain from spinal cord injury18Anodal tDCS+visual illusionM1N/A20 min2Evoked pain and heat pain threshold in spinal cord injury with neuropathic pain were significant changes after treated with anodal tDCS + visual illusion2 weeksN/A
