<?xml version="1.0"?>
Neuroimage ClinNeuroimage ClinNeuroImage : Clinical2213-1582Elsevier4377841S2213-1582(15)00027-310.1016/j.nicl.2015.02.009Regular ArticleResponse of the medial temporal lobe network in amnestic mild cognitive impairment to therapeutic intervention assessed by fMRI and memory task performanceBakkerArnoldabakker@jhu.edua⁎AlbertMarilyn S.bKraussGregorybSpeckCaroline L.aGallagherMichelacaDepartment of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21287, USAbDepartment of Neurology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD 21287, USAcDepartment of Psychological and Brain Sciences, Johns Hopkins School of Arts and Sciences, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA⁎Corresponding author at: Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, 600 N. Wolfe Street/Phipps 300, Baltimore, MD 21287, USA. Tel.: +1 410 502 6944; fax: +1 410 614 3676. abakker@jhu.edu21220152015212201576886981111201421120151922015© 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc.2015This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).Studies of individuals with amnestic mild cognitive impairment (aMCI) have detected hyperactivity in the hippocampus during task-related functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). Such elevated activation has been localized to the hippocampal dentate gyrus/CA3 (DG/CA3) during performance of a task designed to detect the computational contributions of those hippocampal circuits to episodic memory. The current investigation was conducted to test the hypothesis that greater hippocampal activation in aMCI represents a dysfunctional shift in the normal computational balance of the DG/CA3 regions, augmenting CA3-driven pattern completion at the expense of pattern separation mediated by the dentate gyrus. We tested this hypothesis using an intervention based on animal research demonstrating a beneficial effect on cognition by reducing excess hippocampal neural activity with low doses of the atypical anti-epileptic levetiracetam. In a within-subject design we assessed the effects of levetiracetam in three cohorts of aMCI participants, each receiving a different dose of levetiracetam. Elevated activation in the DG/CA3 region, together with impaired task performance, was detected in each aMCI cohort relative to an aged control group. We observed significant improvement in memory task performance under drug treatment relative to placebo in the aMCI cohorts at the 62.5 and 125 mg BID doses of levetiracetam. Drug treatment in those cohorts increased accuracy dependent on pattern separation processes and reduced errors attributable to an over-riding effect of pattern completion while normalizing fMRI activation in the DG/CA3 and entorhinal cortex. Similar to findings in animal studies, higher dosing at 250 mg BID had no significant benefit on either task performance or fMRI activation. Consistent with predictions based on the computational functions of the DG/CA3 elucidated in basic animal research, these data support a dysfunctional encoding mechanism detected by fMRI in individuals with aMCI and therapeutic intervention using fMRI to detect target engagement in response to treatment.Highlights•Patients with aMCI show increased fMRI activation in DG/CA3 relative to controls.•Low dose levetiracetam treatment decreases excess DG/CA3 activation in aMCI.•Low dose levetiracetam treatment normalizes decreased entorhinal activation in aMCI.•Low dose levetiracetam treatment improves task related memory performance in aMCI.•Targeting excess hippocampal activity has therapeutic potential in amnestic MCI.KeywordsMild cognitive impairmentLevetiracetamMemoryfMRIDentate gyrusEntorhinal cortex<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design</title><p>The design for this study is schematically shown in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. The entire RCT protocol consisted of 4 study visits over an 8-week period. Each cohort of aMCI participants was randomized, double-blind, in a within-subject crossover design, with the order of treatment on drug and placebo counterbalanced within each cohort. Age-matched controls were treated single-blind on placebo as further described in the procedures that follow.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Participants and clinical characterization</title><p>During the baseline visit all participants completed the dementia rating scale (CDR: <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Morris, 1993</xref>), and underwent medical, psychiatric, neurological and neuropsychological evaluations, which included the Mini Mental Status Exam (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Folstein et al., 1975</xref>), the Buschke Selective Reminding Test (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Buschke and Fuld, 1974</xref>), the Verbal Paired Associated subtest of the Wechsler Memory Scale (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler, 1987</xref>) and the Benton Visual Retention Test (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Benton, 1974</xref>). All aMCI participants had a global CDR score of 0.5 with a sum of boxes score not exceeding 2.5 and met criteria for aMCI proposed by Petersen (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Petersen, 2004</xref>), which includes impaired memory function on testing and no decline in basic activities of daily living. All control subjects had a global CDR score of 0. None of the aMCI participants or age-matched control subjects met criteria for dementia. Other exclusion criteria included major neurological and psychiatric disorders, head trauma with loss of consciousness, history of substance abuse or dependency, and general contraindications to having an MRI examination (e.g. cardiac pacemaker, aneurysm coils and claustrophobia) or taking the study medication (e.g. known sensitivity or allergies, or severe renal impairment). Participants taking anti-epileptic medications were excluded from participation in the study but use of other neuroactive medications was permitted if the participant was stable on the medication for at least 12 weeks and if the treatment regimen was not altered for the duration of the study. The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions. All participants provided written informed consent and were paid for their participation in the study.</p><p>At the baseline evaluation sixty-nine participants with aMCI and 24 age-matched controls met criteria for enrollment. Complete data from 54 participants with aMCI and 17 control participants were included in the analysis. Nine aMCI participants and 6 control participants did not complete the study protocol. Data from an additional 6 aMCI participants and 1 control participant were excluded before analysis due to excessive motion or in-scanner task performance that was inadequate for analysis of the fMRI data.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Study procedures</title><p>All participants completed the same study procedures with fMRI study visits after each of two treatment phases, separated by a washout period of 4 weeks as shown in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Control subjects were given placebo during both treatment phases (single-blind) while participants with aMCI were given placebo during one treatment phase and drug during the other treatment phase, with the order of treatment counterbalanced (randomized, double-blind). A first cohort of aMCI participants received treatment with 125 mg BID of levetiracetam (Keppra, UCB Laboratories), as was previously reported (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Bakker et al., 2012</xref>). Based on those initial findings and earlier preclinical data in animals (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Koh et al., 2010</xref>), two additional doses were selected for two subsequent cohorts of aMCI participants, receiving treatment with 62.5 mg BID and 250 mg BID of levetiracetam, respectively. All study treatments (drug and placebo) were prepared in identical non-descript capsules by the Investigational Drug Service at Johns Hopkins Hospital. Capsules were provided in blister packs labeled for morning and evening daily doses. After 2 weeks on treatment, each study visit included a brief medical and psychiatric examination, the neuropsychological assessment, a blood draw and an MRI scan during performance of the 3-judgment memory task. At the end of the washout visit, each participant had a blood draw and was provided with the study medication for the second treatment phase of the study. Treatment compliance was assessed by participant self-report at the end of each treatment phase, medication diaries, and analysis of levetiracetam blood values at each visit during the study protocol.</p><p>The study team was blind to the status of the aMCI participants and levetiracetam blood levels until final group analysis of the data. In addition to providing the study medication the Investigational Drug Service randomized aMCI participants to the treatment conditions and controlled blinding and unblinding of study data according to standard clinical trial procedures. Data safety was monitored by three physicians not related to the study in collaboration with the Investigational Drug Service.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>fMRI activation paradigm</title><p>The fMRI activation paradigm was a 3-alternative forced choice task designed to assess pattern separation and completion processes, as mentioned above (<xref rid="ref4 ref3" ref-type="bibr">Bakker et al., 2012, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Kirwan and Stark, 2007</xref>). For this task participants were asked to view a series of stimuli consisting of 768 pictures of common namable objects (see <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). This included 96 pairs of related but not identical pictures of the same object referred to as lures, 96 pairs in which the identical picture was repeated, referred to as repeats and 384 unrelated single pictures of objects used as foils. Stimuli were divided over eight runs of 96 stimuli per run. Each stimulus was presented for 2500 ms with a 500 ms inter-stimulus-interval consisting of a blank screen. All trials were presented in pseudo-random order with the limitation that a lure or repeated stimulus was presented within 30 trials of its pair. For each stimulus, the participant was asked to judge if the picture was ‘new’, ‘old’ or ‘similar’ but not identical. Stimuli were presented and responses collected using an Apple Macintosh laptop computer running MATLAB software (The Mathworks, Natick, MA), a back-projection screen and an LCD projector located outside of the scan room. Participants viewed stimuli via a mirror mounted on the head coil. Responses were made using one button in the left hand and two buttons in the right hand connected to a Cedrus RB-610 response box. Before each MRI session subjects completed a brief practice task consisting of 96 trials outside of the scanner to familiarize themselves with the stimuli and the procedures.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>MRI data acquisition</title><p>Imaging sessions were conducted on a 3 Tesla Philips scanner (Philips, Eindhoven, The Netherlands) equipped with a SENSE parallel imaging head coil (MRI Devices, Inc., Waukesha) and higher order shims to compensate for local field distortions at the F.M. Kirby Research Center for Functional Brain Imaging at the Kennedy Krieger Institute on the Johns Hopkins Medical Campus. High-resolution functional images were collected using a T2*-weighted echo planar single shot pulse sequence with an acquisition matrix of 64 × 64, an echo time of 30 ms, a flip angle of 70°, a sense factor of 2, an in plane resolution of 1.5 × 1.5 mm and a TR of 1.5 s (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Kirwan et al., 2007</xref>). Each volume consisted of 19 oblique 1.5 mm thick axial slices with no gap oriented along the principal axis of the hippocampus and covered the medial temporal lobe bilaterally. Four dummy scans were completed at the beginning of each run to allow for stabilization of the MR signal. In addition, a whole brain structural scan was acquired using a magnetization prepared rapid gradient echo (MPRAGE) T<sub>1</sub>-weighted sequence with 231 oblique slices, 0.65 mm isotropic resolution and a field of view of 240.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>fMRI data analysis</title><p>Image data analysis was performed using the Analysis of Functional Neuroimages (AFNI) software package (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Cox, 1996</xref>). The functional images were first co-registered to correct for slice timing and head motion, using a three-dimensional registration algorithm creating motion vectors to remove trials in which a significant head motion occurred plus and minus one TR from further analysis. Of critical interest were the participants' responses on the ‘lure’ items used to assess the balance between pattern separation and pattern completion functions in the hippocampal formation. To avoid confusion, throughout the paper we will refer to items subsequently tested with repetitions as ‘<italic>subsequent targets</italic>’ and novel items subsequently tested with a similar lure as ‘<italic>subsequent lures</italic>’. The subsequent items all refer to the 1st presentation trials. During the 2nd presentation, trials will be referred to as <italic>targets</italic> and <italic>lures</italic> respectively.</p><p>Following this convention, functional runs were concatenated and 6 vectors were defined to model the different trial types: (1) repeats subsequently called “old”, (2) lures subsequently called “similar”, (3) lures subsequently called “old”, (4) repeats called “old”, (5) lures called “similar” and (6) lures called “old”. All other response types (misses, false alarms, etc.) were modeled but not included in the secondary analyses. The full set of vectors were used to model each individual's data using a deconvolution approach based on general linear regression treating the single foil presentations that were correctly rejected as a non-zero baseline against which all other conditions were compared. The resulting statistical fit coefficient maps represent the difference in activity between each of the trial types and the baseline for a given time point for a given voxel. The sum of the fit coefficients over the length of the hemodynamic response (~3–12 s after the onset of the trial) was taken as the model's estimate of the response to each trial type. The statistical maps were then smoothed using a Gaussian kernel of 3 mm to account for variations in individual functional anatomy.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Cross-participant alignment</title><p>Methods used for cross-participant alignment in this study increase the power of multi-subject regional fMRI studies by focusing the alignment power to the regions of interest using a segmentation of the subject's anatomical image. Initial affine registration was used to transform the subject's anatomical and functional images to the Talairach coordinate system (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Talairach and Tournoux, 1988</xref>). Subregions of the medial temporal lobe and the hippocampus were manually segmented into three dimensions using the structural scan and methods described previously (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Bakker et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Kirwan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Yassa and Stark, 2009</xref>). Briefly, the entorhinal cortex, perirhinal cortex, parahippocampal cortex, and temporopolar cortices were defined bilaterally in the coronal plane using methods described by <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Insausti et al. (1998)</xref>. The CA1, DG/CA3 and subiculum subregions of the hippocampus were also defined in the coronal plane following landmarks described in the atlas of <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Duvernoy (2005)</xref>. The DG/CA3 region included the CA2/CA3/CA4 and dentate gyrus subregions as these regions cannot be reliably separated on MRI scans. Using both the segmentation label-based information for the point-set expectation (PSE) error metric and the grayscale structural image for the pure cross-correlation (PR) error metric, Advanced Normalization Tools (ANTs) was used to calculate the 3D vector field transformation for each subject needed to align the individual's ROIs to a template modal model of the ROIs based on the entire sample (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Klein et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Yushkevich et al., 2009</xref>) equally weighing the segmentations and T<sub>1</sub> gray scale data. The 3D vector field for each individual was then applied to the concatenated fit coefficient maps resulting from the functional analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Age, education and neuropsychological and functional assessment scores between groups were compared using independent sample t-tests. The distribution of sex between groups was compared using a chi-square test.</p><p>The primary objective of the study was to determine the efficacy of levetiracetam treatment in participants with aMCI, using within-subject comparisons for each cohort. To facilitate a comparison of the fMRI data across the three cohorts of aMCI participants, independent analyses were first conducted for each cohort using a two-way ANOVA with trial type (6 trial type vectors) and group status (aMCI on placebo and aged-matched control group) as fixed factors and subject as a random factor nested within group. A liberal voxel threshold of p &lt; 0.07 was used on the main effect of group F-statistic in combination with a spatial extent threshold of 40 voxels to select areas of task-related activation. The resulting areas of activation were then combined with the anatomical segmentations in order to include only voxels within our areas of interest. The hybrid functional/anatomical analysis resulted in clusters of voxels in each aMCI cohort where activity varied systematically between aMCI and control cohorts within each of the anatomical regions of interest. Voxels within each functional/anatomical region of interest were then collapsed for further analysis. Planned comparisons using t-tests were used for comparisons between the control and the aMCI cohorts on placebo and for the comparisons within each aMCI cohort comparing the aMCI participants on placebo and on levetiracetam on the critical trial type.</p></sec></sec>ReferencesAlmeC.B.MiaoC.JezekK.TrevesA.MoserE.I.MoserM.-B.Place cells in the hippocampus: eleven maps for eleven roomsProc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.11152201418428184352548908925489089Andrews-ZwillingY.Bien-LyN.XuQ.LiG.BernardoA.YoonS.Y.ZwillingD.YanT.X.ChenL.HuangY.Apolipoprotein E4 causes age- and Tau-dependent impairment of GABAergic interneurons, leading to learning and memory deficits in miceJ. Neurosci.3041201013707137172094391120943911BakkerA.KirwanC.B.MillerM.StarkC.E.Pattern separation in the human hippocampal CA3 and dentate gyrusScience31958702008164016421835651818356518BakkerA.KraussG.L.AlbertM.S.SpeckC.L.JonesL.R.StarkC.E.YassaM.A.BassettS.S.SheltonA.L.GallagherM.Reduction of hippocampal hyperactivity improves cognition in amnestic mild cognitive impairmentNeuron74320124674742257849822578498BentonA.The Revised Visual Retention Test1974Psychological CorporationNew YorkBerchtoldN.C.SabbaghM.N.BeachT.G.KimR.C.CribbsD.H.CotmanC.W.Brain gene expression patterns differentiate mild cognitive impairment from normal aged and Alzheimer's diseaseNeurobiol. Aging3592014196119722478663124786631BuschkeH.FuldP.A.Evaluating storage, retention, and retrieval in disordered memory and learningNeurology241119741019102544731514473151ChinJ.MassaroC.M.PalopJ.J.ThwinM.T.YuG.-Q.Bien-LyN.BenderA.MuckeL.Reelin depletion in the entorhinal cortex of human amyloid precursor protein transgenic mice and humans with Alzheimer's diseaseJ. Neurosci.27112007272727331736089417360894CoxR.W.AFNI: software for analysis and visualization of functional magnetic resonance neuroimagesComput. Biomed. Res.293199616217388120688812068DuvernoyH.The Human Hippocampus: Functional Anatomy, Vascularization, and Serial Sections with MRI2005Springer VerlagFolsteinM.F.FolsteinS.E.McHughP.R.“Mini-mental state.” A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinicianJ. Psychiatr. Res.123197518919812022041202204InsaustiR.JuottonenK.SoininenH.InsaustiA.M.PartanenK.VainioP.LaaksoM.P.PitkänenA.MR volumetric analysis of the human entorhinal, perirhinal, and temporopolar corticesA.J.N.R. Am. J. Neuroradiol.19419986596719576651KirwanC.B.JonesC.K.MillerM.I.StarkC.E.High-resolution fMRI investigation of the medial temporal lobeHum. Brain Mapp.281020079599661713338117133381KirwanC.B.StarkC.E.Overcoming interference: an fMRI investigation of pattern separation in the medial temporal lobeLearn. Mem.14920076256331784850217848502KleinA.AnderssonJ.ArdekaniB.A.AshburnerJ.AvantsB.ChiangM.-C.ChristensenG.E.CollinsD.L.GeeJ.HellierP.SongJ.H.JenkinsonM.LepageC.RueckertD.ThompsonP.VercauterenT.WoodsR.P.MannJ.J.ParseyR.V.Evaluation of 14 nonlinear deformation algorithms applied to human brain MRI registrationNeuroimage46320097868021919549619195496KohM.T.HabermanR.P.FotiS.McCownT.J.GallagherM.Treatment strategies targeting excess hippocampal activity benefit aged rats with cognitive impairmentNeuropsychopharmacology3542010101610252003296720032967KohM.T.Rosenzweig-LipsonS.GallagherM.Selective GABA(A) α5 positive allosteric modulators improve cognitive function in aged rats with memory impairmentNeuropharmacology6420131451522273244022732440LacyJ.W.YassaM.A.StarkS.M.MuftulerL.T.StarkC.E.Distinct pattern separation related transfer functions in human CA3/dentate and CA1 revealed using high-resolution fMRI and variable mnemonic similarityLearn. Mem.181201115182116417321164173LeeI.YoganarasimhaD.RaoG.KnierimJ.J.Comparison of population coherence of place cells in hippocampal subfields CA1 and CA3Nature430699820044564591522961415229614LeutgebS.LeutgebJ.K.TrevesA.MoserM.-B.MoserE.I.Distinct ensemble codes in hippocampal areas CA3 and CA1Science30556882004129512981527212315272123Lyseng-WilliamsonK.A.Levetiracetam: a review of its use in epilepsyDrugs71420114895142139536021395360MalykhinN.V.LebelR.M.CouplandN.J.WilmanA.H.CarterR.In vivo quantification of hippocampal subfields using 4.7 T fast spin echo imagingNeuroimage4922010122412301978610419786104McClellandJ.L.McNaughtonB.L.O'ReillyR.C.Why there are complementary learning systems in the hippocampus and neocortex: insights from the successes and failures of connectionist models of learning and memoryPsychol. Rev.1023199541945776244557624455MillerS.L.FenstermacherE.BatesJ.BlackerD.SperlingR.A.DickersonB.C.Hippocampal activation in adults with mild cognitive impairment predicts subsequent cognitive declineJ. Neurol. Neurosurg. Psychiatr.79620086306351784610917846109MorrisJ.C.The Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR): current version and scoring rulesNeurology431119932412241482329728232972NeunuebelJ.P.KnierimJ.J.CA3 retrieves coherent representations from degraded input: direct evidence for CA3 pattern completion and dentate gyrus pattern separationNeuron81220144164272446210224462102NormanK.A.O'ReillyR.C.Modeling hippocampal and neocortical contributions to recognition memory: a complementary-learning-systems approachPsychol. Rev.110420036116461459923614599236O'BrienJ.L.O'KeefeK.M.LaVioletteP.S.DeLucaA.N.BlackerD.DickersonB.C.SperlingR.A.Longitudinal fMRI in elderly reveals loss of hippocampal activation with clinical declineNeurology74242010196919762046328820463288O'ReillyR.C.McClellandJ.L.Hippocampal conjunctive encoding, storage, and recall: avoiding a trade-offHippocampus46199466168277041107704110PetersenR.C.Mild cognitive impairment as a diagnostic entityJ. Intern. Med.256320041831941532436215324362PoppenkJ.EvensmoenH.R.MoscovitchM.NadelL.Long-axis specialization of the human hippocampusTrends Cogn. Sci.17520132302402359772023597720PutchaD.BrickhouseM.O'KeefeK.SullivanC.RentzD.MarshallG.DickersonB.SperlingR.Hippocampal hyperactivation associated with cortical thinning in Alzheimer's disease signature regions in non-demented elderly adultsJ. Neurosci.3148201117680176882213142822131428RhinnH.FujitaR.QiangL.ChengR.LeeJ.H.AbeliovichA.Integrative genomics identifies APOE ε4 effectors in Alzheimer's diseaseNature5007460201345502388393623883936SanchezP.E.ZhuL.VerretL.VosselK.A.OrrA.G.CirritoJ.R.DevidzeN.HoK.YuG.-Q.PalopJ.J.MuckeL.Levetiracetam suppresses neuronal network dysfunction and reverses synaptic and cognitive deficits in an Alzheimer's disease modelProc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.1092012E2895E29032286975222869752ScheffS.W.PriceD.A.SchmittF.A.MufsonE.J.Hippocampal synaptic loss in early Alzheimer's disease and mild cognitive impairmentNeurobiol. Aging27102006137213841628947616289476ShiJ.-Q.WangB.-R.TianY.-Y.XuJ.GaoL.ZhaoS.-L.JiangT.XieH.-G.ZhangY.-D.Anti-epileptics topiramate and levetiracetam alleviate behavioral deficits and reduce neuropathology in APPswe/PS1dE9 transgenic miceC.N.S. Neurosci. Ther.1911201387188123889921SmithT.D.AdamsM.M.GallagherM.MorrisonJ.H.RappP.R.Circuit-specific alterations in hippocampal synaptophysin immunoreactivity predict spatial learning impairment in aged ratsJ. Neurosci.20172000658765931096496410964964SpiegelA.M.KohM.T.VogtN.M.RappP.R.GallagherM.Hilar interneuron vulnerability distinguishes aged rats with memory impairmentJ. Comp. Neurol.521152013350835232374948323749483StargardtA.SwaabD.F.BossersK.The storm before the quiet: neuronal hyperactivity and Aβ in the presymptomatic stages of Alzheimer's diseaseNeurobiol. Aging36120151112544460925444609StarkS.M.YassaM.A.LacyJ.W.StarkC.E.A task to assess behavioral pattern separation (BPS) in humans: data from healthy aging and mild cognitive impairmentNeuropsychologia51122013244224492331329223313292StranahanA.M.HabermanR.P.GallagherM.Cognitive decline is associated with reduced reelin expression in the entorhinal cortex of aged ratsCereb. Cortex21220113924002053874020538740SuberbielleE.SanchezP.E.KravitzA.V.WangX.HoK.EilertsonK.DevidzeN.KreitzerA.C.MuckeL.Physiologic brain activity causes DNA double-strand breaks in neurons, with exacerbation by amyloid-βNat. Neurosci.16520136136212352504023525040TalairachJ.TournouxP.Co-planar Stereotaxic Atlas of the Human Brain: 3 Dimensional Proportional System: An Approach to Cerebral Imaging1988ThiemeTonerC.K.PirogovskyE.KirwanC.B.GilbertP.E.Visual object pattern separation deficits in nondemented older adultsLearn. Mem.16520093383421940379719403797TrevesA.RollsE.T.Computational analysis of the role of the hippocampus in memoryHippocampus43199437439178420587842058WechslerD.WMS-R: Wechsler Memory Scale —Revised Manual1987WilsonI.A.GallagherM.EichenbaumH.TanilaH.Neurocognitive aging: prior memories hinder new hippocampal encodingTrends Neurosci.291220066626701704607517046075WilsonI.A.IkonenS.GallagherM.EichenbaumH.TanilaH.Age-associated alterations of hippocampal place cells are subregion specificJ. Neurosci.25292005687768861603389716033897WilsonI.A.IkonenS.McMahanR.W.GallagherM.EichenbaumH.TanilaH.Place cell rigidity correlates with impaired spatial learning in aged ratsNeurobiol. Aging24220032973051249896312498963YassaM.A.LacyJ.W.StarkS.M.AlbertM.S.GallagherM.StarkC.E.Pattern separation deficits associated with increased hippocampal CA3 and dentate gyrus activity in nondemented older adultsHippocampus2120119689792086573220865732YassaM.A.MattfeldA.T.StarkS.M.StarkC.E.Age-related memory deficits linked to circuit-specific disruptions in the hippocampusProc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.108212011887388782155558121555581YassaM.A.StarkC.E.A quantitative evaluation of cross-participant registration techniques for MRI studies of the medial temporal lobeNeuroimage44220093193271892966918929669YassaM.A.StarkC.E.Pattern separation in the hippocampusTrends Neurosci.3420115155252178808621788086YassaM.A.StarkS.M.BakkerA.AlbertM.S.GallagherM.StarkC.E.High-resolution structural and functional MRI of hippocampal CA3 and dentate gyrus in patients with amnestic mild cognitive impairmentNeuroimage5132010124212522033824620338246YushkevichP.A.AvantsB.B.PlutaJ.DasS.MinkoffD.Mechanic-HamiltonD.GlynnS.PickupS.LiuW.GeeJ.C.GrossmanM.DetreJ.A.A high-resolution computational atlas of the human hippocampus from postmortem magnetic resonance imaging at 9.4 TNeuroimage44220093853981884053218840532AcknowledgmentsWe would like to thank Dr. Jason Brandt and Dr. Paul Dash for their help with participant recruitment. We would like to thank the staff of the F.M. Kirby Center for Functional Brain Imaging for their assistance with data collection. This work was supported by the NIH grant RC2AG036419 to M.G.Fig. 1Schematic of the study design.Fig. 2Task designed to tax hippocampal DG/CA3 function. Participants were shown a series of pictures of every day objects and asked to judge if the item was new (seen for the first time), old (a repeated item) or similar (resembled a previously shown item). The lure items served as the critical trials for assessing performance dependent on the dentate gyrus/CA3.Fig. 3Increased hippocampal DG/CA3 activation is observed in the context of impaired memory performance in three aMCI cohorts. Task related activation and behavioral performance during the placebo condition in participants with aMCI in the (A) 62.5 mg BID treatment group, (B) 125 mg BID treatment group and (C) 250 mg BID treatment group. (A–C) Top left in A–C: sagittal view of the left medial temporal lobe. Green vertical lines identify slices through the hippocampus shown to the right. Top middle in A–C: segmentation of the structures of interest including the CA1, dentate gyrus/CA3 (DG/CA3), and subiculum (SUB) subregions of the hippocampus. Top right in A–C: coronal slices show statistical maps of the extent of task related activity in the left DG/CA3 from anterior to posterior. Bottom left in A–C: mean activity during lure trials correctly called similar. Participants with aMCI on placebo in each of the treatment groups show increased activity in the left DG/CA3 compared to healthy control subjects during lure trials based on independent samples t-tests. Bottom right in A–C: participants with aMCI on placebo in each of the treatment groups show impaired memory performance by more often incorrectly judging lure items as “old” instead of similar when compared to healthy control subjects. Statistics show p-values resulting from a planned post-hoc contrast for the interaction of group as a function of response type (old versus similar). Values are means ± SEM. *p &lt; 0.05.Fig. 4Low dose levetiracetam normalizes DG/CA3 activation and improves task-related memory performance on critical lure items in participants with aMCI. Top graphs show mean fMRI activity during lure trials correctly called similar. Bottom graphs show behavioral performance as the proportion of lure trials called “old”, “new” and “similar”. For each cohort all analyses were within-subject comparing placebo with drug treatment. (A) In the 62.5 mg BID cohort levetiracetam did not significantly reduce activity in the DG/CA3 in participants with aMCI although activity under drug treatment was no longer significantly different from healthy control subjects. (B) In the 62.5 mg BID cohort levetiracetam improved memory performance in aMCI participants by reducing errors in which lures were incorrectly judged “old”, with more correct judgments of “similar”. (C) In the 125 mg BID cohort levetiracetam significantly reduced activation in the DG/CA3 and (D) significantly improved memory performance. (E) In the 250 mg BID cohort treatment levetiracetam did not reduce activity in the DG/CA3 and (F) did not alter memory performance in these patients. Values are means ± SEM. *p &lt; 0.05.Fig. 5Low dose levetiracetam normalizes entorhinal cortex activity in participants with aMCI. Task-related activation in (A) 62.5 mg BID treatment group and (B) 125 mg BID treatment group. Top left in A–B: sagittal view of the left medial temporal lobe. Green vertical lines identify slices through the entorhinal cortex shown to the right. Top middle A–B: segmentation of the medial temporal lobe structures including the entorhinal (EC) and perirhinal (PRC) cortices. Top right A–B: coronal slices show statistical maps of the extent of task related activity in the left EC in the 62.5 mg BID treatment cohort and the 125 mg BID treatment cohort.Table 1Demographics and clinical characterization of healthy controls and aMCI participants.CharacteristicControlsaMCI 62.5 mg BIDaMCI 125 mg BIDaMCI 250 mg BIDMeanSDMeanSDp-ValueMeanSDp-ValueMeanSDp-ValueSubjects1720−17−17−Sex (M/F)9/89/110.7196/110.3816/110.381Age (years)69.47.071.06.40.47672.98.90.20170.87.00.542Education (years)15.92.615.32.80.50515.82.90.95116.82.60.290CDR00.5−0.5−0.5−CDR sum of boxes0.030.10.880.5−1.00.6−1.20.6−MMSE27.91.526.52.50.04825.72.30.00225.92.50.007LM delayed recall29.55.217.89.4&lt;0.00115.48.2&lt;0.00122.97.70.006BSRT delayed recall7.71.94.52.9&lt;0.0013.62.4&lt;0.0013.42.1&lt;0.001Wechsler VPA delayed recall7.01.54.32.6&lt;0.0013.92.9&lt;0.0015.22.70.026BVRT5.81.84.91.60.0914.51.50.0265.21.70.338CDR: Clinical Dementia Rating; MMSE: Mini Mental Status Exam; LM: Logical Memory Paragraph Recall; BSRT: Buschke Selective Reminding Test; VPA: Verbal Paired Associates; BVRT: Benton Visual Retention Test. p-Values are based on independent sample t-tests comparing each aMCI cohort to the control group.
