<?xml version="1.0"?>
Neurol TherNeurol TherNeurology and Therapy2193-82532193-6536Springer Healthcare CommunicationsHeidelberg4389038310.1007/s40120-012-0003-9Original ResearchVirtual Reality Versus Conventional Treatment of Reaching Ability in Chronic Stroke: Clinical Feasibility StudyLevinMindy F.mindy.levin@mcgill.caSnirOsnatLiebermannDario G.WeingardenHaroldWeissPatrice L.School of Physical and Occupational Therapy, Faculty of Medicine, 3654 Promenade Sir William Osler, Montreal, QC H3G 1Y5 Canada Center for Interdisciplinary Research in Rehabilitation, Montreal, Canada Department of Occupational Therapy, Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel Hannah Khoushy Child Development Center, Bnai Zion Medical Center, Haifa, Israel Department of Physical Therapy, Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel Department of Neurological Rehabilitation, Sheba Medical Center, Tel Hashomer, Israel Department of Occupational Therapy, Faculty of Social Welfare and Health Sciences, University of Haifa, Haifa, Israel 248201224820121220121131262012© The Author(s) 2012IntroductionThe objective of this study was to evaluate the potential of exercises performed in a 2D video-capture virtual reality (VR) training environment to improve upper limb motor ability in stroke patients compared to those performed in conventional therapy.MethodsA small sample randomized control trial, in an outpatient rehabilitation center with 12 patients with chronic stroke, aged 33–80 years, who were randomly allocated to video-capture VR therapy and conventional therapy groups. All patients participated in four clinical evaluation sessions (pre-test 1, pre-test 2, post-test, follow-up) and nine 45-minute intervention sessions over a 3-week period. Main outcomes assessed were Body Structure and Function (impairment: Fugl–Meyer Assessment [FMA]; Composite Spasticity Index [CSI]; Reaching Performance Scale for Stroke), Activity (Box and Blocks; Wolf Motor Function Test [WMFT]), and Participation (Motor Activity Log) levels of the International Classification of Functioning.ResultsImprovements occurred in both groups, but more patients in the VR group improved upper limb clinical impairment (FMA, CSI) and activity scores (WMFT) and improvements occurred earlier. Patients in the VR group also reported satisfaction with the novel treatment.ConclusionsThe modest advantage of VR over conventional training supports further investigation of the effect of video-capture VR or VR combined with conventional therapy in larger-scale randomized, more intense controlled studies.KeywordsClinical outcomesInterventionReachingStrokeVirtual realityissue-copyright-statement© Springer Healthcare 2012<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Participants</title><p>Patients were included if they had sustained a unilateral left- or right-sided stroke more than 3 months previously, had no hemispatial neglect or uncorrected visual field deficits, including hemianopia, and could understand and follow instructions (no receptive aphasia, mini-mental state evaluation &gt;25) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Participants were excluded if they had shoulder or arm pain, or lack of endurance as judged by their treating physician. Of 50 eligible patients, 14 (33–80 years, 10 months to 5 years after first stroke) were recruited from discharge lists of a large rehabilitation center and randomly allocated to one of two intervention groups having the same therapeutic goals: VR (<italic>n</italic> = 8) and Conventional (<italic>n</italic> = 6) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Randomization was carried out using a coin toss by an individual who was not involved in either participant assessment or intervention. Two patients withdrew from the VR group before commencement of the intervention because of transportation and financial difficulties (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>—consort diagram). All participants signed informed consent forms approved by the Institutional Ethics Review Board.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Consort statement</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40120_2012_3_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Procedures</title><p>Four clinical evaluations and nine intervention sessions were delivered by different personnel. A clinician (occupational therapist), experienced in neurological rehabilitation and blinded as to treatment group allocation, performed the entire battery of tests on individual subjects. All clinical tests used have previously published evidence of acceptable levels of validity and inter-rater reliability. Two clinical evaluations separated by 1 week were performed before the intervention: one was done immediately after and one was done 1 month after the intervention.</p><p>During the intervention sessions, VR therapy focused on goal-directed reaching tasks by the affected arm via virtual games and a virtual supermarket (e.g., Birds &amp; Balls, Soccer, Volleyball, VMall) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The reaching movements combined shoulder flexion to ~130°, shoulder abduction to ~60°, elbow extension to ~180°, and wrist flexion and extension. Reaching movements were made into all areas of the arm workspace (e.g., ipsilateral, contralateral, midline, upper, and lower) to accomplish discrete and sequential reaching movements. Practice in the VE did not include grasping and manipulation tasks. Conventional therapy consisted of occupational therapy, including exercises involving reaching for and holding cones, cups, and other objects in all motion planes with and without external loading. These tasks were performed in a standard clinical treatment room.</p><p>The two types of therapy were equivalent in duration and type of feedback provided by the therapist concerning the quality of the reaching movements (e.g., amount of elbow extension, shoulder flexion) as well as the use of compensatory movements (e.g., trunk displacement). Participants in both environments were encouraged to work as hard as possible but the number of trials was not prescribed to avoid making the activities artificial. For both groups, the initial level of task difficulty was matched to patient impairment level and increased throughout the intervention to ensure that practice remained challenging to the individual.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Instruments</title><p>The VR therapy was done on the Gesture Xtreme<sup>®</sup> (GestureTek, Inc. Toronto, Canada) video-capture system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Users stood or sat in a demarcated area with a chroma-key backdrop and viewed a simulated VE on a 34″ screen. The user’s image was recorded and displayed within the VE, which responded to user gestures in real-time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Primary Outcome Measures</title><p>Primary outcomes were clinical measures of UL performance at three levels of the International Classification of Function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. At the Body Structure and Function level, UL impairment was assessed with Fugl–Meyer Arm Scale (FMA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] (total score = 66), spasticity in elbow flexors was assessed with the Composite Spasticity Index (CSI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] in which scores of 0–6, 7–9, and 10–16 correspond to mild, moderate, and severe spasticity respectively and motor compensations were assessed with the Reaching Performance Scale for Stroke (RPSS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], which evaluated six movement components for a total score of 18. To assess the UL Activity level, the authors used the Box and Blocks test (BBT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] in which the number of blocks transferred by the more affected hand was expressed as a percentage of the number transferred by the less affected hand and the Wolf Motor Function Test (WMFT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], which assessed 15 arm function tasks. For the WMFT, results are reported as the mean Functional Abilities Scale Score and the mean time score. At the Performance level, patients completed the 30-item Motor Activity Log (MAL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], which assessed the amount (Amount of Use [AOU]) and the type (Quality of Movement [QOM]) of arm use in everyday life situations. Finally, social validity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], defined as the social acceptability of the intervention and its impact on patients, was monitored by logging patients’ comments throughout therapy. This also assessed patient satisfaction/dissatisfaction with therapy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Owing to the small sample size and heterogeneity, the authors used a single subject research design (SSRD) with baseline (pre-test 1, pre-test 2), immediate post-intervention (post-test) and follow-up (follow-up) contrasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. SSRD alone or combined with case reports and group analysis has been used previously to evaluate treatment outcomes in children and adults with motor deficits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p>Intervention effects for each clinical outcome in each patient were assessed by calculating effect sizes (ESs) obtained through standard mean differences. For single subject designs, the ES represents the proportion of points that are less than or greater than the average points in the baseline phase. The authors considered ES of &gt;0.30 to be significant and those &gt;0.50 to be large, as at this level, more than 69% of data points differ from the baseline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p>There were no differences between pre-test 1 and 2 scores for all of the outcome measures (<italic>P</italic> values of paired <italic>t</italic>-tests ranged from 0.05 to 0.905) except for the WMFT mean score in the conventional group (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.03). For these outcomes, the second pre-test scores were used as the baseline values for each test. For the WMFT mean score in the conventional group, the authors used the higher score of the two pre-tests. Between-mean differences of post-test or follow-up assessments were divided by pre-test standard deviation (SD).</p></sec></sec>NIH Clinical Trial Registration: NCT01388400.The authors certify that no party having a direct interest in the results of the research supporting this article has or will confer a benefit on us or on any organization with which we are associated and we certify that all financial and material support for this research (e.g., NIH or NHS grants) and work are clearly identified here. This work was supported by FRSQ-REPAR International Collaborative Grant, Israel Ministry of Health no. 3-00000-4227. Sheba Medical Center, Tel Hashomer, Israel, hosted the study and provided access to patients. Dr. Levin is the guarantor for this article, and takes responsibility for the integrity of the work as a whole.Conflict of InterestNone of the authors declare any conflicts of interest.Open AccessThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.References1.KwakkelGKollenBJvan der GrondJPrevoAJProbability of regaining dexterity in the flaccid upper limb: impact of severity of paresis and time since onset in acute strokeStroke2003342181218610.1161/01.STR.0000087172.16305.CD129078182.MayoNEWood-DauphineeSCoteRDurcanLCarltonJActivity, participation, and quality of life 6 months poststrokeArch Phys Med Rehabil2002831035104210.1053/apmr.2002.33984121618233.MaldonadoMAAllredRPFelthauserELJonesTAMotor skill training, but not voluntary exercise, improves skilled reaching after unilateral ischemic lesions of the sensorimotor cortex in ratsNeurorehabil Neural Repair20082225026110.1177/1545968307308551180733244.ProteauLBlandinYAlainCDorionAThe effects of the amount and variability of practice on the learning of a multi-segmented motor taskActa Psychol199485617410.1016/0001-6918(94)90020-55.WinsteinCJMeriansASSullivanKJMotor learning after unilateral brain damageNeuropsychologia19993797598710.1016/S0028-3932(98)00145-6104265216.KantakSSSullivanKJFisherBEKnowltonBJWinsteinCJNeural substrates of motor memory consolidation depend on practice structureNat Neurosci20101392392510.1038/nn.2596206228727.KwakkelGWagenaarRCKoelmanTWLankhorstGJKoetsierJCEffects of intensity of rehabilitation after stroke. A research synthesisStroke1997281550155610.1161/01.STR.28.8.155092597478.KleimJAJonesTAPrinciples of experience-dependent neural plasticity: implications for rehabilitation after brain damageJ Speech Lang Hear Res200851S225S23910.1044/1092-4388(2008/018)182308489.CirsteaCMPtitoALevinMFFeedback and cognition in arm motor skill reacquisition after strokeStroke2006371237124210.1161/01.STR.0000217417.89347.631660121810.NudoRJMillikenGWReorganization of movement representations in primary motor cortex following focal ischemic infarcts in adult squirrel monkeysJ Neurophysiol19967521442149873461011.RizzoAVirtual reality and disability: emergence and challengeDisabil Rehabil20022456756910.1080/0963828011011131512.RizzoAAKimGJA SWOT analysis of the field of VR rehabilitation and therapyPresence-TeleopVirt20051411914610.1162/105474605396709413.WeissPLRingHCommentary on virtual reality in stroke rehabilitation: still more virtual than realDisabil Rehabil2007291147114910.1080/0963828060096575914.YouSHJangSHKimYHVirtual reality-induced cortical reorganization and associated locomotor recovery in chronic stroke: an experimenter-blind randomized studyStroke2005361166117110.1161/01.STR.0000162715.43417.911589099015.HoldenMKVirtual environments for motor rehabilitation: reviewCyberpsychol Behav2005818721110.1089/cpb.2005.8.1871597197016.HendersonAKKorner-BitenskyNLevinMFVirtual reality in stroke rehabilitation: a systematic review of its effectiveness for upper limb motor recoveryTop Stroke Rehabil200714526110.1310/tsr1402-521751757517.AdamovichSVFluetGGTunikEMeriansASSensorimotor training in virtual reality: a reviewNeurorehabilitation20092529441971361718.LuccaLFVirtual reality and motor rehabilitation of the upper limb after stroke: a generation of progress?J Rehabil Med2009411003100610.2340/16501977-04051984183219.WeissPLSveistrupHRandDKizonyRVideo capture virtual reality: a decade of rehabilitation assessment and interventionPhys Ther Rev20091430732110.1179/108331909X1248866711733920.CrosbieJHLennonSBasfordJRMcDonoughSMVirtual reality in stroke rehabilitation: still more virtual than realDisabil Rehabil2007291139114610.1080/096382806009609091761300021.MumfordNWilsonPHVirtual reality in acquired brain injury upper limb rehabilitation: evidence-based evaluation of clinical researchBrain Inj20092317919110.1080/026990508026955661920595422.LaverKEGeorgeSThomasSDeutschJECrottyMVirtual reality for stroke rehabilitationCochrane Database Syst Rev.20119CD0083492190172023.SaposnikGLevinMFVirtual reality in stroke rehabilitation: a metanalysis and implications for cliniciansStroke2011421380138610.1161/STROKEAHA.110.6054512147480424.Creem-RegehSHWillemsenPGoochAAThompsonWBThe influence of restricted viewing conditions on egocentric distance perception: implications for real and virtual environmentsPerception20053419120410.1068/p51441583256925.MagdalonECMichaelsenSMQuevedoAAFLevinMFComparison of grasping movements made by healthy subjects in a 3-dimentional immersive virtual versus physical environmentActa Psychol (Amst)201113812613410.1016/j.actpsy.2011.05.0152168450526.Liebermann DG, Berman S, Weiss PL, Levin MF. Kinematics of reaching movements in a 2D virtual environment in adults with and without stroke. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehab Eng. 2012. (In press).27.KnautLASubramanianSMcFadyenBJBourbonnaisDLevinMFKinematics of pointing movements made in a virtual versus a physical 3D environment in strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil20099079380210.1016/j.apmr.2008.10.0301940629928.IOM: Institute of MedicineSmall Clinical Trials: Issues and Challenges2001WashingtonNational Academies29.JackDBoianRMeriansASVirtual reality-enhanced stroke rehabilitationIEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehab Eng2011930831810.1109/7333.94846030.FolsteinMFFolsteinSEMcHughPR“Mini-mental state”. A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinicianJ Psychiatr Res19751218919810.1016/0022-3956(75)90026-6120220431.RandDKatzNWeissPLEvaluation of virtual shopping in the VMall: comparison of post-stroke participants to healthy control groupsDisabil Rehabil2007291710171910.1080/096382806011074501785222332.World Health OrganizationICF: International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health2001GenevaWorld Health Organization33.Fugl-MeyerARJääskoLLeymanLOlssonSSteglindSThe post-stroke hemiparetic patient. I. A method for evaluation of physical performanceScand J Rehab Med19757133134.LevinMFHui-ChanCWRelief of hemiparetic spasticity by TENS is associated with improvement in reflex and voluntary motor functionsElectroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol19928513114210.1016/0168-5597(92)90079-Q137336635.LevinMFDesrosiersJBeaucheminDBergeronNRochetteADevelopment and validation of a scale for rating motor compensations used for reaching in patients with hemiparesis: the reaching performance scalePhys Ther2004848221499267336.MathiowetzVVollandGKashmanNWeberKAdult norms for the Box and Block Test of manual dexterityAm J Occup Ther19853938639110.5014/ajot.39.6.386316024337.WolfSLCatlinPAEllisMArcherALMorganBPiacentinoAAssessing Wolf motor function test as outcome measure for research in patients after strokeStroke2001321635163910.1161/01.STR.32.7.16351144121238.UswatteGTaubEMorrisDLightKThompsonPAThe Motor Activity Log-28: assessing daily use of the hemiparetic arm after strokeNeurology2006671189119410.1212/01.wnl.0000238164.90657.c21703075139.SchwartzISBaerDMSocial validity assessments: is current practice state of the art?J Appl Behav Anal19912418920410.1901/jaba.1991.24-189189004040.BarlowDHNockMKHersenMSingle case experimental designs—strategies for studying behavior change2009BostonPearson Education41.TrahanJMalouinFIntermittent intensive physiotherapy in children with cerebral palsy: a pilot studyDev Med Child Neurol20024423323910.1017/S00121622010020061199589142.SchneibergSMckinleyPSveistrupHGiselEMayoNELevinMFTask-oriented intervention and trunk restraint on upper limb movement quality in children with cerebral palsyDev Med Child Neurol201052e245e25310.1111/j.1469-8749.2010.03768.x2081301943.SaposnikGMamdaniMBayleyMThorpeKEHallJCohenLGTeasellREVREST Steering CommitteeEVREST Study Group for the Stroke Outcome Research Canada Working GroupEffectiveness of Virtual Reality Exercises in STroke Rehabilitation (EVREST): rationale, design, and protocol of a pilot randomized clinical trial assessing the Wii gaming systemInt J Stroke20105475110.1111/j.1747-4949.2009.00404.x2008899444.ScruggsTEMastropieriMASummarizing single-subject research: issues and applicationsBehav Modif19942222124210.1177/01454455980223001972247345.CampbellJMStatistical comparison of four effect sizes for single-subject designsBehav Modif20042823424610.1177/01454455032592641499795046.BinghamGPPaganoCThe necessity of a perception/action approach to definite distance perception: monocular distance perception to guide reachingJ Exp Psych Human Perc Perf19982414516810.1037/0096-1523.24.1.14547.Bernstein NA. The Co-ordination and Regulation of Movements. Chapter II. The problem of the interrelation of co-ordination and localization, Oxford: Pergamon Press; 1967:15–60.48.LevinMFKleimJFWolfSWhat do motor ‘recovery’ and ‘compensation’ mean in patients following stroke?Neurorehabil Neural Repair2009233133191911812849.SubramanianSKMassieCLMalcolmMPLevinMFDoes provision of extrinsic feedback result in improved motor learning in the upper limb poststroke? A systematic review of the evidenceNeurorehabil Neural Repair20102411312410.1177/15459683093499411986159150.Subramanian SK, Lourenco CB, Chilingaryan G, Sveistrup H, Levin MF. Arm motor recovery using virtual reality intervention in chronic stroke: randomized control trial. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2012. [Epub ahead of print]. 51.GrezesJDecetyJFunctional anatomy of execution, mental simulation, observation, and verb generation of actions: a meta-analysisHum Brain Mapp20011211910.1002/1097-0193(200101)12:1&lt;1::AID-HBM10&gt;3.0.CO;2-V1119810152.AnquetilTJeannerodMSimulated actions in the first and in the third person perspectives share common representationsBrain Res2007113012512910.1016/j.brainres.2006.10.0911717387853.NewportRBrownLHusainMMortDJacksonSRThe role of the posterior parietal lobe in prism adaptation: failure to adapt to optical prisms in patients with bilateral damage to posterior parietal cortexCortex20064272072910.1016/S0010-9452(08)70410-616909632
