<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front Hum NeurosciFront Hum NeurosciFront. Hum. Neurosci.Frontiers in Human Neuroscience1662-5161Frontiers Media S.A.426726810.3389/fnhum.2014.00993NeuroscienceReview ArticleNovel insights into the rehabilitation of memory post acquired brain injury: a systematic reviewSpreijLauriane A.1Visser-MeilyJohanna M. A.2van HeugtenCaroline M.3NijboerTanja C. W.12*1Department of Experimental Psychology, Helmholtz Institute, Utrecht UniversityUtrecht, Netherlands2Brain Center Rudolf Magnus, Center of Excellence for Rehabilitation Medicine, University Medical Center Utrecht, and De Hoogstraat RehabilitationUtrecht, Netherlands3Department of Psychiatry and Neuropsychology, Faculty of Health, Medicine and Life Sciences, Maastricht UniversityMaastricht, NetherlandsEdited by: Francesco Di Russo, University of Rome Foro Italico, ItalyReviewed by: Arun Bokde, Trinity College Dublin, Ireland; Rocco Salvatore Calabrò, IRCCS Centro Neurolesi Bobibo-Pulejo, Italy*Correspondence: Tanja C. W. Nijboer, Department Experimental Psychology, Hemholtz Institue, Utrecht University, Heidelberglaan 2, 3584 CS Utrecht, Netherlands e-mail: t.c.w.nijboer@uu.nlThis article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Human Neuroscience.0611201416122014201489930810201422112014Copyright © 2014 Spreij, Visser-Meily, van Heugten and Nijboer.2014This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Objective: Acquired Brain Injury (ABI) frequently results in memory impairment causing significant disabilities in daily life and is therefore a critical target for cognitive rehabilitation. Current understanding of brain plasticity has led to novel insights in remediation-oriented approaches for the rehabilitation of memory deficits. We will describe 3 of these approaches that have emerged in the last decade: Virtual Reality (VR) training, Computer-Based Cognitive Retraining (CBCR) and Non-Invasive Brain Stimulation (NBS) and evaluate its effectiveness.Methods: A systematic literature search was completed in regard to studies evaluating interventions aiming to improve the memory function after ABI. Information concerning study content and reported effectiveness were extracted. Quality of the studies and methods were evaluated.Results: A total of 786 studies were identified, 15 studies met the inclusion criteria. Three of those studies represent the VR technique, 7 studies represent CBCR and 5 studies NBS. All 3 studies found a significant improvement of the memory function after VR-based training, however these studies are considered preliminary. All 7 studies have shown that CBCR can be effective in improving memory function in patients suffering from ABI. Four studies of the 5 did not find significant improvement of the memory function after the use of NBS in ABI patients.Conclusion: On the basis of this review, CBCR is considered the most promising novel approach of the last decade because of the positive results in improving memory function post ABI. The number of studies representing VR were limited and the methodological quality low, therefore the results should be considered preliminary. The studies representing NBS did not detect evidence for the use of NBS in improving memory function.acquired brain injurymemoryremediation-oriented techniquevirtual realitycomputer-based cognitive retrainingnon-invasive brain stimulation<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Search method and article selection</title><p>A systematic literature search was performed using PubMed and Web of Science for studies published between January 2004 and August 2014 using the terms <italic>Acquired Brain Injury, (Traumatic) Brain Injury</italic> or <italic>Stroke</italic> in combination with <italic>Virtual Reality, Computer-based Cognitive Retraining, Computerized Training, Non-Invasive Brain Stimulation, Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation, repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</italic>, or <italic>transcranial Direct Current Stimulation</italic> as well as <italic>Memory</italic>. The search in PubMed was limited in the following features: publication date (published in the last 10 years), species (human), adults (≥19 years of age), and language (English). Likewise, the search in Web of Science was limited in the following features: language (English) and time span (2004 to 2014).</p><p>Intervention studies for improving memory function after ABI were selected when they met the following inclusion criteria: (1) individuals experiencing memory deficits resulting from ABI as confirmed by neurological examination; (2) ≥18 years of age; (3) studies using specific measurements of memory functioning consisting of objective measures of memory function using standardized memory tests or batteries; and (4) had a study design with at least a pre and post intervention measurement. Memory treatment was considered any cognitive intervention attempting to improve memory, with neuropsychological tests as outcome measures. Studies published in languages other than English were excluded.</p><p>The first author (L.A.S.) conducted the search and screened the titles and abstracts, followed by an exclusion of duplicates. From screen-positive abstracts, full-text articles were collected when available and evaluated. In case the first author had doubt about inclusion of an article, the other authors were consulted. Articles meeting the aforesaid criteria were included in the final selection. The final selection was checked by the other authors as well.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction</title><p>After the final selection, data extraction was performed by the first author (L.A.S.) and was based on data extraction methods from similar reviews (Schrijnemaekers et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In case of doubt about which data to be extracted, the other authors were consulted. The following <italic>study characteristics</italic> were extracted from the articles: authors, design of the study, number of patients, outcome measures, <italic>p</italic>-value, and timing of measurements. The following <italic>intervention characteristics</italic> were extracted from the articles: aim of intervention, type of intervention, duration and intensity. The following <italic>patient characteristics</italic> were extracted from the articles: diagnostic criteria and severity, age, and time after onset. Results were considered to be positive when statistically significant at the <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 level.</p></sec><sec><title>Quality assessment</title><p>Two authors (L.A.S. and T.C.W.N.) independently appraised the characteristics and the quality of the selected studies. The methodological quality was evaluated based on the following elements: (1) randomization of intervention or different condition, (2) comparison of an experimental group and a control group that received either an alternative form of treatment or no memory intervention, (3) blinding of participants, (4) blinding of researchers, (5) reporting completeness of follow-up (Tijssen and Assendelft, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). We added 3 relevant elements to evaluate the methodological quality: (6) group size (≥10 per group), (7) reporting effect size, and (8) reporting time post-ABI. We consider it important to report the time between the injury onset and the start of the intervention, to facilitate a comparison of the effect and to gain insights into the phase in which the patients were at time of the intervention (sub-acute phase vs. chronic phase). This 8-point checklist yielded a total score between 0 and 8. Each study were giving a total score and consequently divided into high (total scores ≥6), moderate (≥3 and ≤6), and low (≤3) quality studies (Schrijnemaekers et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Additionally, a distinction was made between effectiveness studies and feasibility studies for the interpretation of the results of each study.</p></sec></sec>Author contributionsConception and design of the work: Lauriane A. Spreij, Johanna M. A. Visser-Meily, Caroline M. van Heugten, Tanja C. W. Nijboer. Acquisition of data: Lauriane A. Spreij. Analysis of data: Lauriane A. Spreij, Tanja C. W. Nijboer. Interpretation of data: Lauriane A. Spreij, Tanja C. W. Nijboer. Drafting and revising the work: Lauriane A. Spreij, Johanna M. A. Visser-Meily, Caroline M. van Heugten, Tanja C. W. Nijboer. Final approval of the version to be published: Lauriane A. Spreij, Johanna M. A. Visser-Meily, Caroline M. van Heugten, Tanja C. W. Nijboer. Agreement to be accountable for all aspects of the work: Lauriane A. Spreij, Johanna M. A. Visser-Meily, Caroline M. van Heugten, Tanja C. W. Nijboer.Conflict of interest statementThe authors alone are responsible for the content and writing of this review. The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.Tanja C. W. Nijboer is supported by the NWO (Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research; grant 451-10-013).ReferencesAbenL.Heijenbrok-KalM. H.van LoonE. M. P.GroetE.PondsR. W. H. M.BusschbachJ. J. V.. (2013). Training memory self-efficacy in the chronic stage after stroke: a randomized controlled trial. Neurorehabil. Neural Repair27, 110–117. 10.1177/154596831245522222895620ÅkerlundE.EsbjörnssonE.SunnerhagenK. S.BjörkdahlA. (2013). Can computerized working memory training improve impaired working memory, cognition, and psychological health?
Brain Inj. 27, 13–14. 10.3109/02699052.2013.83019524087909BjörkdahlA.ÅkerlundE.SvenssonS.EsbjörnssonE. (2013). A randomized study computerized working memory training and effects on functioning in everyday life for patients with brain injury. Brain Inj. 27, 1658–1665. 10.3109/02699052.2013.83019624131298BrooksB. M.RoseF. D. (2003). The use of virtual reality in memory rehabilitation: current findings and future directions. Neurorehabilitation
18, 147–157. 12867677BrooksB. M.RoseF. D.PotterJ.JayawardenaS.MorlingA. (2004). Assessing stroke patients'prospective memory using virtual reality. Brain Inj. 18, 391–401. 10.1080/0269905031000161985514742152BrunoniA. R.VanderhasseltM.-A. (2014). Working memory improvement with non-invasive brain stimulation of the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Brain Cogn. 86, 1–9. 10.1016/j.bandc.2014.01.00824514153CaglioM.Latini-CorazziniL.D'AgataF.CaudaF.SaccoK.MonteverdiS.. (2012). Virtual navigation for memory rehabilitation in a traumatic brain injured patient. Neurocase
18, 123–131. 10.1080/13554794.2011.56849922352998CappaS. F.BenkeT.ClarkeS.RossiB.StemmerB.van HeugtenC. M. (2011). Cognitive rehabilitation. Euro. Handb. Neurol. Manag. 1, 545–567
10.1002/9781444328394.ch40CiceroneK. D.LangenbahnD. M.BradenC.MalecJ. F.KalmarK.FraasM.. (2011). Evidence-based cognitive rehabilitation: updated review of the literature from 2003 through 2008. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehab. 92, 519–530. 10.1016/j.apmr.2010.11.01521440699CramerS. C. (2008). Repairing the human brain after stroke: 1. Mechanisms of spontaneous recovery. Ann. Neurol. 63, 272–287. 10.1002/ana.2139318383072Das NairR.LincolnN. (2007). Cognitive rehabilitation for memory deficits following stroke. Cochrane Database of Syst. Rev. 3, 1–15. 10.1002/14651858.CD002293.pub217636703De LucaR.CalabròR. S.GervasiG.De SalvoS.BonannoL.CoralloF.. (2014). Is computer-assisted training effective in improving rehabilitative outcomes after brain injury? A case-control hospital-based study. Disabil. Health J. 7, 356–360. 10.1016/j.dhjo.2014.04.00324947578FasottiL.van KesselM. (2013). Novel insights in the rehabilitation of neglect. Front. Hum. Neurosci. 7:780. 10.3389/fnhum.2013.0078024298249FishJ.ManlyT.EmslieH.EvansJ. J.WilsonB. A. (2008). Compensatory strategies for acquired disorders of memory and planning: differential effects of a paging system for patients with brain injury of traumatic versus cerebrovascular aetiology. J. Neurol. Neurosurg. Psychiatry
79, 930–935. 10.1136/jnnp.2007.12520318039889HallR. C. W.HallR. C. W.CapmanM. J. (2005). Definition, diagnosis, and forensic implications of postconcussional syndrome. Psychosomatics
43, 195–202. 10.1176/appi.psy.46.3.19515883140HolmqvistK.KamwendoK.IvarssonA. B. (2009). Occupational therapists' descriptions of their work with persons suffering from cognitive impairment following acquired brain injury. Scand. J. Occup. Ther. 16, 13–24. 10.1080/1103812080212352018609240JoJ. M.KimM. H.OhnS. H.JoenB.LeeK. H. (2009). Enhancing the working memory of stroke patients using tDCS. Am. J. Psys. Med. Rehabil. 88, 404–409. 10.1097/PHM.0b013e3181a0e4cb19620953JohanssonB. B. (2011). Current trends in stroke rehabilitation: a review with focus on Brain Plasticity. Acta Neurol. Scand. 123, 147–159. 10.1111/j.1600-0404.2010.01417.x20726844JohanssonB. B.TornmalmM. (2012). Working memory training for patients with acquired brain injury: effects in daily life. Scand. J. Occup. Ther. 19, 176–183. 10.3109/11038128.2011.60335221843045KesselsR. P. C.d'AlfonsoA. A. L.PostmaA.de HaanE. H. F. (2000). Spatial working memory performance after high-frequency repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation of the left and right posterior parietal cortex in humans. Neurosci. Lett. 287, 68–70. 10.1016/S0304-3940(00)01146-010841993KimB. R.KimD. Y.ChunM. H.YiJ. H.KwonJ. S. (2010). Effect of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation on cognition and mood in stroke patients: a double-blind, sham-controlled trial. Am. J. Phys. Med. Rehabil. 89, 362–368. 10.1097/PHM.0b013e3181d8a5b120407301KimberleyT.SamargiaS.MooreL.ShakyaJ. K.LangC. E. (2010). Comparison of amounts and types of practice during rehabilitation for traumatic brain injury and stroke. J. Rehabil. Res. Dev. 47, 851–861. 10.1682/JRRD.2010.02.001921174250KlingbergT. (2010). Training and plasticity of working memory. Trends Cogn. Sci. 14, 317–324. 10.1016/j.tics.2010.05.00220630350LeśniakM.PolanowskaK.SeniówJ.CzłonkowskaA. (2014). Effects of repeated anodal tDCS coupled with cognitive training for patients with severe traumatic brain injury: a pilot randomized controlled trial. J. Head Trauma Rehabil. 29, 20–29. 10.1097/HTR.0b013e318292a4c223756431LevineB.FugiwaraE.O'ConnorC.RichardN.KovacevicN.MandicM.. (2006). In vivo characterization of traumatic brain injury neuropathology with structural and functional neuroimaging. J. Neurotrauma
23, 1396–1441. 10.1089/neu.2006.23.139617020478LiK.RobertsonJ.RamosJ.GellaS. (2013). Computer-based cognitive retraining for adults with chronic acquired brain injury: a pilot study. Occup. Ther. Health Care
27, 333–344. 10.3109/07380577.2013.84487724102589LimJ. Y.KangE. K.PaikN. J. (2010). Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation to hemispatial neglect in patients after stroke: an open-label pilot study. J. Rehabil. Med. 42, 447–452. 10.2340/16501977-055320544155LuberB.KinnunenL. H.RakitinB. C.EllsasserR.SternY.LisanbyS. H. (2007). Facilitation of performance in a working memory task with rTMS stimulation of the precuneus: frequency- and time-dependent effects. Brain Res. 1128, 120–129. 10.1016/j.brainres.2006.10.01117113573LundqvistA.GrundströmK.SamuelssonK.RönnbergJ. (2010). Computerized training of working memory in a group of patients suffering from acquired brain injury. Brain Inj. 24, 1173–1183. 10.3109/02699052.2010.49800720715888MiniussiC.CappaS. F.CoohenL.FloelA.FregniF.NitschM. A.. (2008). Efficacy of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation/transcrianial direct current stimulation in cognitive neurorehabilitation. Brain Stimul. 1, 326–336. 10.1016/j.brs.2008.07.00220633391NaeserM. A.MartinP. I.NicholasM.BakerE. H.SeekinsH.KobayashiM.. (2005). Improved picture naming in chronic aphasia after TMS to part of right Broca's area: an open protocol study. Brain Lang. 93, 95–105. 10.1016/j.bandl.2004.08.00415766771NyffelerT.CazzoliD.HessC. W.MuriR. M. (2009). One session of repeated parietal theta burst stimulation trains induces long-lasting improvement of visual neglect. Stroke
40, 2791–2796. 10.1161/STROKEAHA.109.55232319520986OlesenP. J.WesterbergH.KlingbergT. (2004). Increased prefrontal and parietal activity after training of working memory. Nat. Neurosci. 7, 75–79. 10.1038/nn116514699419OliveriM.TurrizianiP.CarlesimoG. A.KochG.TomaiuoloF.PanellaM.. (2001). Parieto-frontal interactions in visual-object and visual–spatial working memory: evidence from transcranial magnetic stimulation. Cereb. Cortex
11, 606–618. 10.1093/cercor/11.7.60611415963OptaleG.UrgesiC.BusatoV.PironL.PriftisK.GamberiniL.. (2009). Controlling memory impairment in elderly adults using virtual reality memory training; a randomized controlled pilot study. Neurorehabil. Neural Repair
24, 348–357. 10.1177/154596830935332819934445ParkS.-H.KohE.-J.ChoiH.-Y.KoM.-H. (2013). A double-blind, sham-controlled, pilot study to assess the effects of the concomitant use of transcranial direct current stimulation with the computer assisted cognitive rehabilitation to the prefrontal cortex on cognitive functions in patients with stroke. J. Korean Neurosurg. Soc. 54, 484–488. 10.3340/jkns.2013.54.6.48424527190ParkS. H.SeoJ. H.KimY.KoM. H. (2014). Long-term effects of transcranial direct current stimulation combined with computer-assisted cognitive training in healthy older adults. Neuroreport
25, 122–126. 10.1097/WNR.000000000000008024176927PrestonG.AndersonE.SilvaC.GoldbergT.WassermannE. M. (2010). Effects of 10 Hz rTMS on the neural efficiency of working memory. J. Cogn. Neurosci. 22, 447–456. 10.1162/jocn.2009.2120919309294ReesL.MarshallS.HartridgeC.MackieD.WeiserM. (2007). Cognitive interventions post acquired brain injury. Brain Inj. 21, 161–200. 10.1080/0269905070120181317364530SchrijnemaekersA.-C.SmeetsS. M. J.PondsR. W. H.van HeugtenC.RasquinS. (2013). Treatment of unawareness of dificits in patients with acquired brain injury: a systematic review. J. Head Trauma Rehabil. 29, 1–21. 10.1097/01.HTR.0000438117.63852.b424263179SnaphaanL.de LeeuwF.-E. (2007). Poststroke memory function in non-demented patients: a systematic review on frequency and neuroimaging correlates. Stroke
38, 198–201. 10.1161/01.STR.0000251842.34322.8f17158333SzaflarskiJ. P.VannestJ.WuS. W.DiFrancescoM. W.BanksC.GilbertD. L. (2011). Excitatory repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation induces improvements in chronic post-stroke aphasia. Med. Sci. Monit. 17, 132–139. 10.12659/MSM.88144621358599TijssenJ. G. P.AssendelftW. J. J. (2003). Beoordeling van een gerandomiseerd effectonderzoek, in Inleiding in Evidence-Based Medicine, eds OffringaM.AssendelftW. J. J.ScholtenR. J. P. M. (Houten: Bohn Stafleu van Loghum), 56–70.UlamF.SheltonC.RichardsL.DavisL.HunterB.FregniF.. (2014). Cumulative effects of transcranial direct current stimulation on EEG oscillations and attention/working memory during subacute neurorehabilitation of traumatic brain injury. Clin. Neurophysiol. [Epub ahead of print]. 10.1016/j.clinph.2014.05.01524947595VillamarM. F.PortillaA. S. P.FregniF.ZafonteR. (2012). Nonivasive Brain stimulation to modulate neuroplasticity in traumatic brain injury. Neuromodulation
15, 326–338. 10.1111/j.1525-1403.2012.00474.x22882244WesterbergH.JacobaeusH.HirvikoskiT.ClevbergerP.OstenssonM.-L.BartfaiA.. (2007). Computerized working memory training after stroke – a pilot study. Brain Inj. 21, 21–29. 10.1080/0269905060114872617364516YipB. C. B.ManD. W. K. (2009). Virtual reality-based prospective memory training program for people with acquired brain injury. Neurorehabilitation
32, 103–115. 10.3233/NRE-13082723422463YipB. C. B.ManD. W. K. (2013). Virtual reality (VR)-based community living skills training for people with acquired brain injury: a pilot study, Brain Inj. 23, 1017–1026. 10.3109/0269905090337941219891532YouS. H.JangS. H.KimY. H.HallettM.AhnS. H.KwonY. H.. (2005). Virtual Reality-induced cortical reorganization and associated locomotor recovery in chronic stroke: an experimenter-blind randomized study. Stroke
36, 1166–1171. 10.1161/01.STR.0000162715.43417.9115890990AbbreviationsABIAcquired Brain InjuryTBITraumatic Brain InjuryWMWorking MemoryVRVirtual RealityCBCRComputer-Based Cognitive RetrainingNBSNon-Invasive Brain StimulationTMSTranscranial Magnetic StimulationrTMSrepetitive Transcranial Magnetic StimulationtDCStranscranial Direct Current Stimulation.
