<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Neurology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5124305</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">754</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12883-016-0754-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Guidelines for dementia or Parkinson&#x02019;s disease with depression or anxiety: a systematic review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Goodarzi</surname><given-names>Zahra</given-names></name><address><phone>403-944-3277</phone><email>zahra.goodarzi@albertahealthservices.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mele</surname><given-names>Bria</given-names></name><address><email>Bria.mele@ucalgary.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Selynne</given-names></name><address><email>s.guo@mail.utoronto.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>Heather</given-names></name><address><email>heather.hanson@ahs.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jette</surname><given-names>Nathalie</given-names></name><address><email>nathalie.jette@ahs.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>Scott</given-names></name><address><email>patten@ucalgary.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pringsheim</surname><given-names>Tamara</given-names></name><address><email>tmprings@ucalgary.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holroyd-Leduc</surname><given-names>Jayna</given-names></name><address><email>jayna.holroyd@ahs.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Community Health Sciences, University of Calgary, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Medicine, University of Calgary and Alberta Health Services, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Faculty of Medicine, Undergraduate Medical Education, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Seniors Health Strategic Clinical Network, Alberta Health Services, Alberta, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Clinical Neurosciences, University of Calgary, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Hotchkiss Brain Institute, and O&#x02019;Brien Institute for Public Health, University of Calgary and Alberta Health Services, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Psychiatry and Pediatrics, University of Calgary and Alberta Health Services, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Psychiatry, University of Calgary and Alberta Health Services, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label>Mathison Centre for Mental Health Research and Education, University of Calgary, Calgary, Canada </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label>10</label>#1104-South Tower. Foothills Medical Centre 3301 Hospital Drive, Calgary, NW T2N 2T9 Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>244</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Depression and anxiety remain under-diagnosed and under-treated in those with neurologic diseases such as dementia or Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease (PD). Our objectives were to first, to provide a synthesis of high quality guidelines available for the identification and management of depression or anxiety in those with dementia or PD. Second, to identify areas for improvement for future guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We searched MEDLINE, PsycINFO, and EMBASE (2009 to July 24, 2015), grey literature (83 sources; July 24-Sept 6, 2015), and bibliographies of included studies. Included studies were evaluated for quality by four independent reviewers the AGREE II tool. Guideline characteristics, statements and recommendations relevant to depression or anxiety for dementia and PD were then extracted. (PROSPERO CRD: 42016014584)</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>8121 citations were reviewed with 31 full text articles included for assessment with the AGREE II tool. 17 were of sufficient quality for inclusion. Mean overall quality scores were between 4.25 to 6.5. Domain scores were lowest in the areas of stakeholder involvement, applicability, and editorial independence.</p><p>Recommendations for the screening and diagnosis of depression were found for PD and dementia. There was little evidence to guide diagnosis or management of anxiety. Non-pharmacologic therapies were recommended for dementia patients. Most advocated pharmacologic treatment for depression, for both PD and dementia, but did not specify an agent due to lack of evidence.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The available recent high quality guidelines outline several recommendations for the management of comorbid depression or anxiety in PD or dementia. However there remain significant gaps in the evidence.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12883-016-0754-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease</kwd><kwd>Dementia</kwd><kwd>Depression</kwd><kwd>Anxiety</kwd><kwd>Guidelines</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000145</institution-id><institution>Alberta Innovates - Health Solutions</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>201400559</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Holroyd-Leduc</surname><given-names>Jayna</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Persons experiencing neurologic disorders, such as dementia or Parkinson&#x02019;s disease (PD), and depressive or anxiety disorders have poorer outcomes with reduced quality of life, poor functional status and worsened cognition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p>It is estimated that the prevalence of depression in dementia is approximately 25% with anxiety occurring in up to 75% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In PD, approximately 17% of patients experience major depression and anxiety between 3.6 to 40% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p>Despite awareness of these comorbidities, depression and anxiety remain under-diagnosed and under-treated in those with neurologic diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Only 20% of PD patients diagnosed with depression receive therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. This represents a significant knowledge-to-practice gap. One way to address this is through the use of Clinical Practice Guidelines (CPGs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. CPGs synthesize available evidence based on a systematic review of the literature, clinical expertise and patient preferences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. CPGs are targeted at practitioners who apply the recommendations to clinical decision-making and reduce disparities in care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p>Thus, in the setting of PD and dementia, CPGs should enable the appropriate management of depression and anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Despite available CPGs, these disorders remain under-managed, suggesting these CPGs are underused or lack sufficient recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Multiple available guidelines of varied quality leads to uncertainty as to which CPGs should be used in practice. Our primary aim is to synthesize the high-quality evidence-based CPGs available for diagnosis, and management of depression or anxiety in those with dementia or PD. We chose to summarize and evaluate guidelines as the majority of physicians will use CPGs as a tool to review evidence and inform practice. Secondarily we aim to, identify areas gaps within the existing guidelines to inform future guideline development. This provides a broad over view of evidence in the area and identifies areas for further study and development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>The study protocol follows the recommendations provided by the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA)&#x02014;Protocols Statement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] and guidelines and the protocol was registered with PROSPERO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] (CRD: 42016014584).</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Search strategy</title><p>The literature search was developed in conjunction with an experienced librarian (DL) and was verified independently by a second librarian (HLR), using the Peer Review of Electronic Search Strategies (PRESS) methodology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Any recommendations were incorporated into the final search.</p><p>Databases included MEDLINE, EMBASE, and PsycINFO. Clusters of terms (controlled vocabulary and key words) were used to search each database; these include dementia, Parkinson&#x02019;s disease, depression, anxiety and CPGs (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Box S1). The search was completed by cluster, first searching the terms in each cluster (combined with the Boolean operator &#x02018;OR&#x02019;) and keyword searches of abstracts and titles. The clusters were then combined with &#x02018;AND&#x02019;. We searched for several pathological variants of dementia including Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, vascular, frontotemporal, Lewy Body disease, Huntington&#x02019;s Disease, CADASIL, primary progressive aphasia, and Creutzfeldt Jakob (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Box S1). We included relevant derivatives of terms or broad key words related to depressive or anxiety disorders (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Box S1).</p><p>This was augmented by a search of the grey literature (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). This search was limited from 2009 to search date, such that we would only capture CPGs developed within the past 5&#x000a0;years; given the evidence that CPGs may become out of date after only 3&#x000a0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. All languages were included in this search.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Selection &#x00026; eligibility</title><p>All citations were reviewed for eligibility by two independent authors; citations meeting initial eligibility criteria were included in full text review. If there was disagreement at the abstract stage, the full article was pulled for review. Bibliographies for all included articles were searched. If multiple CPGs were identified from a single agency on the same topic the most recent was used.</p><p>At the first stage of abstract review, any article that represented a guideline for PD or dementia was included. Eligibility at the full text stage required that the CPGs included at least one recommendation related to depression and/or anxiety in patients with PD and/or dementia. The kappa statistic was used to quantify inter-rater reliability.</p><p>For non-English articles that met eligibility at the full text stage, the language was determined using online translation software. Citations were translated using the online (Google translate) function to determine if an article was a guideline. When included, the documents were searched using translated relevant terms; for example, if a guideline pertained to PD in the abstract, the text was searched for depression or anxiety (and all translated synonyms). If those criteria were met, the full guideline was translated and reviewed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Assessment of quality</title><p>The Appraisal of Guidelines Research &#x00026; Evaluation (AGREE II) tool was used to assess guideline quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This tool was designed to evaluate guideline quality and to aid in guideline development and reporting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The tool includes 6 domains covering scope and purpose, stakeholder involvement, rigour of development, clarity of presentation, applicability and editorial independence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Within each domain there are between 2 to 8 questions, to a total of 23 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Each item is rated from 1 (not included or very poorly reported) to 7 (exceptional reporting of all criteria outlined in the AGREE II Manual) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p>Each domain was scored independently by four reviewers, along with the assignment of an overall score. An initial assessment of 5 citations was done and compared across all 4 reviewers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The 4 reviewers met to discuss discrepancies and address questions about rating, before the remainder of the guidelines were reviewed and scored. This also served to ensure that all raters were aligned in their understanding of the AGREE II items. Any further discrepancies were resolved by discussion.</p><p>Domain scores pooled across the 4 assessors were calculated, as outlined in the AGREE II user manual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The higher score indicates a higher quality across rated items. It has been demonstrated that the quality across the AGREE II domains predicts guideline implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The mean overall quality scores with standard deviations (SD) were calculated, as well as for each domain item. CPGs with a mean overall quality score 5 or greater were assigned at least moderate quality and included in further analysis. CPGs with a score below 3 were excluded due to low quality. A score less than 5 but greater than 3 were re-evaluated and inclusion status was decided by consensus.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data extraction &#x00026; synthesis of evidence</title><p>Guideline characteristics were extracted by one author (ZG) and independently verified by a second author (BM). Items extracted included the primary conditions covered, region/organizations, number of committee members, numbers of references, and sources of funding.</p><p>Two independent reviewers then extracted relevant recommendations (ZG, BM). Specifically, guidelines were searched for any mention of relevant recommendations and supporting text or statements. Three authors reviewed the extracted recommendations (ZG, BM and JHL). Recommendations were compiled across the guidelines into relevant categories and subcategories, and reported using descriptive statistics including the quality, number of guidelines supporting the statement and subpopulations included. As the evidence in the guidelines is represented by practice recommendations, it was not amenable to meta-analysis. The main output of this systematic review was an appraisal of the quality of all guidelines pertaining to comorbid depression or anxiety in PD or dementia, and a synthesis of the recommendations across the different guidelines. Data were analyzed using STATA 13.1 (Stata Corp. College Station, TX).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Study selection</title><p>The database search generated 4441 citations after duplicates were removed, with a further 3681 citations identified from the grey literature (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). When screened for eligibility, 360 citations met criteria for full text review (&#x003ba;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.88, 95.7% agreement). At this stage most articles were excluded because they were not relevant (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;218), were not guidelines, or were unrelated guidelines. Other common reasons for exclusion at the full text stage were being out of the date range (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;33) or a duplicate (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;35). Excluded citations also included 26 mental health guidelines that did not address PD or dementia. Similarly there were 5 PD and 9 dementia guidelines that did not address depression or anxiety. The dementia guidelines primarily pertained to Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, vascular dementia, general dementia care and one referred to Lewy Body Disease. Of these articles, 4 were identified to be summary documents of included guidelines and were used as supplemental material to these included guidelines. Twenty-six CPGs met all eligibility criteria and were evaluated using the AGREE II tool, of which 17 met the quality cut off for inclusion.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA Flow Diagram</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2016_754_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Guideline characteristics</title><p>The 17 included guidelines addressed PD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5), dementia (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) and mental health (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) CPGs (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). They included recommendations from many regions, including Canada (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), USA (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3), Pan-European (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4), UK (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), Scotland (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1), Spain (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), South Korea (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) and international (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2). The associations or organizations are outlined in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. All guidelines used a method for grading the evidence (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S1). Most guidelines were funded through government or non-commercial funding; only two CPGs had some pharmaceutical funding.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Guideline Characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Author (year)</th><th>Organiz-ation</th><th>Primary condition<sup>a</sup>
</th><th>Focus</th><th>Region of origin</th><th># of Committee members<sup>i</sup>
</th><th>#of Refs</th><th>Systematic search (Y/N)</th><th>Grading of evidence (Y/N)</th><th>Funding (NS, P, NC, G)<sup>j</sup>
</th><th>Mean quality score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Zesiewicz et al<italic>.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>The American Academy of Neurology (AAN)</td><td>PD</td><td>Treatment</td><td>USA</td><td>9</td><td>40</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>4.5</td></tr><tr><td>No Author (2010)<sup>b</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td>Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN)</td><td>PD</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>Scotland</td><td>20</td><td>189</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>G</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Grimes et al<italic>.</italic> (2012)<sup>c</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>Canadian Neurological Sciences Federation (CNSF) &#x00026; Parkinson Society Canada</td><td>PD</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>Canada</td><td>22</td><td>62</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC &#x00026; P</td><td>6.5</td></tr><tr><td>Berardelli et al<italic>.</italic> (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td>European Federation of Neurological Societies &#x00026; Movement Disorder Society&#x02014;European Section (EFNS-MDS-ES)</td><td>PD</td><td>Diagnosis</td><td>Europe</td><td>25</td><td>245</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NS <sup>h</sup>
</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Ferreira et al<italic>.</italic> (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td>European Federation of Neurological Societies &#x00026; Movement Disorder Society&#x02014;European Section (EFNS-MDS-ES)</td><td>PD</td><td>Treatment</td><td>Europe</td><td>22</td><td>363</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>4.5</td></tr><tr><td>Hort et al<italic>.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>Europe</td><td>8</td><td>100</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>4.25</td></tr><tr><td>No Author (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td><td>Ministry of Health, Social Services and Equality &#x00026; Agency for Health Quality and Assessment of Catalonia (AIAQS)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>Spain</td><td>67</td><td>688</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC &#x00026; G</td><td>5.75</td></tr><tr><td>No Author (2011)<sup>d</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>National Institute for Health and Care Excellence, National Collaborating Centre for Mental Health, British Psychological Society &#x00026; The Royal College of Psychiatrists (NICE)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Diagnosis &#x00026; Treatment</td><td>UK</td><td>28</td><td>NN<sup>h</sup>
</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC &#x00026; G</td><td>6.5</td></tr><tr><td>Ihl et al<italic>.</italic> (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td><td>World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry (WFSBP)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Treatment</td><td>International</td><td>39</td><td>215<sup>f</sup>
</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>4.5</td></tr><tr><td>No Author (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>Clinical Research Centre for Dementia (CRCD)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Diagnosis</td><td>South Korea</td><td>20</td><td>NN<sup>h</sup>
</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>G</td><td>5.25</td></tr><tr><td>O&#x02019;Brien et al<italic>.</italic> (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]</td><td>British Association of Psychopharmacology (BPA)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Treatment</td><td>UK</td><td>16</td><td>148<sup>f</sup>
</td><td>N</td><td>Y</td><td>NC &#x00026; P</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Sorbi et al<italic>.</italic> (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td><td>European Federation of Neurological Societies &#x00026; European Neurological Society (EFNS-ES)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>Europe</td><td>17</td><td>189</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>4.5</td></tr><tr><td>Gauthier et al (2012)<sup>e</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td><td>Canadian Consensus Conference on the Diagnosis and Treatment of Dementia (CCCDTD4)</td><td>Dementia</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>Canada</td><td>38</td><td>19</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>5.5</td></tr><tr><td>Gelenberg et al<italic>.</italic> (2010)<sup>g</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td>American Psychiatric Association (APA)</td><td>Depression</td><td>Treatment</td><td>USA</td><td>7</td><td>1170</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>4.75</td></tr><tr><td>Dua et al<italic>.</italic> (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td>World Health Organization (WHO)</td><td>Mental Health</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>International</td><td>29</td><td>36</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC &#x00026; G</td><td>5.5</td></tr><tr><td>No Author (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td><td>Ministry of Health, Social Services and Equality &#x00026; Galician Health Technology Assessment Agency (Availia-T)</td><td>Suicide</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>Spain</td><td>24</td><td>683</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC &#x00026; G</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Mitchell et al<italic>.</italic> (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>Institute for Clinical Systems Improvement (ICSI)</td><td>Depression</td><td>Diagnosis Treatment</td><td>USA</td><td>14</td><td>331</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td>NC</td><td>5.75</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup> Dementia guidelines primarily included Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, vascular dementia, general dementia care and one referred to Lewy Body Disease</p><p>
<sup>b</sup> Includes Grosset et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]</p><p>
<sup>c</sup> Includes Patel et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]</p><p>
<sup>d</sup> Originally created in 2007 and updated in 2011</p><p>
<sup>e</sup> Includes Moore et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], Herrman et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]</p><p>
<sup>f</sup> Number counted from the text</p><p>
<sup>g</sup> Includes Recommendations Referenced in Rabin et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]</p><p>
<sup>h</sup> NS: Not Stated, NN: Not Numbered</p><p>
<sup>i</sup> Committee members&#x02014;extracted from paper as listed (e.g. authors listed, guideline development/working groups etc.)</p><p>
<sup>j</sup> NC: Non-Commercial, G: Government, Pharmaceutical, NS: Not Stated</p><p>References: The American Academy of Neurology (AAN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], Canadian Neurological Sciences Federation (CNSF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], Parkinson&#x02019;s Society Canada [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], European Federation of Neurological Societies (EFNS) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], Movement Disorders Society-European Section (MDS-ES) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], Ministry of Health, Social Services and Equality &#x00026; Agency for Health Quality and Assessment of Catalonia (AIAQS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], British Psychological Society [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], The Royal College of Psychiatrists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry (WFSBP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], Clinical Research Centre for Dementia (CRCD), British Association of Psychopharmacology (BPA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], European Neurological Society, Canadian Consensus Conference on the Diagnosis and Treatment of Dementia (CCCDTD4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], American Psychiatric Association (APA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], World Health Organization (WHO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], Ministry of Health, Social Services and Equality &#x00026; Galician Health Technology Assessment Agency (Availia-T) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] and the Institute for Clinical Systems Improvement (ICSI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Study quality</title><p>These 26 CPGs were assessed for quality using all 23 items across the 6 domains of the AGREE II tool. Nine guidelines were excluded for low quality. Six were excluded with an overall mean rating ranging from 2.25 to 3.75. Three had ratings of 4&#x02013;4.5, where decision to exclude was by consensus. A low rating was typically due to unclear methods; thus scoring low on rigour of development, applicability and editorial independence. Authors of guidelines were contacted for more information in the case that an item was unclear and responses were incorporated in the quality assessment.</p><p>The 17 included guidelines had mean overall scores from 4 to 6.5 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). When examining the individual domain scores, the highest rated domain was Domain 4: Clarity of Presentation (mean score 77.0; SD 11.4). This was followed by Domain 1: Scope and Purpose (mean score 72.1; SD 12.1). Domain 5: Applicability was the lowest rated domain (mean score 41.5; SD 22.6). Stakeholder involvement (Domain 2) also had a low score (mean score 54.5; SD 23.3).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Domain scores from AGREE II evaluation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Guideline (year)</th><th>Domain 1 score scope &#x00026; purpose</th><th>Domain 2 score stakeholder involvement</th><th>Domain 3 score rigour of development</th><th>Domain 4 score clarity of presentation</th><th>Domain 5 score applicability</th><th>Domain 6 score editorial independence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7">Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Zesiewicz et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>56.9</td><td>29.2</td><td>64.6</td><td>72.2</td><td>17.7</td><td>79.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;SIGN (2010)<sup>a</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td>80.6</td><td>80.6</td><td>72.9</td><td>91.7</td><td>72.9</td><td>22.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Grimes et al<italic>.</italic> (2012)<sup>c</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>70.8</td><td>95.8</td><td>90.6</td><td>87.5</td><td>60.4</td><td>58.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Berardelli et al. (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td>72.2</td><td>19.4</td><td>47.9</td><td>86.1</td><td>12.5</td><td>6.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Ferreira et al<italic>.</italic> (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td>47.2</td><td>15.3</td><td>43.2</td><td>66.7</td><td>6.25</td><td>20.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7">Dementia</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;NICE (2011)<sup>b</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>83.3</td><td>81.9</td><td>86.5</td><td>87.5</td><td>64.6</td><td>47.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Hort et al<italic>.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>58.3</td><td>38.9</td><td>54.2</td><td>66.7</td><td>25.0</td><td>62.5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td><td>87.5</td><td>69.4</td><td>73.4</td><td>84.7</td><td>57.3</td><td>79.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Ihl et al<italic>.</italic> (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td><td>68.1</td><td>38.9</td><td>57.8</td><td>48.6</td><td>19.8</td><td>64.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CRCD (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>86.1</td><td>62.5</td><td>74.5</td><td>81.9</td><td>51.0</td><td>54.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;O&#x02019;Brien et al (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]</td><td>59.7</td><td>63.9</td><td>46.4</td><td>76.4</td><td>20.8</td><td>68.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Sorbi et al<italic>.</italic> (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td><td>68.1</td><td>38.9</td><td>53.7</td><td>65.3</td><td>26.0</td><td>62.5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Gauthier et al (2012)<sup>d</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td><td>73.6</td><td>70.8</td><td>70.8</td><td>87.5</td><td>50.0</td><td>79.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7">Mental Health</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Gelenberg et al<italic>.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td>68.1</td><td>41.7</td><td>61.5</td><td>66.7</td><td>32.3</td><td>60.4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Dua et al<italic>.</italic> (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td>70.8</td><td>41.7</td><td>66.7</td><td>84.7</td><td>68.7</td><td>93.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Avalia-T (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td><td>88.9</td><td>70.8</td><td>79.2</td><td>75.0</td><td>49.0</td><td>60.4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Mitchell et al<italic>.</italic> (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>86.1</td><td>66.7</td><td>75.0</td><td>80.6</td><td>71.9</td><td>85.4</td></tr><tr><td>Average Domain Score (SD)</td><td>72.1 (12.1)</td><td>54.5 (23.3)</td><td>65.8 (13.9)</td><td>77.0 (11.4)</td><td>41.5 (22.6)</td><td>59.2 (23.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>SD</italic> Standard Deviation</p><p>
<sup>a</sup> Includes Grosset et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]</p><p>
<sup>b</sup> Originally created in 2007 and updated in 2011</p><p>
<sup>c</sup> Includes Patel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]</p><p>
<sup>d</sup> Includes Moore et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], Herrman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The mean rating across each question in the domain scores were also examined to explore differences between domains (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S2). Question one pertaining to the overall objectives was the highest rated item at 5.88 (SD 0.61), followed by link between evidence and recommendations at 5.78 (SD 0.51). The lowest rated item was providing a procedure for updating the guideline is provided, with a mean rating of 3.16 (SD 1.73). The views and preferences of the target population have been sought was also rated poorly with a mean score of 3.25 (SD 1.92). All items in Domain 5 had low mean scores, ranging between 3.27 (SD 1.46) for resource implications and 3.72 (SD 1.53) for advice on putting recommendations into practice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Guideline recommendations</title><p>The details of extracted recommendations are summarized in the Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> for PD and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> for dementia. 21 categories of recommendations were extracted in total.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Statements &#x00026; recommendations for Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">Anxiety</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Evidence for the Management &#x00026; Treatment of Anxiety in PD is Lacking.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>AAN Level U (Uncertain or Lack of Evidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Zesiewicz et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], Grimes et al. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Depression</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Screening for Depression in PD is recommended.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>EFNS Level A (Effective), SIGN Grade C (Case Control to Cohort Evidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Berardelli et al<italic>.</italic> (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], Grosset et al<italic>.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">There are several available tools screening for Depression in PD.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>SIGN Level C &#x00026; Good Practice Point (GDS, BDI, HADS, MADRS &#x00026; HDRS) &#x00026; EFNS Class I (Diagnostic Accuracy Study)(MDS-UPDRS)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Grosset et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], Berardelli et al<italic>.</italic> (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Comment</td><td>A patient with PD should be screened for depression with either a clinician or self-rated tool. Diagnosis should not be based on the solely on the tool. Those with a positive screening test should be referred for further assessment and diagnosis (including collateral history).</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Practitioners should have a low threshold for diagnosing Depression in PD.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>CFNS Good Practice Point</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Grimes et al<italic>.</italic> (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Treatment of Depression in PD needs to be individualized to each case.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>CFNS Good Practice Point</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Grimes et al<italic>.</italic> (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Anti-depressant Therapy is recommended; there is little evidence to suggest one agent over another.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gelenberg et al<italic>.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Grosset et al<italic>.</italic> (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Tricyclic Antidepressants (e.g. Amitriptyline or Desipramine) have some evidence for treatment, but this must be balanced with the adverse effects (e.g. Anticholinergic).</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>CFNS Level C (Possibly Effective)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Grimes et al<italic>.</italic> (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], Grosset et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors have some evidence for treatment, but this must be balanced with the adverse effects (e.g. RLS, PLM, RBD).</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>EFNS Class II (Prospective Matched Group Cohort or Controlled Trial) to Class IV (Uncontrolled Studies), APA Level II (Moderate Clinical Evidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Ferreira et al. (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Certain agents such as Amoxapine or Lithium should be avoided due to worsening of PD Symptoms.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">There is some evidence for the use of dopamine agonists (e.g. Pramipexole) &#x00026; MAOI (e.g. Selegiline) for depression, but not for levodopa.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>EFNS Class I (RCT), Class III (Other Controlled Trial), APA Level I (Recommended with substantial confidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Ferreira et al. (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Grimes et al. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">There is insufficient evidence regarding the use of ECT, TCMS and psychotherapy in depression with PD.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Ferreira et al. (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Grimes et al. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Statements &#x00026; recommendations for Dementia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">Anxiety</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Patients with Dementia should be assessed for Anxiety (e.g. HADS).</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>AIAQS Level D (Expert Opinion)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], NICE (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Psychological Interventions can be considered for Anxiety in Dementia</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>NICE (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">There is little evidence about the treatment of Anxiety in those with Dementia.<break/>Cholinesterase Inhibitors can be considered for treating Dementia-related behaviours, including anxiety.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>AIAQS&#x000a0;Level A (Meta-analysis or RCT)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Depression</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Patients experiencing Dementia should be evaluated for Depression, including possible secondary causes.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>CRCD Level A (Useful), AIAQS Level D, WFSBP Grade 3 (Limited Evidence from Controlled Studies), EFNS GPP</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>NICE (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], CRCD (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], Sorbi et al (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], Ihl et al. (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Patients with Depression in Dementia should be evaluated for suicide risk, however evidence varies.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>APA Level I (Substantial Clinical Confidence) or Inconclusive</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Avalia-T (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Use of a valid screening tool (e.g. CSDD, GDS, HADS or DMAS) for Depression is recommended.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>AIAQS Level D to Good Practice Point, Low Quality Evidence, EFNS GPP/Class II (Prospective Study)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], Sorbi et al (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], Hort et al (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], Mitchell et al. (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">fMRI needs further study to determine its utility in Depression in the context of Dementia</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>CCCDT4 Grade 2C (Moderate Recommendation, Low Level Evidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gauthier et al. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Therapy for Depression in Dementia should include a variety of Non-pharmacologic options.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>AIAQS Level C (Case-control, Cohort), APA Level II (Moderate Clinical Confidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>NICE (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Mitchell et al. (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Comment</td><td>These include: cognitive behavioural therapy, reminiscence therapy, multi-sensory stimulation, animal-assisted therapy, exercise, stimulation-oriented treatment (recreational or pleasurable activities), or improvements to a living situation. Consider the involvement of carers.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Although evidence is mixed, a trial of Anti-depressants could be considered for Depression in Dementia.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>CCCDT4 Grade 2A (Moderate Recommendation, High Level Evidence), EFNS Class IV (Un-blinded, Expert Opinion), WFSBP Grade 5 (Inconsistent Results), APA Level II (Moderate Clinical Confidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gauthier et al. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], NICE (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], Sorbi et al (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Ihl et al. (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], Dua et al (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">When choosing an anti-depressant (E.g. SSRIs, SNRIs or TCAs) it is important to consider the anticholinergic side effects.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>EFNS Level B (Case-control, Cohort), EFNS Class IV (Un-blinded, Expert Opinion), APA Level I (Substantial Clinical Confidence) to APA Level II (Moderate Clinical Confidence), AIAQS Level B</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gauthier et al. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], NICE (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], Sorbi et al (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], Hort et al (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Comment</td><td>SSRIs (Citalopram or Sertraline) and TCAs have similar efficacy, but TCAs are not recommended given anticholinergic effects. SSRIs appear to be better tolerated. Other agents such as bupropion, venlafaxine and mirtazapine may be effective.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Stimulants can be considered for treatment of Depression in Dementia.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>APA Level III (Depends on Individual Circumstances), AIAQS Level B (Case-control, Cohort)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Cholinesterase Inhibitors can be considered for treating Dementia-related behaviours, including depression.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>AIAQS&#x000a0;Level A (Meta-analysis or RCT)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>AIAQS (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">ECT can be considered in certain cases for Depression in those with Dementia.</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>APA Level II (Moderate Clinical Confidence)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>Gelenberg et al. (2010) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Cholinesterase Inhibitors may improve neuropsychiatric symptoms in Lewy Body Disease</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Level of Evidence</td><td>Level A (Meta-analysis or RCT)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Guidelines</td><td>O&#x02019;Brien et al (2011) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Parkinson&#x02019;s disease recommendations</title><p>Only two guidelines discussed anxiety in those with PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. These stated there was little evidence for either the diagnosis or treatment of anxiety in PD, and that there was insufficient evidence for the treatment of anxiety with levodopa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p>There were clear recommendations surrounding the diagnosis of depression in PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Clinicians should have a low threshold for the diagnosis of depression in PD given the difficulties making a diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Use of a validated tool for detecting depression (or neuropsychiatric symptoms) was advocated by two guidelines, with varying levels of recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Tools that were recommended include the HDRS, the MADRS or the UPDRS&#x02014;Part 1 Non-Motor, among others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The diagnosis should be made based on a clinical interview and not based on the tool alone and should seek collateral information from carers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p>Antidepressant therapy is recommended, however there is little evidence to support one agent over another (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Additionally, the choice of an agent must be individualized (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) and the practitioner should consider side effects and drug interactions prior to initiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. There have been prior studies on the tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), specifically amitriptyline, and although they were beneficial for mood, this was offset by the side effects (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. One guideline noted that selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) showed some benefit in uncontrolled studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], but noted that the SSRIs could worsen PD symptoms of restless legs (RLS), periodic limb movement (PLM) and REM sleep behaviour disorder (RBD) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. It is recommended to avoid amoxapine and lithium in those with PD, due to the risk of worsening motor symptoms (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p>There is some weak evidence supporting the use of dopamine agonists and monoamine oxidase inhibitors for the management of depression in PD (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Pramipexole was suggested to have an antidepressant effect not solely due a motor effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Selegiline has some antidepressant effects but further studies are needed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. If the mood symptoms are only present during off periods, it was suggested that patients might benefit from drugs addressing the motor symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. However there was no evidence levodopa alone affected mood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p>Other therapies for depression are not well explored in PD. The European Federation of Neurological Sciences (EFNS) concluded there was insufficient data to recommend psychotherapy, electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) or transcranial magnetic stimulation (TCMS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Other guideline assert that ECT has been used in PD, but that there are no specific trials in PD and is associated with risk (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Dementia recommendations</title><p>It is recommended that patients with dementia be assessed for anxiety (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), however there is no clear consensus on what tools to use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. One guideline recommended the use of the Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The evidence for the treatment of anxiety in dementia is lacking (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p>It is recommended that patients with dementia be evaluated and re-evaluated over time for depression (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. As part of this assessment, patients should be evaluated for other secondary&#x000a0;causes of depression. It is suggested that these patients be assessed for suicidality by one guideline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], however another reported there was inconclusive evidence regarding this [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p><p>The use of a valid screening tool was recommended for depression case finding (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5) in dementia, including the CSDD, GDS or Dementia Mood Assessment Scale (DMAS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The CSDD was more commonly recommended given it is a clinician-rating tool that involves caregivers with higher sensitivity (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p><p>Therapy for depression in those with dementia should include a variety of non-pharmacologic options (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) such as stimulation oriented, cognitive behavioural, reminiscence, exercise or multi-sensory therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Pharmacologic therapy is recommended despite variable evidence (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. It is suggested by one guideline that, if there is no improvement with non-pharmacologic therapy, an antidepressant be considered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Another notes that for moderate-severe depression, pharmacologic treatment is warranted (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. However, there needs to be a clear risk-benefit assessment and discussion (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Based largely on clinical experience, most guidelines recommend the use of SSRIs given the lower side effect profile over TCAs (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The concern with TCAs is largely anticholinergic side effects causing worsened cognition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Other antidepressants such as mirtazapine, bupropion, and venlafaxine may also be of benefit (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Other adjunct therapies recommended include stimulants (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], cholinesterase inhibitors (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and ECT on a case-by-case basis (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study provides a synthesis and quality assessment of available guidelines for the management of depression or anxiety in PD or dementia. We identified clear gaps in guideline quality and the evidence, which inform future research and knowledge translation.</p><sec id="Sec15"><title>Guideline quality</title><p>Guidelines that were excluded due to low quality were typically those that lacked explicit development methods, thus ratings across all the domains were low. When examining the AGREE II ratings overall, the lowest rating was in assessing the guideline description of barriers and facilitators, implementation, resource implications, or monitoring/auditing criteria (Domain 5). In fact, few guidelines had discrete sections addressing knowledge translation. The concern about guideline applicability was explored in a 2015 systematic review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], which found that applicability scored lower than any other domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. If guidelines rarely address their implementation in practice, then there will be continued practice variation. There is clear evidence supporting the use of implementation tools to improve guideline uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Thus making guidelines without a clear knowledge translation plan does a disservice to stakeholders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p>The engagement of patients and caregivers was notably absent in CPG development. This process is important, as it is aimed at improving implementability, by ensuring the recommendations are comprehensive, adaptable and applicable to the target group and have an open process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Given the constant changing nature of evidence, having up-to-date guidelines certainly makes a difference to the validity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. However, the lowest rated item was for the guideline update procedures.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Guideline content</title><p>There is an overall lack of recommendations related to the diagnosis or treatment of anxiety in either PD or dementia. This stems from the fact there is little evidence on how to approach the assessment. One guideline suggested the use Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale for dementia, but they did not provide diagnostic accuracy information or suggestions for implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. There is also a concern that the medications traditionally used for anxiety can have major adverse effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], and there are few studies to guide treatment. Anxiety was less frequently mentioned than depression in the included CPGs, and in some cases was only mentioned in combination with other neuropsychiatric symptoms. The overall lack of evidence for anxiety care in PD and dementia is a major gap in the current research.</p><p>Guidance for depression was present in a higher proportion of guidelines. Despite this, there is variability in the reporting of levels of evidence and recommendations (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S1). In some cases the recommendations for depression in PD only had 1 or 2 guidelines supporting them, indicating variance in guideline reporting. In other cases recommendations were vague, which can lead to difficulty with end user interpretation and implementation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p>It is clear that screening for depression with a validated tool in PD is recommended, although evidence varies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. It is recommended, as a good practice point, that any diagnosis of depression is not made solely on a brief assessment tool, as these tools are more focused on case finding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Although this is an important concept in detection, it was only recommended by one guideline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. A 2015 systematic review identified several validated tools for the detection of depression in PD, with the GDS-15 having the highest pooled sensitivity (0.81; 95% CI 0.64, 0.91) and area under the curve (0.94) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p><p>Recommendations surrounding non-pharmacologic therapy were few, stating there was insufficient evidence for the use of psychotherapy, ECT or TMS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Two recent trials demonstrated the effectiveness of cognitive behavioural therapy in PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. This highlights the need for further large high quality studies on a range of non-pharmacologic therapies and the need for constant update of guidelines. Pharmacological therapy is recommended for managing depression in PD, but there is little evidence on choosing agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. This has resulted in a variety of treatment recommendations, with little evidence to direct clinical practice.</p><p>Depression in dementia was more frequently addressed. However, these recommendations also had varied guideline and evidentiary support. Guidelines supported the evaluation of depression in dementia, but evidence ranged from high quality to good practice points [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Commonly recommended tools were the CSDD and GDS, with preference towards the CSDD due to better accuracy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. This was confirmed by a 2015 systematic review of depression tools for dementia, finding that the CSDD had a area under the curve of 0.89 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].</p><p>Interestingly, the issue of evaluating for suicide risk was raised in two guidelines with divergent recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. One stating there was inconclusive evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] and another stating substantial evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. It is unclear why there is such a difference in reported evidence; perhaps development groups have different evidence available or differing interpretations of the evidence.</p><p>There are stronger recommendations for non-pharmacologic treatment in dementia than in PD, outlining several options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The evidence for pharmacologic therapy is described as mixed with Grade 2A (Moderate Recommendation, High Level Evidence) to Class IV (Un-blinded Study, Expert Opinion) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Again SSRIs and TCAs are the focus, with TCAs being less likely to be recommended due to side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. For those with dementia, there were more options recommended for therapy including stimulants, cholinesterase inhibitors and ECT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>Limitations</title><p>There is a well-recognized issue with heterogeneity in the terms used to refer to guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. For our database search we used indexed terms from each of the three databases as well as key words using known nomenclature for guidelines and the comorbidities. It is also possible that the addition of the depression or anxiety criteria to the search may have been restrictive, however without these terms the search was impractical. To address this, we developed the search strategy with experts in the area of guideline systematic review and an experienced librarian, and we had an external reviewer independently assess the search strategy. To reduce the risk of missing literature not indexed in databases we contacted experts, searched references of included studies and performed an extensive search of the grey literature search.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Given the burden of comorbid mental illness in dementia and PD, it is key that we understand clearly the current knowledge base so we can improve care for these populations. This study provides a synthesis and quality assessment of the relevant guidelines. By synthesizing the recommendations, we identified areas of knowledge that are potentially ready to be translated into practice but also clear evidence gaps. This data was further evaluated in a subsequent study by stakeholders in focus groups to understand the other barriers and facilitators to the use of guidelines. This was to inform and help develop a comprehensive knowledge/end-user focused plan for addressing these gaps.</p></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec19"><title>Additional files</title><p>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12883_2016_754_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Box S1.</label><caption><p>Search Strategy. (DOCX 22&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12883_2016_754_MOESM2_ESM.docx" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2: Table S1.</label><caption><p>Grey Literature Sources (<italic>n</italic> = 83). (DOCX 15&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12883_2016_754_MOESM3_ESM.docx" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3: Figure S1.</label><caption><p>Evidence Levels &#x00026; Grading Schemes Used Across Guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. (DOCX 65.4&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media>
<media position="anchor" xlink:href="12883_2016_754_MOESM4_ESM.docx" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4: Table S2.</label><caption><p>Mean Domain Question Scores From AGREE II Evaluation. (DOCX 16&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media>
</p></sec></app></app-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AAN</term><def><p>American Academy of Neurology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>APA</term><def><p>American Psychiatric Association</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AIAQS</term><def><p>Agency for Health Quality and Assessment of Catalonia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Avalia-T</term><def><p>Galician Health Technology Assessment Agency</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BDI</term><def><p>Beck Depression Inventory</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BPA</term><def><p>British Association of Psychopharmacology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CADASIL</term><def><p>Cerebral Autosomal-Dominant Arteriopathy with Subcortical Infarcts and Leukoencephalopathy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCCDTD4</term><def><p>Canadian Consensus Conference on the Diagnosis and Treatment of Dementia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNSF</term><def><p>Canadian Neurological Sciences Foundation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPG</term><def><p>Clinical Practice Guideline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRCD</term><def><p>Clinical Research Centre for Dementia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSDD</term><def><p>Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMAS</term><def><p>Dementia Mood Assessment Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ECT</term><def><p>Electroconvulsive Therapy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EFNS</term><def><p>European Federation of Neuroscience</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GDS</term><def><p>Geriatric Depression Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GRADE</term><def><p>Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development and Evaluation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HADS</term><def><p>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HDRS</term><def><p>Hamilton Depression Rating Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICSI</term><def><p>Institute for Clinical Systems Improvement</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MADRS</term><def><p>Montgomery &#x000c5;sberg Depression Rating Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDS</term><def><p>Movement Disorders Society</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NICE</term><def><p>National Institute of Clinical Excellence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PD</term><def><p>Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PLM</term><def><p>Periodic Limb Movement Syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PRESS</term><def><p>Peer Review of Electronic Search Strategies</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PRISMA</term><def><p>Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RBD</term><def><p>REM Sleep Behaviour Disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RCT</term><def><p>Randomized Control Trial</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>REM</term><def><p>Rapid Eye Movement</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RLS</term><def><p>Restless Legs Syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>Standard Deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SIGN</term><def><p>Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SSRI</term><def><p>Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCA</term><def><p>Tricyclic Acid Antidepressants</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCMS</term><def><p>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UPDRS</term><def><p>Unified Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease Rating Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WFBSP</term><def><p>World Federation of Societies of Behavioural Psychiatry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p>World Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Diane Lorenzetti MLS, Research Librarian (DL) for her input into the search strategy, and Helen Lee Robertson MLIS, Liaison Librarian for Clinical Medicine for her (Peer Review of Electronic Search Strategies) PRESS review of our search strategy.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>This project had funding from an Alberta Innovates Health Solutions&#x02014;Knowledge to Action Grant.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and material</title><p>The datasets during and/or analysed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. All data from this study are presented in detail. For the quality assessment the individual ratings are not published as the AGREE group recommends publication f the mean scaled domain scores. The extracted recommendations are summarized in the tables and text, full details are available in the source guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>ZG and BM performed all citation/full text screening, quality assessments, data extraction and analysis and drafted the manuscript. ZG completed all statistical analysis. SG was involved in the grey literature search and quality assessment. JHL supervised all parts of the systematic review and analysis, was involved in the quality assessment and determination of inclusion. ZG, BM, SG, HH, SS, TP, NJ and JHL provided input and reviewed the proposal, protocol, analysis and manuscript. ZG registered the protocol with PROSPERO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. All authors had access to the data, reviewed and approved the final manuscript. ZG and JHL had full access to the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and accuracy of the data.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>ZG has received funding by Canadian Institutes for Health Research&#x02014;Canadian Graduate Student Scholarship, Alberta Innovates Health Solutions Clinician Fellowship Award, Canadian Society for Clinical Investigation Resident Research Award, Alberta Student and Western Regional Training Centre affiliate award. BM and SG report no disclosures. HH has no disclosures. SP holds funding from Hotchkiss Brain Institute (HBI), CIHR and a grant co-funded by the University of Calgary HBI and Pfizer Canada. TP has an unrestricted educational grants from Shire Canada. TP has research grant support from Sick Kids Foundation, Alberta Health Services Mental Health Strategic Clinical Network, Hotchkiss Brain Institute and Canadian Institutes for Health Research. NJ holds a Canada Research Chair Tier 2 in Health Services Research and is on the editorial board of <italic>Neurology</italic> and holds research grants from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, Alberta Innovates Health Solutions, the Alberta Spine Foundation, the University of Calgary Cumming School of Medicine, Department of Clinical Neurosciences and HBIs and a grant co-funded by the University of Calgary HBI and Pfizer Canada. JHL has received funding from Alberta Health Services as the Scientific Director of the Seniors Health Strategic Clinical Network.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not Applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>University of Calgary Conjoint Health Research Ethics Board (CHREB) REB 14-1449</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pachana NA, Egan SJ, Laidlaw K, Dissanayaka N, Byrne GJ, Brockman S, Marsh R, Starkstein S. Clinical issues in the treatment of anxiety and depression in older adults with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease. Movement disorders: official journal of the Movement Disorder Society. 2013;28(14):1930&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reijnders</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Aarsland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leentjens</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of prevalence studies of depression in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Mov Disord</source><year>2008</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.21803</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17987654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17987654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leentjens</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parkinson disease: scales to detect depression in Parkinson disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurol</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2012.96</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22584157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22584157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moberg</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Duda</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of psychiatric and other nonmotor symptoms on disability in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2004</year><volume>52</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>784</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2004.52219.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15086662?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15086662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kostic</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekmezovic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jecmenica-Lukic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojkovic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Spica</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Svetel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzoljic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suicide and suicidal ideation in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>289</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2009.08.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19737673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19737673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mindham</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Spokes</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease and its association with dementia and depression</article-title><source>Acta Neurol Scand</source><year>2004</year><volume>110</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0404.2004.00292.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15242420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orgeta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Orrell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological treatments for depression and anxiety in dementia and mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>CD009125</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Katona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sertraline or mirtazapine for depression in dementia (HTA-SADD): a randomised, multicentre, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2011</year><volume>378</volume><issue>9789</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60830-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21764118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21764118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enache</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Winblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aarsland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression in dementia: epidemiology, mechanisms, and treatment</article-title><source>Curr Opin Psychiatry</source><year>2011</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21926624?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21926624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckwalter</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiety and stigma in dementia: a threat to aging in place</article-title><source>Nurs Clin North Am</source><year>2014</year><volume>49</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cnur.2014.02.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24846469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24846469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van der Mussele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekelaar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bastard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermeiren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saerens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marien</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Goeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Deyn</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelborghs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and associated behavioral symptoms of depression in mild cognitive impairment and dementia due to Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.3909</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23255479?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23255479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dissanayaka</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Sullivan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Silburn</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellick</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiety disorders in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: prevalence and risk factors</article-title><source>Mov Disord</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.22833</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20461800?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20461800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression and Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: current knowledge</article-title><source>Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>409</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11910-013-0409-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24190780?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24190780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djamshidian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiety and depression in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Curr Treat Options Neurol</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>285</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11940-014-0285-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24532378?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knapskog</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Barca</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Engedal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of the validity of the Cornell Scale and the MADRS in detecting depression among memory clinic patients</article-title><source>Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000334983</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22262043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Modrego</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrandez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression in patients with mild cognitive impairment increases the risk of developing dementia of Alzheimer type: a prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>2004</year><volume>61</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1290</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.61.8.1290</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15313849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15313849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ownby</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Crocco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression and risk for Alzheimer disease: systematic review, meta-analysis, and metaregression analysis</article-title><source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.63.5.530</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16651510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16651510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frisina</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Borod</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Foldi</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: health risks, etiology, and treatment options</article-title><source>Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18728814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18728814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davis D, J. Goldman, P. Valerie: Handbook on Clinical Practice Guidelines. In<italic>.</italic>: Canadian Medical Association; 2007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gagliardi AR, Brouwers MC, Palda VA, Lemieux-Charles L, Grimshaw JM. How can we improve guideline use? A conceptual framework of implementability. Implementation Sci. 2011;6:26. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21426574">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21426574</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller-Wolman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical Practice Guidelines We Can Trust</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on Standards for Developing Trustworthy Clinical Practice Guidelines. National Academy of Sciences</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLennan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Matowe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness and efficiency of guideline dissemination and implementation strategies</article-title><source>Health Technol Assess</source><year>2004</year><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>iii</fpage><lpage>iv</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3310/hta8060</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14960256?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramasubbu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Samaan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sockalingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Canadian Network for Mood and Anxiety Treatments (CANMAT) task force recommendations for the management of patients with mood disorders and select comorbid medical conditions</article-title><source>Ann Clin Psychiatry</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22303525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramasubbu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><collab>Canadian Network for M</collab><collab>Anxiety Treatments Task F</collab></person-group><article-title>The CANMAT task force recommendations for the management of patients with mood disorders and comorbid medical conditions: diagnostic, assessment, and treatment principles</article-title><source>Ann Clin Psychiatry</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22303524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22303524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Besag</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Toffol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ettinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanemoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnamoorthy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>LaFrance</surname><given-names>WC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>International consensus clinical practice statements for the treatment of neuropsychiatric conditions associated with epilepsy</article-title><source>Epilepsia</source><year>2011</year><volume>52</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2133</fpage><lpage>2138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2011.03276.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21955156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21955156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Iliffe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Carroll</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Keady</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concordance with clinical practice guidelines for dementia in general practice</article-title><source>Aging Ment Health</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13607860802636206</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19347682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19347682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Teasell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherence to Canadian best practice recommendations for stroke care: assessment and management of poststroke depression in an Ontario rehabilitation facility</article-title><source>Top Stroke Rehabil</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1310/tsr1902-132</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22436361?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22436361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCluskey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vratsistas-Curto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schurr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers and enablers to implementing multiple stroke guideline recommendations: a qualitative study</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>323</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6963-13-323</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23958136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23958136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Moher D, Liberati A, Tetzlaff J, Altman DG, Group P. Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. Bmj 2009, 339:b2535.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Making the Case for Investing in Mental Health in Canada. In<italic>.</italic>: Mental Health Commission of Canada; 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">PRESS: peer review of electronic search strategies. 2015 Guideline Explanation and Elaboration (PRESS E&#x00026;E). Ottawa: Canadian Agency for Drugs and Technologies in Health; 2016. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cadth.ca/sites/default/files/pdf/CP0015_PRESS_Update_Report_2016.pdf">https://www.cadth.ca/sites/default/files/pdf/CP0015_PRESS_Update_Report_2016.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez Garcia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanabria</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia Alvarez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Trujillo-Martin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Etxeandia-Ikobaltzeta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotzeva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Louro-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barajas-Nava</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz Del Campo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The validity of recommendations from clinical guidelines: a survival analysis</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2014</year><volume>186</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1211</fpage><lpage>1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.140547</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25200758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25200758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouwers</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kho</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Browman</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgers</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cluzeau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Feder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fervers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AGREE II: advancing guideline development, reporting and evaluation in health care</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2010</year><volume>182</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>E839</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.090449</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20603348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20603348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Snelgrove</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim-Carter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchowersky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajput</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Canadian guidelines on Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Can J Neurol Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>39</volume><issue>4 Suppl 4</issue><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23126020?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23126020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zesiewicz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnulf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gronseth</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyasaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Iverson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><collab>Quality Standards Subcommittee of the American Academy of N</collab></person-group><article-title>Practice parameter: treatment of nonmotor symptoms of Parkinson disease: report of the quality standards subcommittee of the American Academy of Neurology</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2010</year><volume>74</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181d55f24</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20231670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20231670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing clinical behaviour by making guidelines specific</article-title><source>Bmj</source><year>2004</year><volume>328</volume><issue>7435</issue><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.328.7435.343</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14764503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14764503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Diagnosis and pharmacological management of Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: A national clinical guideline. Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network; 2010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berardelli A, Wenning GK, Antonini A, Berg D, Bloem BR, Bonifati V, Brooks D, Burn DJ, Colosimo C, Fanciulli A, et al. EFNS/MDS-ES/ENS [corrected] recommendations for the diagnosis of Parkinson&#x02019;s disease. European journal of neurology: the official journal of the European Federation of Neurological Societies. 2013;20(1):16&#x02013;34.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gelenberg AJ, Freeman MP, Markowitz JC, Rosenbaum JF, Thase ME, Trivedi MH, Van Rhoads RS. Practice Guideline for Treatment of Patients with Major Depressive Disorder 3rd Edition. American Pyschiatric Association; 2010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferreira JJ, Katzenschlager R, Bloem BR, Bonuccelli U, Burn D, Deuschl G, Dietrichs E, Fabbrini G, Friedman A, Kanovsky P, et al. Summary of the recommendations of the EFNS/MDS-ES review on therapeutic management of Parkinson&#x02019;s disease. Eur J Neurol. 2013;20(1):5&#x02013;15. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23279439">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23279439</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dementia: Guidelines on Supporting People with Dementia and their carers in Health and Social Care. National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence. National Collaborating Centre for Mental Health. Social Care Institute for Excellence National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence. In<italic>.</italic> London: The British Psychological Society &#x00026; Gaskell The Royal College of Psychiatrists; 2011.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Development Group of the Clinical Practice Guideline on the comprehensive care of people with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease and other dementias. Clinical Practice Guideline on the comprehensive care of people with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease and other dementias. <italic>Quality Plan for the National Health System of the Ministry of Health, Social Policies and Equality Ag&#x000e8;ncia d&#x02019;Informaci&#x000f3;, Avaluaci&#x000f3; i Qualitat en Salut of Catalonia Clinical Practice Guidelines in the Spanish National Health Service: AIAQS No 2009/07</italic> 2010. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.guiasalud.es/GPC/GPC_484_Alzheimer_AIAQS_comp_eng.pdf">http://www.guiasalud.es/GPC/GPC_484_Alzheimer_AIAQS_comp_eng.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clinical Research Center for Dementia of South Korea. Clinical practice guideline for dementia. Part I: diagnosis &#x00026; evaluation. Seoul: Clinical Research Center for Dementia of South Korea; 2011. p. 117. The guideline cited is available here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jkma.org/src/SM/jkma-54-861-s002.pdf">http://jkma.org/src/SM/jkma-54-861-s002.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ihl R, Frolich L, Winblad B, Schneider L, Burns A, Moller HJ, Disease WTFoTGfAs, other D. World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry (WFSBP) guidelines for the biological treatment of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease and other dementias. World J Biol Psychiatry. 2011;12(1):2&#x02013;32. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21288069">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21288069</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sorbi S, Hort J, Erkinjuntti T, Fladby T, Gainotti G, Gurvit H, Nacmias B, Pasquier F, Popescu BO, Rektorova I, et al. EFNS-ENS Guidelines on the diagnosis and management of disorders associated with dementia. Eur J Neurol. 2012;19(9):1159&#x02013;79. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22891773">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22891773</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Working Group of the Clinical Practice Guideline for the Prevention and Treatment [trunc]. Clinical practice guideline for the prevention and treatment of suicidal behaviour. Madrid: Ministry of Health and Social Policy, Galician Health Technology Assessment Agency; 2012. p. 382. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.guiasalud.es/GPC/GPC_481_Conducta_Suicida_Avaliat_compl_en.pdf">http://www.guiasalud.es/GPC/GPC_481_Conducta_Suicida_Avaliat_compl_en.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gainotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirttila</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rektorova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorbi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheltens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><collab>Dementia ESPo</collab></person-group><article-title>EFNS guidelines for the diagnosis and management of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Eur J Neurol</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1236</fpage><lpage>1248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2010.03040.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20831773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20831773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mitchell J, Trangle M, Degnan B, Gabert T, Haight B, Kessler D, Mack N, Mallen E, Novak H, Rossmiller D, et al. Adult Depression in Primary Care. Institute for Clinical Systems Improvement; 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dua T, Barbui C, Clark N, Fleischmann A, Poznyak V, van Ommeren M, Yasamy MT, Ayuso-Mateos JL, Birbeck GL, Drummond C, et al. Evidence-based guidelines for mental, neurological, and substance use disorders in low- and middle-income countries: summary of WHO recommendations. PLoS Med. 2011;8(11):e1001122. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22110406">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22110406</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chertkow</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockwood</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa-Neto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Soucy</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recommendations of the 4th Canadian consensus conference on the diagnosis and treatment of dementia (CCCDTD4)</article-title><source>Can Geriatr J</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5770/cgj.15.49</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23259025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23259025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagliardi</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouwers</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do guidelines offer implementation advice to target users? A systematic review of guideline applicability</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e007047</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25694459?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25694459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauro</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunkley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Janszky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumlien</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moshe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakasato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedley</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Perucca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Senties</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The current state of epilepsy guidelines: A systematic review</article-title><source>Epilepsia</source><year>2016</year><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.13273</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26659723?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26659723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shekelle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schunemann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developing clinical practice guidelines: target audiences, identifying topics for guidelines, guideline group composition and functioning and conflicts of interest</article-title><source>Implementation Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1748-5908-7-60</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grosset</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Macphee</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nairn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guideline Development</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and pharmacological management of Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: summary of SIGN guidelines</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2010</year><volume>340</volume><fpage>b5614</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.b5614</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20068048?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20068048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goodarzi ZS, Mrklas K, Roberts DJ, Jette N, Pringsheim T, Holroyd-Leduc J. Depression case finding in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease patients: a systematic review of depression screening tools. Montreal: Canadian Geriatric Society Scientific Meeting 2015; 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobkin</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Menza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gara</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienfait</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive-behavioral therapy for depression in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: a randomized, controlled trial</article-title><source>Am J Psychiatry</source><year>2011</year><volume>168</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2011.10111669</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21676990?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21676990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Troeung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A waitlist-controlled trial of group cognitive behavioural therapy for depression and anxiety in Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>BMC Psychiatry</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-14-19</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24467781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24467781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodarzi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mele</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Holroyd-Leduc</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Depression case finding in dementia patients: a systematic review of depression screening tools</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Conference on Dementia Meeting 2015</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Guidance notes for registering a systematic review protocol with PROSPERO. In: <italic>PROSPERO: International prospective register of systematic reviews</italic> Centre for Reviews and Dissemination, National Institute for Health Research; 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">O&#x02019;Brien JT, Burns A, Group BAPDC. Clinical practice with anti-dementia drugs: a revised (second) consensus statement from the British Association for Psychopharmacology. J Psychopharmacol. 2011;25(8):997&#x02013;1019. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21088041">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21088041</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><collab>Parkinson Society C</collab></person-group><article-title>Parkinson&#x02019;s disease guidelines for pharmacists</article-title><source>Can Pharm J</source><year>2014</year><volume>147</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1715163514529740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><collab>Canadian Consensus Conference on the D</collab><collab>Treatment of D</collab></person-group><article-title>Fourth Canadian Consensus Conference on the Diagnosis and Treatment of Dementia: recommendations for family physicians</article-title><source>Can Fam Physician</source><year>2014</year><volume>60</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24829003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24829003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herrmann N, Lanctot KL, Hogan DB. Pharmacological recommendations for the symptomatic treatment of dementia: the Canadian Consensus Conference on the Diagnosis and Treatment of Dementia 2012. Alzheimer&#x02019;s Res Ther. 2013;5 Suppl 1:S5. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24565367">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24565367</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rabins PV, Blacker D, Rovner BW, Rummans T, Schneider LS, Tariot PN, Blass DM. Practice Guidelines for the Treatment of Patients With Alzheimer&#x02019;s Disease and Other Dementias. American Pyschiatric Association; 2007.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>