<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front Syst NeurosciFront. Syst. Neurosci.Frontiers in Systems Neuroscience1662-5137Frontiers Research Foundation298272410.3389/fnsys.2010.00150NeuroscienceOriginal ResearchInfluences of Neural Pathway Integrity on Children's Response to Reading InstructionDavisNicole123*FanQiuyun24ComptonDonald L.15FuchsDoug15FuchsLynn S.15CuttingLaurie E.1235GoreJohn C.1234AndersonAdam W.12341Vanderbilt University Kennedy Center for Research on Human DevelopmentNashville, TN, USA2Vanderbilt University Institute of Imaging ScienceNashville, TN, USA3Department of Radiology and Radiological Sciences, Vanderbilt UniversityNashville, TN, USA4Department of Biomedical Engineering, School of Engineering, Vanderbilt UniversityNashville, TN, USA5Vanderbilt Peabody, Department of Special Education, Vanderbilt UniversityNashville, TN, USAEdited by: Barry Horwitz, National Institutes of Health, USAReviewed by: Kristina Simonyan, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, USA; Mohamed L. Seghier, University College London, UK*Correspondence: Nicole Davis, Vanderbilt University, Peabody Box 328, 230 Appleton Place, Nashville, TN 37203, USA. e-mail: nikki.davis@vanderbilt.edu2910201020104150146201001102010Copyright © 2010 Davis, Fan, Compton, Fuchs, Fuchs, Cutting, Gore and Anderson.2010This is an open-access article subject to an exclusive license agreement between the authors and the Frontiers Research Foundation, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original authors and source are credited.As the education field moves toward using responsiveness to intervention to identify students with disabilities, an important question is the degree to which this classification can be connected to a student's neurobiological characteristics. A few functional neuroimaging studies have reported a relationship between activation and response to instruction; however, whether a similar correlation exists with white matter (WM) is not clear. To investigate this issue, we acquired high angular resolution diffusion images from a group of first grade children who differed in their levels of responsiveness to a year-long reading intervention. Using probabilistic tractography, we calculated the strength of WM connections among nine cortical regions of interest and correlated these estimates with participants’ scores on four standardized reading measures. We found eight significant correlations, four of which were connections between the insular cortex and angular gyrus. In each of the correlations, a relationship with children's response to intervention was evident.diffusion tensor imagingprobabilistic tractographyreading disabilityresponse to interventionconnectivitymagnetic resonance imagingchildren<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Imaging data were acquired on 15 children with a mean age of 7.5 years (SD = .43). All participants were recruited from a sample of first graders in Nashville participating in a federally funded randomized control trial (RCT). The RCT explores the effectiveness of response to intervention (RTI) as a means of identifying and preventing RD. All participants, including control participants, were screened and determined to be at-risk for reading difficulties at the beginning of first grade. Children with brain injury, other physical disabilities, severe emotional problems, uncorrected sensory disorders, ADHD, or an IQ &lt; 80 were excluded during recruitment for this neuroimaging portion of the project. No child who was defined as having limited proficiency in English participated in the imaging study. No restriction was made for gender, ethnicity, or socioeconomic status. This study was approved by the Vanderbilt University Institutional Review Board. Written informed consent was obtained from the children's guardians. Written assent was obtained from the children.</p><p>Of the 15 datasets, four were not included due to severe head motion that rendered the tractography data unreliable. The remaining 11 participants were placed into groups based upon RCT categorization (described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s1">Behavioral Measures and Responsiveness</xref> section below). As such, classroom controls (C; <italic>n</italic> = 4) were defined as children who were initially identified as at risk in the fall of first grade but benefited from classroom-based tier 1 instruction and therefore did not qualify for small-group tier 2 reading intervention. Treatment responders (R; <italic>n</italic> = 2) were defined as children who did not benefit from tier 1 instruction, were eligible for small-group tier 2 reading intervention, and achieved adequate results on behavioral measures indicating response to intervention. Treatment non-responders (NR; <italic>n</italic> = 4) were children who did not benefit from tier 1 instruction, were eligible for small-group tier 2 reading intervention, and did not achieve adequate results on behavioral measures, indicating a failure to respond to intervention.</p></sec><sec id="s1"><title>Behavioral measures and responsiveness</title><p>Within the RCT, children's response to the instruction was estimated with a measure of word identification fluency (WIF; Fuchs et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2004</xref>; Compton et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">2010</xref>), which was administered weekly. Growth modeling of WIF over 6 weeks at the beginning of the school year indicated each child's responsiveness to the general classroom instruction (prior to small-group tier 2 intervention). Children identified as unresponsive to general classroom instruction were assigned to small-group tier 2 intervention (tier 2), in which trained research assistants provided a prescribed reading intervention 3 days/week for 17 weeks. For participants receiving tier 2 intervention, weekly progress monitoring using WIF continued throughout the course of intervention. Upon conclusion of the intervention, responsiveness was determined using WIF intercept and slope over the duration of the intervention.</p><p>It is important to note that for the imaging study, limitations in sample size necessitated ranking participants by WIF intercept and slope and dividing participants to designate equal groups of responders and non-responders. These designations of responders and non-responders were used in all subsequent analyses.</p><sec><title>Measures</title><p>Pre- and post-test behavioral measures were administered to all participants receiving tier 2 intervention. As stated above, the WIF growth was used to identify the participants’ group membership. The pre- and post-test measures listed below were correlated with DTI data.</p><sec><title>Word identification fluency</title><p>WIF consists of single-page lists of 100 high-frequency words randomly sampled from the Dolch pre-primer, primer, and first-grade level lists (Fuchs et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2004</xref>). The task is to read as many words as possible in 1 min.</p></sec><sec><title>Untimed word identification skill</title><p>The Woodcock Reading Mastery Test – R/NU: Word Identification (WRMT-R: WID, Woodcock, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">1998</xref>) is a norm-referenced test in which subjects read individual words ordered in difficulty until six sequential incorrect responses occur.</p></sec><sec><title>Untimed decoding skill</title><p>The Woodcock Reading Mastery Test – R/NU: Word Attack (WRMT-R: WAT, Woodcock, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">1998</xref>) is a norm-referenced test that requires subjects to pronounce decodable pseudowords presented in ordered difficulty until a ceiling of six sequential incorrect responses is reached.</p></sec><sec><title>Sight word reading efficiency</title><p>The Test of Sight Word Reading Efficiency (TOWRE: SWE, Torgesen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">1997</xref>) is a norm-referenced measure of sight word reading accuracy and fluency in which participants read a list of words of increasing difficulty for 45 s.</p></sec><sec><title>Phonemic decoding efficiency</title><p>The Test of Phonemic Decoding Efficiency (TOWRE: PDE, Torgesen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">1997</xref>) is a norm-referenced measure of decoding accuracy and fluency that requires participants to read a list of decodable pseudowords of increasing difficulty for 45 s.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Intake procedure</title><p>In May, letters were sent to the parents of children who had successfully completed the RCT research protocol (including R, NR, and C participants) and met our recruitment criteria. All participants attended a single imaging session, in which each child was acclimated to the lab and received a child-oriented explanation of the study procedures. A play tunnel and a mock scanner were used to practice the tasks and prepare the child for the scanning environment.</p></sec><sec><title>Imaging and analysis</title><p>All imaging was performed on a research-dedicated Philips Achieva 3T MR scanner.</p><sec><title>Structural imaging</title><p>High resolution 3D T1-weighted anatomical images were acquired (in a sagittal orientation) in just under 6 min. This was an inversion-prepared turbo field echo sequence (IR-TFE) with TI = 916 ms, TR = 7.9 ms, TE = 3.6 ms, SENSE acceleration factor of 2, matrix size 256 × 256 × 170, and FOV 170 mm × 256 mm × 256 mm for isotropic 1 mm<sup>3</sup> resolution. These images were used for subsequent scan prescription and for cortical parcellation.</p></sec><sec><title>Diffusion imaging</title><p>To measure brain tissue microstructure, we acquired high angular resolution diffusion images using a pulsed-gradient spin echo, echo planar imaging (single shot EPI) pulse sequence to image the entire brain at 2.5 mm isotropic resolution (50 slices, 96 × 96 matrix, TE = 65 ms, TR = 8.5 s, SENSE acceleration factor 2). We acquired 10 non-diffusion weighted and 92 diffusion weighted image volumes (92 directions at b = 1600 s/mm<sup>2</sup>).</p></sec><sec><title>Field map</title><p>To correct for EPI distortions, we acquired a field map (1.875 mm × 1.875 mm × 4.934 mm voxels, TE = 2.9 and 3.9 ms, TR = 173 ms, scan time 28 s).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Image analysis</title><p>The image analysis procedure performed for each participant is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. As shown, diffusion weighted images were corrected for image distortions due to both eddy current (Netsch and van Muiswinkel, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">2004</xref>) and static magnetic field errors (Jezzard and Balaban, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">1995</xref>), the latter using the acquired field maps and FSL software<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref>. Cortical reconstruction and volumetric segmentation was performed with the Freesurfer image analysis suite to identify the cortical and subcortical gray matter regions of interest (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) on the T<sub>1</sub>-weighted structural scan. Briefly, this automated process includes motion correction, removal of non-brain tissue (Segonne et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">2004</xref>), segmentation of the subcortical WM and deep gray matter volumetric structures (Fischl et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">2004</xref>), intensity normalization (Sled et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">1998</xref>), tessellation of the gray matter WM boundary, automated topology correction (Fischl et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2001</xref>; Segonne et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">2007</xref>), and surface deformation (Dale and Sereno, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">1993</xref>; Dale et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1999</xref>; Fischl and Dale, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">2000</xref>). Information on Freesurfer is freely available online<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>2</sup></xref>. Regions were registered to the diffusion image space using a 12-parameter affine transformation calculated in FSL.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Procedure used for imaging analysis</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnsys-04-00150-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Regions of interest</bold>. Shown on the left column are lateral and inferior views of ROIs rendered on the inflated surface of a left hemispherical brain. On the right column is a transverse slice of brain showing THA. Eighteen ROIs identified in this paper are labeled in the following manner: a prefix for cerebral hemisphere (L, left hemisphere; R, right hemisphere), a dot following the prefix, and one of the designators: ANG, angular gyrus; FUS, fusiform; IFS, inferior frontal sulcus; INS, insula; OPE, pars opercularis; PLA, planum temporale; STC, superior temporal gyrus; THA, thalamus; TRI, pars triangularis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnsys-04-00150-g002"/></fig><p>A probabilistic tractography algorithm (Behrens et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2003a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2007</xref>), implemented in FSL, was then used to quantify the connectivity among these gray matter regions. Each of the 18 gray matter ROIs was used as a seed region, with the other 8 ROIs in the same hemisphere serving as possible termination regions. WM was used as a waypoint mask (i.e., all paths had to pass through the WM). Streamline tractography was initiated 10,000 times within each voxel of the seed region. The streamlines were propagated along directions sampled from the distribution characterizing the estimated uncertainty in the primary diffusion direction. A pathway is comprised of all the streamlines found connecting seed and target regions. In the current study we were only interested in direct pathways connecting region A to region B. Therefore, paths passing through the thalamus were excluded except when the thalamus was the seed or target region. For each pairing of seed and target regions, the number of connecting streamlines was calculated automatically by FSL. We divided this number by the number of seed voxels in A and used it to quantify the one-way connection ratio, <italic>r</italic>(A− &gt; B). The same procedure was done for <italic>r</italic>(B− &gt; A). The connectivity, or connection strength, between regions A and B was defined as the symmetrized connection ratio, c (A,B) = (r(A− &gt; B) + r(B− &gt; A))/2. For each participant, we calculated the volume of each region of interest (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Because volume varied across participants, we calculated the correlation between region volume and the different behavioral measures. Connectivity was calculated for each of the possible 72 pairs of regions. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> shows the result of these steps, a connectivity matrix, for one of the C participants in the study. An individual connectivity value that deviated from the original sample mean by two standard deviations or more was defined as an outlier and removed from the associated correlation analysis.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Connectivity matrix</bold>. Matrix of connectivity between all intra-hemispherical pairs of <italic>n</italic> = 18 ROIs. Pairs within left-hemisphere are displayed in the lower left half, pairs within right-hemisphere in the upper right half. All connectivity strengths are displayed with a logarithmic grayscale map.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnsys-04-00150-g003"/></fig></sec></sec>ResultsTo test the hypothesis that reading performance was correlated with connectivity of key gray matter regions, we correlated each element of the connectivity matrix with the participants’ scores on standardized tests of reading proficiency. Figure 4 is a visual representation of the correlations between participants’ connectivity estimates and their performance on each of the standardized measures. Within these matrices, left hemisphere connections are in the bottom triangle and right hemisphere connections are in the top triangle. The gray scale denotes significance level, with lighter colors indicating more significant correlations. Because of the small sample size, significant correlations were reported at p &lt; 0.05 uncorrected. Connections with significant correlation at the p &lt; 0.05 level are starred. We investigated age and gender influences on the behavioral and imaging results using two separate one way ANOVAs. Results showed a single significant effect: The left TRI to IFS pathway had a significant gender effect, in which girls had a significantly greater number of WM fibers connecting these regions. In addition, we correlated participant's performance on the behavioral tasks with the volume of each region. We found a positive correlation between the PDE subtest of the TOWRE and the left planum temporal (p = 0.02) and the left superior temporal cortex (p = 0.03).Figure 4Correlation matrices. Matrix of correlations between intra-hemispherical pairs of gray matter regions. Connectivity between each pair of ROIs is correlated with Phonological Decoding Efficiency (A), Sight Word Efficiency (B), Word Attack (C), and Word Identification (D), and the significance level of the correlation is displayed on a logarithmic scale. Significant correlations were marked by a star (*p &lt; 0.05, uncorrected).To facilitate interpretation of the significant connections, scatterplots for each finding are shown in Figures 5 and 6. These scatterplots also represent the relationship with response to instruction. In these plots, the NR participants are red, R participants are blue, and C participants are green.Figure 5Angular to insula scatterplots. Correlation scatterplots for L. INS and L.ANG. (A–D) Scatterplots showing detailed relationship between connectivity and specific test performances. (E) Locations of L.INS and L.ANG. A single NR participant was identified as an outlier and excluded from this analysis.Figure 6Remaining significant correlations. Scatterplots showing correlations between connectivity and behavioral test performance. Each scatterplot corresponds to one pair of gray matter regions: (A) L.TRI and L.IFS, (B) L.THA and L.STC, (C) R.STC and R.TRI, (D) R.THA and R.TRI. Locations of these regions are illustrated in (E).As shown in Figure 5, increased reading score on each of the reading measures is related to greater connectivity between the left ANG and INS; the NR participants generally have lower connectivity than R or C participants. Similarly, performance on the WAT subtest correlated positively with connectivity values between TRI to STC (Figure 6). Scatterplots of this correlation showed that NR participants had lower connectivity than R or C participants (although only one R dataset survived outlier rejection). Alternatively, three negative correlations were found in which poorer readers, and more particularly, NR participants, had a greater magnitude of connectivity between brain regions than the other two groups. Two correlations involve connections to the THAL, yet in different hemispheres of the brain: the first was right THAL to right TRI and the second was left THAL to left STC. The third remaining region was also in the right hemisphere – TRI to STC.Conflict of Interest StatementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.This work was supported in part by the Vanderbilt Kennedy Center Hobbs Discovery grant, Grant R324G060036 from the U.S. Department of Education, Institute of Education Sciences, and the National Institutes of Health through the Biomedical MRI and MRS Training Program T32EB001628.1www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl2surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.eduReferencesAylwardE. H.RichardsT. L.BerningerV. W.NagyW. E.FieldK. M.GrimmeA. C.RichardsA. L.ThomsonJ. B.CramerS. C. (2003). Instructional treatment associated with changes in brain activation in children with dyslexia. Neurology61, 212–21912874401BasserP. J.PajevicS.PierpaoliC.DudaJ.AldroubiA. (2000). In vivo fiber tractography using DT-MRI data. Magn. Reson. Med.44, 625–63210.1002/1522-2594(200010)44:4&lt;625::AID-MRM17&gt;3.0.CO;2-O11025519BeaulieuC.PlewesC.PaulsonL. A.RoyD.SnookL.ConchaL.PhillipsL. (2005). Imaging brain connectivity in children with diverse reading ability. Neuroimage25, 1266–127110.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.12.05315850744BehrensT. E.BergH. J.JbabdiS.RushworthM. F.WoolrichM. W. (2007). Probabilistic diffusion tractography with multiple fibre orientations: what can we gain?Neuroimage34, 144–155 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.09.01817070705BehrensT. E.Johansen-BergH.WoolrichM. W.SmithS. M.Wheeler-KingshottC. A.BoulbyP. A.BarkerG. J.SilleryE. L.SheehanK.CiccarelliO.ThompsonA. J.BradyJ. M.MatthewsP. M. (2003a). Non-invasive mapping of connections between human thalamus and cortex using diffusion imaging. Nat. Neurosci.6, 750–75710.1038/nn107512808459BehrensT. E.WoolrichM. W.JenkinsonM.Johansen-BergH.NunesR. G.ClareS.MatthewsP. M.BradyJ. M.SmithS. M. (2003b). Characterization and propagation of uncertainty in diffusion-weighted MR imaging. Magn. Reson. Med.50, 1077–108810.1002/mrm.1060914587019BinderJ. R.DesaiR. H.GravesW. W.ConantL. L. (2009). Where is the semantic system? A critical review and meta-analysis of functional neuroimaging studies. Cereb. Cortex19, 2767–279610.1093/cercor/bhp05519329570BremS.HadlerP.BucherK.SummersP.MartinE.BrandeisD. (2009). Tuning of the visual word processing system: distinct developmental ERP and fMRI effects. Hum. Brain Mapp.30, 1833–184410.1002/hbm.2075119288464BrunswickN.McCroryE.PriceC. J.FrithC. D.FrithU. (1999). Explicit and implicit processing of words and pseudowords by adult developmental dyslexics: a search for Wernicke's Wortschatz?Brain122, 1901–1917 10.1093/brain/122.10.190110506092ChenC. H.RidlerK.SucklingJ.WilliamsS.FuC. H.Merlo-PichE.BullmoreE. (2007). Brain imaging correlates of depressive symptom severity and predictors of symptom improvement after antidepressant treatment. Biol. Psychiatry62, 407–41410.1016/j.biopsych.2006.09.01817217921ComptonD. L.FuchsD.FuchsL. S.BoutonB.GilbertJ. K.BarqueroL. A.ChoE.CrouchR. C. (2010). Selecting at-risk first-grade readers for early intervention: eliminating false positives and exploring the promise of a two-stage gated screening process. J. Educ. Psychol.102, 327–34010.1037/a001844820689725ConturoT. E.LoriN. F.CullT. S.AkbudakE.SnyderA. Z.ShimonyJ. S.McKinstryR. C.BurtonH.RaichleM. E. (1999). Tracking neuronal fiber pathways in the living human brain. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.96, 10422–1042710.1073/pnas.96.18.1042210468624DaleA. M.FischlB.SerenoM. I. (1999). Cortical surface-based analysis. I. Segmentation and surface reconstruction. Neuroimage9, 179–19410.1006/nimg.1998.03959931268DaleA. M.SerenoM. I. (1993). Improved localization of cortical activity by combining EEG and MEG with MRI cortical surface reconstruction: a linear approach. J. Cogn. Neurosci.5, 162–17610.1162/jocn.1993.5.2.162DavisN.BarqueroL.ComptonD.FuchsL. S.FuchsD.GoreJ.AndersonA. (in press). Functional correlates of children's responsiveness to intervention. Dev. Neuropsychol..14561563DeutschG. K.DoughertyR. F.BammerR.SiokW. T.GabrieliJ. D.WandellB. (2005). Children's reading performance is correlated with white matter structure measured by diffusion tensor imaging. Cortex41, 354–36310.1016/S0010-9452(08)70272-715871600DolanR. J. (2002). Emotion, cognition, and behavior. Science298,1191–119410.1126/science.107635812424363DupontS.BouilleretV.HasbounD.SemahF.BaulacM. (2003). Functional anatomy of the insula: new insights from imaging. Surg. Radiol. Anat.25, 113–11910.1007/s00276-003-0103-412819943FiebachC. J.FriedericiA. D.MullerK.von CramonD. Y. (2002). fMRI evidence for dual routes to the mental lexicon in visual word recognition. J. Cogn. Neurosci.14, 11–2310.1162/08989290231720528511798383FischlB.DaleA. M. (2000). Measuring the thickness of the human cerebral cortex from magnetic resonance images. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.97, 11050–1105510.1073/pnas.20003379710984517FischlB.LiuA.DaleA. M. (2001). Automated manifold surgery: constructing geometrically accurate and topologically correct models of the human cerebral cortex. IEEE Trans. Med. Imaging20, 70–8010.1109/42.90642611293693FischlB.SalatD. H.BusaE.AlbertM.DieterichM.HaselgroveC.van der KouweA.KillianyR.KennedyD.KlavenessS.MontilloA.MakrisN.RosenB.DaleA. M. (2002). Whole brain segmentation: automated labeling of neuroanatomical structures in the human brain. Neuron33, 341–35510.1016/S0896-6273(02)00569-X11832223FischlB.SalatD. H.van der KouweA. J.MakrisN.SegonneF.QuinnB. T.DaleA. M. (2004). Sequence-independent segmentation of magnetic resonance images. Neuroimage23(Suppl. 1), S69 – S8410.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.07.01615501102FrithC. D.SingerT. (2008). The role of social cognition in decision making. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond., B, Biol. Sci.363, 3875–388610.1098/rstb.2008.015618829429FuchsL. S.FuchsD.ComptonD. L. (2004). Monitoring early reading development in first grade: word identification fluency versus nonsense word fluency. Except. Child.7–21GalaburdaA. M.EidelbergD. (1982). Symmetry and asymmetry in the human posterior thalamus. Thalamic lesions in a case of developmental dyslexia. Arch. Neurol.39, 333–3367092609HickokG.BuchsbaumB.HumphriesC.MuftulerT. (2003). Auditory-motor interaction revealed by fMRI: speech, music, and working memory in area Spt. J. Cogn. Neurosci.15, 673–68212965041HorwitzB.RumseyJ. M.DonohueB. C. (1998). Functional connectivity of the angular gyrus in normal reading and dyslexia. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.95, 8939–894410.1073/pnas.95.15.89399671783IDEA, Public Law 108–446 (2004), 118 STAT. 2647, 2657–2658JezzardP.BalabanR. S. (1995). Correction for geometric distortion in echo planar images from B0 field variations. Magn. Reson. Med.34, 65–7310.1002/mrm.19103401117674900Johansen-BergH.MatthewsP. M. (2002). Attention to movement modulates activity in sensori-motor areas, including primary motor cortex. Exp. Brain Res.142, 13–2410.1007/s00221-001-0905-811797080KellerT. A.JustM. A. (2009). Altering cortical connectivity: remediation-induced changes in the white matter of poor readers. Neuron64, 624–63110.1016/j.neuron.2009.10.01820005820KlingbergT.HedenhusM.TempleE.SalzT.GabrieliJ. D.MoseleyM. E.PoldrackR. A. (2000). Microstructure of temporoparietal white matter as a basis for reading ability: evidence from diffusion tensor magnetic resonance imaging. Neuron25, 493–50010.1016/S0896-6273(00)80911-310719902KurthF.ZilesK.FoxP. T.LairdA. R.EickhoffS. B. (2010). A link between the systems: functional differentiation and integration within the human insula revealed by meta-analysis. Brain Struct. Funct.214, 519–53410.1007/s00429-010-0255-z20512376LuoL.O'LearyD. D. (2005). Axon retraction and degeneration in development and disease. Annu. Rev. Neurosci.28, 127–15610.1146/annurev.neuro.28.061604.13563216022592MoriS.CrainB. J.ChackoV. P.van ZijlP. C. (1999). Three-dimensional tracking of axonal projections in the brain by magnetic resonance imaging. Ann. Neurol.45, 265–26910.1002/1531-8249(199902)45:2&lt;265::AID-ANA21&gt;3.0.CO;2-39989633NetschT.van MuiswinkelA. (2004). Quantitative evaluation of image-based distortion correction in diffusion tensor imaging. IEEE Trans. Med. Imaging23, 789–79810.1109/TMI.2004.82747915250631NiogiS. N.McCandlissB. D. (2006). Left lateralized white matter microstructure accounts for individual differences in reading ability and disability. Neuropsychologia44, 2178–218810.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2006.01.01116524602OdegardT. N.RingJ.SmithS.BigganJ.BlackJ. (2008). Differentiating the neural response to intervention in children with developmental dyslexia. Ann. Dyslexia58, 1–1410.1007/s11881-008-0014-518483867O'LearyD. D.StanfieldB. B. (1989). Selective elimination of axons extended by developing cortical neurons is dependent on regional locale: experiments utilizing fetal cortical transplants. J. Neurosci.9, 2230–22462545833PaulesuE.DemonetJ. F.FazioF.McCroryE.ChanoineV.BrunswickN.CappaS. F.CossuS. F.HabibM.FrithC. D.FrithU. (2001). Dyslexia: cultural diversity and biological unity. Science291, 2165–216710.1126/science.105717911251124PortasC. M.ReesG.HowsemanA. M.JosephsO.TurnerR.FrithC. D. (1998). A specific role for the thalamus in mediating the interaction of attention, and arousal in humans. J. Neurosci.18, 8979–89899787003PriceC. J.WiseR. J.WatsonJ. D.PattersonK.HowardD.FrackowiakR. S. (1994). Brain activity during reading. The effects of exposure duration and task. Brain117, 1255–126910.1093/brain/117.6.12557820564PughK. R.MenclW. E.JennerA. R.KatzL.FrostS. J.LeeJ. R.ShaywitzS. E.ShaywitzB. A. (2001). Neurobiological studies of reading and reading disability. J. Commun. Disord.34, 479–49210.1016/S0021-9924(01)00060-011725860PughK. R.MenclW. E.ShaywitzB. A.ShaywitzS. E.FulbrightR. K.ConstableR. T.SkudarskiP.MarchioneK. E.JennerA. R.FletcherJ. M.LibermanA. M.ShankweilerD. P.KatzL.LacadieC.GoreJ. C. (2000). The angular gyrus in developmental dyslexia. Psychol. Sci.11, 51–5610.1111/1467-9280.0021411228843RimrodtS. L.PetersonD. J.DencklaM. B.KaufmannW. E.CuttingL. E. (2010). White matter microstructural differences linked to left perisylvian language network in children with dyslexia. Cortex46, 739–74910.1016/j.cortex.2009.07.00819682675RumseyJ. M.NaceK.DonohueB.WiseD.MaisogJ. M.AndreasonP. (1997). A positron emission tomographic study of impaired word recognition and phonological processing in dyslexic men. Arch. Neurol.54, 562–5739152113SarkariS.SimosP. G.FletcherJ. M.CatilloE. M.BrieierJ. I.PapanicolaouA. C. (2002). Contributions of magnetic source imaging to the understanding of dyslexia. Semin. Pediatr. Neurol.9, 229–23810.1053/spen.2002.3550612350044SegonneF.DaleA. M.BusaE.GlessnerM.SalatD.HahnH. K.FischlB. (2004). A hybrid approach to the skull stripping problem in MRI. Neuroimage22, 1060–107510.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.03.03215219578SegonneF.PachecoJ.FischlB. (2007). Geometrically accurate topology-correction of cortical surfaces using nonseparating loops. IEEE Trans. Med. Imaging26, 518–52910.1109/TMI.2006.88736417427739ShaywitzB. A.ShaywitzS. E.BlachmanB. A.PughK. R.FulbrightR. K.SkudlarskiP.MenclW. E.ConstableR.T.HolahanJ.M.MarchioneK. E.FletcherJ. M.LyonG. R.GoreJ. C. (2004). Development of left occipitotemporal systems for skilled reading in children after a phonologically-based intervention. Biol. Psychiatry55, 926–93310.1016/j.biopsych.2003.12.01915110736ShaywitzS. E.ShaywitzB. A. (2003). Dyslexia (specific reading disability). Pediatr. Rev.24, 147–15310.1542/pir.24-5-14712728187ShaywitzS. E.ShaywitzB. A.FulbrightR. K.SkudlarskiP.MenclW. E.ConstableR. T.PughK. R.HolahanJ. M.MarchioneK. E.FletcherJ. M.LyonG. R.GoreJ. C. (2003). Neural systems for compensation and persistence: young adult outcome of childhood reading disability. Biol. Psychiatry1, 25–3310.1016/S0006-3223(02)01836-X12842305ShaywitzB. A.ShaywitzS. E.PughK. R.MenclW. E.FulbrightR. K.SkudlarskiP.ConstableR. T.MarchioneK. E.FletcherJ. M.LyonG. R.GoreJ. C. (2002). Disruption of posterior brain systems for reading in children with developmental dyslexia. Biol. Psychiatry52, 101–11010.1016/S0006-3223(02)01365-312114001SimosP. G.FletcherJ. M.BergmanE.BreierJ. I.FoormanB. R.CastilloE. M.DavisR. N.FitzgeraldM.PapanicolaouA.C. (2002). Dyslexia-specific brain activation profile becomes normal following successful remedial training. Neurology58, 1203–121311971088SimosP. G.FletcherJ. M.DentonC.SarkariS.Billingsley-MarshallR.PapanicolaouA. C. (2006). Magnetic source imaging studies of dyslexia interventions. Dev. Neuropsychol.30, 591–61110.1207/s15326942dn3001_416925476SledJ. G.ZijdenbosA. P.EvansA. C. (1998). A nonparametric method for automatic correction of intensity nonuniformity in MRI data. IEEE Trans. Med. Imaging17, 87–9710.1109/42.6686989617910TorgesenJ. K.WagnerR. K.RashotteC. A. (1997). Test of Word Reading Efficiency. Austin, Tx: Pro:EdTurkeltaubP. E.EdenG. F.JonesK. M.ZeffiroT. A. (2002). Meta-analysis of the functional neuroanatomy of single-word reading: method and validation. Neuroimage16, 765–78010.1006/nimg.2002.113112169260TurkeltaubP. E.GareauL.FlowersD. L.ZeffiroT. A.EdenG. F. (2003). Development of neural mechanisms for reading. Nat. Neurosci.6, 767–77310.1038/nn106512754516WoodcockR. W. (1998). Woodcock Reading Mastery Test-Revised/Normative Update. Circle Pines, MN: AGS
