<?xml version="1.0"?>
Contemp Oncol (Pozn)Contemp Oncol (Pozn)WOContemporary Oncology1428-25261897-4309Termedia Publishing House49257302762410.5114/wo.2016.60065Review PaperAcupuncture: could it become everyday practice in oncology?Kilian-KitaAnetaPuskulluogluMirosławaKonopkaKamilKrzemienieckiKrzysztofDepartment of Clinical Oncology, University Hospital in Krakow, Krakow, PolandAddress for correspondence: Mirosława Puskulluoglu, Department of Clinical Oncology, University Hospital in Krakow, Śniadeckich 10, 31-501 Krakow, Poland. e-mail: mircoll@wp.pl1462016201620211912316320141672014Copyright © 2016 Termedia2016This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) License, allowing third parties to copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format and to remix, transform, and build upon the material, provided the original work is properly cited and states its license.Acupuncture is a complementary and alternative medical treatment (CAM) which is increasingly used in the care of cancer patients. Traditionally derived from Chinese medicine, nowadays it is becoming a part of evidence-based oncology. The use of acupuncture in these patients has been recommended by the American Cancer Society (ACS) for the treatment of side effects associated with conventional cancer therapy and cancer-related ailments. A growing body of evidence supports the use of acupuncture in the treatment of cancer-induced pain and chemotherapy-related nausea and vomiting. Also other indications, such as xerostomia, fatigue, hot flashes, anxiety and peripheral neuropathy, are being constantly evaluated. This article summarizes the most important discoveries related to the possible usefulness of this method in contemporary oncology. Emphasis is placed on the results of randomized controlled trials with an adequate level of evidence. However, explanation of the mechanisms responsible for these effects requires confirmation in further studies with an adequate level of evidence. In future, acupuncture may become an interesting and valuable addition to conventional medicine.acupuncturecancercomplementary and alternative treatmentside effectssupportive treatmentWhat is acupuncture?Acupuncture is a method of treatment that has its origins in Traditional Chinese Medicine and is based on over 4,000 years of empirical evidence. The technique involves the insertion of thin needles into specific locations (energy points) on the patient's body along energy pathways or meridians. According to Chinese philosophy, the hypothetical substance Qi (vital energy) flows in the human body along the meridians, and blockage of Qi leads to a particular ailment [18]. There are 12 main and 8 extra meridians. All the main meridians consist of internal channels connected with the 12 body organs and the external channels spreading symmetrically on the skin surface. The literature describes around 360 energy points located on the external parts of the meridians. Acupuncture is considered to cure diseases by stimulating particular acupoints and removing blockage of Qi [19]. Figures 1–3 present acupuncture meridian pathways.Fig. 1The course of main meridians on the anterior surface of the bodyFig. 2The course of main meridians on the posterior surface of the bodyFig. 3The course of main meridians on the lateral surface of the bodyAlthough acupuncture has been studied extensively in both animal and human models, little is known about its mechanisms that could explain acupuncture's therapeutic qualities. Table 1 shows suggested mechanisms of acupuncture. This treatment method has been the focus of increased interest, which has resulted in a growing number of studies.
Table 1Possible mechanisms of action of acupuncturePossible mechanisms of action of acupunctureEffectsReferences
Local inflammatory response
HistamineProstaglandinsChemokines

increasing permeability and dilatation of the capillariespromotion of blood flow to the siteinitiation of the migration of phagocytes and signaling them to increase production of various mediators
[20]
Cytokines
decreased expression of IL-6, βNGF and TIMP-1reducing proinflammatory cytokines IL-1, IL-6, TNF-α through activation of CB2 receptors

anti-inflammatory effectantinociceptive effect on inflammatory pain
[21, 22]
ANS
increasing synchronization between the two branches of the ANS and improvement of HRV

mediating global physiological regulation
[23]
Stem cells
increasing levels of non-differentiated progenitor of stem cells CD133+ and CD34– cell in the serum of patients after spinal cord injurypromotion of proliferation and differentiation of neural stem cells, up-regulation of the growth factors and the expression of VEGF mRNA in the rats ischemic brain

spinal cord stem cell mobilizationprotection cerebral injuries after ischemia and promotion nerve regeneration
[24]IL – interleukin; NGF – nerve growth factor; TIMP-1 – tissue inhibitors of metalloproteinase-1; CB2 – cannabinoid receptor 2; ANS – autonomic nervous system; HRV – heart rate variability; CD – cluster of differentiation; VEGF – vascular endothelial growth factorAcupuncture as supportive treatmentChemotherapy agents are considered to be medications with the most severe side effects, which in many cases may force the patient to abandon therapy. Because of that, proper alleviation of side effects is most crucial. Acupuncture should not be seen as a replacement for modern medicines, but rather an adjunct with a low level of procedure-related complications that may enhance efficacy and in some cases allow the dosage of other drugs to be reduced. Acupuncture as part of supportive treatment in oncology has been tested for numerous indications. The strongest evidence from a randomized controlled trial (RCT) with low risk of bias supports the use of acupuncture for control of nausea and vomiting related to chemotherapy [25]. This indication seems to be very important, as the high emetogenicity of many cytostatic agents is hard to control even with three-drug therapy [26]. Despite many RCTs on treatment of other chemotherapy-induced side effects, the level of evidence is not yet satisfactory, but considering its relative safety, acupuncture may be useful in everyday practice. Descriptions of these clinical trials on the effectiveness of acupuncture in minimizing cancer treatment-related side effects are summarized in Table 2.
Table 2Possible mechanisms of action of acupuncture and its effectiveness in the treatment of various types of ailments related to cancer therapyConditionPossible molecular mechanisms of actionClinical trialsReferences
Randomized control trials

Nausea and chemotherapy-induced vomiting
Multiple mechanismsinfluences the endogenous opioid system and changes the serotonin transmissionhas effects on the gastric myoelectrical activityincreases vagal modulationinfluences the cerebellar vestibular activities
RCT:acupuncture significantly reduced the number of episodes of emesis between three groups: electroacupuncture, minimal needling and pharmacotherapy alone (median number of episodes, 5, 10, and 15, respectively; p &lt; 0.001)
[26]
Cancer pain
Opioid peptidesincreased concentration level observed in the serum and brain tissue after acupunctureNeuromodulationactivity modulation of the human brain areas (activated in acute or chronic pain) during acupuncture in neuroimaging (fMRI, PET, EEG)
Meta-analysis of RCTs:acupuncture did not make a better effect than drug therapy (n = 886; RR 1.12; 95% CI: 0.98 to 1.28; p = 0.09)combination therapy (acupuncture with drug therapy) was more effective than drug therapy alone (n = 437; RR 1.36; 95% CI: 1.13–1.64; p = 0.003)
[7, 8, 27–31]
Chemotherapy-induced leucopoenia
Multiple mechanismspromotes the release of WBC from bone marrowprolonging the life of WBCincreases the activity of CSFspromotes the proliferation of haemopoietic stem cellsreduces haemopoietic stem cells damage by chemotherapyimproves microcirculation
Meta-analysis of RCTs from China:acupuncture was effective in increasing WBC levelmean difference in the WBC level was 1221 WBC/µl (95% CI: 636–1807, p &lt; 0.0001)Pilot study from USA:Significant increase in the median leukocyte value for baseline value after acupuncture (p = 0.046):8600 WBC/µl, 95% CI: 4800–12000 in the test group4400 WBC/µl, 95% CI: 2300–10000 in the control groupDecrease in the frequency of occurrence of severe leucopoenia (p = 0.02):30% in the test group90% in the control group
[11, 32–34]
AI-induced arthralgias
Multiple mechanismsincreases the opioid peptides levelimproves blood flow
RCT:Significant difference between the test group and the control group at 6 weeks of treatment was observed in:the mean BPI-SF worst pain scores (on the scale from 0–10, 10 being the most intense pain; 3.0 vs. 5.5; p &lt; 0.001)pain severity (2.6 vs. 4.5; p = 0.003)pain-related interference (2.5 vs. 4.5; p = 0.002)
[35]
Radiation-induced xerostomia
Neural transmission:bilateral activation of the brain function area in fMRI that is responsible for salivary productionCGRP:increase the release of CGRP, which positively affects the salivary flow rates
RCT:In the acupuncture group as compared to the control group was observed:significant reduction in dry mouth symptoms measured by means of the VAS (p &lt; 0.05)increase in unstimulated and stimulated salivary flow and production (p &lt; 0.001)
[9, 36, 37]
Hot flushes
Neuromodulationincreases endorphin release and decrease noradrenalin and serotonin activity in the central nervous system (make thermoregulation more stable)CGRPdirect effect on the release of vasodilator – CGRP in peripheral nerve endings
RCT:Significant reduction of hot flushes and sleep disturbances was observed in:16 patients (52%) of the test group7 patients (24%) of the control group.effect was obtained after the second acupuncture session and lasted for the next 12 weeks after treatment
[38, 39]
Anxiety-like behaviour and stress
NPY and CRFincreases NPY mRNA levels and reduces CRF mRNA levels in the amygdala of rats after acupuncture
Randomized controlled experimental study:after 10 acupuncture sessions patients with generalized anxiety disorders demonstrated significantly reduced anxiety (85.7%) following compared to a placebo group
[13, 40, 41]
Non RCT studies

Chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy
Purinergetic signalingstimulating purinergic signals (increase in the release of adenine nucleotides and adenosine from skin keratinocytes) and neurotransmission in the central and peripheral nervous system
Pilot study:acupuncture treatment for 6 weeks was effective in 82% (n = 14) of patients
[16]
Cancer-related fatigue

multicomponent
Prospective, clinical study:significant improvement after 2 weeks of treatment was observed with regard to: general fatigue (p &lt; 0.001), physical fatigue (p = 0.016), activity (p = 0.004) and motivation (p = 0.024), and lasted for 2 weeks after the end of the intervention
[12]
CRT-induced dysphagia
Multiple mechanismsincrease the saliva productionrestore swallowing reflexinhibition the fibrosis process
Case series study:The treatment was effective in: 9/10 patients (90%) of the test group (subjective improvement in the swallowing function, decrease in dry mouth symptoms, pain and fatigue level)in 6/7 patients (86%) it was possible to remove the PEG tube (a median time of 114 days from the last CRT session and acupuncture treatment, the range from 49 to 368 days)
[42]
Hiccup
Modulation of the hiccup reflex arclocally: changing blood perfusion, activating the autonomic nervous system, regulating inflammatory mediatorscentrally: influences the hiccup center by modulating the secretion of neurotransmitters and neurohormones (endogenous opioids, norepinephrine, serotonin, substance P)
Case series study:After 1–3 courses of treatment (over a 1–7-day period) was observed:complete symptom relief in 13 patients (81%, p &lt; 0.0001);partial symptom relief in 3 patients (18.8%)substantial improvement in discomfort (p &lt; 0.0001), fatigue (p = 0.0078) and anxiety (p &lt; 0.0001)
[43]
Lymphoedema

unclear
Pilot study:After 4 weeks of treatment, 30% reduction of oedema in comparison to the baseline results was observed in 4/9 patients (44.5%)[15]RCTs – randomized controlled trials; fMRI – functional magnetic resonance imaging; RR – relative risk; PET – positron emission tomography; EEG – electroencephalography; NPY – neuropeptide Y; CRF – corticotropin-releasing factor; CGRP – calcitonin gene-related peptide; VAS – visual analogue score; CRT – chemoradiation therapy; PEG – percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy; AI – aromatase inhibitors; BPI-SF – the Brief Pain Inventory – Short Form; WBC – white blood cells; CSFs – colony-stimulating factorsLevel of evidence issueA recently published systemic review stated that other indications, such as pain, xerostomia, vasomotor symptoms, fatigue, mood disorders, and insomnia, were not evaluated in RCTs with an appropriate level of evidence [44]. One of the major problems with the reviewed studies is their poor methodological quality, mostly difficulty with blinding and a low number of subjects. Also the optimal design of such studies (acupuncture vs placebo, acupuncture vs sham acupuncture) has not been established yet [45]. In spite of satisfactory results in most of these studies, further research on a larger group of patients is necessary.SummaryIn an oncological setting, acupuncture is still being constantly reviewed. Nevertheless, the present available evidence suggests that acupuncture may become a safe, low-cost and efficient form of complementary therapy in modern oncology. The potential role of acupuncture has been found in alleviation of various symptoms, but the data from the majority of clinical studies on acupuncture are heterogeneous. The incomplete description of procedural methodology and insufficient patient groups limit their value. Thus, further research on a larger scale on the potential use of acupuncture in contemporary oncology is required. It should be emphasized that alternative medicine may become the source of a number of interesting concepts worth examining and testing in research and clinical settings.AcknowledgmentsThe authors would like to thank Ms Joanna Gołąb for editing the article.The authors declare no conflict of interest.References1MolassiotisAFernadez-OrtegaPPudDUse of complementary and alternative medicine in cancer patients: a European surveyAnn. Oncol20051665563156990212HökJTishelmanCPlonerAMapping patterns of complementary and alternative medicine use in cancer: an explorative cross-sectional study of individuals with reported positive “exceptional” experiencesBMC Complement Altern Med2008848186913933WhiteAA cumulative review of the range and incidence of significant adverse events associated with acupunctureAcupunct Med20042212233155519364StreitbergerKEzzoJSchneiderAAcupuncture for nausea and vomiting: an update of clinical and experimental studiesAuton Neurosci200612910717169506595YangYZhangYJingNElectroacupuncture at Zusanli (ST 36) for treatment of nausea and vomiting caused by the chemotherapy of the malignant tumor: a multicentral randomized controlled trialZhongguo Zhen Jiu2009299558200884126GottschlingSReindlTKMeyerSAcupuncture to alleviate chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in pediatric oncology – a randomized multicenter crossover pilot trialKlin Padiatr200822036570189496727DangWYangJClinical study on acupuncture treatment of stomach carcinoma painJ Tradit Chin Med199818318104372608AlimiDRubinoCPichard-LéandriEAnalgesic effect of auricular acupuncture for cancer pain: a randomized, blinded, controlled trialJ Clin Oncol20032141206146154409BragaFPLemos JuniorCAAlvesFAMigliariDAAcupuncture for the prevention of radiation-induced xerostomia in patients with head and neck cancerBraz Oral Res20112518052153764510LiljegrenAGunnarssonPLandgrenB-MReducing vasomotor symptoms with acupuncture in breast cancer patients treated with adjuvant tamoxifen: a randomized controlled trialBreast Cancer Res. Treat.201213579182115369911LuWMatulonisUADoherty-GilmanAAcupuncture for chemotherapy-induced neutropenia in patients with gynecologic malignancies: a pilot randomized, sham-controlled clinical trialJ Altern Complement Med200915745531955259712MolassiotisASyltPDigginsHThe management of cancer-related fatigue after chemotherapy with acupuncture and acupressure: a randomised controlled trialComplement Ther Med200715228371805472413EichHAgelinkMWLehmannEAcupuncture in patients with minor depressive episodes and generalized anxiety. Results of an experimental studyFortschr Neurol Psychiatr200068137441075884514FriskJKällströmA-CWallNAcupuncture improves health-related quality-of-life (HRQoL) and sleep in women with breast cancer and hot flushesSupport Care Cancer201220715242146862615CassilethBRVan ZeeKJChanYA safety and efficacy pilot study of acupuncture for the treatment of chronic lymphoedemaAcupunct Med20112917022168549816DonaldGKTobinIStringerJEvaluation of acupuncture in the management of chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathyAcupunct Med20112923032187592917NIHConsensus Conference. AcupunctureJAMA1998280151824980973318ZhaoXLHanJXThe connotation of the Quantum Traditional Chinese Medicine and the exploration of its experimental technology system for diagnosisDrug Discov Ther20137225322442365319PerlowBWAcupuncture: its theory and use in general practiceProc R Soc Med1973664268471629220ChaeYHongM-SKimG-HProtein array analysis of cytokine levels on the action of acupuncture in carrageenan-induced inflammationNeurol Res200729S5581735964221SuT-FZhaoY-QZhangL-HElectroacupuncture reduces the expression of proinflammatory cytokines in inflamed skin tissues through activation of cannabinoid CB2 receptorsEur J Pain201216624352233728522AndersonBNielsenAMcKeeDAcupuncture and heart rate variability: a systems level approach to understanding mechanismExplore (NY)20128991062238556423MoldenhauerSBurgaunerMHellwegRMobilization of CD133(+)CD34(-) cells in healthy individuals following whole-body acupuncture for spinal cord injuriesJ Neurosci Res2010881645502002996424YangZChenPYuHResearch advances in treatment of cerebral ischemic injury by acupuncture of conception and governor vessels to promote nerve regenerationZhong Xi Yi Jie He Xue Bao20121019242223727025ShenJWengerNGlaspyJElectroacupuncture for control of myeloablative chemotherapy-induced emesis: A randomized controlled trialJAMA20002842755611110518226GrallaRJde WitRHerrstedtJAntiemetic efficacy of the neurokinin-1 antagonist, aprepitant, plus a 5HT3 antagonist and a corticosteroid in patients receiving anthracyclines or cyclophosphamide in addition to high-dose cisplatin: analysis of combined data from two Phase III randomized clinical trialsCancer200510486481597366927HanJ-SAcupuncture and endorphinsNeurosci Lett2004361258611513594228HanJSXieGXZhouZFAcupuncture mechanisms in rabbits studied with microinjection of antibodies against beta-endorphin, enkephalin and substance PNeuropharmacology19842315620177229WuGCZhuJCaoXInvolvement of opioid peptides of the preoptic area during electroacupuncture analgesiaAcupunct Electrother Res19952016757232730HsiehJCTuCHChenFPActivation of the hypothalamus characterizes the acupuncture stimulation at the analgesic point in human: a positron emission tomography studyNeurosci Lett200130710581142731131ChoiTYLeeMSKimTHAcupuncture for the treatment of cancer pain: a systematic review of randomised clinical trialsSupport Care Cancer2012201147582244736632ZhaoXWangHTianKReview on mechanisms of acupuncture-moxibustion against leukopenia due to chemotherapy induced myeloid inhibitionAcupuncture Research2003170333ZhaoXHuangXWangHStudy on the Mechanism of Acupuncture in Fighting Chemotherapeutic Marrow Depression and Enhancing WBCShanghai Journal of Acupuncture and Moxibustion20031293334LuWHuDDean-ClowerEAcupuncture for chemotherapy-induced leukopenia: exploratory meta-analysis of randomized controlled trialsJ Soc Integr Oncol200751101730980835CrewKDCapodiceJLGreenleeHRandomized, blinded, sham-controlled trial of acupuncture for the management of aromatase inhibitor-associated joint symptoms in women with early-stage breast cancerJ Clin Oncol2010281154602010096336DengGHouBLHolodnyAICassilethBRFunctional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) changes and saliva production associated with acupuncture at LI-2 acupuncture point: a randomized controlled studyBMC Complement Altern Med20088371860601937DawidsonIAngmar-MânssonBBlomMSensory stimulation (acupuncture) increases the release of calcitonin gene-related peptide in the saliva of xerostomia sufferersNeuropeptides199933244501065749938Spetz HolmA-CEFriskJHammarMLAcupuncture as treatment of hot flashes and the possible role of calcitonin gene-related PeptideEvid Based Complement Alternat Med201220125793212211054539BokmandSFlygerHAcupuncture relieves menopausal discomfort in breast cancer patients: a prospective, double blinded, randomized studyBreast20132232032290694840ParkHJChaeYJangJThe effect of acupuncture on anxiety and neuropeptide Y expression in the basolateral amygdala of maternally separated ratsNeurosci Lett2005377179841575552241ChaeYYeomMHanJHEffect of acupuncture on anxiety-like behavior during nicotine withdrawal and relevant mechanismsNeurosci Lett2008430981021806069742LuWPosnerMRWaynePAcupuncture for dysphagia after chemoradiation therapy in head and neck cancer: a case series reportIntegr Cancer Ther20109284902071337443GeAXRyanMEGiacconeGAcupuncture treatment for persistent hiccups in patients with cancerJ Altern Complement Med20101681162057570244GarciaMKMcQuadeJHaddadRSystematic review of acupuncture in cancer care: a synthesis of the evidenceJ Clin Oncol201331952602334152945WhiteARFilshieJCummingsTMInternational Acupuncture Research ForumClinical trials of acupuncture: consensus recommendations for optimal treatment, sham controls and blindingComplement Ther Med200192374512184353
