<?xml version="1.0"?>
Neuropsychol RevNeuropsychol RevNeuropsychology Review1040-73081573-6660Springer USNew York4762927930110.1007/s11065-015-9301-1ReviewMultisensory Stimulation to Improve Low- and Higher-Level Sensory Deficits after Stroke: A Systematic ReviewTingaAngelica MariaVisser-MeilyJohanna Maria Augustavan der SmagtMaarten JeroenVan der StigchelStefanvan EeRaymondNijboerTanja Cornelia Wilhelmina0031 30 253 3572t.c.w.nijboer@uu.nlDepartment of Experimental Psychology, Hemholtz Institute, Utrecht University, Utrecht, The Netherlands Brain Center Rudolf Magnus, and Center of Excellence for Rehabilitation Medicine, University Medical Center Utrecht, and De Hoogstraat Rehabilitation, Utrecht, The Netherlands Department of Brain, Body &amp; Behavior, Philips Research Laboratories, Eindhoven, The Netherlands Department of Biophysics, Donders Institute, Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands Laboratory of Experimental Psychology, University of Leuven, Leuven, Belgium 2110201521102015201626739131520151102015© The Author(s) 2015Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.The aim of this systematic review was to integrate and assess evidence for the effectiveness of multisensory stimulation (i.e., stimulating at least two of the following sensory systems: visual, auditory, and somatosensory) as a possible rehabilitation method after stroke. Evidence was considered with a focus on low-level, perceptual (visual, auditory and somatosensory deficits), as well as higher-level, cognitive, sensory deficits. We referred to the electronic databases Scopus and PubMed to search for articles that were published before May 2015. Studies were included which evaluated the effects of multisensory stimulation on patients with low- or higher-level sensory deficits caused by stroke. Twenty-one studies were included in this review and the quality of these studies was assessed (based on eight elements: randomization, inclusion of control patient group, blinding of participants, blinding of researchers, follow-up, group size, reporting effect sizes, and reporting time post-stroke). Twenty of the twenty-one included studies demonstrate beneficial effects on low- and/or higher-level sensory deficits after stroke. Notwithstanding these beneficial effects, the quality of the studies is insufficient for valid conclusion that multisensory stimulation can be successfully applied as an effective intervention. A valuable and necessary next step would be to set up well-designed randomized controlled trials to examine the effectiveness of multisensory stimulation as an intervention for low- and/or higher-level sensory deficits after stroke. Finally, we consider the potential mechanisms of multisensory stimulation for rehabilitation to guide this future research.KeywordsStrokeHemianopiaPerceptual disordersNeglectRehabilitationMultisensoryReviewissue-copyright-statement© Springer Science+Business Media New York 2016<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Literature Search and Article Selection</title><p>The literature search (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) was conducted in the Scopus and PubMed databases for articles that have been published before May 2015. Date last searched was May 5, 2015. The string used to search for articles was: (TITLE-ABS-KEY (“multisensory” or “multimodal integration” or “multimodal stimul*” or “audiovisual” or “audio-visual” or “visuo-auditory” or “visuotactile” or “visuo-tactile” or “tactile-visual” or “audiotactile” or “audio-tactile” or “tactile-audio” or “visual* enhanc*” or “tactile enhanc*” or “audit* enhanc*” or “somatosens* enhanc*”) AND (TITLE-ABS-KEY (“hemianop*” or “visual field defect” or “visual field deficit” or “auditory disorder” or “auditory deficit” or “auditory defect” or “somatosensory disorder” or “somatosensory defect” or “somatosensory deficit” or “perceptual disorder” or “perceptual deficit” or “perceptual defect” or “neglect” or “stroke”)) AND NOT (TITLE-ABS-KEY (“migraine” or “synesthesia” or “synaesthesia” or “spinal cord injury” or “autism” or “aphasia” or “schizophrenia” or “dyslexia”)). Documents retrieved from this initial search that were classified as an article by Scopus or as a journal article by PubMed and as being written in English were screened on their titles and abstracts. Studies were included which evaluated the effects of multisensory stimulation on patients with low- or higher-level sensory deficits caused by stroke. In all included studies at least two sensory modalities were stimulated at the exact same moment in time. The stimulation had to be passive and not active (i.e., the stimulation itself had to be independent of any action by the patient). Excluded were animal studies, studies in healthy participants (e.g., Laurienti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2004</xref>; van Ee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2009</xref>), reviews, and studies of which the full article was not available. Articles that focused on competition of multisensory attention in patients with extinction were excluded as well. The included articles were read completely and their references were scanned for relevant articles that might also meet criteria for inclusion. In total, 21 articles met the criteria for eligibility and were included for review and quality assessment.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Schematic of the literature search and article selection used by the authors to identify studies on multisensory stimulation in stroke patients</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11065_2015_9301_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Quality Assessment</title><p>The quality of the included studies was assessed based on the following eight elements (following Spreij et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2014</xref>): 1) randomization; 2) inclusion of control patient group; 3) blinding of participants; 4) blinding of researchers; 5) follow-up (i.e., subsequent examination of participants); 6) group size; 7) reporting effect sizes; and 8) reporting time post-stroke. Studies could score 1 or 0 on each element, when it was dealt with in a sufficient or insufficient way respectively. Additionally, an element was scored as 0 if it could not be inferred from the article. If these quality elements were not sufficiently dealt with, the effect of an intervention might have been either under- or overestimated (Tijssen and Assendelft <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2008</xref>).</p><p>The criteria for sufficient <italic>randomization</italic> were randomized allocation to an intervention or randomized or counterbalanced presentation of the order of conditions. <italic>Inclusion of control patient group</italic> was sufficient if a control group of patients receiving either an alternative form of treatment or no intervention was included. When patients and researchers were prevented from having access to certain information that might have influenced them and thereby the results, the criteria for <italic>blinding of participants</italic> and <italic>blinding of researchers</italic> respectively were sufficiently dealt with. The criteria for sufficient <italic>follow</italic>-<italic>up</italic> were incorporation of a follow-up in the study’s design and disclosure of the total number of losses-to-follow-up (i.e., dropouts). The element <italic>group size</italic> was scored as 1 when 10 or more patients were included in a within-subjects design or when 10 or more patients were included in each group in a between-subject design (this criterion is based on the common group size in fundamental studies in healthy participants [10–12 participants] and is used in other reviews as well [e.g., Spreij et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2014</xref>]). Additionally, <italic>reporting effect sizes</italic> and <italic>reporting time post</italic>-<italic>stroke</italic> were sufficiently dealt with when effect sizes and time post-stroke respectively were reported. If none of the elements were sufficiently dealt with, the study would receive a total score of 0, if all of the elements were sufficiently dealt with, the study would receive a total score of 8. Based on the study’s total score, its quality was classified as high (total score ≥ 6), moderate (total score ≥ 3 and ≤ 5), or low (total score ≤ 2).</p></sec></sec>Quality AssessmentIn the section above the included studies on multisensory stimulation after stroke were discussed. Overall, twenty out of twenty-one studies reported a beneficial effect of multisensory stimulation in improving sensory deficits. In this section we assess the discussed studies on 1) randomization; 2) inclusion of control patient group; 3) blinding of participants; 4) blinding of researchers; 5) follow-up; 6) group size; 7) reporting effect sizes; and 8) reporting time post-stroke (Table 5).Table 5Scores of the quality assessment of the discussed studies, based on eight elements a
StudyRandomization of intervention or conditionsInclusion of control patient groupBlinding of participantsBlinding of researchersFollow-upGroup sizeReporting effect sizesReporting time post-strokeTotalQualityFrassinetti et al. 2005
100000001lowLeo et al. 2008
000001012lowTen Brink et al. 2015
000000011lowCecere et al. 2014
000000011lowBrown et al. 2008
100000012lowSchendel and Robertson 2004
100000012lowSmith et al. 2008
100000012lowPassamonti et al. 2009a
000000011lowBolognini et al. 2005a
000010012lowPassamonti et al. 2009b
000111014moderateKeller and Lefin-Rank 2010
110001014moderateBolognini et al. 2005b
100000012lowNewport et al. 2001
100000012lowSerino et al. 2007
100001013moderateCalamaro et al. 1995
000000000lowSoroker et al. 1995
000000000lowFrassinetti et al. 2002
100000012lowvan Vleet and Robertson 2006
100100013moderateLàdavas et al. 1997
100001013moderatedi Pellegrino and Frassinetti 2000
100000012lowSambo et al. 2012
100000113moderate
a 0 = element was dealt with insufficiently; 1 = element was dealt with sufficientlyStudy CharacteristicsOf the 21 discussed studies, only 1 (Keller and Lefin-Rank 2010) consisted of a between-subjects design. The other studies were within-subjects designs, 6 (di Pellegrino and Frassinetti 2000; Newport et al. 2001; Schendel and Robertson 2004; Bolognini et al. 2005b; van Vleet and Robertson 2006; Cecere et al. 2014) of which were single case studies. On a 8-point scale (representing the 8 elements on which the articles were assessed, with 8 indicating the highest and 0 the lowest possible score), the average total score for all studies was 2 (SD = 1.1, range 0–4). Based on the total scores, 6 studies were of moderate quality (4 studies had a total score of 3, and 2 studies had a total score of 4) and fifteen were of low quality (2 studies had a total score of 0, 4 studies had a total score of 1, and 9 studies had a total score of 2). The average score for studies on visual field defects was 2 (11 studies), on auditory deficits 2 (1 study), on somatosensory deficits 2.5 (2 studies), and on neglect 2 (9 studies). Of the 21 studies, only a single study (Smith et al. 2008), which included patients with hemianopia, did not report beneficial effects of multisensory stimulation, this study was assessed with a total score of 2.All discussed studies included detection, localization, exploration, discrimination and/or identification outcome measures in their design. Only 3 of the 21 studies discussed (all on hemianopia; Bolognini et al. 2005a; Passamonti et al. 2009b; Keller and Lefin-Rank 2010) included ADL outcome measures in their design, rendering the discussed studies’ foci mostly experimental.Randomization and Inclusion of Control GroupIdeally, studies investigating the effect of an intervention should have a group of patients receiving an intervention and a control group of patients, either not receiving any intervention or receiving a ‘control intervention’ (Higgins et al. 2011). Only a single study (Keller and Lefin-Rank 2010) had incorporated a control patient group: two randomly allocated groups of patients with hemianopia or quadrantanopia received either multisensory or unisensory training. The study demonstrated that patients benefited more from multisensory training than unisensory training.In all the other discussed studies, each patient participated in at least two different conditions, namely an experimental condition (with multisensory stimulation) and a control condition (without multisensory stimulation). In this way, effects of multisensory stimulation could be compared within patients. Twelve of twenty within-subjects design studies (Làdavas et al. 1997; di Pellegrino and Frassinetti 2000; Newport et al. 2001; Frassinetti et al. 2002; Schendel and Robertson 2004; Bolognini et al. 2005b; Frassinetti et al. 2005; van Vleet and Robertson 2006; Serino et al. 2007; Brown et al. 2008; Smith et al. 2008; Sambo et al. 2012) reported that they had randomized or counterbalanced the different conditions, in the other studies this was not reported.To allow for monitoring of ‘practice effects’ and verification of improvement of performance toward normal levels, a control group of healthy participants is very useful. Only six of the studies incorporated a control group of healthy subjects (Calamaro et al. 1995; Soroker et al. 1995; Newport et al. 2001; Passamonti et al. 2009b; Serino et al. 2007; Sambo et al. 2012) but in one study (Passamonti et al. 2009b) the healthy control group did not receive the exact experimental training as the patients. These studies demonstrated that the effect of multisensory stimulation was larger in patients compared to healthy controls (Newport et al. 2001; Passamonti et al. 2009b; Sambo et al. 2012) or that patients could perform on the level of healthy controls when multisensory information was presented (Calamaro et al. 1995). Moreover, these studies demonstrated that multisensory stimulation could lead to improvements both in patients and healthy controls (Soroker et al. 1995) or in patients and healthy controls with a low sensory acuity only (Serino et al. 2007).Blinding of Participants and ResearchersOnly three of the twenty-one studies reported that researchers were blinded for one important aspect (van Vleet and Robertson 2006; Passamonti et al. 2009b; Keller and Lefin-Rank 2010). Yet, in one of these studies (Keller and Lefin-Rank 2010) not all researchers were blinded. The two studies that dealt with blinding of researchers sufficiently demonstrated that multisensory stimulation could be beneficial in patients with hemianopia (Passamonti et al. 2009b) or neglect (van Vleet and Robertson 2006). None of the studies reported that patients were blinded. As a direct result of the design chosen, blinding is more difficult when each patient is tested in all conditions and when the difference between the conditions is clear (for example: performing a task with or without a distinctive sound), which was the case in most of the discussed studies.Follow-UpSufficient follow-up to the examination is of great importance to assess the effects of the intervention over a prolonged period of time. Only two of the twenty-one studies discussed (Bolognini et al. 2005a; Passamonti et al. 2009b) incorporated a follow-up in their design (with no losses-to-follow-up). They found that patients with hemianopia could improve in visual detection and (oculomotor) exploration in the impaired field and in different tasks of daily life with multisensory stimulation. These beneficial effects were stable at a one month (Bolognini et al. 2005a) and at a one year (Passamonti et al. 2009b) follow-up. With respect to the other studies on low-level sensory impairment and neglect, no follow-up results were reported.Group SizeStudies with small groups often have large confidence intervals and are less able to detect clinically relevant effects statistically. Group sizes in the discussed studies were relatively small. The average group size in the discussed studies was 6.36 (SD = 4.81, range 1–20). The largest group had 20 patients (Làdavas et al. 1997), 9 studies (including 6 case studies) had 1 to 5 patients, and 11 studies had 7 to 12 patients. The average group size for studies on visual field defects was 6.7 (11 studies), on auditory deficits 1 (1 study), on somatosensory deficits 5.5 (2 studies), on neglect 6.9 (9 studies). One of the twenty-one discussed studies (Smith et al. 2008) did not find a difference between unisensory and multisensory stimulation in patients with hemianopia; this study included 5 patients.Reporting Effect Sizes and Time Post-StrokeAn important factor that should be reported is the effect size to determine the strength of the statistically significant results. Yet, only 1 of the 21 studies discussed (Sambo et al. 2012) reported effect sizes. This study found that multisensory stimulation enhanced tactile detection, with an effect size (η2) ranging from 0.46 to 0.76, which is considered as a large effect size (Cohen 1988). Another important factor that should be mentioned is the time post-stroke onset to verify response to treatment in different phases of recovery. Three of the studies discussed (Frassinetti et al. 2005; Calamaro et al. 1995; Soroker et al. 1995) did not report the time post-stroke of their included patients. Overall, studies demonstrating beneficial effects of multisensory stimulation included patients between 0.5 months to 32 years post stroke, effects in the early acute phase were not reported.AbbreviationsADLActivities of Daily LivingfMRIFunctional Magnetic Resonance ImagingMSIMultisensory IntegrationRCTRandomized Controlled TrialAAuditoryAVAudiovisualdDaysFrFrontalhHoursLHLeft HemispheremMonthsmsMillisecondsOcOccipitalPProprioceptivePaParietalRHRight HemisphereSSomatosensorySCSubcorticalSign.Statistically SignificantTeTemporalVVisualvYearsThis study was performed at the Helmholtz Institute Utrecht, the Netherlands.The manuscript or substantially similar work, has not been published and is not under consideration for publication elsewhere.Artwork was created in Adobe Photoshop CS6 and Microsoft Word 2010.Compliance with Ethical StandardsConflict InterestsThe authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.Financial DisclosureTanja C. W. Nijboer was supported by Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research grant #451-10-013. Raymond van Ee was supported by a grant from the Flemish Methusalem program (METH/08/02 assigned to J. Wagemans), the EU HealthPac grant (assigned to J.A. van Opstal), and the Flanders Scientific Organization.The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.ReferencesAimolaLSchindlerISimoneAMVenneriANear and far space neglect: task sensitivity and anatomical substratesNeuropsychologia201250611152310.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2012.01.02222306826AllmanBLKenistonLPMeredithMANot just for bimodal neurons anymore: the contribution of unimodal neurons to cortical multisensory processingBrain Topography2009213–41576710.1007/s10548-009-0088-319326204AmediAMalachRHendlerTPeledSZoharyEVisuo-haptic object-related activation in the ventral visual pathwayNature Neuroscience2001433243010.1038/8520111224551AmediAJacobsonGHendlerTMalachRZoharyEConvergence of visual and tactile shape processing in the human lateral occipital complexCerebral Cortex2002121112021210.1093/cercor/12.11.120212379608BeauchampMSYasarNEFryeRERoTTouch, sound and vision in human superior temporal sulcusNeuroImage200841310112010.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.03.01518440831BologniniNRasiFCocciaMLàdavasEVisual search improvement in hemianopic patients after audio-visual stimulationBrain20051281228304210.1093/brain/awh65616219672BologniniNRasiFLàdavasEVisual localization of soundsNeuropsychologia2005431116556110.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2005.01.01516009247BologniniNConventoSRossettiAMerabetLBMultisensory processing after a brain damage: clues on post-injury crossmodal plasticity from neuropsychologyNeuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews20133732697810.1016/j.neubiorev.2012.12.00623253947BrownLEKroliczakGDemonetJFGoodaleMAA hand in blindsight: hand placement near target improves size perception in the blind visual fieldNeuropsychologia200846378680210.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2007.10.00618206962BumaFKwakkelGRamseyNUnderstanding upper limb recovery after strokeRestorative Neurology and Neuroscience20133167072223963341BuxbaumLJFerraroMKVeramontiTHemispatial neglect: subtypes, neuroanatomy, and disabilityNeurology20046257495610.1212/01.WNL.0000113730.73031.F415007125CalamaroNSorokerNMyslobodskyMSFalse recovery from auditory hemineglect produced by source misattribution of auditory stimuli (the ventriloquist effect)Restorative Neurology and Neuroscience199573151621551783CappeCMorelABaronePRouillerEMThe thalamocortical projection systems in primate: an anatomical support for multisensory and sensorimotor interplayCerebral Cortex200919920253710.1093/cercor/bhn22819150924CareyLMSomatosensory loss after strokeCrit Rev Phys Rehabil Med199571519110.1615/CritRevPhysRehabilMed.v7.i1.40CareyLMMatyasTAFrequency of discriminative sensory loss in the hand after stroke in a rehabilitation settingJournal of Rehabilitation Medicine20114332576310.2340/16501977-066221305243CecereRRomeiVBertiniCLàdavasECrossmodal enhancement of visual orientation discrimination by looming sounds requires functional activation of primary visual areas: a case studyNeuropsychologia201456350810.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2014.02.00824534140CohenJStatistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences19882HillsdaleLawrence ErlbaumDancauseNBarbaySFrostSBExtensive cortical rewiring after brain injuryJournal of Neuroscience20052544101677910.1523/JNEUROSCI.3256-05.200516267224di PellegrinoGFrassinettiFDirect evidence from parietal extinction of enhancement of visual attention near a visible handCurrent Biology200010221475710.1016/S0960-9822(00)00809-511102814FalchierASchroederCEHackettTAProjection from visual areas V2 and prostriata to caudal auditory cortex in the monkeyCerebral Cortex201020715293810.1093/cercor/bhp21319875677FortenbaughFCVanVleetTMSilverMARobertsonLCSpatial distortions in localization and midline estimation in hemianopia and normal visionVision Research201511111210.1016/j.visres.2015.03.02225872177FrassinettiFPavaniFLàdavasEAcoustical vision of neglected stimuli: interaction among spatially converging audiovisual inputs in neglect patientsJournal Cognitive Neuroscience200214162910.1162/089892902317205320FrassinettiFBologniniNBottariDBonoraALàdavasEAudiovisual integration in patients with visual deficitJournal Cognitive Neuroscience200517914425210.1162/0898929054985446GallaceASpenceCThe cognitive and neural correlates of “tactile consciousness”: a multisensory perspectiveConsciousness and Cognition200817137040710.1016/j.concog.2007.01.00517398116GatchelRJLurieJDMayerTGMinimal clinically important differenceSpine2010351917394310.1097/BRS.0b013e3181d3cfc920700084HalliganPWFinkGRMarshallJCVallarGSpatial cognition: evidence from visual neglectTrends in Cognitive Sciences20037312513310.1016/S1364-6613(03)00032-912639694HeilmanKMValensteinEWatsonRTNeglect and related disordersSeminars in Neurology20002044637010.1055/s-2000-1317911149702HigginsJPAltmanDGGøtzschePCThe Cochrane collaboration’s tool for assessing risk of bias in randomized trialsBMJ2011343d592810.1136/bmj.d592822008217JiangHSteinBEMchaffieJGMultisensory training reverses midbrain lesion-induced changes and ameliorates haemianopiaNature Communications20156726310.1038/ncomms826326021613JohanssonBBMultisensory stimulation in stroke rehabilitationFrontiers in Human Neuroscience201266010.3389/fnhum.2012.0006022509159KandelERSchwartzJHJessellTMPrinciples of neural science20004New YorkMcGraw-Hill122746KellerILefin-RankGImprovement of visual search after audiovisual exploration training in hemianopic patientsNeurorehabilitation and Neural Repair20102476667310.1177/154596831037277420810740KeysersCKohlerEUmiltàMANanettiLFogassiLGalleseVAudiovisual mirror neurons and action recognitionExperimental Brain Research200315346283610.1007/s00221-003-1603-512937876KingMTA point of minimal important difference (MID): a critique of terminology and methodsExpert Review of Pharmacoeconomics &amp; Outcomes Research20111121718410.1586/erp.11.921476819KinsbourneMRobertsonIHMarshallJCOrientational bias model of unilateral neglect: Evidence from attentional gradients within hemispaceUnilateral neglect: Clinical and experimental studies1993HoveLawrence Erlbaum6386KlemenJChambersCDCurrent perspectives and methods in studying neural mechanisms of multisensory interactionsNeuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews20123611113310.1016/j.neubiorev.2011.04.01521569794KwakkelGKollenBLindemanEUnderstanding the pattern of functional recovery after stroke: facts and theoriesRestorative Neurology and Neuroscience2004223–52819915502272LàdavasEBertiARuozziEBarboniFNeglect as a deficit determined by an imbalance between multiple spatial representationsExperimental Brain Research1997116349350010.1007/PL000057779372298LaurientiPJKraftRAMaldjianJABurdetteJHWallaceMTSemantic congruence is a critical factor in multisensory behavioral performanceExperimental Brain Research200415844051410.1007/s00221-004-1913-215221173LeoFBologniniNPassamontiCSteinBELàdavasECross-modal localization in hemianopia: new insights on multisensory integrationBrain200813138556510.1093/brain/awn00318263626LevinMFKleimJAWolfSLWhat do motor “recovery” and “compensation” mean in patients following stroke?Neurorehabilitation and Neural Repair2009234313910.1177/154596830832872719118128MacalusoEFrithCDDriverJModulation of human visual cortex by crossmodal spatial attentionScience200028954821206810.1126/science.289.5482.120610947990MartuzziRMurrayMMMichelCMMultisensory interactions within human primary cortices revealed by BOLD dynamicsCerebral Cortex20071771672910.1093/cercor/bhl07716968869MesulamMMSpatial attention and neglect: parietal, frontal and cingulate contributions to the mental representation and attentional targeting of salient extrapersonal eventsPhilosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological Sciences1999354138713254610.1098/rstb.1999.048210466154NagyAEördeghGParóczyZMárkusZBenedekGMultisensory integration in the basal gangliaEuropean Journal of Neuroscience20062439172410.1111/j.1460-9568.2006.04942.x16930419NewportRHindleJVJacksonSRLinks between vision and somatosensation. Vision can improve the felt position of the unseen handCurrent Biology200111129758010.1016/S0960-9822(01)00266-411448775NijboerTCWKollenBJKwakkelGTime course of visuospatial neglect early after stroke: a longitudinal cohort studyCortex20134982021710.1016/j.cortex.2012.11.00623332473NijboerTCWKollenBJKwakkelGThe impact of recovery of visuo-spatial neglect on motor recovery of the upper paretic limb after strokePLoS ONE20149610.1371/journal.pone.010058424950224NudoRJWiseBMSiFuentesFMillikenGWNeural substrates for the effects of rehabilitative training on motor recovery after ischemic infarctScience1996272536917919410.1126/science.272.5269.17918650578PapageorgiouEHardiessGSchaeffelFAssessment of vision-related quality of life in patients with homonymous visual field defectsGraefes Archive for Clinical and Experimental Ophthalmology20072451217495810.1007/s00417-007-0644-zPassamontiCBertiniCLàdavasEAudio-visual stimulation improves oculomotor patterns in patients with hemianopiaNeuropsychologia20094725465510.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2008.10.00818983860PassamontiCFrissenILàdavasEVisual recalibration of auditory spatial perception: two separate neural circuits for perceptual learningEuropean Journal of Neuroscience200930611415010.1111/j.1460-9568.2009.06910.x19735289PavlovskayaMSorokerNBonnehYExtinction is not a natural consequence of unilateral spatial neglect: evidence from contrast detection experimentsNeuroscience Letters20074203240410.1016/j.neulet.2007.05.01117537575RocklandKSOjimaHMultisensory convergence in calcarine visual areas in macaque monkeyInternational Journal of Psychophysiology2003501–2192610.1016/S0167-8760(03)00121-114511833SamboCFVallarGFortisPVisual and spatial modulation of tactile extinction: behavioural and electrophysiological evidenceFrontiers in Human Neuroscience2012621710.3389/fnhum.2012.0021722848197SchendelKRobertsonLCReaching out to see: arm position can attenuate human visual lossJournal Cognitive Neuroscience20041669354310.1162/0898929041502698SerinoAFarnèARinaldesiMLHaggardPLàdavasECan vision of the body ameliorate impaired somatosensory function?Neuropsychologia20074551101710.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2006.09.01317101158ShoreSEMultisensory integration in the dorsal cochlear nucleus: unit responses to acoustic and trigeminal ganglion stimulationEuropean Journal of Neuroscience2005211233344810.1111/j.1460-9568.2005.04142.x16026471SmithDTLaneARSchenkTArm position does not attenuate visual loss in patients with homonymous field deficitsNeuropsychologia200846923202510.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2008.03.01018440573SorokerNCalamaroNMyslobodskyMMcGurk illusion” to bilateral administration of sensory stimuli in patients with hemispatial neglectNeuropsychologia19953344617010.1016/0028-3932(94)00130-H7617155SpreijLAVisser-MeilyJMvan HeugtenCMNijboer TCW Novel insights into the rehabilitation of memory post acquired brain injury: a systematic reviewFrontiers in Human Neuroscience2014899310.3389/fnhum.2014.0099325566021SteinBEThe new handbook of multisensory processing2012CambridgeMIT PressTeasell R., &amp; Hussein N., (2014) Brain reorganization, recovery and organized care. In: Stroke rehabilitation clinician handbook. Retrieved August 26, 2015 from http://www.ebrsr.com.Ten BrinkAFNijboerTCWBergsmaDPBartonJJSVan der StigchelSLack of multisensory integration in hemianopia: no influence of visual stimuli on aurally guided saccades to the blind hemifieldPLoS ONE201510410.1371/journal.pone.012205425835952TijssenJGPAssendelftWJJOffringaMAssendelftWJJScholtenRJPMBeoordeling van een gerandomiseerd effectonderzoekInleiding in evidence-based medicine2008HoutenBohn Stafleu van Loghum88103TingDSPollockADuttonGNVisual neglect following stroke: current concepts and future focusSurvey of Ophthalmology20115621143410.1016/j.survophthal.2010.08.00121335145Van der StoepNVisser-MeilyJMKappelleLJExploring near and far regions of space: distance-specific visuospatial neglect after strokeJ Clin Exp Neuropsyc201335879981110.1080/13803395.2013.824555Van der StoepNNijboerTCWVan der StigchelSSpenceCMultisensory interactions in the depth plane in front and rear space: a reviewNeuropsychologia2015703354910.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2014.12.00725498407van EeRvan BoxtelJJParkerALAlaisDMultisensory congruency as a mechanism for attentional control over perceptual selectionJournal of Neuroscience2009293711641910.1523/JNEUROSCI.0873-09.200919759311van VleetTMRobertsonLCCross-modal interactions in time and space: auditory influence on visual attention in hemispatial neglectJournal Cognitive Neuroscience200618813687910.1162/jocn.2006.18.8.1368WatkinsSShamsLTanakaSHaynesJDReesGSound alters activity in human V1 in association with illusory visual perceptionNeuroImage200631312475610.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.01.01616556505WildeEAHunterJVBiglerEDA primer of neuroimaging analysis in neurorehabilitation outcome researchNeuroRehabilitation20123132274223093452ZamarianLEggerCDelazerMThe mental representation of ordered sequences in visual neglectCortex20074345425010.1016/S0010-9452(08)70248-X17624000
