<?xml version="1.0"?>
F1000ResF1000ResF1000ResearchF1000Research2046-1402F1000 Research LimitedLondon, UK56210962905707010.12688/f1000research.12330.2ReviewArticlesMotor SystemsMovement DisordersNeurobiology of Disease &amp; RegenerationTourette syndrome research highlights from 2016[version 2; referees: 4 approved]BlackKevin J.InvestigationWriting – Original Draft PreparationWriting – Review &amp; Editinghttps://orcid.org/0000-0002-6921-9567a1
1Departments of Psychiatry, Neurology, Radiology, and Neuroscience, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, 63110, USAakevin@wustl.edu
Competing interests: KJB participated in clinical trials supported by Psyadon Pharmaceuticals and Neurocrine Biosciences, Inc.2911201720176143022112017Copyright: © 2017 Black KJ2017This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.This article presents highlights chosen from research that appeared during 2016 on Tourette syndrome and other tic disorders. Selected articles felt to represent meaningful advances in the field are briefly summarized.Tourette syndrometic disordersreviewanimal modelsgeneticspathophysiologytherapypremonitoryNational Institutes of HealthR01MH104030National Institutes of HealthR21NS091635Tourette Association of AmericaThis work was supported in part by the U.S. National Institutes of Health (NIH) (grants R21 NS091635 and R01 MH104030), and by a research grant from the Tourette Association of America (PI: Cheryl A. Richards, Ph.D.).The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>A PubMed search was conducted using the search strategy “(“Tic Disorders” [MeSH] OR Tourette NOT Tourette[AU]) AND 2016[PDAT] NOT 1950:2015[PDAT]”. On 06 Jan 2017, this search
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/myncbi/collections/51739590/">returned 186 citations</ext-link>, none of which had first appeared in 2017. The author also identified articles or news from other sources, such as colleagues, email lists, and professional meetings. The studies cited below were selected subjectively, but guided by a personal judgment of their potential importance to the field.</p></sec>1
YangJHirschLMartinoD:
The prevalence of diagnosed Tourette syndrome in Canada: A national population-based study.
Mov Disord.
2016;31(11):1658–1663.
10.1002/mds.26766
275484012
YangCZhangLZhuP:
The prevalence of tic disorders for children in China: A systematic review and meta-analysis.
Medicine (Baltimore).
2016;95(30):e4354.
10.1097/MD.0000000000004354

274727243
BlackKJBlackERGreeneDJ:
Provisional Tic Disorder: What to tell parents when their child first starts ticcing [version 1; referees: 3 approved].
F1000Res.
2016;5:696.
10.12688/f1000research.8428.1

271584584
RobertsonMMBanerjeeSKurlanR:
The Tourette syndrome diagnostic confidence index: development and clinical associations.
Neurology.
1999;53(9):2108–12.
10.1212/WNL.53.9.2108
105997905
GoetzCGLeurgansSChmuraTA:
Home alone: methods to maximize tic expression for objective videotape assessments in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
Mov Disord.
2001;16(4):693–7.
10.1002/mds.1159
114816936
WoodsDWWaltherMRBauerCC:
The development of stimulus control over tics: a potential explanation for contextually-based variability in the symptoms of Tourette syndrome.
Behav Res Ther.
2009;47(1):41–7.
10.1016/j.brat.2008.10.013
190264067
BuseJEnghardtSKirschbaumC:
Tic Frequency Decreases during Short-term Psychosocial Stress - An Experimental Study on Children with Tic Disorders.
Front Psychiatry.
2016;7:84.
10.3389/fpsyt.2016.00084

272425548
BarneaMBenaroya-MilshteinNGilboa-SechtmanE:
Subjective versus objective measures of tic severity in Tourette syndrome - The influence of environment.
Psychiatry Res.
2016;242:204–9.
10.1016/j.psychres.2016.05.047
272893269
HersheyTBlackKJHartleinJ:
Dopaminergic modulation of response inhibition: an fMRI study.
Brain Res Cogn Brain Res.
2004;20(3):438–48.
10.1016/j.cogbrainres.2004.03.018
1526892110
RoessnerVAlbrechtBDechentP:
Normal response inhibition in boys with Tourette syndrome.
Behav Brain Funct.
2008;4:29.
10.1186/1744-9081-4-29

1863836811
KalsiNTambelliRAcetoP:
Are Motor Skills and Motor Inhibitions Impaired in Tourette Syndrome? A Review.
J Exp Neurosci.
2015;9:57–65.
10.4137/JEN.S25095

2627963012
WylieSAClaassenDOKanoffKE:
Impaired inhibition of prepotent motor actions in patients with Tourette syndrome.
J Psychiatry Neurosci.
2013;38(5):349–56.
10.1503/jpn.120138

2382018513
WylieSAClaassenDOKanoffKE:
Stopping Manual and Vocal Actions in Tourette’s Syndrome.
J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci.American Psychiatric Publishing;2016;28(4):306–11.
10.1176/appi.neuropsych.15110387
2725585214
SchunkeOGrashornWKahlU:
Quantitative Sensory Testing in adults with Tourette syndrome.
Parkinsonism Relat Disord.
2016;24:132–6.
10.1016/j.parkreldis.2016.01.006
2681862815
BelluscioBAJinLWattersV:
Sensory sensitivity to external stimuli in Tourette syndrome patients.
Mov Disord.
2011;26(14):2538–43.
10.1002/mds.23977

2203893816
BesteCTübingJSeeligerH:
Altered perceptual binding in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
Cortex.
2016;83:160–6.
10.1016/j.cortex.2016.07.015
2754434617
SambraniTJakubovskiEMüller-VahlKR:
New Insights into Clinical Characteristics of Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome: Findings in 1032 Patients from a Single German Center.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:415.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00415

2767235718
GreeneDJKollerJMRobichaux-ViehoeverA:
Reward enhances tic suppression in children within months of tic disorder onset.
Dev Cogn Neurosci.
2015;11:65–74.
10.1016/j.dcn.2014.08.005

2522007519
BrandtVCBeckCSajinV:
Temporal relationship between premonitory urges and tics in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
Cortex.Elsevier BV;2016;77:24–37.
10.1016/j.cortex.2016.01.008
2692250320
BrabsonLABrownJLCapriottiMR:
Patterned changes in urge ratings with tic suppression in youth with chronic tic disorders.
J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry.
2016;50:162–70.
10.1016/j.jbtep.2015.07.004
2625505221
DruryHWilkinsonVRobertsonMM:
Self-reported emotion regulation in adults with Tourette’s syndrome.
Psychiatry Res.
2016;245:157–63.
10.1016/j.psychres.2016.08.026
2754382922
WrightARickardsHCavannaAE:
Impulse-control disorders in gilles de la tourette syndrome.
J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci.
2012;24(1):16–27.
10.1176/appi.neuropsych.10010013
2245061023
de HaanMJDelucchiKLMathewsCM:
Tic symptom dimensions and their heritabilities in Tourette’s syndrome.
Psychiatr Genet.
2015;25(3):112–8.
10.1097/YPG.0000000000000084

2571444924
MathewsCAWallerJGliddenD:
Self injurious behaviour in Tourette syndrome: correlates with impulsivity and impulse control.
J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry.
2004;75(8):1149–55.
10.1136/jnnp.2003.020693

1525821825
CavannaAECritchleyHDOrthM:
Dissecting the Gilles de la Tourette spectrum: a factor analytic study on 639 patients.
J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry.
2011;82(12):1320–3.
10.1136/jnnp.2010.225029
2143622726
Mol DebesNMHjalgrimHSkovL:
Validation of the presence of comorbidities in a Danish clinical cohort of children with Tourette syndrome.
J Child Neurol.
2008;23(9):1017–27.
10.1177/0883073808316370
1882726827
PiedadJCCavannaAE:
Depression in Tourette syndrome: A controlled and comparison study.
J Neurol Sci.
2016;364:128–32.
10.1016/j.jns.2016.03.030
2708423028
JohncoCMcGuireJFMcBrideNM:
Suicidal ideation in youth with tic disorders.
J Affect Disord.
2016;200:204–11.
10.1016/j.jad.2016.04.027

2713641929
HuangAYYuDDavisLK:
Rare copy number variants in
NRXN1 and
CNTN6 increase risk for Tourette syndrome.
bioRxiv.Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press;2016
10.1101/062471
30
HuangAYYuDDavisLK:
Rare Copy Number Variants in
NRXN1 and
CNTN6 Increase Risk for Tourette Syndrome.
Neuron.
2017;94(6):1101–11.e7.
10.1016/j.neuron.2017.06.010
2864110931
PintoRMonzaniBLeckmanJF:
Understanding the covariation of tics, attention-deficit/hyperactivity, and obsessive-compulsive symptoms: A population-based adult twin study.
Am J Med Genet B Neuropsychiatr Genet.
2016;171(7):938–47.
10.1002/ajmg.b.32436
2691982332
HirschtrittMEDarrowSMIllmannC:
Social disinhibition is a heritable subphenotype of tics in Tourette syndrome.
Neurology.
2016;87(5):497–504.
10.1212/WNL.0000000000002910

2737148733
AlexanderJPotamianouHXingJ:
Targeted Re-Sequencing Approach of Candidate Genes Implicates Rare Potentially Functional Variants in Tourette Syndrome Etiology.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:428.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00428

2770856034
SteinbergTShmuel-BaruchSHoreshN:
Life events and Tourette syndrome.
Compr Psychiatry.
2013;54(5):467–73.
10.1016/j.comppsych.2012.10.015
2321948935
MathewsCAScharfJMMillerLL:
Association between pre- and perinatal exposures and Tourette syndrome or chronic tic disorder in the ALSPAC cohort.
Br J Psychiatry.
2014;204(1):40–5.
10.1192/bjp.bp.112.125468

2426281536
ChaoTKHuJPringsheimT:
Prenatal risk factors for Tourette Syndrome: a systematic review.
BMC Pregnancy Childbirth.
2014;14:53.
10.1186/1471-2393-14-53

2447940737
LeivonenSChudalRJoelssonP:
Prenatal Maternal Smoking and Tourette Syndrome: A Nationwide Register Study.
Child Psychiatry Hum Dev.
2016;47(1):75–82.
10.1007/s10578-015-0545-z
2579637338
AbdulkadirMTischfieldJAKingRA:
Pre- and perinatal complications in relation to Tourette syndrome and co-occurring obsessive-compulsive disorder and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder.
J Psychiatr Res.
2016;82:126–35.
10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.07.017

2749407939
NespoliERizzoFBoeckersTM:
Addressing the Complexity of Tourette’s Syndrome through the Use of Animal Models.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:133.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00133

2709204340
McCairnKWNagaiYHoriY:
A Primary Role for Nucleus Accumbens and Related Limbic Network in Vocal Tics.
Neuron.
2016;89(2):300–7.
10.1016/j.neuron.2015.12.025
2679669041
Batista-BritoRVinckMFergusonK:
Developmental dysfunction of VIP interneurons impairs cortical circuits.
bioRxiv.Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals;2016
10.1101/077891
42
KalanithiPSZhengWKataokaY:
Altered parvalbumin-positive neuron distribution in basal ganglia of individuals with Tourette syndrome.
Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.
2005;102(37):13307–12.
10.1073/pnas.0502624102

1613154243
XuMLiLPittengerC:
Ablation of fast-spiking interneurons in the dorsal striatum, recapitulating abnormalities seen post-mortem in Tourette syndrome, produces anxiety and elevated grooming.
Neuroscience.
2016;324:321–9.
10.1016/j.neuroscience.2016.02.074

2696876344
GodarSCMosherLJStrathmanHJ:
The D1CT-7 mouse model of Tourette syndrome displays sensorimotor gating deficits in response to spatial confinement.
Br J Pharmacol.
2016;173(13):2111–21.
10.1111/bph.13243

2617166645
JankovicJ:
Stereotypies. In: Marsden CD, Fahn S, editors.
Movement Disorders 3 Boston: Butterworth-Heinemann Ltd.1994;503–17.46
KalueffAVStewartAMSongC:
Neurobiology of rodent self-grooming and its value for translational neuroscience.
Nat Rev Neurosci.
2016;17(1):45–59.
10.1038/nrn.2015.8

2667582247
TaylorJLRajbhandariAKBerridgeKC:
Dopamine receptor modulation of repetitive grooming actions in the rat: potential relevance for Tourette syndrome.
Brain Res.
2010;1322:92–101.
10.1016/j.brainres.2010.01.052

2011403648
PépésSEDraperAJacksonGM:
Effects of age on motor excitability measures from children and adolescents with Tourette syndrome.
Dev Cogn Neurosci.
2016;19:78–86.
10.1016/j.dcn.2016.02.005
2693463849
Jimenez-ShahedJTelkesIViswanathanA:
GPi Oscillatory Activity Differentiates Tics from the Resting State, Voluntary Movements, and the Unmedicated Parkinsonian State.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:436.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00436

2773381550
ShephardEJacksonGMGroomMJ:
Electrophysiological correlates of reinforcement learning in young people with Tourette syndrome with and without co-occurring ADHD symptoms.
Int J Dev Neurosci.
2016;51:17–27.
10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2016.04.005
2710323151
Morand-BeaulieuSO’ConnorKPRichardM:
The Impact of a Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy on Event-Related Potentials in Patients with Tic Disorders or Body-Focused Repetitive Behaviors.
Front Psychiatry.
2016;7:81.
10.3389/fpsyt.2016.00081

2724255152
GreeneDJWilliams IiiACKollerJM:
Brain structure in pediatric Tourette syndrome.
Mol Psychiatry.
2016;22(7):972–80.
10.1038/mp.2016.194

2777741553
WenHLiuYWangJ:
Combining tract- and atlas-based analysis reveals microstructural abnormalities in early Tourette syndrome children.
Hum Brain Mapp.
2016;37(5):1903–19.
10.1002/hbm.23146
2692922154
EddyCMCavannaAERickardsHE:
Temporo-parietal dysfunction in Tourette syndrome: Insights from an fMRI study of Theory of Mind.
J Psychiatr Res.
2016;81:102–11.
10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.07.002
2742406355
HaenseCMüller-VahlKRWilkeF:
Effect of Deep Brain Stimulation on Regional Cerebral Blood Flow in Patients with Medically Refractory Tourette Syndrome.
Front Psychiatry.
2016;7:118.
10.3389/fpsyt.2016.00118

2745838956
Lessov-SchlaggarCNRubinJBSchlaggarBL:
The Fallacy of Univariate Solutions to Complex Systems Problems.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:267.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00267

2737542557
KanaanASGeraschSGarcía-GarcíaI:
Pathological glutamatergic neurotransmission in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome.
Brain.
2017;140(Pt 1):218–34.
10.1093/brain/aww285
2800799858
GremelCMChanceyJHAtwoodBK:
Endocannabinoid Modulation of Orbitostriatal Circuits Gates Habit Formation.
Neuron.
2016;90(6):1312–24.
10.1016/j.neuron.2016.04.043

2723886659
BlackKJ:
Smoke gets in your tics.
Authorea.
2017
10.22541/au.149308896.61629534
60
Kononoff VanhanenJNuutinenSTuominenM:
Histamine H3 Receptor Regulates Sensorimotor Gating and Dopaminergic Signaling in the Striatum.
J Pharmacol Exp Ther.
2016;357(2):264–72.
10.1124/jpet.115.230771
2694508761
JonasMThomallaGBiermann-RubenK:
Imitation in patients with Gilles de la Tourette syndrome--a behavioral study.
Mov Disord.
2010;25(8):991–9.
10.1002/mds.22994
2053582462
FinisJMoczydlowskiAPollokB:
Echoes from childhood--imitation in Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome.
Mov Disord.
2012;27(4):562–5.
10.1002/mds.24913
2227895063
BrandtVCPatalayPBäumerT:
Tics as a model of over-learned behavior-imitation and inhibition of facial tics.
Mov Disord.
2016;31(8):1155–62.
10.1002/mds.26607
2706218464
DelormeCSalvadorAVoonV:
Illusion of agency in patients with Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome.
Cortex.
2016;77:132–40.
10.1016/j.cortex.2016.02.003
2696308365
GanosCAsmussLBongertJ:
Volitional action as perceptual detection: predictors of conscious intention in adolescents with tic disorders.
Cortex.
2015;64:47–54.
10.1016/j.cortex.2014.09.016
2546170666
HollisCPennantMCuencaJ:
Clinical effectiveness and patient perspectives of different treatment strategies for tics in children and adolescents with Tourette syndrome: a systematic review and qualitative analysis.
Health Technol Assess.
2016;20(4):1–450, vii–viii.
10.3310/hta20040

2678693667
PetersonALMcGuireJFWilhelmS:
An Empirical Examination of Symptom Substitution Associated With Behavior Therapy for Tourette’s Disorder.
Behav Ther.
2016;47(1):29–41.
10.1016/j.beth.2015.09.001
2676349568
YatesREdwardsKKingJ:
Habit reversal training and educational group treatments for children with Tourette syndrome: A preliminary randomised controlled trial.
Behav Res Ther.
2016;80:43–50.
10.1016/j.brat.2016.03.003
2703748369
JakubovskiEReichertCKarchA:
The ONLINE-TICS Study Protocol: A Randomized Observer-Blind Clinical Trial to Demonstrate the Efficacy and Safety of Internet-Delivered Behavioral Treatment for Adults with Chronic Tic Disorders.
Front Psychiatry.
2016;7:119.
10.3389/fpsyt.2016.00119

2744587470
RickettsEJGoetzARCapriottiMR:
A randomized waitlist-controlled pilot trial of voice over Internet protocol-delivered behavior therapy for youth with chronic tic disorders.
J Telemed Telecare.
2016;22(3):153–62.
10.1177/1357633X15593192
2616935071
RickettsEJGilbertDLZinnerSH:
Pilot Testing Behavior Therapy for Chronic Tic Disorders in Neurology and Developmental Pediatrics Clinics.
J Child Neurol.
2016;31(4):444–50.
10.1177/0883073815599257
2627179072
FranklinMEBestSHWilsonMA:
Habit Reversal Training and Acceptance and Commitment Therapy for Tourette Syndrome: A Pilot Project.
J Dev Phys Disabil.Springer Nature,2011;23(1):49–60.
10.1007/s10882-010-9221-1
73
ReeseHEVallejoZRasmussenJ:
Mindfulness-based stress reduction for Tourette Syndrome and Chronic Tic Disorder: a pilot study.
J Psychosom Res.Elsevier BV,2015;78(3):293–8.
10.1016/j.jpsychores.2014.08.001
2514987974
GevEPilowsky-PelegTFennigS:
Acceptance of premonitory urges and tics.
J Obsessive Compuls Relat Disord.
2016;10:78–83.
10.1016/j.jocrd.2016.06.001
75
O’ConnorKLavoieMBlanchetP:
Evaluation of a cognitive psychophysiological model for management of tic disorders: an open trial.
Br J Psychiatry.
2016;209(1):76–83.
10.1192/bjp.bp.114.154518
2625074276
LeclercJBValoisPJ-NolinG:
A Therapy for Tics in Children Managing Underlying Processes: a Pilot Study.
J Dev Phys Disabil.
2016;28(4):581–93.
10.1007/s10882-016-9496-y
77
LeclercJBO’ConnorKPJ-NolinG:
The Effect of a New Therapy for Children with Tics Targeting Underlying Cognitive, Behavioral, and Physiological Processes.
Front Psychiatry.
2016;7:135.
10.3389/fpsyt.2016.00135

2756329278
SpechtMWMahoneEMKlineT:
Efficacy of parent-delivered behavioral therapy for primary complex motor stereotypies.
Dev Med Child Neurol.
2017;59(2):168–73.
10.1111/dmcn.13164

2725946479
JankovicJJimenez-ShahedJBudmanC:
Deutetrabenazine in Tics Associated with Tourette Syndrome.
Tremor Other Hyperkinet Mov (N Y).
2016;6:422.
10.7916/D8M32W3H

2791730980
GeraschSKanaanASJakubovskiE:
Aripiprazole Improves Associated Comorbid Conditions in Addition to Tics in Adult Patients with Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:416.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00416

2767235881
U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration:
FDA Drug Safety Communication: FDA warns about new impulse-control problems associated with mental health drug aripiprazole (Abilify, Abilify Maintena, Aristada).2016
Reference Source
82
BlochMHPanzaKEYaffaA:

N-Acetylcysteine in the Treatment of Pediatric Tourette Syndrome: Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Add-On Trial.
J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol.
2016;26(4):327–34.
10.1089/cap.2015.0109
2702720483
GhoshDBurkmanEL:
Relationship of serum ferritin level and tic severity in children with Tourette syndrome. In:
Mov Disord.2016;31(suppl 2).
Reference Source
84
Akbarian-TefaghiLZrinzoLFoltynieT:
The Use of Deep Brain Stimulation in Tourette Syndrome.
Brain Sci.
2016;6(3): pii: E35.
10.3390/brainsci6030035

2754823585
ServelloDZekajESalehC:
Deep Brain Stimulation in Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome: What Does the Future Hold? A Cohort of 48 Patients.
Neurosurgery.
2016;78(1):91–100.
10.1227/NEU.0000000000001004
2634801286
PortaMSalehCZekajE:
Why so many deep brain stimulation targets in Tourette’s syndrome? Toward a broadening of the definition of the syndrome.
J Neural Transm (Vienna).
2016;123(7):785–90.
10.1007/s00702-015-1494-1
2673944587
HartmannA:
Deep brain stimulation in Gilles de la Tourette syndrome: killing several birds with one stone? [version 1; referees: 3 approved].
F1000Res.
2016;5:2255.
10.12688/f1000research.9521.1

2774691088
SmeetsAYDuitsAAPlantingaBR:
Deep Brain Stimulation of the internal globus pallidus in refractory Tourette Syndrome.
Clin Neurol Neurosurg.
2016;142:54–9.
10.1016/j.clineuro.2016.01.020
2681186689
ZhangXHLiJYZhangYQ:
Deep Brain Stimulation of the Globus Pallidus Internus in Patients with Intractable Tourette Syndrome: A 1-year Follow-up Study.
Chin Med J (Engl).
2016;129(9):1022–7.
10.4103/0366-6999.180512

2709878590
ChangADBergesVAChungSJ:
High-Frequency Stimulation at the Subthalamic Nucleus Suppresses Excessive Self-Grooming in Autism-Like Mouse Models.
Neuropsychopharmacology.
2016;41(7):1813–21.
10.1038/npp.2015.350

2660684991
DeebWRossiPJPortaM:
The International Deep Brain Stimulation Registry and Database for Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome: How Does It Work?
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:170.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00170

2719963492
BrownWC:
Influence of Musical Engagement on Symptoms of Tourette’s Disorder [PhD thesis]. University of South Florida;2016
Reference Source
93
GarveyMAGieddJSwedoSE:
PANDAS: the search for environmental triggers of pediatric neuropsychiatric disorders. Lessons from rheumatic fever.
J Child Neurol.
1998;13(9):413–23.
10.1177/088307389801300901
973328694
WilliamsKASwedoSEFarmerCA:
Randomized, Controlled Trial of Intravenous Immunoglobulin for Pediatric Autoimmune Neuropsychiatric Disorders Associated With Streptococcal Infections.
J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry.
2016;55(10):860–7.e2.
10.1016/j.jaac.2016.06.017
2766394195
EapenVCavannaAERobertsonMM:
Comorbidities, Social Impact, and Quality of Life in Tourette Syndrome.
Front Psychiatry.
2016;7:97.
10.3389/fpsyt.2016.00097

2737550396
WadmanRGlazebrookCBeerC:
Difficulties experienced by young people with Tourette syndrome in secondary school: a mixed methods description of self, parent and staff perspectives.
BMC Psychiatry.Springer Science+Business Media;2016;16(1):14.
10.1186/s12888-016-0717-9

2679221197
MathewsCASternJS:
The First World Congress on Tourette Syndrome and Tic Disorders: Controversies and Hot Topics in Etiology and Treatment.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:246.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00246

2737541198
ThenganattMAJankovicJ:
Recent advances in understanding and managing Tourette syndrome [version 1; referees: 3 approved].
F1000Res.F1000 Research Ltd.2016;5(F1000 Faculty Rev):152, pii: F1000 Faculty Rev-152.
10.12688/f1000research.7424.1

2691818599
BlackKJBlackERGreeneDJ:
Provisional Tic Disorder: What to tell parents when their child first starts ticcing [version 1; referees: 3 approved].
F1000Res.
2016;5:696.
10.12688/f1000research.8428.1

27158458100
GeorgitsiMWillseyAJMathewsCA:
The Genetic Etiology of Tourette Syndrome: Large-Scale Collaborative Efforts on the Precipice of Discovery.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:351.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00351

27536211101
PagliaroliLVetőBArányiT:
From Genetics to Epigenetics: New Perspectives in Tourette Syndrome Research.
Front Neurosci.
2016;10:277.
10.3389/fnins.2016.00277

27462201102
StevensJRBlachlyPH:
Successful treatment of the maladie des tics: Gilles de la Tourette’s syndrome.
Am J Dis Child.
1966;112(6):541–5.
10.1001/archpedi.1966.02090150085006
5224880103
ButtonKSIoannidisJPMokryszC:
Power failure: why small sample size undermines the reliability of neuroscience.
Nat Rev Neurosci.
2013;14(5):365–76.
10.1038/nrn3475
23571845104
BakerM:
1,500 scientists lift the lid on reproducibility.
Nature.
2016;533(7604):452–4.
10.1038/533452a
2722510010.5256/f1000research.14399.r28529Referee response for version 2LeckmanJames F.1Refereehttps://orcid.org/0000-0002-3902-4478
1Child Psychiatry, Psychiatry, Psychology and Pediatrics, Yale Child Study Center, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, CT, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.30112017Version 2recommendationapproveThank you for the clarification.I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard.10.5256/f1000research.13348.r25613Referee response for version 1GanosChristos1Referee
1Department of Neurology, Charité, University Medicine Berlin, Berlin, Germany
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.4102017Version 1recommendationapproveI thoroughly enjoyed the "Tourette Syndrome research highlights from 2016" article by Prof. Black. It is a very well organised effort to present a succinct summary of relevant research from that year and I would like to congratulate Prof. Black for his dedication in putting this together.  I only have some minor suggestions.
It might be thematically more suitable to integrate the first paragraph of the sensory findings of the "Clinical and neuropsychological studies" ["Thresholds for externally applied sensory... ...or central sensorimotor processing"] to the "Premonitory Urges" section, as indeed these refer to the same topic.On the reference of the mouse model of Xu et al. ["These mice developed anxiety and increased frequency of grooming rituals."] it might be of relevance to highlight that the abnormal behaviours only occurred after exposure to environmental stressors. On the Treatments/psychological interventions section, it could be relevant to mention that CBIT responders in those trials as measured by the CGI-I were 45% of the total sample. [Data from the cited publication: "CBIT were significantly more likely to be classified as treatment responders on the CGI-I (child = 53%, adult = 38%, combined sample = 45%)"]
I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard.BlackKevin JDepartment of Psychiatry, Washington University in St Louis, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.4102017Thanks for the kind comments and expert suggestions, which I can include in a revision.10.5256/f1000research.13348.r25611Referee response for version 1MartinoDavide1Referee
1University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.2892017Version 1recommendationapproveThe authors present an interesting and comprehensive review of highlighted articles published in 2016 on Tourette syndrome. The article is very well written. There are a few articles that might also be considered for highlight, in addition to those already referenced. Comorbidities:
Johnco C et al. (2016)
1
 This is particularly relevant in view also of an important finding coming from a 2017 population-based study (Fernandez de la Cruz, Biol Psychiatry 2017) Genetics:
Bertelsen B et al. (2016)
2
 Environmental factors (etiology):
Abdulkadir M et al. (2016)
3
 Imaging:
Wen H et al. (2016)
4
Liao W et al. (2017)
5

I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard.References1
JohncoCMcGuireJFMcBrideNMMurphyTKLewinABStorchEA:
Suicidal ideation in youth with tic disorders.
J Affect Disord.2016;200:
10.1016/j.jad.2016.04.027
204-11
10.1016/j.jad.2016.04.027
271364192
BertelsenBStefánssonHRiff JensenLMelchiorLMol DebesNGrothCSkovLWergeTKaragiannidisITarnokZBartaCNagyPFarkasLBrøndum-NielsenKRizzoRGulisanoMRujescuDKiemeneyLATosatoSNawazMSIngasonAUnnsteinsdottirUSteinbergSLudvigssonPStefanssonKKussAWPaschouPCathDHoekstraPJMüller-VahlKStuhrmannMSilahtarogluAPfundtRTümerZ:
Association of AADAC Deletion and Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome in a Large European Cohort.
Biol Psychiatry.2016;79(5) :
10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.08.027
383-91
10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.08.027
264440753
AbdulkadirMTischfieldJAKingRAFernandezTVBrownLWCheonKACoffeyBJde BruijnSFElzermanLGarcia-DelgarBGilbertDLGriceDEHagstrømJHedderlyTHeymanIHongHJHuyserCIbanez-GomezLKimYKKimYSKohYJKookSKupermanSLamerzALeventhalBLudolphAGMadruga-GarridoMMarasAMesschendorpMDMirPMorerAMünchauAMurphyTLOpenneerTJPlessenKJRathJJRoessnerVFründtOShinEYSivalDASongDHSongJStolteAMTübingJvan den BanEVisscherFWandererSWoodsMZinnerSHStateMWHeimanGAHoekstraPJDietrichA:
Pre- and perinatal complications in relation to Tourette syndrome and co-occurring obsessive-compulsive disorder and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder.
J Psychiatr Res.2016;82:
10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.07.017
126-35
10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.07.017
274940794
WenHLiuYWangJRekikIZhangJZhangYTianHPengYHeH:
Combining tract- and atlas-based analysis reveals microstructural abnormalities in early Tourette syndrome children.
Hum Brain Mapp.2016;37(5) :
10.1002/hbm.23146
1903-19
10.1002/hbm.23146
269292215
LiaoWYuYMiaoHHFengYXJiGJFengJH:
Inter-hemispheric Intrinsic Connectivity as a Neuromarker for the Diagnosis of Boys with Tourette Syndrome.
Mol Neurobiol.2017;54(4) :
10.1007/s12035-016-9863-9
2781-2789
10.1007/s12035-016-9863-9
27011382BlackKevin JDepartment of Psychiatry, Washington University in St Louis, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.2892017Thanks for your input. These are excellent suggestions and I plan to include them in a revision.BlackKevin JDepartment of Psychiatry, Washington University in St Louis, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.22112017We cited the Bertelsen et al paper in our 2015 highlights paper [1]. The Liao et al paper [2] uses a relatively lenient threshold for censoring head motion [3], complicating interpretation. I've included your other suggestions in version 2.[1] Richards CA and Black KJ. Tourette syndrome research highlights 2015 [version 1; referees: 3 approved]. 
F1000Research 2016, 
5:1493 (doi: 
10.12688/f1000research.8769.1).[2] Liao W, Yu Y, Miao HH, Feng YX, Ji GJ, Feng JH: Inter-hemispheric Intrinsic Connectivity as a Neuromarker for the Diagnosis of Boys with Tourette Syndrome.
Mol Neurobiol. 2017; 
54 (4): 2781-2789 
PubMed Abstract | 
Publisher Full Text
[3] Power JD, Mitra A, Laumann TO, Snyder AZ, Schlaggar BL, Petersen SE: Methods to detect, characterize, and remove motion artifact in resting state fMRI. 
Neuroimage 2014; 
84:320-341 (doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.08.048)10.5256/f1000research.13348.r25610Referee response for version 1LeckmanJames F.1Refereehttps://orcid.org/0000-0002-3902-4478
1Child Psychiatry, Psychiatry, Psychology and Pediatrics, Yale Child Study Center, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, CT, USA
Competing interests: I am a co-author of each of the articles that I have suggested that Dr. Black cite in his review.1292017Version 1recommendationapprove-with-reservationsProf. Kevin Black has provided an up-to-date and largely comprehensive summary of the current status of our knowledge concerning the phenomenology, natural history, etiology, pathophysiology, and treatment of Tourette syndrome (TS). However, one important area that is largely missing concerns the findings from post-mortem studies of the brains of individuals with TS that have been conducted by Flora Vaccarino and her laboratory at Yale University. The most notable and highly-cited article from 2016 presents an analysis of the transcriptome of striatal tissue (caudate and putamen) from the brains of nine TS and nine matched normal control subjects (Lennington et al., 2016
1). The authors found 309 down-regulated and 822 up-regulated genes using a data-driven gene network analysis. More specifically, they identified 17 gene co-expression modules associated with TS. The top-scoring down-regulated module in TS was enriched for striatal interneuron transcripts. This finding confirmed earlier studies by the Vaccarino laboratory that had reported decreased numbers of cholinergic and gamma-aminobutyric acidergic interneurons in the same brain regions (Kalathini et al., 2005; Kataoka et al., 2010
2). However, the top-scoring up-regulated module was enriched in immune-related genes, consistent with activation of microglia in patients’ striatum. While these findings confirm the earlier post-mortem studies using unbiased stereological techniques, they also point to the important role of neuroinflammation in TS pathophysiology. Indeed, a deeper understanding of neuroimmunology may well transform the field of neuropsychiatry and point to novel treatment approaches to TS and related disorders (Leckman &amp; Vaccarino, 2015
3).I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard, however I have significant reservations, as outlined above.References1
LenningtonJBCoppolaGKataoka-SasakiYFernandezTVPalejevDLiYHuttnerAPletikosMSestanNLeckmanJFVaccarinoFM:
Transcriptome Analysis of the Human Striatum in Tourette Syndrome.
Biol Psychiatry.2016;79(5) :
10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.07.018
372-82
10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.07.018
251999562
KataokaYKalanithiPSGrantzHSchwartzMLSaperCLeckmanJFVaccarinoFM:
Decreased number of parvalbumin and cholinergic interneurons in the striatum of individuals with Tourette syndrome.
J Comp Neurol.2010;518(3) :
10.1002/cne.22206
277-91
10.1002/cne.22206
199413503
LeckmanJFVaccarinoFM:
Editorial commentary:.
Brain Res.2015;1617:
10.1016/j.brainres.2014.09.052
1-6
10.1016/j.brainres.2014.09.052
25283746BlackKevin JDepartment of Psychiatry, Washington University in St Louis, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.1292017I agree with the importance of the Lennington et al., 2016, paper.
1 It is absent from the "from 2016" highlights article only because (since the final version appeared online before its official publication date) we discussed it in the 2015 highlights article
2 (first paragraph under Pathophysiology). We cited the Kataoka et al publication
3 in the 2014 highlights paper.
4 I do appreciate the reference to the 2015 editorial,
5 which together with your review above better highlights the relevance of the Lennington et al. report to the broader question of neuroimmunology in Tourette syndrome.
Lennington JB, Coppola G, Kataoka-Sasaki Y, Fernandez TV, Palejev D, Li Y, Huttner A, Pletikos M, Sestan N, Leckman JF, Vaccarino FM: Transcriptome Analysis of the Human Striatum in Tourette Syndrome.
Biol Psychiatry. 2016; 
79 (5): 372-82 
PubMed Abstract | 
Publisher Full Text Richards CA and Black KJ. Tourette syndrome research highlights 2015 [version 1; referees: 3 approved]. 
F1000Research 2016, 
5:1493 (doi: 
10.12688/f1000research.8769.1)Kataoka Y, Kalanithi PS, Grantz H, Schwartz ML, Saper C, Leckman JF, Vaccarino FM: Decreased number of parvalbumin and cholinergic interneurons in the striatum of individuals with Tourette syndrome.
J Comp Neurol. 2010; 
518 (3): 277-91 
PubMed Abstract | 
Publisher Full Text
Richards CA and Black KJ. Tourette Syndrome research highlights 2014 [version 2; referees: 1 approved, 2 approved with reservations]. 
F1000Research 2015, 
4:69 (doi: 
10.12688/f1000research.6209.2)Leckman JF, Vaccarino FM: Editorial commentary:. 
Brain Res. 2015; 
1617: 1-6 
PubMed Abstract | 
Publisher Full Text

10.5256/f1000research.13348.r24972Referee response for version 1CoffmanKeith A.1Refereehttps://orcid.org/0000-0003-2474-7857
1Division of Pediatric Neurology, Department of Pediatrics, Children's Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.2982017Version 1recommendationapproveThe manuscript submitted by Dr. Black is a very thorough and comprehensive review of the recent literature on Tourette Syndrome. It is exceptionally well written and organized.  There is one error that needs to be corrected. In the following sentence, there is a missing word and simply a citation number.
"Another potentially useful approach to TS genetic research was illustrated by
28, who sequenced candidate genes suggested by previous research in order to identify potential functional variants linked to TS."
 Other than this, I could find no errors or modifications that I would recommend before publishing this manuscript.I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard.BlackKevin JDepartment of Psychiatry, Washington University in St Louis, USA
Competing interests: No competing interests were disclosed.2982017Thank you! I can correct the missing author name in a revision after other reviews are back.
