<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC MedBMC MedBMC Medicine1741-7015BioMed Central31415401741-7015-9-752168286710.1186/1741-7015-9-75Research ArticleBest practice for motor imagery: a systematic literature review on motor imagery training elements in five different disciplinesSchusterCorina12c.schuster@reha-rhf.chHilfikerRoger3roger.hilfiker@hevs.chAmftOliver45oliver.amft@gmail.comScheidhauerAnne1a.scheidhauer@reha-rhf.chAndrewsBrian67brian.andrews@brunel.ac.ukButlerJenny2jabutler@brookes.ac.ukKischkaUdo18udo.kischka@noc.anglox.nhs.ukEttlinThierry19th.ettlin@reha-rhf.ch1Reha Rheinfelden, Rheinfelden, Switzerland2School of Health and Social Care, Oxford Brookes University, Oxford, UK3Department of Health &amp; Social Work, HES-SO, University of Applied Sciences, Western Switzerland, Sion, Switzerland4Faculty of Electrical Engineering, Technical University Eindhoven, Eindhoven, The Netherlands5Department of Information Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland6Brunel Institute for Bioengineering, Brunel University, London, UK7Nuffield Department of Surgical Sciences, Oxford University, Oxford, UK8Oxford Centre for Enablement, Oxford, UK9Department of Behavioural Neurology, Medical Faculty, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland20111762011975759220111762011Copyright ©2011 Schuster et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.2011Schuster et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.BackgroundThe literature suggests a beneficial effect of motor imagery (MI) if combined with physical practice, but detailed descriptions of MI training session (MITS) elements and temporal parameters are lacking. The aim of this review was to identify the characteristics of a successful MITS and compare these for different disciplines, MI session types, task focus, age, gender and MI modification during intervention.MethodsAn extended systematic literature search using 24 databases was performed for five disciplines: Education, Medicine, Music, Psychology and Sports. References that described an MI intervention that focused on motor skills, performance or strength improvement were included. Information describing 17 MITS elements was extracted based on the PETTLEP (physical, environment, timing, task, learning, emotion, perspective) approach. Seven elements describing the MITS temporal parameters were calculated: study duration, intervention duration, MITS duration, total MITS count, MITS per week, MI trials per MITS and total MI training time.ResultsBoth independent reviewers found 96% congruity, which was tested on a random sample of 20% of all references. After selection, 133 studies reporting 141 MI interventions were included. The locations of the MITS and position of the participants during MI were task-specific. Participants received acoustic detailed MI instructions, which were mostly standardised and live. During MI practice, participants kept their eyes closed. MI training was performed from an internal perspective with a kinaesthetic mode. Changes in MI content, duration and dosage were reported in 31 MI interventions. Familiarisation sessions before the start of the MI intervention were mentioned in 17 reports. MI interventions focused with decreasing relevance on motor-, cognitive- and strength-focused tasks. Average study intervention lasted 34 days, with participants practicing MI on average three times per week for 17 minutes, with 34 MI trials. Average total MI time was 178 minutes including 13 MITS. Reporting rate varied between 25.5% and 95.5%.ConclusionsMITS elements of successful interventions were individual, supervised and non-directed sessions, added after physical practice. Successful design characteristics were dominant in the Psychology literature, in interventions focusing on motor and strength-related tasks, in interventions with participants aged 20 to 29 years old, and in MI interventions including participants of both genders. Systematic searching of the MI literature was constrained by the lack of a defined MeSH term.IntroductionIn sports psychology, there is evidence that mental practice (MP) can accelerate learning and improve motor skills. In their extensive meta-analysis in 1983, Feltz and Landers included single-group interventions with pre- and post-tests (tests before and after the interventions), and studies with multiple groups to compare an MP group versus controls [1]. They summarised 60 studies regardless of their quality and methods. Analysis of effect sizes showed that performing MP is not as good as physical practice (PP) but is better than doing no practice at all. In their revised meta-analysis in 1988, they replicated the previous results [2].MP can be considered an umbrella term that includes various mental training interventions. In recent years, researchers have started to use the term 'motor imagery' (MI) to specifically address the imagination of moving specific body parts.Over the past two decades, the publication of MP literature has increased tremendously, from 122 publications up to 1980 to a total of 20,011 publications in 2009 (PubMed search on 12 April 2010 with the search term 'mental practice'). The MI technique has been adopted in other research areas (education, medicine, music and sports), where the beneficial effect of MI added to PP has been confirmed, and 27 reviews summarise the research findings in those fields [1-27]. Despite the different review foci (for example, history and development of MI, theoretical concepts of MI functioning and effectiveness evaluation), all reviews attribute a beneficial effect to MI when added to PP. In some reviews, the methodological procedure lacked a systematic approach.Aim of the current systematic literature reviewNone of the published reviews have analysed the design of the MI training session (MITS) to determine successful MI intervention techniques, such as the position of the person during MI, the number of MI trials, and the instruction mode and type. However, the MITS design is of vital importance for researchers and clinicians planning to implement MI interventions adapted to participant health status, age and gender. In this systematic literature review, we extracted and analysed 17 MITS elements based on the PETTLEP (physical, environment, timing, task, learning, emotion, perspective) approach. Furthermore, we analysed seven temporal parameters, including duration times and number of repetitions. In total, we analysed five disciplines in which MI represents an important training strategy.Imagery models and frameworks in the education and psychology literatureHall described the cognitive processes and neural basis of MI in a review on educational literature, based on a MEDLINE search [7]., and proposed a six-stage procedure for explicit learning of surgical skills: task definition, prior learning, mental rehearsal, reflection, problem solving and reality check.In psychology, various tasks, participant groups and reporting statistics have been considered for MI. Driskell et al. summarised the effects of MP and determined under which conditions MI was most effective [13]. They defined five conditions of interest: 1) type of task, 2) retention interval, 3) experience level of trainees, 4) length of practice and 5) type of control group. The results of their meta-analysis showed a positive effect of MI when the following criteria were met: examination mainly of the cognitive aspects of the task performance, short retention interval, participants being novices to the task, and the MI session being about 20 minutes or shorter. They reported a non-significant trend for larger effects of MI compared with a non-treatment group and with an equivalent control treatment group.Imagery models and frameworks in the sports literatureIn the sports psychology literature, six imagery models and frameworks were reviewed by Guillot and Collet [26]. The models included a four-component scheme originally designed by Martin et al., who described how MI influences cognitive, affective and behavioural outcomes [20]. The six-stage model from Munroe et al. was also evaluated, including the well known 'W' questions (where, when and why do athletes use MI, and what do they imagine?) [28]. This qualitative method includes the type (visual, kinaesthetic) and perspective (internal, external) of MI. MacIntyre and Moran extended the framework of Munroe et al. by adding the question: 'How should MI be executed and used by athletes?' [29], and they described a multimodal model that includes definition, outcome and importance of MI. Holmes and Collins introduced the PETTLEP framework, building on findings in functional neuroscientific research literature and experience in sport psychology [30]. PETTLEP aims to facilitate designing MI interventions for athletes, and comprises seven components (physical, environment, task, timing, learning, emotion and perspective). These components describe the physical position of the individual, the environment that has to be imagined, the task involved, the timing or duration of the imagery, the learning or changes involved during imagery, the emotions that are associated with the task, and imagery perspective. By contrast, the three-step model described by Watt et al. focused on MI ability and two image-generation approaches: 1) vividness, control, duration, ease, and speed; and 2) visual sensory methods [31]. The recent framework proposed by Guillot and Collet aimed to combine key components from previously described models. Their Motor Imagery Integrative Model in Sport (MIIMS) includes four MI outcomes: 1) motor learning and performance; 2) motivation, self-confidence and anxiety; 3) strategies and problem-solving; and 4) injury rehabilitation. The scheme aimed to combine different imagery types (visual, kinaesthetic, olfactory, tactile and auditory) to create a complete mental version of the movement [26].Motor imagery in medicineMI research from sports psychology has been used in medicine, particularly in neurological rehabilitation [11-13]. Literature reviews have evaluated the overall beneficial effect of MI [5,9,11], but none has described the MITS elements or temporal parameters. In this review, we analysed the MITS elements and temporal parameters that have been successfully used in different disciplines: Education, Medicine, Music, Psychology and Sports (in this review, we use the term 'Sports' for all studies that include athletes as participants and the term 'Psychology' for all studies including healthy participants who are not athletes).<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Search terms and search strategy</title><p>Search terms were identified by a previous search of databases (including PubMed) and internet search engines (including Google and Google Scholar). Additionally, each searched database was checked for pre-defined MeSH terms, and where available, these terms were integrated into the search strategy. The following terms were used: 'mental imagery', 'mental practice', 'mental rehearsal', 'mental movements', 'eidetic imagery', 'visual imagery', 'guided imagery', 'motor imagery' and 'mental training'. The Appendix provides the complete search strategy for Scopus. The Scopus search strategy was adapted to individual databases and trial registers to account for specific vocabulary and syntax rules. No restrictions were made regarding year of publication, study design or age of the study population.</p></sec><sec><title>Study identification</title><p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> provides an overview of all databases, trial and dissertation registers, and conference proceedings searched. Database retrievals were imported into a reference management software package (EndNote; Thomson Reuters, Carlsbad, CA, USA). In total, 21,739 references were retrieved in February 2007. The literature search was repeated in June 2010 for references published between spring 2007 and 2010 in the largest databases of each discipline: the Education Resources Information Center (ERIC), Scopus, Répertoire International de Littérature Musicale (RILM), PsycINFO and SPORTDiscus. This search resulted in 5,741 additional references.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Overview of searched databases, trial and dissertation registers and conference proceedings, and the number of references found</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Number</th><th align="left">Discipline</th><th align="left">Database</th><th align="left">Searched time period</th><th align="left">References found, n</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Education</td><td align="left">Academic Search Premier</td><td align="left">1975 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">1040</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Medicine</td><td align="left">AMED</td><td align="left">1985 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">623</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Education</td><td align="left">ASSIA</td><td align="left">1987 to March 2007</td><td align="left">353</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td/><td align="left">AEI</td><td align="left">1979 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">84</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td/><td align="left">BEI</td><td align="left">1975 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Medicine</td><td align="left">BNI</td><td align="left">1985 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">54</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td/><td align="left">CINAHL</td><td align="left">1982 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">1606</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td/><td align="left">Cochrane Library</td><td align="left">1948/1995 to march 2007</td><td align="left">363</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td/><td align="left">Digital dissertations</td><td align="left">1930 to March 2007</td><td align="left">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td/><td align="left">DIMDI</td><td align="left">1967 to March 2007</td><td align="left">130</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Sports</td><td align="left">EMAERALD</td><td align="left">1965 to March 2007</td><td align="left">134</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">Education</td><td align="left">ERIC</td><td align="left">1966 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">795</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">Medicine</td><td align="left">GMS meetings</td><td align="left">2002 to March 2007</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td/><td align="left">ISI Proceedings</td><td align="left">1990 to March 2007</td><td align="left">241</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">Music</td><td align="left">JSTOR</td><td align="left">1665 (1800) to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">200</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Psychology</td><td align="left">PsycINFO</td><td align="left">1887 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">4588</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">Music</td><td align="left">RILM</td><td align="left">1967 to March 2007</td><td align="left">180</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">Medicine</td><td align="left">Scopus</td><td align="left">1996 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">2550</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">Sports</td><td align="left">SPORTD<italic>iscus</italic></td><td align="left">1800 to Feb 2007</td><td align="left">4023</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">Sports</td><td align="left">SPORLIT, SPOFOR, SPORMED</td><td align="left">1974 to Jan 2007</td><td align="left">589</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">Medicine</td><td align="left">ClinicalTrials.gov</td><td align="left">1997 to March 2007</td><td align="left">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">22</td><td/><td align="left">ISRCTN</td><td align="left">1998 March 2007</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">23</td><td/><td align="left">National Research Register</td><td align="left">2000 to March 2007</td><td align="left">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">24</td><td/><td align="left">Web of Science</td><td align="left">1970 to March 2007</td><td align="left">2837</td></tr><tr><td align="left">25</td><td/><td align="left">Zetoc</td><td align="left">1993 to March 2007</td><td align="left">1270</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="left">21,739</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AMED = Allied and Complementary Medicine, ASSIA = Applied Social Sciences Index and Abstracts, AEI = Australian Education International, BEI = British Education Index, BNI = British Nursing Index, CINAHL = Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health Literature, DIMDI = German Institute for Medical Documentation and Information, ERIC = Educational Resources Information Center, GMS = General Medical Services, ISI = Web of Knowledge, JSTOR = Journal STORage, RILM = Répertoire international de Littérature Musicale, SPORLIT = Sporlit(eratur), SPORFOR = Sporfor(schung), SPORMED = Spormed(ia), ISRCTN = International Standard Randomised Controlled Trial Number</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Study selection criteria</title><p>The references were selected for review inclusion based on the following criteria:</p><p>• Any design of quantitative intervention studies with a focus on imagining movements.</p><p>• Studies that included healthy volunteers, students, children, professionals, athletes or patients from any discipline.</p><p>• Study intervention that focused on motor skill, performance or strength improvement.</p><p>The following exclusion criteria were used:</p><p>• Mental practice not related to movements (audition, odour, any kind of visual imagery with static pictures).</p><p>• Mental practice based on a computer-animated technique (virtual reality).</p><p>• Mental practice used during a functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) session.</p><p>• Mental practice carried out during hypnosis or psychotherapy (guided imagery, eidetic imagery).</p><p>• Mental practice used as mental rotation or diagnostic tool.</p><p>• Suggested frameworks without participant evidence or experience.</p><p>• Publication language other than English or German.</p></sec><sec><title>Selection process</title><p>During the manual selection process (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), articles were evaluated based on title, abstract or keywords. Two of the authors (CS and RH) reviewed the articles; CS evaluated all references, and RH evaluated a randomly selected proportion (20%) of the initial number of references selected from each discipline. Full texts were ordered if no decision could be made based on the available information. If one reviewer could not reach a decision for a reference, this reference was discussed by both reviewers, and if both reviewers had not been able to agree on a decision (which was not the case in this investigation) a third reviewer (JB) would have been consulted.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>The literature selection process</bold>. Numbers in brackets indicate references retrieved from the search in June 2010. MI = motor imagery; MP = mental practice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1741-7015-9-75-1"/></fig><p>Owing to the large number of references, EndNote search options were used to eliminate studies based on the exclusion criteria.</p><p>To confirm the selection congruency between both independent reviewers, the inter-rater congruency was calculated. Reviewer agreement ranged between 78% and 100% (average 96%) for the five disciplines. Because some studies reported more than one MI intervention, the total exceeded the number of included studies. Each MI intervention was subsequently analysed as an independent investigation.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction</title><p>Information on study methods, MITS elements and temporal parameters were extracted by three researches (RB, AS, CS) and checked for accuracy (CS). Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> summarises all extracted information. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> illustrates the temporal parameters and the MITS terminology.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Overview of extracted MITS<sup>a </sup>elements</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Number</th><th align="left">MITS element</th><th align="left">MITS element description and categories</th><th align="left">PETTLEP category</th><th align="left">Dominant category found in successful MI<sup>b </sup>interventions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Position</td><td align="left">Describes the position of the individual during MI practice as <italic>task</italic>-<italic>specific </italic>or <italic>not task</italic>-<italic>specific</italic>.</td><td align="left">Physical</td><td align="left">Task-specific</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Location</td><td align="left">Describes the location of MITS as task-specific or <italic>not task</italic>-<italic>specific</italic>.</td><td align="left">Environment</td><td align="left">Task-specific</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Focus</td><td align="left">Each task consists of different parts. Focus of the intervention classifies the main focus of task-related activities that had to be imagined: <italic>motor</italic>, <italic>cognitive or strength</italic>.</td><td align="left">Task</td><td align="left">Motor-focused activities</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">Order</td><td align="left">Describes temporal order of MI and PP<sup>c </sup>trials. MI trials could have been performed <italic>before</italic>, <italic>between</italic>, <italic>after </italic>or <italic>simultaneously </italic>with PP.</td><td align="left">Timing</td><td align="left">MI after PP</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Integration</td><td align="left">Describes whether MI practice has been <italic>added </italic>to PP or <italic>embedded</italic><sup><italic>d </italic></sup>into PP.</td><td/><td align="left">Added</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">MI instructions medium</td><td align="left">MI instructions can be provided differently through one or more media types. Media type was scored as <italic>acoustic</italic>, <italic>written </italic>or <italic>visual</italic>. More than one media type could be assigned.</td><td align="left">Learning</td><td align="left">Acoustic</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">Instruction mode</td><td align="left">In addition to the instruction medium, the mode was classified as <italic>live </italic>or <italic>pre</italic>-<italic>recorded </italic>(for example, using tape or video).</td><td/><td align="left">Live</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">Supervision</td><td align="left">MITS could have been <italic>supervised </italic>or <italic>not supervised </italic>by an instructor present during the session.</td><td/><td align="left">Supervised</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">Directedness</td><td align="left">MITS could have been <italic>directed</italic><sup><italic>d </italic></sup>or <italic>non-directed </italic>when stepwise guidance was present or not.</td><td/><td align="left">Non-directed</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">Instruction type</td><td align="left">The description of MI instructions varied. Instructions could cover <italic>detailed </italic>descriptions for each part of the task that had to be imagined, <italic>simple keywords</italic>, or <italic>coarse </italic>(<italic>broad) </italic>overall MI instructions.</td><td/><td align="left">Detailed</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Instruction individuali-sation</td><td align="left">MI instructions could have been individualised to the participant's problems with the task that had to be imagined (<italic>tailored</italic>), or could have been the same for each participant (<italic>standardised</italic>).</td><td/><td align="left">Standardised</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">Familiari-sation</td><td align="left">Describe whether study participants had received an MI <italic>familiarisation session before </italic>the MI intervention began.</td><td/><td align="left">No familiarisation</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">Change</td><td align="left">Indicated whether modification of content, duration or dosage of the MI training occurred, to facilitate the learning process during the MI intervention period.</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">MI session</td><td align="left">MITS could have been classified as <italic>group </italic>sessions with more than one person participating in a MITS or as <italic>individual </italic>sessions with one participant only.</td><td align="left">Emotion</td><td align="left">Individual</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">Eyes</td><td align="left">During the MI, the participant's eyes could have been <italic>closed </italic>or <italic>open</italic>. In some interventions, participants started with one condition and changed to the other after one or several MITS.</td><td/><td align="left">Closed</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Perspective</td><td align="left">During the MI, participants could have imagined the task from an <italic>internal </italic>or <italic>external </italic>perspective. In some interventions, participants started with one condition and changed to the other after one or several MITS.</td><td align="left">Perspective</td><td align="left">Internal</td></tr><tr><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">Mode</td><td align="left">During the MI, participants could have used a <italic>kinaesthetic </italic>or <italic>visual </italic>mode. In some MI interventions, participants started with one condition and changed to the other during one or after several MITS.</td><td/><td align="left">Kinaesthetic</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Motor imagery training session.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Motor imagery.</p><p><sup>c</sup>Physical practice.</p><p><sup>d</sup>Used in MI interventions with no change or negative results, and differing from successful MI interventions.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Overview of extracted and calculated temporal parameters</bold>. MI = motor imagery; MITS = motor imagery training session; total MI time: = (total MITS count) × (MITS duration).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1741-7015-9-75-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Study quality rating</title><p>Two rating lists were used because studies with different quantitative designs were included. The Physiotherapy Evidence Database (PEDro) list was used to evaluate randomised controlled trials (RCTs) (maximum of ten points) and non-RCTs (maximum of eight points) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. For case series or single cases experimental designs, the 11-point Single Case Experimental Design (SCED) scale was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. All studies were rated by CS based on detailed rating guidelines. Studies received one point for each fulfilled methodological criterion on the respective rating list. The higher the achieved score, the better the study quality.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>Raw information was extracted into Excel (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA, USA). After coding and classification, MI intervention data was imported into statistical analysis software packages (SPSS versions 16 and 17 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA), MATLAB version 2009b (The MathWorks Inc., Natick, MA, USA)) for frequency analyses, frequency and mean comparison tests and visualisation. MI intervention data was not pooled or analysed for significant differences because of the variability in experimental settings and missing information in MI intervention descriptions. The heterogeneity between MI interventions was also present in standard deviations of temporal parameters. All MI interventions were classified into two categories: positive change (129 MI interventions, 91.5%), and no or negative change from pre- to post-test (12 MI interventions, 8.5%). MITS elements and temporal parameters of studies with positive change were summarised under the term 'average positive MI intervention' and used for comparison in three analyses.</p><p>First, trend analyses were performed to identify MITS elements for MI interventions with positive results versus no changes or negative results. Further analyses aimed to identify changing trends in MITS element frequencies in MI interventions with positive results for five different disciplines, integration approaches, MI training focus, session type, age and gender groups and MI intervention modifications. Secondly, the χ<sup>2 </sup>was used to test for significant differences between actual and expected observation frequencies for each MITS element. The tests were performed if 20% of the expected frequency showed an amount of 5 or more [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Thirdly, for temporal parameters, normal distribution was tested using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, and variance homogeneity was confirmed by the Levene test. Depending on the test results, group means were compared using Student <italic>t</italic>-test or Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test. The tests were used if at least five observations were available to estimate the statistic. For all temporal parameters, group means were compared against the average positive MI intervention.</p><p>For all statistical tests p ≤ 0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec>List of abbreviationsCCT: clinical controlled trial; CS: case series; fMRI = functional magnetic resonance imaging; MI: motor imagery; MITS: Motor Imagery Training Session; MP: mental practice; PP: physical practice; PETTLEP: physical, environment, timing, task, learning, emotion, perspective; PEDro: Physiotherapy Evidence Database; RCT = randomised controlled trial; SCRD: single-case research designConflicts of interestThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors' contributionsCS, BA, JB, UK and TE made substantial contributions to conception and design of the review. CS, RH, OAM, AS made substantial contributions to acquisition of data, and analysis and interpretation of data. CS, OAM, BA, JB, UK, TE were involved in drafting the manuscript and critically revising it. All authors have given final approval of the manuscript.AppendixExample search strategySearch strategy Scopus database from 22 February 2007: (((TITLE-ABS-KEY("mental imagery")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("mental practice")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("mental rehearsal")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("mental movements")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("eidetic imagery")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("visual imagery")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("guided imagery")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("motor imagery")) OR (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("mental training"))) AND NOT (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("mental health"))) AND NOT (TITLE-ABS-KEY-AUTH("body image")) 2,556 referencesPre-publication historyThe pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/9/75/prepubAcknowledgementsWe are grateful to Mr Jo Akers, Librarian, who helped with the search strategy and the reference export from the databases. We are also very thankful to all librarians who helped with the identification of authors, references and publications, and provided necessary documents. Additionally, we thank all the authors who answered our requests and provided the searched literature.FundingThe project was partially funded by the Gottfried und Julia Bangerter-Rhyner Foundation.FeltzDLLandersDMThe effects of mental practice on motor skill learning and performance: a meta-analysisJ Sport Exerc Psych198352557FeltzDLandersDMBeckerBJDruckmann D, Swets JAA revised meta-analysis of the mental practice literature on motor skill learningEnhancing Human Performance: Issues, theories, and techniques1988Washington D.C. National Academy Press61101FellNTMental rehearsal as a complementary treatment in geriatric rehabilitationPhys Occup Ther Geriatr20011845163BatsonGMotor imagery for stroke rehabilitation: current research as a guide to clinical practiceAlternative &amp; Complementary Therapies2004102848910.1089/107628004773933325BraunSMBeurskensAJBormPJSchackTWadeDTThe effects of mental practice in stroke rehabilitation: a systematic reviewArch Phys Med Rehabil200687684285210.1016/j.apmr.2006.02.03416731221FeltzDLLandersDMBeckerBJA Revised Meta-analysis of the Mental Practice Literature on Motor Skill Learning1988Washington, DC: National Academy PressHallJCImagery practice and the development of surgical skillsAm J Surg2002184546510.1016/S0002-9610(02)01007-312433615MulderTMotor imagery and action observation: cognitive tools for rehabilitationJ Neural Transm2007114101265127810.1007/s00702-007-0763-z17579805SharmaNPomeroyVMBaronJCMotor imagery - A backdoor to the motor system after stroke?Stroke20063771941195210.1161/01.STR.0000226902.43357.fc16741183WarnerLMcNeillMEMental imagery and its potential for physical therapyPhys Ther19886845165213281175Zimmermann-SchlatterASchusterCPuhanMSiekierkaESteurerJEfficacy of motor imagery in post-stroke rehabilitation: a systematic reviewJ NeuroEng Rehabil200858AnnettJMotor imagery: perception or action?Neuropsychologia199533111395141710.1016/0028-3932(95)00072-B8584177DriskellJCCopperCMoranADoes mental practice enhance performance?J Appl Psychol199479481192HamelO"Imagerie mentale": A review of mental imagery in the French language on the world wide webJ Ment Imagery2001251/28398HoneycuttJMFordSGMental imagery and intrapersonal communication: a review of research on imagined interactions (IIs) and current developmentsCommunication Yearbook20012531534610.1207/s15567419cy2501_9McKennaKTToothLRMental practice and its implications for occupational therapists: A literature reviewBrit J Occup Ther1991545169172SheikhAAPanagiotouNCUse of mental imagery in psychotherapy: a critical reviewPercept Mot Skills1975412555585241971SurburgPRApplication of imagery techniques to special populationsAdap Phys Activty Quart198964328337LeBoutillierNDavidFMMental imagery and creativity: a meta-analytic review studyBrit J Psychol20039412910.1348/00071260376284208412648387MartinKMoritzSHallCImagery use in sports: a literature review and applied model. Mental practiceInt J Sport Psychol1999245268MurphySJModels of imagery in sport psychology: a reviewJ Ment Imagery199014153172RichardsonAMental practice: a review and discussion part IRes Q19673895107RichardsonAMental practice: a review and discussion IIRes Q19673822632735338007TaktekKThe effects of mental imagery on the acquisition of motor skills and performance: A literature review with theoretical implicationsJ Ment Imagery20042879114GrouiosGMental practice: a reviewJ Sport Behav19921514259GuillotAColletCConstruction of the motor imagery integrative model in sport: a review and theoretical investigation of motor imagery useInt Rev Sport Exercise Psych200811314410.1080/17509840701823139Van LeeuwenRInglisJTiMental practice and imagery: a potential role in stroke rehabilitationPhys Ther Rev1998314754MunroeKJGiacobbiPRHallCWeinbergRThe four Ws of imagery use: where, when, why, and whatSport Psychol2000142119137MacIntyreTMoranAA qualitative investigation of meta-imagery processes and imagery direction among elite athletesJ Imagery Res Sport Phys Activity200721article 4.HolmesPSCollinsDJThe PETTLEP approach to motor imagery: A functional equivalence model for sport psychologistsJ Appl Sport Psychol20011316083WattAPMorrisTAndersenMBIssues in the development of a measure of imagery ability in sportJ Ment Imagery200428149180MaherCGSherringtonCHerbertRDMoseleyAMElkinsMReliability of the PEDro scale for rating quality of randomized controlled trialsPhys Ther200383871372112882612TateRLMcDonaldSPerdicesMTogherLSchultzRSavageSRating the methodological quality of single-subject designs and n-of-1 trials: introducing the Single-Case Experimental Design (SCED) ScaleNeuropsychol Rehabil200818438540110.1080/0960201080200920118576270MunroBHStatistical methods for health care research20055Philadelphia, Penn.; London: Lippincott Williams &amp; WilkinsRappGSchoderGKinesthetic imagination and learning of motor skillsPsychol Erz Unterr1973205279288TaktekKSalmoniARigalRThe Effects of Mental Imagery on the Learning and Transfer of a Discrete Motor Task by Young ChildrenJ Ment Imagery2004283-487120VergeerIJRMovement and stretching imagery during flexibility trainingJournal of sports sciences200624219720810.1080/0264041050013181116368630GuillotALebonFVernayMGirbonJPDoyonJColletCEffect of motor imagery in the rehabilitation of burn patientsJ Burn Care Res200930468669310.1097/BCR.0b013e3181ac000319506494CohnJExperimentelle Untersuchungen über das Zusammenwirken des akustisch motorischen und des visuellen GedächtnissesZ Psychol Sinn189715161183GaltonFStatistics of mental imageryMind18805301318EtnierJLLandersDMThe influence of procedural variables on the efficacy of mental practiceSport Psychol19961014857JarusTRatzonNZCan you imagine? The effect of mental practice on the acquisition and retention of a motor skill as a function of ageOccup ther J Res2000203163178ButlerTImperato-McGinleyJPanHVoyerDCorderoJZhuYSSternESilbersweigDSex differences in mental rotation: Top-down versus bottom-up processingNeuroimage200632144545610.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.03.03016714123GiacobbiPAge and activity-level differences in the use of exercise imageryJ Appl Sport Psychol200719448749310.1080/10413200701601508LutzRLandersDMLinderDEProcedural variables and skill level influences on pre-performance mental practice efficacyJ Ment Imagery2001253-4115134CallowNHardyLThe relationship between the use of kinaesthetic imagery and different visual imagery perspectivesJ Sports Sci200422216717710.1080/0264041031000164144914998095MoseleyGLGraded motor imagery for pathologic pain - A randomized controlled trialNeurology200667122129213410.1212/01.wnl.0000249112.56935.3217082465LoreyBBischoffMPilgrammSStarkRMunzertJZentgrafKThe embodied nature of motor imagery: the influence of posture and perspectiveExp Brain Res2009194223324310.1007/s00221-008-1693-119139856MahoneyMJAvenerMPsychology of the elite athlete: an exploratory studyCognitive Ther Res19772135141UngerleiderSGoldingJMMental practice among Olympic athletesPercep motor skills1991721007101710.2466/PMS.72.3.1007-1017KimBHGiacobbiPRJrThe Use of exercise-related mental imagery by middle-aged adultsJ Imagery Res Sport Phys Activity200941Article 1MulderTHochstenbachJBHvan HeuvelenMJGden OtterARMotor imagery: The relation between age and imagery capacityHum Movement Sci200726220321110.1016/j.humov.2007.01.001JacksonPLLafleurMFMalouinFRichardsCDoyonJPotential role of mental practice using motor imagery in neurologic rehabilitationArch Phys Med Rehabil20018281133114110.1053/apmr.2001.2428611494195GrouiosGOn the reduction of reaction time with mental practiceJ Sport Behav1992152141157GuillotATolleronCColletCDoes motor imagery enhance stretching and flexibility?J Sport Sci201028329129810.1080/02640410903473828IsaacARMental practice: Does it work in the field?Sport Psychol199262192198LejeuneMDeckerCSanchezXMental rehearsal in table tennis performancePercept Motor Skills199479Spec Issue Aug6276417808903Bovend'EerdtTJDawesHSackleyCIzadiHWadeDTAn integrated motor imagery program to improve functional task performance in neurorehabilitation: a single-blind randomized controlled trialArch Phys Med Rehabil201091693994610.1016/j.apmr.2010.03.00820510987DicksteinRDunskyAMarcovitzEMotor imagery for gait rehabilitation in post-stroke hemiparesisPhys Ther200484121167117715563257WrightCHogardEEllisRSmithDKellyCEffect of PETTLEP imagery training on performance of nursing skills: Pilot studyJ Adv Nurs200863325926510.1111/j.1365-2648.2008.04706.x18702772JacksonPLRichardsCLDoyonJMalouinFiThe efficacy of combined physical and mental practice in the learning of a foot-sequence task after stroke: A case reportNeurorehabil Neural Repair200418210611110.1177/088843900426524915228806MalouinFRichardsCLDoyonJDesrosiersJBellevilleSTraining mobility tasks after stroke with combined mental and physical practice: a feasibility studyNeurorehabil Neural Repair2004182667510.1177/088843900426630415228801MalouinFRichardsCLDurandADescentMPoireDFremontPPeletSGressetJDoyonJEffects of practice, visual loss, limb amputation, and disuse on motor imagery vividnessNeurorehabil Neural Repair200923544946310.1177/154596830832873319182047PageSJLevinePSistoSJohnstonMVA randomized efficacy and feasibility study of imagery in acute strokeClin Rehabil200115323324010.1191/02692150167206323511386392PageSJLevinePSistoSAJohnstonMVMental practice combined with physical practice for upper-limb motor deficit in subacute strokePhys Ther20018181455146211509075StenekesMWGeertzenJHNicolaiJPADe JongBMMulderTMotor imagery for peripheral injury responseArch Phys Med Rehabil20099081443144419651284MartinKAHallCRUsing mental imagery to enhance intrinsic motivationJ Sport Exerc Psych19951715469MunroeJOChandlerKJThe effects of image speed on the performance of a soccer taskSport Psychol2008221117ReiserMStrength gains by motor imagery of maximal muscle contractionsZ Sportpsychol20051121RyanEDSimonsJCognitive demand, imagery, and frequency of mental rehearsal as factors influencing acquistion of motor skillsJ Sport Psychol198133545SmithDCollinsDMental practice, motor performance, and the late CNVJ Sport Exerc Psych2004263412426SmithDHolmesPWhitemoreLCollinsDDevonportTThe effect of theoretically-based imagery scripts on field hockey performanceJ Sport Behav2001244408419ToussaintLBlandinYOn the role of imagery modalities on motor learningJ Sport Sci201028549750410.1080/02640410903555855WakefieldCJSmithDImpact of differing frequencies of PETTLEP imagery on netball shooting performanceJ Imagery Res Sport Phys Act200941ArtID 7.WhiteKDAshtonRLewisSLearning a complex skill: Effects of mental practice, physical practice, and imagery abilityInt J Sport Psychol19791027178WilliamsJGOdleyJLCallaghanMMotor imagery boosts proprioceptive neuromuscular facilitation in the attainment and retention of range of motion at the hip jointJ Sport Sci Med200433160166WrightCJSmithDThe effect of PETTLEP imagery on strength performanceJ Sport Exerc Psych20091831YaguezLNagelDHoffmanHCanavanAGMWistEHombergVA mental route to motor learning: Improving trajectorial kinematics through imagery trainingBehav Brain Res19989019510610.1016/S0166-4328(97)00087-99520217RobinNDominiqueLToussaintLBlandinYGuillotALe HerMEffects of motor imagery training in service return accuracy in tennis: the role of imagery abilityInt J Sport Exerc Psychol200752175186SmithDWrightCAllsoppAWestheadHIt's All in the Mind: PETTLEP-Based Imagery and Sports PerformanceJ Appl Sport Psychol2007191809210.1080/10413200600944132SmithDWrightCJCantwellCBeating the Bunker: The effect of PETTLEP imagery on golf bunker shot performanceRes Q Exerc Sport200879338539118816950SmithGGMoreyJTjoeEFeature Masking in Computer Game Promotes Visual ImageryJournal of Educational Computing Research200736335137210.2190/U124-1761-7PU5-3666RodriguesECLemosTGouveaBVolchanEImbiribaLAVargasCDKinesthetic motor imagery modulates body swayNeuroscience2010169274375010.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.04.08120457223Bovend'EerdtTJHDawesHSackleyCIzadiHWadeDTMental techniques during manual stretching in spasticity - a pilot randomized controlled trialClin Rehabil200923213714510.1177/026921550809729819164401DohenyMOEffects of mental practice on performance of a psychomotor skillJ Ment Imagery199317111118MoseleyGLZaluckiNBirkleinFMarinusJvan HiltenJJLuomajokiHThinking about movement hurts: The effect of motor imagery on pain and swelling in people with chronic arm painArthrit rheumat200859562363110.1002/art.23580StartKBIntelligence and the improvement in a gross motor skill after mental practiceBrit J Educ Psychol1964341859010.1111/j.2044-8279.1964.tb00608.xStartKBRichardsonAImagery and mental practiceBrit J Educ Psychol196434328028410.1111/j.2044-8279.1964.tb00638.xBraunSBeurskensAJKleynenMOudelaarBScholsJMWadeDTEffects of mental practice in stroke rehabilitation in Dutch nursing homes: results of a randomised controlled trial2010 in press BraunSBeurskensAJKleynenMScholsJMWadeDTEffects of mental practice in patients with Parkinson's disease: results from a multi-centre randomised controlled trial2010 in press MorinLLathamGPThe effect of mental practice and goal setting as a transfer of training intervention on supervisors' self-efficacy and communication skills: An exploratory studyAppl Psychol Int Rev200049356657810.1111/1464-0597.00032RodgersKCDirected imagery versus free imagery for inducing changes in self-perspective and moodDis Abstr Int1982427-B3001BucherLThe effects of imagery abilities and mental rehearsal on learning a nursing skillJ Nurs Edu1993327318324DohenyMOEffects of mental practice on psychomotor skills with baccalaureate nursing studentsDis Abstr Int1990512-B659ImmenrothMEberspacherHNagelschmidtMTroidlHBurgerTBrennerJBergTMullerMKemmlerRMental training in surgery - Security by a better training: Design and first results of a studyMIC20051416974KomesuYUrwitzLaneROzelBLukbanJKahnMMuirTFennerDRogersRDoes mental imagery prior to cystoscopy make a difference? A randomized controlled trialAm J Obstet Gynecol20092012218.e211218.e21919481728SandersCWSadoskiMBramsonRWiprudRVan WalsumKComparing the effects of physical practice and mental imagery rehearsal on learning basic surgical skills by medical studentsAm J Obstet Gynecol200419151811181410.1016/j.ajog.2004.07.07515547570SandersCWSadoskiMvan WalsumKBramsonRWiprudRFossumTWLearning basic surgical skills with mental imagery: using the simulation centre in the mindMed Educ200842660761210.1111/j.1365-2923.2007.02964.x18435713StigLCChristensenHWByfieldDSasnowMComparison of the effectiveness of physical practice and mental practice in the learning of chiropractic adjustive skillsEur J Chiropractic19893737076WelkAImmenrothMSakicPBernhardtOEberspächerHMeyerGMental training in dentistryQuintessence Int200738648949717625632CramerSCOrrELRCohenMJLacourseMGEffects of motor imagery training after chronic, complete spinal cord injuryExp Brain Res2007177223324210.1007/s00221-006-0662-916944108CrosbieJHMcDonoughSMGilmoreDHWiggamMIThe adjunctive role of mental practice in the rehabilitation of the upper limb after hemiplegic stroke: a pilot studyClin Rehabil2004181606810.1191/0269215504cr702oa14763720DijkermanHCIetswaartMJohnstonMMacWalterRSDoes motor imagery training improve hand function in chronic stroke patients? A pilot studyClin Rehabil200418553854910.1191/0269215504cr769oa15293488DunskyADicksteinRAriavCDeutschJMarcovitzEMotor imagery practice in gait rehabilitation of chronic post-stroke hemiparesis: four case studiesInt J Rehabil Res200629435135610.1097/MRR.0b013e328010f55917106356DunskyADicksteinRMarcovitzELevySDeutschJHome-based motor imagery training for gait rehabilitation of people with chronic poststroke hemiparesisArch Phys Med Rehabil20088981580158810.1016/j.apmr.2007.12.03918674992GustinSMWrigleyPJGandeviaSCMiddletonJWHendersonLASiddallPJMovement imagery increases pain in people with neuropathic pain following complete thoracic spinal cord injuryPain2008137223724410.1016/j.pain.2007.08.03217942228HewettTEFordKRLevinePPageSJReaching kinematics to measure motor changes after mental practice in strokeTop Stroke Rehabil2007144232910.1310/tsr1404-2317698455JacksonPLDoyonJRichardsCLMalouinFThe efficacy of combined physical and mental practice in the learning of a foot-sequence task after stroke: a case reportNeurorehabil Neural Repair200418210611110.1177/088843900426524915228806LiuKPChanCCLeeTMHuiChanCWMental imagery for promoting relearning for people after stroke: A randomized controlled trialArch Phys Med Rehabil20048591403140810.1016/j.apmr.2003.12.03515375808LiuKPChanCCLeeTMHui-ChanCWMental imagery for relearning of people after brain injuryBrain Inj200418111163117210.1080/0269905041000167188315545212LiuKPYChanCCHWongRSMKwanIWLYauCSFLiLSWLeeTMCA randomized controlled trial of mental imagery augment generalization of learning in acute poststroke patientsStroke20094062222222510.1161/STROKEAHA.108.54099719390069McCarthyMBeaumontJGThompsonRPringleHThe role of imagery in the rehabilitation of neglect in severely disabled brain-injured adultsArch Clin Neuropsych2002175407422MoseleyGLGraded motor imagery is effective for long-standing complex regional pain syndrome: a randomised controlled trialPain20041081-219219810.1016/j.pain.2004.01.00615109523MoseleyGLIs successful rehabilitation of complex regional pain syndrome due to sustained attention to the affected limb? A randomised clinical trialPPA News20051141-25461MuellerKButefischCMSeitzRJHombergVMental practice improves hand function after hemiparetic strokeRestor Neurol Neurosci2007255-650151118334768PageSJImagery improves upper extremity motor function in chronic stroke patients: a pilot studyOccup Ther J Res2000203200215PageSJLevinePLeonardACEffects of mental practice on affected limb use and function in chronic strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil200586339940210.1016/j.apmr.2004.10.00215759218PageSJLevinePHillVMental practice as a gateway to modified constraint-induced movement therapy: A promising combination to improve functionAm J Occup Ther200761332132717569389PageSJLevinePLeonardAMental practice in chronic stroke: Results of a randomized, placebo-controlled trialStroke20073841293129710.1161/01.STR.0000260205.67348.2b17332444PageSJSzaflarskiJPEliassenJCPanHCramerSCCortical plasticity following motor skill learning during mental practice in strokeNeurorehabil Neural Repair200923438238819155350PageSJLevinePKhouryJCModified constraint-induced therapy combined with mental practice thinking through better motor outcomesStroke200940255155410.1161/STROKEAHA.108.52876019109542RiccioIIolasconGBarillariMRGimiglianoRGimiglianoFMental practice is effective in upper limb recovery after stroke: A randomized single-blind cross-over studyEur J Rehabil Med20104611925SimmonsLSharmaNBaronJCPomeroyVMMotor imagery to enhance recovery after subcortical stroke: who might benefit, daily dose, and potential effectsNeurorehabil Neural Repair200822545846710.1177/154596830831559718780881StevensJAStoykovMEUsing motor imagery in the rehabilitation of hemiparesisArch Phys Med Rehabil20038471090109210.1016/S0003-9993(03)00042-X12881842TamirRDicksteinRHubermanMIntegration of motor imagery and physical practice in group treatment applied to subjects with Parkinson's diseaseNeurorehabil Neural Repair2007211687510.1177/154596830629260817172556YooEChungBThe effect of visual feedback plus mental practice on symmetrical weight-bearing training in people with hemiparesisClin Rehabil2006205388397(334 ref) NLI: 880218110.1191/0269215506cr962oa16774089CoffmanDDEffects of mental practice, physical practice, and knowledge of results on piano performanceJ Res Music Educ199038318719610.2307/3345182RossSLThe effectiveness of mental practice in improving the performance of college trombonistsJ Res Music Educ198533422123010.2307/3345249Rubin RabsonGStudies in the psychology of memorizing piano music. VI: A comparison of two forms of mental rehearsal and keyboard overlearningJ Educ Psychol1941328593602SonnenscheinIMentales Training in der Instrumentenausbildung (MTI)Psychol Erz Unterr1990373232236TheilerAMLippmanLGEffects of mental practice and modeling on guitar and vocal performanceJ Gen Psychol1995122432934310.1080/00221309.1995.9921245AllamiNPaulignanYBrovelliABoussaoudDVisuo-motor learning with combination of different rates of motor imagery and physical practiceExp Brain Res2008184110511317849109AlvesJBelgaPBritoAPMental Training and Motor Learning in VolleyballPrague: European Federation of Sport Psychology19995961AndreJCMeansJRRate of imagery in mental practice: An experimental investigationJ Sport Psychol198682124128ChevalierNBoucherJPGeoffrionRDenisMVisual and kinesthetic imagery in the mental rehearsal of a complex movement: an exploratory studySports science: 8 Commonwealth and international conference on sport, physical education, dance, recreation and health: 1986; Glasgow1986343348ClarkLVEffect of mental practice on the development of a certain motor skillRes Q Am Ass Health, Phys Ed Recr196031560569CleggBAWoodJABuggJMReal and imagined movements in older and younger adultsJ Ment Imagery2004281-2116CorbinCBEffects of mental practice on the development of a specific motor skill. PhD thesis1966Eugene, Ore.; United States: University of New MexicoCornwallMWBruscatoMPBarrySThe effect of mental practice on isometric muscular strengthJ Orthop Sport Phys199113231234DecetyJMotor information may be important for updating the cognitive processes involved in mental imagery of movementCur Psychol Cogn1991114415426GassnerKEinsiedelTLinkeMGrlichPMayerJDoes mental training improve learning to walk with a femoral prosthesis?Orthopade200736767367810.1007/s00132-007-1092-517522841GordonSWeinbergRJacksonAEffect of internal and external imagery on cricket performanceJ Sport Behav1994176076GraySWEffect of visuomotor rehearsal with videotaped modeling on racquetball performance of beginning playersPercept Motor Skills199070237938510.2466/PMS.70.2.379-3852342836HellwingWKnuffWMental preparation: a possibility for intensifying physical educationSportunterricht1976256180187HemayattalabRMovahediAEffects of different variations of mental and physical practice on sport skill learning in adolescents with mental retardationRes Dev Disabil2009311818619875270HerreroJAGarciaDSoriaEInfluence of imagery rehearsal on the maximum isometric force in bench pressPoliclinico Sez Med200411111120JaehmeWSteinhoeferDEmpirical study on the effectiveness of mental training in swimming with 10th and 11th grade high school studentsLehrhilf Sportunterr19782757174JonesJGMotor learning without demonstration of physical practice, under two conditions of mental practiceRes Quart1965363270276KelseyIBEffects of mental practice and physical practice upon muscular enduranceRes Quat1961324754KohlRMRoenkerDLBilateral transfer as a function of mental imageryJ Motor Behav1980123197206KornspanASOverbyLLernerBSAnalysis and performance ofpre-performance imagery and other strategies on a golf putting taskJ Ment Imagery2004285974KremerPSpittleMMcNeilDShinnersCAmount of mental practice and performance of a simple motor taskPercept Motor Skills2009109234735610.2466/pms.109.2.347-35620037987KrigolsonOVan GynGTremblayLHeathMIs There "Feedback" During Visual Imagery? Evidence From a Specificity of Practice ParadigmCan J Exp Psychol2006601243216615715LindenCAUhleyJESmithDBushMAThe effects of mental practice on walking balance in an elderly populationOccup Ther J Res198993155169MaringJREffects of mental practice on rate of skill acquisitionPhys Ther19907031651722304974McAleneyPJBarabaszAFBarabaszMEffects of flotation restricted environmental stimulation on intercollegiate tennis performancePercept Motor Skills199071310231028MinasSCMental practice of a complex perceptual-motor skillJ Hum Movement Stud197842102107PapaxanthisCPozzoTSkouraXSchieppatiMDoes order and timing in performance of imagined and actual movements affect the motor imagery process? The duration of walking and writing taskBehav Brain Res20021341-220921510.1016/S0166-4328(02)00030-X12191807PhippsSJMorehouseCAEffects of mental practice on the acquisition of motor skills of varied difficultyRes Q Exericse Sport1969404773778RanganathanVKSiemionowVLiuJZSahgalVYueGHFrom mental power to muscle power--gaining strength by using the mindNeuropsychologia200442794495610.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2003.11.01814998709RawlingsEIRawlingsILChenSSYilkMDThe facilitating effects of mental rehearsal in the acquisition of rotary pursuit trackingPsychon Sci19722627173RyanEDSimonsJCognitive demand, imagery, and frequency of mental rehearsal as factors influencing acquisition of motor skillsJ Sport Psychol1981313545RyanEDSimonsJEfficacy of mental imagery in enhancing mental rehearsal of motor skillsJ Sport Psychol1982414151ShackellEMStandingLGMind Over Matter: Mental Training Increases Physical StrengthN Am J Psychol200791189200SidawaySTrzaskaACan mental practice increase ankle dorsiflexor torque?Phys Ther200585101053106016180954SingerRNWitkerJMental rehearsal and point of introduction within the context of overt practicePercept Motor Skills1970311169170SmithLEHarrisonJSComparison of the effects of visual, motor, mental, and guided practice upon speed and accuracy of performing a simple eye-hand coordination taskRes Q Am Assoc Health, Phys Ed Recr1962332299307SmythMMThe role of mental practice in skill acquisitionJ Motor Behav197573199206StartKBRelationship between intelligence and the effect of mental practice on the performance of a motor skillRes Q Am Assoc Health, Phys Ed Recr196031644649StartKBKinaesthesis and mental practiceRes Q Am Assoc Health, Phys Ed Recr1964353316320StebbinsRJA comparison of the effects of physical and mental practice in learning a motor skillRes Quart1968393714720SurburgPRAging and effect of physical-mental practice upon acquisition and retention of a motor skillJ Gerontol197631164671244405TunneyNBillingsKBlakelyBGBurchDJacksonKMental practice and motor learning of a functional motor task in older adults: a pilot studyPhys Occup Ther Geriatr20062436380TwiningWEMental practice and physical practice in learning a motor skillRes Q Am Assoc Health, Phys Ed Recr194920432435Van GynGWengerHAGaulCImagery as a method of enhancing trenasfer from training to performanceJ Sport Exerc Psychol199012366375VandellRADavisRAClugstonHAThe function of mental practice in the acquisition of motor skillsJ Gen Psychol194329243250WhiteleyGEffect of mental rehearsal in association with physical practice in the acquisitions of simple gymnastic techniquesResearch papers in physical education19663Dec2528WohldmannELHealyAFBourneLEPushing the Limits of Imagination: Mental Practice for Learning SequencesJ Exp Psychol Learn Mem Cogn200733125426117201567WoolfolkRLMurphySMGottesfeldDAitkenDEffects of mental rehearsal of task motor activity and mental depiction of task outcome on motor skill performanceJ Sport Psychol198572191197WoolfolkRLParrishMWMurphySMThe effects of positive and negative imagery on motor skill performanceCognitive Ther Res19859333534110.1007/BF01183852ZeckerSGMental practice and knowledge of results in the learning of a perceptual motor skillJ Sport Psychol1982415263CasbyAMoranAExploring mental imagery in swimmers: A single-case study designIrish J Psychol1998194525531GuillotANadrowskaEColletCUsing Motor Imagery to Learn Tactical Movements in BasketballJ Sport Behav2009322189OlssonCJJonssonBNybergLInternal imagery training in active high jumpersScand J Psychol2008Apr 2008ShambrookCJBullSJThe use of a single-case research design to investigate the efficacy of imagery trainingJ Appl Sport Psychol199681274310.1080/10413209608406306ZiemainzHStollOKusterCAdlerKEvaluation of the mental training of the change from one event to the other in youth and junior triathlonLeistungssport20033322022
