<?xml version="1.0"?>
J Hum KinetJ Hum KinetJHKJournal of Human Kinetics1640-55441899-7562Akademia Wychowania Fizycznego w Katowicach366189510.2478/hukin-2013-0006jhk-36-55Research ArticleSection II-Exercise Physiology &amp; Sports MedicineCardiorespiratory Fitness and Motor Skills in Relation to Cognition and Academic Performance in Children – A ReviewHaapalaEero A.11Department of Physiology, Institute of Biomedicine, University of Eastern Finland, Campus of Kuopio, Finland.Authors submitted their contribution of the article to the editorial board.Corresponding author: Eero A. Haapala, Department of Physiology, Institute of Biomedicine, University of Eastern Finland., Keskussairaalantie 11 A 10, FI-40600, Jyväskylä, Finland., Phone: +35840 725 4025, E-mail: ehaapala@student.uef.fi32013283201336556832013© Editorial Committee of Journal of Human Kinetics2013This article is an open-access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/).Different elements of physical fitness in children have shown a declining trend during the past few decades. Cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills have been associated with cognition, but the magnitude of this association remains unknown. The purpose of this review is to provide an overview of the relationship of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills with cognitive functions and academic performance in children up to 13 years of age. Cross-sectional studies suggest that children with higher cardiorespiratory fitness have more efficient cognitive processing at the neuroelectric level, as well as larger hippocampal and basal ganglia volumes, compared to children with lower cardiorespiratory fitness. Higher cardiorespiratory fitness has been associated with better inhibitory control in tasks requiring rigorous attention allocation. Better motor skills have been related to more efficient cognitive functions including inhibitory control and working memory. Higher cardiorespiratory fitness and better motor skills have also been associated with better academic performance. Furthermore, none of the studies on cardiorespiratory fitness have revealed independent associations with cognitive functions by controlling for motor skills. Studies concerning the relationship between motor skills and cognitive functions also did not consider cardiorespiratory fitness in the analyses. The results of this review suggest that high levels of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills may be beneficial for cognitive development and academic performance but the evidence relies mainly on cross-sectional studies.physical fitnessmovement skillsphysical activitychildrenscholastic achievementIntroductionFewer than 20% of children meet the recommendations for health enhancing physical activity: at least 60 minutes of moderate to vigorous intensity physical activity, preferably on every day of the week (Verloigne et al., 2012). Furthermore, a decreasing trend in cardiorespiratory fitness has been documented (Tomkinson and Olds, 2007). Evidence indicates a similar trend in mastery of fundamental motor skills (Hardy et al., 2011).Concerns have arisen as to whether today’s lifestyle has a similarly negative effect on children’s metabolic, cardiovascular, and brain health as it has on adults (Hillman et al., 2008). Physical activity has been found to be a foundation of development and reinforcement of motor skills (Riethmuller et al., 2009). Moreover, children with higher physical activity level also have a higher level of cardiorespiratory fitness, although the effect of physical exercise on cardiorespiratory fitness is smaller in children than in adults (Rowland, 2007). In addition, a higher level of physical activity has been related to better academic performance and executive functions in children and adolescents (Hillman et al., 2008). Executive function is an umbrella term for goal-oriented mental processes, which include planning, organising, behavioural inhibition, and working memory processes.It is hypothesised that a positive effect of physical activity on cognitive functions is partly caused by physiological changes in the body such as increased levels of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), that facilitates learning and maintains cognitive functions by improving synaptic plasticity and acting as a neuroprotective agent, increased brain circulation and improved neuroelectric functionality (Hillman et al., 2008). In animal studies it has been shown that different kinds of activities cause different adaptations in the brain. Endurance exercise is shown to increase capillary density (angiogenesis) and thereby to increase the brain blood flow whereas motor exercises are shown to cause synaptogenesis or an increased number of synapses (Adkins et al., 2006). Therefore, cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills may be differently related to cognition and academic performance among children. Although higher physical activity level in general has been linked to improved cognitive performance, only few studies have compared aerobic and motor exercise in relation to cognitive functions among children and therefore, it is appropriate to compare cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills although those measures are affected by maturation and genetic factors (Malina et al., 2004).As children are becoming increasingly sedentary and unfit, it is important to recognise effective interventions to improve metabolic, cardiovascular, as well as cognitive health. The purpose of the present review is to summarise the evidence of associations of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills with some important components of cognition and brain functioning that are linked to academic performance among children up to 13-years of age. Also relevant literature of associations of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills with academic performance is described. These data is accompanied by the existence of physical or motor activity studies that report measures of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills. In addition, factors that may confound these results are discussed.Inhibitory controlInhibitory control is the core of the higher cognitive functions called the executive control. Inhibitory control refers to higher order mental processes that are related to the control of attention, behaviour and emotions and involves mainly the neural networks in the prefrontal and parietal cortices (Diamond, 2013). Inhibitory control includes a selective attention to the requisite stimulus despite inappropriate or interfering stimuli and maintenance of information in working memory. Among children, inhibitory control is shown to be an important predictor of academic performance but also physical and mental health in adulthood and thereby, it is an important component of childhood cognitive development (Diamond, 2013).The Eriksen flanker task is one of the most used tests for inhibitory control among children in fitness studies. The flanker task requires the child to identify as quickly and accurately as possible the direction of the centrally positioned arrow in either congruent (e.g. &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt;) or incongruent (e.g. &lt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt;) conditions. The demands of inhibitory control can be further increased using incompatible conditions. That is, the child is instructed to answer the opposite direction from the direction that the centrally presented arrow is pointing.Evidence suggests that high levels of cardiorespiratory fitness is associated with a better response accuracy in the flanker task (Chaddock et al., 2012a; Chaddock et al., 2012b; Hillman et al., 2009; Pontifex et al., 2011; Voss et al., 2011) (Table 1). Moreover, some studies indicate that compared to unfit children, highly fit children are more accurate in the incongruent condition (but not in congruent condition) and have less variability in the response accuracy and reaction times in the flanker task conditions that involved a variable amount of interference (Pontifex et al., 2011; Voss et al., 2011).Improved flanker task accuracy is accompanied by more efficient brain activation. Studies using event-related brain potentials (ERP) have shown that highly fit children have better inhibitory control and exhibit larger P3 amplitudes than unfit children (Hillman et al., 2009; Pontifex et al., 2011) (Table 1). The P3 is a positive-going component that is believed to reflect a subject’s attention to stimuli and processing speed. A larger P3 amplitude indicates an increased amount of attentional resources allocated towards a stimulus (Hillman et al., 2008). Moreover, highly fit children also have reduced error-related negativity (ERN) amplitude during the flanker task (Hillman et al., 2009). In addition, higher levels of fitness have been related to a larger change in ERN amplitude between the compatibility conditions (Pontifex et al., 2011).The ERN is an ERP component that has been related to erroneous responses in tasks that emphasise reaction time. Some evidence indicates that the ERN is related to known mistakes and is therefore a marker for error detection and compensation, that is, action monitoring (Gehring et al., 1993). Furthermore, increased ERN may also be associated with an increased level of response conflict (Gehring and Fencsik, 2001) and reduced ERN may reflect more efficient action monitoring (Gehring et al., 1993). Thus, these results indicate that higher levels of cardiorespiratory fitness is related to a better attention allocation, action monitoring and increased modulation of cognitive control.Cross-sectional studies using functional magnetic resonance imaging technique (fMRI) indicate that children with high levels of fitness exhibit more efficient neural activation and cognitive adaptation during the flanker task compared with less fit children (Chaddock et al., 2012b; Voss et al., 2011) (Table 1). Findings suggest that cortical activation does not differ between highly fit and unfit children during the congruent condition, but when cognitive demands increase during the incongruent condition, highly fit children maintain their response accuracy and exhibit greater activation in the prefrontal and parietal cortices in the early task period and reduced activation in the later periods indicating more effective cognitive flexibility (Chaddock et al., 2012b). Another study showed increased activation in the prefrontal cortex and decreased activation in the posterior parietal cortex of highly fit children during the flanker task (Voss et al., 2011). Moreover, highly fit children showed lower or the same activation than unfit children in the left central opecular cortex in the incongruent condition of the flanker task. Interestingly, higher activation was related to task performance only among highly fit children. Of these brain regions, the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex is involved in the manipulation of task relevant information within working memory (Diamond, 2013) and is related to top-down regulation of executive functions (MacDonald III et al., 2000). Also, the parietal cortex is involved in inhibitory control (Brass et al., 2005), and like the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, parietal cortex is important for the working memory function (Hillman et al., 2008). Thus, the findings indicate that 9 to 10-year-old children with superior cardiorespiratory fitness are capable of activating their frontal and parietal circuitry in demanding cognitive tasks more efficiently than their less fit counterparts.Moreover, some evidence indicates that better response accuracy among highly fit children in comparison with unfit children is related to larger subcortical structure volumes (Table 1). Chaddock et al. (2012a) found that compared to unfit children, highly fit children had larger bilateral putamen and glopus pallidus volumes and greater response accuracy during a modified flanker task in the baseline as well as in the one-year follow-up. Highly fit children also had shorter reaction times in the follow-up. The authors concluded that greater volumes of the putamen and the globus pallidus were associated with better cognitive control.Also motor skills have been studied in relation to cognitive control. Among studies, the results are inconsistent and the magnitude of associations is dependent on the assessment of inhibitory control. Better manual dexterity (but not throwing accuracy or balance) has been associated with shorter reaction times in the modified day-night Stroop task whereas motor skills were not related to the reaction times during the Go/NoGo task (Livesey et al., 2006) (Table 1). Better whole body coordination (including sideways jumping speed and better ability to quickly change posture from lying down to an upright position and back to lying down i.e. postural flexibility) and better manual dexterity have been linked to shorter reaction times of correct responses during the Simon task (Roebers and Kauer, 2009). In addition, a better sideways jumping performance was associated with shorter reaction times in the flanker task, whereas other whole body coordination and manual dexterity skills were not related to the flanker task performance (Roebers and Kauer, 2009). However, these studies did not investigate relationships between motor skills and response accuracy. There is some vagueness whether reaction time is an appropriate measure of inhibitory control. Evidence suggests that children with high and low cardiorespiratory fitness did not differ in their reaction times in the flanker task but children with higher levels of fitness have better response accuracy than those with lower levels of fitness (Hillman et al., 2009; Pontifex et al., 2011).Working and short term memoryWorking memory involves holding and manipulating the information in mind and relies on dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. Working memory involves also associative or relational memory. Relational memory involves learning about the relationship between two stimuli. In contrast, short term memory involves keeping information in mind without manipulating it, thus learning the properties of the stimulus (i.e. item memory). Short term memory does not need involvement of dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and it relies on ventrolateral prefrontal cortex (Diamond, 2013). In the behavioural point of view, working memory has been linked to academic performance among children. Moreover, inhibitory control is linked to working memory, thus inhibitory control is shown to support the working memory processes (Diamond, 2013).The current evidence suggests that higher levels of cardiorespiratory fitness are related to a better relational memory and thereby hippocampal encoding (Chaddock et al., 2010; Monti et al., 2012) (Table 2). However, these studies did not find a relationship between cardiorespiratory fitness and item memory. In addition, a larger bilateral hippocampal volume has been related to a better relational memory and based on mediating analyses, bilateral hippocampal volume is shown to mediate the relationship between cardiorespiratory fitness and relational memory (Chaddock et al., 2010b) (Table 2). Moreover, Monti et al. (2012) extended these cross-sectional designs by conducting a longitudinal analyses to study whether nine-month aerobic training was related to working memory performance and eye movement patterns during a memory task in the follow-up. Children in the training group increased their VO2max percentile whereas the VO2max percentile among children in the control group slightly decreased. Children in the training group had a longer viewing time for displayed pictures during relational memory tasks that required the children to encode and correctly retrieve self-chosen sets of scenes and faces. In contrast, no differences in viewing time were observed during an item memory task that required retrieval of familiar faces without any need to relate them to a scene. Moreover, they found no differences in task accuracy or reaction times. Although no fitness differences were observed in response accuracy, these results indicated that increased cardiorespiratory fitness is related to more efficient hippocampal encoding. Evidence suggests that improved hippocampal encoding alone is not enough to elicit correct responses during relational memory tasks; high performance on tasks requires prefrontal cortex activation and efficient hippocampal prefrontal cortex connectivity (Hannula and Ranganath, 2009). Moreover, these results by Monti et al. (2012) should be interpreted cautiously because there was no baseline assessment for memory performance.In addition, findings by Niederer et al. (2011) support other studies on a non-significant relationship between cardiorespiratory fitness and item memory (Table 2). However, Kamijo et al. (2011) conducted a RCT study whether aerobic exercise training over a nine-month period would have an effect on item memory and ERP component called contingent negative variation (CNV). The CNV reflects cognitive, motor, and sensory processes in preparation for an upcoming stimulus. The CNV includes at least two components, initial and terminal waves, which have different functions (Brunia and van Boxtel, 2001). The initial CNV wave has been associated with stimulus orientation (Weerts and Lang, 1973) whereas the late wave is mainly related to motor and response preparation (Brunia and van Boxtel, 2001). Kamijo et al. (2011) adopted a modified Stenberg task to assess a delayed recognition of previously presented arrays of letters. After the intervention, only the training group (relative to the control group) improved their VO2max by 4.2 ml/kg/min, as well as their response accuracy in comparison to pre-intervention accuracy. Improved accuracy was observed only in the task condition, where the child was required to encode an array of three letters; no significant improvement was found when one or five letters were encoded. The exercise group also exhibited greater frontal initial CNV (iCNV) amplitude compared with controls on post-intervention testing. The authors speculated that cardiorespiratory fitness-related increases in iCNV amplitude indicate an increased efficiency of anticipatory attention and pronounced top-down control. However, these results concerning the effect of cardiorespiratory fitness on item memory are in contrast to other studies showing no relationship between cardiorespiratory fitness and item memory. Therefore, improved item memory may be due to physical exercise per se, without a mediating effect of cardiorespiratory fitness.The relationship between motor skills and memory has been investigated using mainly item memory tests. Both, a better whole body coordination and manual dexterity, have been associated with a better item memory (Niederer et al., 2011; Piek et al., 2008; Roebers and Kauer, 2009; Wassenberg et al., 2005) (Table 2). Furthermore, some evidence indicates that earlier gross motor development predict item memory at later years (Piek et al., 2008). Moreover, motor skills may be differently related to working memory depending on whether the assessment of motor skills is an outcome oriented (e.g. distance in the standing long jump) or a process oriented (e.g. throwing technique). Wassenberg et al. (2005) demonstrated no relationship between motor test outcomes, but showed a positive relationship between fluency and technique during the motor task and item working memory test performance. Moreover, in one study, more agile children showed superior item recall than their less agile peers. Furthermore, children with better dynamic balance at the baseline showed significant improvement in item memory during a nine-month follow-up (Niederer et al., 2011). However, not all studies have found a relationship between motor skills (manual dexterity) and spatial working memory (Pangelinan et al., 2011) indicating some specificity of effects of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills on memory functions.Academic performanceAcademic performance refers to a child′s success in school, measured by grade point averages or the child’s meeting standards of various achievement tests. In addition to plain academic knowledge, grade point averages usually contain information about class attendance or classroom behaviour, whereas standardised tests rely on academic knowledge. Academic performance is affected by inhibitory control and working memory performance, as well as efficiency of other aspects of executive control (Diamond, 2013).Cross-sectional studies suggest that higher cardiorespiratory fitness is related to better results and higher scores in standardised achievement tests (Van Dusen et al., 2011; Welk et al., 2010; Wittberg et al., 2010, Davis and Cooper, 2011) and to higher scholastic ratings (Dwyer et al., 2001) in comparison to peers with a lower fitness level (Table 3).Most studies have addressed the relationship between cardiorespiratory fitness and academic performance using field-based exercise tests and cut-offs for cardiorespiratory fitness (Van Dusen et al., 2011; Welk et al., 2010). These studies indicate that achieving a certain cardiorespiratory fitness level is significantly and positively associated with improved academic performance (Table 3). Studies that have adopted linear methods also indicate that higher cardiorespiratory fitness is related to better academic performance (Dwyer et al., 2001; Wittberg et al., 2010; Davis and Cooper, 2011). Furthermore, these studies suggest that the degree of the association between cardiorespiratory fitness and academic performance depends on the assessment of cardiorespiratory fitness. Whereas Dwyer et al. (2001) did not find a significant association between academic performance and cardiorespiratory fitness estimated by a cycle ergometer, a significant association was found when they used time spent on a 1.6 km running test as a measure of cardiorespiratory fitness. Instead, one study found that low running time in one mile test was associated with better academic performance, whereas no association was found between endurance shuttle run test and academic performance among 9- to 13-year-old boys. In contrast, the association between cardiorespiratory fitness and academic performance was only found with endurance shuttle run performance in girls (Wittberg et al., 2010) (Table 3).In contrast to studies concerning the relationships of cardiorespiratory fitness to academic performance that have used grade point averages and standardised achievement tests as measures of academic performance, associations of motor skills with academic performance include measures of grade point averages, estimated academic performance by a class-room teacher and reading skills. The evidence indicates that children with better overall perceptual motor abilities have better grade point averages than children with lower perceptual motor skills. Positive associations have also been found between manual coordination, static balance, asynchronous movement, and grade point averages in girls who were 10–11 years of age (Nourbakhsh, 2006).Evidence from longitudinal studies indicates that only fine motor skills in young childhood predict improvement in reading and math skills in later years (Pagani et al., 2010). However, none of the studies involved an analysis of the possible relationship between current motor skills, cognition, and academic performance.Intervention studies aimed at improving motor skills have documented a weak positive connection between motor skill training and improved academic performance and reading skills among school-aged children (Ericsson, 2008; Uhrich and Swalm, 2007), but the evidence is not consistent (Bassin and Breihan, 1978). Ulrich and Swalm (2007) showed that children who participated in bimanual dexterity training for six weeks improved their reading comprehension, but not reading decoding in comparison with the children in the control group.Furthermore, Ericsson (2008) showed that children who were assigned to a physical training programme for motor skills not only improved their motor skills, but also their Swedish language (the first language of the participants) and mathematic performance. However, Bassin and Breihan (1978) documented no effect of twenty-week visuomotor training on reading achievement.Interplay of cardiorespiratory fitness, motor skills, genetics, and maturationAlthough cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills evidently play a role in cognition and academic performance, the extent to which these differences are mediated by genetic or biological factors is unclear. It is known that genetic factors can explain approximately 50% of cardiorespiratory fitness (Malina et al., 2004) and moreover, many childhood cognitive deficits are highly inheritable (Rutter, 2006). Cognitive deficits, such as learning disabilities, are often associated with coordination and motor skill disorders. Some authors have suggested that coordination disorders and learning disabilities may share a genetic cause (Martin et al., 2006). Again, there is some evidence that genetically regulated biological maturation may affect the relationships presented in this review. Boys who mature early show better motor skills than average and late maturing boys during early adolescence (Malina et al., 2004). However, the association between maturity and motor skills is somewhat mixed in girls (Malina et al., 2004). These results indicate that, at least in boys, biological maturity may confound the relationship between motor skills and cognitive functions. This means that more mature children may have an advanced neuromuscular system, leading them to perform better in motor tests. Moreover, children with older skeletal age, a marker of biological maturity, show better cognitive capacity in comparison to children with younger skeletal age (Goldstein, 1987). Thus, the relationship between motor skills and cognitive functions may be at least partly explained by differences in genetic background and maturation status. In contrast, the majority of studies that addressed relationships between cardiorespiratory fitness and cognitive functioning controlled their data for sexual maturity; that is, children who participated in those studies were classified as prepubertal according to their secondary sex characteristics (Chaddock et al., 2010; 2012a; 2012b; Hillman et al., 2009; Monti et al., 2012; Pontifex et al., 2011; Voss et al., 2011). In those studies, it is less likely that maturation confounded the results. Moreover, although genetic factors may have had an influence on the results presented here, genes usually act in a probabilistic fashion; thus, environment and other factors can downregulate or upregulate gene expression (Rutter, 2006). In this respect, the intervention results (Ericsson, 2008; Kamijo et al., 2011; Uhrich and Swalm, 2007) are encouraging in showing that training which improves cardiorespiratory fitness and/or motor skills may be beneficial for brain function and learning in childhood.Interplay between cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skillsIt is an oversimplification to suggest that only cardiorespiratory fitness or only motor skills are the important determinants of cognitive functions in children. In fact, the evidence suggests that cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills are positively correlated, suggesting that children with high cardiorespiratory fitness also have better motor skills than those with low fitness (Lubans et al., 2010). In this respect, it is not known whether exercise training consisting of aerobic exercise (for example treadmill running) without any component of motor skill training improves cognitive functions. Although Kamijo et al. (2011) showed that improved cardiorespiratory fitness enhanced cognitive performance, their intervention also consisted of exercises that potentially improved motor skills and musculoskeletal fitness. Results by Ericsson (2008), in contrast, indicated that children who improved motor skills through increased motor skill training improved their academic performance as well. However, it is likely that children who underwent physical activity intervention also saw an improvement in cardiorespiratory fitness. Thus, although aerobic walking has been related to improved cognitive functions in older adults (Hillman et al., 2008), it remains unclear as to whether simple aerobic exercise (such as walking) or motor skill training without an aerobic component, assists developing cognitive functions and brain health in growing children. On the other hand, it may be the case that aerobic training combined with motor skill training produces the best combination for cognitive development. Exercise training that leads to improved cardiorespiratory fitness creates an environment that supports neural growth and survival via increased levels of nerve growth factors, and motor skill training increases and refines structural efficiency of neural networks in children (Adkins et al., 2006).Situating the results into the context of the obesity epidemicIn the point of view of public health, the findings reviewed here are of great importance. The number of obese children continues to increase (Janssen et al., 2005), and a growing amount of children and adolescents spend their waking hours in sedentary activities (Verloigne et al., 2012). Moreover, a recent study showed that excess adiposity and especially intra-abdominal adiposity assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) was negatively associated with inhibitory control and academic performance in 7- to 9-year-old children (Kamijo et al., 2012). Studies suggest that obese children have lower cardiorespiratory fitness (Stigman et al., 2009) and poorer motor skills (D’Hondt et al., 2012) in comparison to their normal weight peers. Moreover, more physical activity leads to decreased adiposity and improved motor skills in young children 0 to 4 years of age (Timmons et al., 2012). This negative relationship between adiposity and cognitive function may be partially explained by the poor development of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills through a lack of physically and mentally challenging activities. Moreover, there exists a threat that as younger children increasingly become sedentary and obese, they do not reach the level of physical fitness (including cardiorespiratory and motor components) necessary to support brain health and development. However, physical activity consisting of moderate to vigorous aerobic exercise and demanding motor skill exercises seems to be an effective intervention to enhance cognitive functioning, academic performance and brain health among overweight children (Davis et al., 2011b). The children in the training group, relative to the control group, showed increased activation in the bilateral prefrontal cortex and decreased activation in the bilateral posterior parietal cortex during the antisaccade task (Davis et al., 2011b) indicating more efficient cognitive processes. Unfortunately, the authors did not report task performance in relation to brain activation. Thus, there is some evidence that interventions aimed at increasing children’s physical activity levels and improving cardiovascular and neuromuscular health also have the potential to contribute to cognitive development.ConclusionThe evidence summarised in the present review suggests that compared to less fit children, highly fit children have larger subcortical brain structures, more efficient brain activation and neuroelectric efficiency during cognitive tasks, superior inhibitory control, working memory, attention and better academic performance. Similarly, children with better motor skills show better inhibitory control, attention capacity and academic performance than children with poorer motor skills. Thus, the evidence suggests that both cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills play an important role in cognitive development during childhood. It is strongly suggested that children are allowed to get appropriate stimulation from the environment via physical activities in order to improve the functions of their cardiovascular and neuromuscular systems. Besides the known cardiometabolic benefits, developmentally appropriate physical activity may improve brain health and function. There is a need for multidisciplinary studies that assess the interdependent relationships of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skill with cognitive functions in cross-sectional and longitudinal settings.This work was supported by a grant from the Juho Vainio Foundation and by a grant from the University of Eastern Finland. The author wishes to thank Katriina Kukkonen-Harjula, Henna Haapala, and Anna-Sofia Kuoppa for their comments concerning the manuscript.ReferencesAdkinsDBoychukJRempleMKleimJMotor training induces experience-specific patterns of plasticity across motor cortex and spinal cordJ Appl Physiol20061011776178216959909BassinSBreihanSRelationship of performance on motor activities and reading-achievementPercept Mot Skills1978463811814673637BrassMUllspergerMKnoescheTRvon CramonDYPhillipsNAWho comes first? the role of the prefrontal and parietal cortex in cognitive controlJ Cogn Neurosci20051791367137516197690BruniaCHMvan BoxtelGJMWait and seeInt J Psychophysiol200143597511742685ChaddockLHillmanCHPontifexMBJohnsonCRaineLBKramerAFChildhood aerobic fitness predicts cognitive preformance one year laterJ Sports Sci2012a30542143022260155ChaddockLEricksonKPrakashRVossMWVanpatterMPontifexMBHillmanCHKramerAA functional MRI investigation of the association between childhood aerobic fitness and neurocognitive controlBiol Psychol2012b89126026822061423ChaddockLEricksonKIPrakashRSKimJSVossMWVanPatterMPontifexMBRaineLBKonkelAHillmanCHCohenNJKramerAFA neuroimaging investigation of the association between aerobic fitness, hippocampal volume, and memory performance in preadolescent childrenBrain Res2010135817218320735996DavisCLCooperSFitness, fatness, cognition, behavior, and academic achievement among overweight children: Do cross-sectional associations correspond to exercise trial outcomes?Prev Med201152suppl. 16569DavisCLTomporowskiPDMcDowellJEAustinBPMillerPHYanasakNEAllisonJDNaglieriJAExercise improves executive function and achievement and alters brain activation in overweight children: A randomized, controlled trialHealth Psychol2011b301919821299297D’HondtEDeforcheBGentierIDe BourdeaudhuijIVaeyensRPhilippaertsRLenoirMA longitudinal analysis of gross motor coordination in overweight and obese children versus normal-weight peersInt J Obes20133716167DiamondAExecutive functionsAnnu Rev Psychol20136413516823020641DwyerTSallisJBlizzardLLazarusRDeanKRelation of academic performance to physical activity and fitness in childrenPed Exerc Sci2001133225237EricssonIMotor skills, attention and academic achievements. an intervention study in school years 1–3Brit Educ Res J2008343301313GehringWJFencsikDFunctions of the medial frontal cortex in the processing of conflict and errorsJ Neurosci200121239430943711717376GehringWJGossBColesMGHMeyerDEDonchinEA neural system for error detection and compensationPsychol Sci199346385390GoldsteinHSkeletal maturity and cognitive development of 12-year-old to 17-year-old malesDev Med Child Neurol19872933483503596070HannulaDERanganathCThe eyes have it: Hippocampal activity predicts expression of memory in eye movementsNeuron200963559259919755103HardyLLKingLEspinelPCosgroveCBaumanANSW schools physical activity and nutrition survey (SPANS) 2010: Full ReportSydney, AustraliaNSW Ministry of Health2011HillmanCHEricksonKIKramerAFBe smart, exercise your heart: Exercise effects on brain and cognitionNat Rev Neurosci200891586518094706HillmanCHBuckSMThemansonJRPontifexMBCastelliDMAerobic fitness and cognitive development: Event-related brain potential and task performance indices of executive control in preadolescent childrenDev Psychol200945111412919209995JanssenIKatzmarzykPTBoyceWFVereeckenCMulvihillCRobertsCCurrieCPickettWComparison of overweight and obesity prevalence in school-aged youth from 34 countries and their relationships with physical activity and dietary patternsObes Rev20056212313215836463KamijoKKhanNAPontifexMBScudderMRDrolletteESRaineLBEvansEMCastelliDMHillmanCHThe relation of adiposity to cognitive control and scholastic achievement in preadolescent childrenObesity201220122406241122546743KamijoKPontifexMBO'LearyKCScudderMRWuCCastelliDMHillmanCHThe effects of an afterschool physical activity program on working memory in preadolescent childrenDev Sci20111451046105821884320LiveseyDKeenJRouseJWhiteFThe relationship between measures of executive function, motor performance and externalising behaviour in 5- and 6-year-old childrenHum Mov Sci200625506416442172LubansDMorganPCliffDBarnettLOkelyAFundamental movement skills in children and adolescents. Review of associated health benefitsSports Med201040121019103521058749MacDonaldAWIIICohenJDStengerVACarterCSDissociating the role of the dorsolateral prefrontal and anterior cingulate cortex in cognitive controlScience200028854721835183810846167MalinaRMBouchardCBar-Or O Growth, maturation, and physical activityChampaign, IllHuman Kinetics2004MartinNCPiekJPHayDDCD and ADHD: A genetic study of their shared aetiologyHum Mov Sci200625111012416442650MontiJMHillmanCHCohenNJAerobic fitness enhances relational memory in preadolescent children: The FITKids randomized control trialHippocampus20122291876188222522428NiedererIKriemlerSGutJHartmannTSchindlerCBarralJPuderJRelationship of aerobic fitness and motor skills with memory and attention in preschoolers (ballabeina): A cross-sectional and longitudinal studyBMC Pediatr201111113421569343NourbakhshPPerceptual-motor abilities and their relationships with academic performance of fifth grade pupils in comparison with Oseretsky scaleKinesiology20063814048PaganiLSFitzpatrickCArchambaultIJanoszMSchool readiness and later achievement: A French Canadian replication and extensionDev Psychol201046598499420822217PangelinanMMZhangGVanMeterJWClarkJEHatfieldBDHauflerAJBeyond age and gender: Relationships between cortical and subcortical brain volume and cognitive-motor abilities in school-age childrenNeuroImage20115443093310021078402PiekJPDawsonLSmithLMGassonNThe role of early fine and gross motor development on later motor and cognitive abilityHum Mov Sci200827566868118242747PontifexMBRaineLBJohnsonCRChaddockLVossMWCohenNJKramerAFHillmanCHCardiorespiratory fitness and the flexible modulation of cognitive control in preadolescent childrenJ Cogn Neurosci20112361332134520521857RiethmullerAMJonesRAOkelyADEfficacy of interventions to improve motor development in young children: A systematic reviewPediatrics2009124411911191RoebersCMKauerMMotor and cognitive control in a normative sample of 7-year-oldsDev Sci20091217518119120425RowlandTEvolution of maximal oxygen uptake in childrenMed Sport Sci20075020020917387259RutterMGenes and behavior nature/nurture interplay explainedMalden, MA, USABlackwell Pub2006StigmanSRintalaPKukkonen-HarjulaKKujalaURinneMFogelholmMEight-year-old children with high cardiorespiratory fitness have lower overall and abdominal fatnessInt J Pediatr Obes2009429810518608634TimmonsBWLeblancAGCarsonVGorberSCDillmanCJanssenIKhoMESpenceJCStearnsJATremblayMSSystematic review of physical activity and health in the early years (aged 0–4 years)Appl Physiol Nutr Metab201237477379222765840TomkinsonGROldsTMSecular changes in pediatric aerobic fitness test performance: The global pictureMed Sport Sci200750466617387251UhrichTASwalmRA pilot study of a possible effect from a motor task on reading performancePercept Mot Skills200710431035104117688161Van DusenDPKelderSHKohlHWRanjitNPerryCLAssociations of physical fitness and academic performance among schoolchildrenJ School Health2011811273374022070504VerloigneMVan LippeveldeWMaesLYildirimMChinapawMManiosYAndroutsosOKovácsEBringolf-IsterBBrugJDe BourdeaudhuijILevels of physical activity and sedentary time among 10- to 12-year-old boys and girls across 5 European countries using accelerometers: An observational study within the ENERGY-projectInt J Behav Nutr Phys Act201293422462550VossMChaddockLKimJVanpatterMPontifexMBRaineLBCohenNJHillmanCHKramerAFAerobic fitness is associated with greater efficiency of the network underlying cognitive control in preadolescent childrenNeuroscience201119916617622027235WassenbergRFeronFKesselsAHendriksenJKalffAKroesMHurksPPBeerenMJollesJVlesJRelation between cognitive and motor performance in 5-to 6-year-old children: Results from a large-scale cross-sectional studyChild Dev20057651092110316150004WeertsTLangPThe effects of eye fixation and stimulus and response location on the contingent negative variation (CNV)Biol Psychol1973111194804295WelkGJJacksonAWJamesRMorrowJHaskellWHMeredithMDCooperKHThe association of health-related fitness with indicators of academic performance in Texas schoolsRes Q Exerc Sport2010811623WittbergRCottrellLADavisCLNorthrupKLAerobic fitness thresholds associated with fifth grade academic achievementAm J Health Educ2010415284291Table 1Summary of relationship of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills with inhibitory controlReference, countryDesign/subjectsFitness or motor skillInhibitory controlMain resultsChaddock et al. (2012a), USACross-sectional / semi-prospective 32 children aged 9–10 yearsMaximal treadmill testaModified flanker task + MRIHF had better accuracy in congruent and incongruent conditions at baseline than UF. After follow-up, HF showed superior performance in accuracy and RT showing better cognitive control. MRI. HF had larger bilateral putamen and GP volumes and these volumes correlated with response accuracy during incompatible condition. Putamen volumes were directly related to follow-up accuracy and RT in incompatible and compatible conditionsChaddock et al. (2012b), USACross-sectional 32 children 9–10 years of ageMaximal treadmill testaModified flanker task + fMRINo differences in congruent task in activation levels between UF and HF. As cognitive demands increased in the incongruent, relative to congruent, condition, HF showed greater activation in the prefrontal and parietal cortex during early task block. Only HF showed a decrease in these brain areas and maintenance of accuracyHillman et al. (2009), USACross-sectional 38 children 9 years of ageEndurance shuttle run testbModified flanker task + ERPHF were more accurate across task conditions than UF. Greater P3 amplitude and reduced ERN was observed in HF than UF.Livesey et al. (2006), AustraliaCross-sectional 36 children 5–6 years of ageMABCGo/NoGo task, day-night stroop taskBetter fine motor skills were associated with shorter reaction times in the Stroop task, but no association with Go/NoGo task performance was foundPontifex et al. (2011), USACross-sectional 48 children 10 years of ageMaximal treadmill test aModified flanker task + ERPHF showed greater response accuracy in compatible and incompatible condition than UF. Difference was larger in incompatible condition indicating that the harder the task, the larger the difference. HF demonstrated a larger change in P3 amplitude and ERN between compatibility conditions than UFRoebers and Kauer (2009), SwitzerlandCross-sectional 112 children 7.5 years of ageJumping moving sideways, postural flexibility, pegboardFlanker task, Simon Task, Cognitive flexibility task (RT)Pegboard test performance was directly associated with reaction time in Simon and Cognitive flexibility tasks. Performance in the postural flexibility test was directly related to reaction times in Simon task. Performance in the sideways moving task was directly associated with reaction times in Cognitive flexibility task. Jumping was directly associated with reaction times during flanker, Simon, and Cognitive flexibility tasksVoss et al. (2011), USACross-sectional 28 children 9–10 years of age (25 young adults 18–30 years served as a control)Maximal treadmill testaFlanker task + fMRIHF exhibited greater overall accuracy percentage and greater accuracy in incongruent condition than UF. HF also showed less variation between congruent and incongruent condition than UF. fMRI. Children showed poorer activation than young adults. HF demonstrated more activation of brain regions involved in cinculo-opercular networkHF, Highly fit children. UF, unfit children. fMRI, functional magnetic resonance imaging.MRI, magnetic resonance imaging. GP, glopus pallidus. ERP, event-related brain potential.RT, reaction time. ERN, error-related negativity.aDivided into &gt; 70th and &lt; 30th percentile according to child’s VO2max.Table 2Summary of relationship of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills with memory functionsReference, countryDesign/subjectsFitness or motor skillMemoryMain resultsChaddock et al. (2010), USACross-sectional 59 children 9–10 years of ageMaximal treadmill testaItem and relational memory paradigm + MRIHF had greater bilateral hippocampal volumes and better relational memory than UF; bilateral hippocampal volume mediated the relationship between fitness and relational memory. No association between fitness and item memory was foundKamijo et al. (2011), USARCT (9 months) 36 children 7–9 years of ageMaximal treadmill exercise test to assess VO2max before and after exercise interventionModified Stenberg task for item memory + ERPIncreased fitness after the intervention was associated with improved overall accuracy in memory task. The intervention group exhibited greater iCNV amplitude in comparison to control group at the end of the intervention periodMonti et al. (2012), USALongitudinal (9 months) 44 children 9 years of age, cognitive assessment of only in the follow-upMaximal treadmill exercise test to assess VO2max before and after exercise interventionWorking memory task for non-relational and relational memory, eye-movement trackingChildren in the exercise intervention group showed longer viewing times for the related pictures than control group during relational memory task. No differences during non-relational memory task accuracy. No differences in performance accuracy or reaction times between intervention and control groupsNiederer et al. (2011), Switzerland, GermanyCross-sectional /longitudinal (nine-month follow-up) 245 children 5.2 years of ageAgility, dynamic balance, multistage shuttle run testItem memoryAgility was associated with item memory in cross-sectional analyses and baseline balance predicted improvement in item memory longitudinallyPangelinan et al.(2011), USACross-sectional 172 children 6– 13 years of agePurdue pegboard taskSpatial working memory + MRIPegboard test performance was not related to spatial working memory.Piek et al. (2008), AustraliaCohort study 33 children 6–11 years of age at the follow-up (initial assessment at the age of four month)Ages and stages questionnaire, McCarron assessment of neuromuscular developmentDigit span and letter-number sequencing = working memory indexEarly gross motor development predicted working memoryRoebers and Kauer (2009), SwitzerlandCross-sectional 112 children 7.5 years of ageSideway jumping, moving sideways, postural flexibility, pegboardBackward colour recallBetter performance in the postural flexibility test was related to higher performance in memory taskWassenberg et al.(2005), the NetherlandsCross-sectional 378 children 6.18 years of ageMaastricht motor test (static balance, dynamic balance, ball skills, manual dexterity)Auditory item memoryBetter qualitative motor skills (i.e. the movement process) were related to a better item memoryHF, highly fit children. UF, unfit children. ERP, event-related brain potential.iCNV, initial contingency negative variationaDivided into &gt; 70th and &lt; 30th percentile according to child’s VO2max.Table 3Summary of relationship of cardiorespiratory fitness and motor skills with academic performanceReference, countryDesign/subjectsFitness or motor skills assessmentAcademic performance assessmentMain resultsBassin and Breihan (1978), USAIntervention 66 childrenVisuomotor activities for trice a week for 20 weeksReading achievementMotor skill based intervention had no effect on reading achievement.Davis and Cooper (2011), USACross-sectional 170 overweight children 7–11 yearsMaximal treadmill testThe Woodcock-Johnson IIIHigher levels of cardiorespiratory fitness was associated with better reading and arithmetic performanceDwyer et al. (2001), AustraliaCross-sectional 7961 children 7–15 years of age1.6 km, indirect submaximal cycle ergometer exercise testScholastic ability rated by 5-point scaleBetter performance in the 1.6 km run was associated with higher scholastic abilityEricsson (2008), SwedenIntervention study 251 primary school children in Grades 1 to 3Motor activities for five lessons / weekSwedish (writing and reading), mathematicsSignificant association between participation to the intervention and academic performanceNourbakhsh (2006) IranCross-sectional 400 girls 10–11 years of ageThe Oseretsky scaleGrade point averageGeneral static and dynamic coordination, synchronous-symmetrical and asynchronous-asymmetrical movements and total perceptual motor skill correlated positively with grade point averagePagani et al. (2010), CanadaCohort study 1145 children (538 boys) 5.4 years of ageGross motor skills, fine motor skillsTeachers’ estimation of academic performanceFine motor skills at the age of five predicted mathematics, reading, and overall academic performance 24 months latervan Dusen et al. (2011), USACross-sectional 254 743 third to 11th grade students1 mile run, endurance shuttle run test (lowest quintile vs. highest quintile)Texas Assessment of Knowledge and Skills (reading and mathematics)High-fit children had better academic performance, but no differences was found in elementary schoolUhrich and Swalm (2007), USACluster-RCT 41 children 8 years of ageSpeed stackingGates-MacGinitie Reading Test (decoding, comprehension)Intervention group performed better in comprehension but no differences were observed in decodingWelk et al. (2010), USACross-sectional 36 835 studentsEndurance shuttle run test, 1.6 km run (meets recommendations vs. does not meet recommendations),Texas Assessment of Knowledge and Skills; attendance, delinquencyMeeting recommendations for aerobic fitness was associated with better academic performance and better attendanceWittberg et al. (2010), USACross-sectional 1740 children 9–13 years of age1 mile run, endurance shuttle run test. (time spent to complete 1 mile; number of circuits in the shuttle run test)West Virginia Standardized TestHigher number of circuits in the PACER was associated with better academic performance in girls and faster time in the 1 mile run was associated with higher academic performance in boys
