<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front Hum NeurosciFront Hum NeurosciFront. Hum. Neurosci.Frontiers in Human Neuroscience1662-5161Frontiers Media S.A.446080410.3389/fnhum.2015.00332NeuroscienceClinical TrialTai Chi Training may Reduce Dual Task Gait Variability, a Potential Mediator of Fall Risk, in Healthy Older Adults: Cross-Sectional and Randomized Trial StudiesWaynePeter M.12*HausdorffJeffrey M.3LoughMatthew4GowBrian J.12LipsitzLewis4NovakVera5MacklinEric A.26PengChung-Kang78ManorBrad41Division of Preventive Medicine, Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Boston, MA, USA2Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA3Department of Neurology, Center for the Study of Movement, Cognition, and Mobility, Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel4Institute for Aging Research, Hebrew Senior Life, Boston, MA, USA5Department of Neurology, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Boston, MA, USA6Biostatistics Center, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA, USA7Division of Interdisciplinary Medicine and Biotechnology, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Boston, MA, USA8Center for Dynamical Biomarkers and Translational Medicine, National Central University, Chungli, TaiwanEdited by: Catherine Kerr, Brown University, USAReviewed by: Guido P. H. Band, Leiden University, Netherlands; Teresa Dianne Hawkes, Air Force Research Laboratory, USA*Correspondence: Peter M. Wayne, Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, Harvard Medical School, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, 900 Commonwealth Avenue, 3rd floor, Boston, MA 02215, USA, pwayne@partners.org096201520159332121220142352015Copyright © 2015 Wayne, Hausdorff, Lough, Gow, Lipsitz, Novak, Macklin, Peng and Manor.2015This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.BackgroundTai Chi (TC) exercise improves balance and reduces falls in older, health-impaired adults. TC’s impact on dual task (DT) gait parameters predictive of falls, especially in healthy active older adults, however, is unknown.PurposeTo compare differences in usual and DT gait between long-term TC-expert practitioners and age-/gender-matched TC-naïve adults, and to determine the effects of short-term TC training on gait in healthy, non-sedentary older adults.MethodsA cross-sectional study compared gait in healthy TC-naïve and TC-expert (24.5 ± 12 years experience) older adults. TC-naïve adults then completed a 6-month, two-arm, wait-list randomized clinical trial of TC training. Gait speed and stride time variability (Coefficient of Variation %) were assessed during 90 s trials of undisturbed and cognitive DT (serial subtractions) conditions.ResultsDuring DT, gait speed decreased (p &lt; 0.003) and stride time variability increased (p &lt; 0.004) in all groups. Cross-sectional comparisons indicated that stride time variability was lower in the TC-expert vs. TC-naïve group, significantly so during DT (2.11 vs. 2.55%; p = 0.027); by contrast, gait speed during both undisturbed and DT conditions did not differ between groups. Longitudinal analyses of TC-naïve adults randomized to 6 months of TC training or usual care identified improvement in DT gait speed in both groups. A small improvement in DT stride time variability (effect size = 0.2) was estimated with TC training, but no significant differences between groups were observed. Potentially important improvements after TC training could not be excluded in this small study.ConclusionIn healthy active older adults, positive effects of short- and long-term TC were observed only under cognitively challenging DT conditions and only for stride time variability. DT stride time variability offers a potentially sensitive metric for monitoring TC’s impact on fall risk with healthy older adults.Tai Chigait analysisdual task performancefalls and fall risk preventioncognitionNational Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (NCCAM)R21 AT005501-01A1National Institutes of Health (NIH)National Institute on Aging (NIA)R03-AG25037NSC102-2911-I-008-001<sec xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="S2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S2-1"><title>Study design</title><p>We employed a hybrid study design that included a two-arm randomized clinical trial (RCT) along with an additional observational comparison group. The Institutional Review Board at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center approved this study. The RCT component of this study was registered at clinicaltrials.gov (NCT01340365). Gait outcomes reported herein are a subset of a larger battery of assessed outcomes including balance, cardiovascular, and cognitive outcomes. These latter outcomes are reported independently (Wayne et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2-2"><title>Randomized trial design</title><p>Sixty healthy older adults, aged 50–79, were randomized 1:1 to receive 6 months of TC training in addition to usual health care, or to usual health care alone (control group). Study participants randomized to usual care were offered a 3-month course of TC as a courtesy following the trial. Randomization was stratified by age (50–59, 60–69, 70–79 years) and utilized a permuted-blocks randomization scheme with randomly varying block sizes. Randomization was performed by the study statistician. All outcomes were assessed at baseline and 6 months, i.e., after completing 6 months of training. The primary staff overseeing assessment and analyses of the gait-related outcomes was blinded to treatment assignment. Recruitment spanned from March 2011 to March 2013. All follow-up procedures were completed by September 2013. Analysis was performed in 2014. Further details related to the design of the RCT component of this study are reported elsewhere (Wayne et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2-3"><title>Recruitment for the randomized trial targeting community-dwelling healthy adults</title><p>Inclusion criteria were (1) age 50–79 years; (2) living within the Greater Boston area; and (3) willing to adhere to a 6-month TC training protocol. Exclusion criteria were (1) chronic medical condition including cardiovascular disease, stroke, active cancer; neurological conditions; or significant neuromuscular or musculoskeletal conditions requiring chronic use of pain medication; (2) acute medical condition requiring hospitalization within the past 6 months; (3) self-reported inability to walk continuously for 15 min unassisted; (4) regular TC practice within past 5 years; and (5) regular participation in physical exercise on average 4 or more times per week. Interested individuals underwent both an initial phone screen and an in-person screen at the BIDMC Clinical Research Center. Eligible individuals provided written informed consent and underwent baseline testing prior to randomization.</p><p>Participants within both groups were encouraged to follow usual health care as prescribed by their primary care physicians. Participants in the TC group received 6 months of TC training in addition to usual care. All TC interventions were administered pragmatically at one of five pre-screened TC schools within the Greater Boston area that met specific guidelines described elsewhere (Wayne et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Study participants were asked to attend, on average, two classes per week over the 6-month intervention. They were also asked to practice a minimum of 30 min, two additional days per week. Attendance at TC classes was recorded by instructors and home practice was tracked by participants using a weekly practice log. Participants that reported attending a minimum of 70% of all classes and completing 70% or more of prescribed home practice between each study visit were considered compliant or “per-protocol.” Adverse events were systematically collected from participants and instructors and are reported elsewhere (Wayne et al., <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2-4"><title>Non-randomized comparison group: Tai Chi experts</title><p>Twenty-seven healthy older adults (age 50–79 years) currently engaged in an active TC training regimen, each with over 5 years of TC practice, were recruited for a single observational visit. No limitation was set on TC style. Eligibility and screening procedures for TC experts were identical to those for healthy adults enrolled in the RCT.</p></sec><sec id="S2-5"><title>Measurements</title><p>Participants reported to the Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center’s Clinical Research Center (Boston, MA, USA) where they underwent in-person screening procedures. Participants with a mini mental state examination (MMSE) score ≥24 and no abnormal findings on an ECG were eligible to participate in the study. All outcome measurements were assessed at the Syncope and Falls in the Elderly (SAFE) laboratory at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center. Outcomes related to gait reported here were part of a larger battery of tests that lasted an average of 3.5 h. Changes in DT gait speed and gait variability from baseline to 6 months were <italic>a priori</italic>-defined outcome measures of primary interest.</p><sec id="S2-5-1"><title>Assessment of Gait</title><p>Gait was assessed along a 75-m long unobstructed hallway. Subjects were instructed to walk at their normal preferred walking pace and make wide turns at the ends of the hallway. Two 90 s walking trials were completed: undisturbed with no superimposed cognitive task (i.e., single task walking) and walking while completing a cognitive DT. The cognitive DT consisted of a serial subtraction exercise counting backwards by threes beginning at 500. Ultrathin, force-sensitive resistor footswitches were placed on each subject’s heel and toe to capture the temporal parameters of gait. Data were collected wirelessly at 1500 Hz with DTS Data Acquisition Software (Noraxon, Scottsdale, AZ, USA). The data for each trial was exported and analyzed in Matlab (Mathworks, Natick, MA, USA) to determine initial and final foot contact times for each stride. Stride times were calculated for each gait cycle as the time between initial heel strike of one foot and the subsequent heel strike of that same foot. Average gait speed was measured using the total distance walked during the trial. Stride time variability was calculated from the stride time time-series as the coefficient of variation (CV, 100 multiplied by the SD of the stride times divided by the mean of each subject’s stride times). To calculate these measures, the first five strides were removed to minimize potential gait initiation effects. A median filter was applied to the stride time time-series to remove large outliers, typically a result of turns at the ends of the hallway. This ensured that the steady state variability was analyzed for each time series. Average stride time and stride time variability was determined from the resultant time series.</p><p>Dual task costs were calculated using both absolute and proportional measures. Absolute DT costs (Abs. DT) were calculated for each participant as the difference in walking speed or stride time variability between undisturbed single task walking (ST) and DT walking. Proportional DT costs (% DT) were calculated for each participant’s walking speed or stride variability as: 100 × ((DT − ST)/ST). Both the number and the accuracy of serial subtractions during DTs were recorded.</p></sec><sec id="S2-5-2"><title>Baseline Cognitive Function and Physical Activity</title><p>Global cognitive function at baseline was assessed with the MMSE. Executive cognitive function was assessed using the trail making test (TMT B and TMT B-A) (Bowie and Harvey, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Sanchez-Cubillo et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). TMT B assesses the time required to connect a series of circles in an alternating sequence of numbers and letters (e.g., 1-A-2-B-3-C). TMT B is considered to evaluate executive control, and is correlated with other executive function measures (Arbuthnott and Frank, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). TMT B is a sensitive indicator of overall neurological impairment and has good reliability (Bowie and Harvey, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). TMT A assesses the time required to connect a series of numbers. The difference between TMTB and A more accurately assesses executive function since it corrects for processing speed. Physical activity level was assessed using the physical activity status scale (PASS). Subjects were asked to estimate their general physical activity during the previous week using an 11-point scale (i.e., 0–10). The scale quantifies physical activity duration by a combination of the minutes of exercise per week and the intensity of this exercise (i.e., heavy, modest, or none) (Heil et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Jackson et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2-5-3"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Cross-sectional measures of gait outcomes in TC experts and TC naïves were compared in a linear model controlling for age, gender, BMI, and physical activity and assuming equal variance across groups. For measures where the assumption of equal variance may have been violated, the larger of the two groups, the TC naïves, had greater estimated variance, leading to potential overestimates of pooled variance and conservative estimates of effect sizes and <italic>p</italic>-values. Inference was unchanged when applying an equivalent generalized least squares model allowing for variance heterogeneity between groups. Trajectories of gait performance over the 6-month intervention were compared between naïve participants randomized to TC or usual care using a random-slopes model with shared baseline. All longitudinal analyses were conducted according to the intention-to-treat paradigm. The model included fixed effect of time, time × treatment, age, gender, BMI, physical activity, and interactions between time and age, gender, BMI, and physical activity. The model included random participant-specific intercepts and slopes with unstructured covariance. The shared baseline assumption, enforced by omitting a treatment main-effect term, properly reflects the true state of the population sampled prior to randomization and has the advantage of adjusting for any chance differences at baseline (Zeger and Liang, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>). Treatment-group differences and adjusted means for a male participant with mean age, BMI, and physical activity were estimated as well as their 95% confidence intervals. Both cross-sectional and longitudinal effect size estimates were calculated using pooled baseline SDs after adjusting for age, gender, BMI, and physical activity (Feingold, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). All inferential tests were two-tailed with alpha set at 0.05. We chose to report comparison-wise <italic>p</italic>-values without adjustment for multiple comparisons to avoid inflating type II errors, recognizing that the nominal <italic>p</italic>-values underestimate the overall experiment-wise type I error rate. Our results are intended as hypothesis generating, not definitive tests of efficacy for TC on any specific measure of gait. No comparisons were significant after a step-down Bonferroni adjustment for multiple comparisons. All analyses were performed in SAS (version 9.3, SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA).</p></sec><sec id="S2-5-4"><title>Sample Size Considerations</title><p>For cross-sectional comparisons, we estimated that a sample size of 27 TC Expert and 60 TC naïve subjects would provide power to detect an effect size of 0.63. For the randomized trial, we estimated that the sample of 60 participants randomized 1:1, the study would have 80% power to detect a main effect of treatment if the true effect size was at least 0.74 based on a two-tailed test at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec></sec>ResultsBaseline characteristics and study flowDemographic characteristics of the TC experts (n = 27) were well-matched with the older TC naïve group with respect to average age and cognitive status as measured by MMSE and trial making B test. Compared with naïve older controls, experts included a slightly greater proportion of men and Asians, had lower BMI’s, and higher levels of physical activity (see Table 1). TC experts reported an average of 24.6 ± 12 years of TC training experience (median: 20 years, range 10–50 years). Approximately equal numbers reported Yang (n = 12) and Wu (n = 15) style TC as their primary training systems; however, all reported having training experience in others styles of TC-related internal and external martial arts (e.g., kung fu, bagua) and/or mind–body practices (e.g., yoga, meditation).Table 1Baseline characteristics.Randomized groupsObservational groupUsual care (n = 29)Tai Chi (n = 31)Tai Chi experts (n = 27)AgeAVG ± SD64.45 ± 7.4263.94 ± 8.0262.78 ± 7.57Gender n (%)Male11 (37.9%)9 (29%)13 (48.1%)Female18 (62.1%)22 (71%)14 (51.9%)Race n (%)White26 (89.7%)29 (93.5%)22 (81.5%)African-American3 (10.3%)0 (0%)1 (3.7%)Asian0 (0%)2 (6.5%)4 (14.8%)Ethnicity n (%)Non-Hispanic/Non-Latino29 (100%)30 (96.8%)26 (96.3%)Hispanic/Latino0 (0%)1 (3.2%)1 (3.7%)Education (years)AVG ± SD16.19 ± 3.0317.13 ± 3.4118.44 ± 3.34Mini mental state exam (MMSE)AVG ± SD29.21 ± 0.8229.03 ± 1.1729.07 ± 1.11Trail making B (s)AVG ± SD59.93 ± 20.8459.69 ± 22.0353.07 ± 22.4Trail making B–A (s)AVG ± SD29.54 ± 18.5830.26 ± 20.0128.09 ± 19.65Body mass index (BMI; kg/m2)AVG ± SD26.54 ± 5.8326.38 ± 5.1923.54 ± 2.35aPhysical activity levelbAVG ± SD4.0 ± 2.04.0 ± 2.06.0 ± 2.0aaCross-sectional comparisons between Tai Chi experts and Tai Chi naïve adults at baseline differed significantly (p &lt; 0.05) in BMI and physical activity level.b4 = Run about 1 mile/week OR walk about 1.3 miles/week OR spend about 30 min/week in comparable physical activity; 6 = run about 6–10 miles/week OR walk 7–13 miles/week OR spend 1–3 h/week in comparable physical activity.Tai Chi naïve adults randomized to TC plus usual care or usual care alone were comparable at baseline (see Table 1). For all variables, values for the subset of participants that were found to be “per-protocol” were comparable to those in the larger sample thereby minimizing potential sources of bias in post hoc comparisons between control and TC compliant groups.A CONSORT flowchart detailing study recruitment, randomization, and retention for the randomized trial component of the study is shown in Figure 1. Sixty healthy adults were successfully screened and enrolled, and 97% (28/29) and 87% (27/31) of individuals in the usual care and TC group completed the primary 6-month follow-up assessment, respectively.Figure 1Participant flow through the randomized trial sub-study.Adherence to the TC protocol was variable. Two participants in the TC group formally withdrew participation due to time commitments and an unrelated injury. Of the remaining 29 participants in the TC group, 21 (72%) were per-protocol – defined as attending 70% of classes and completing 70% of required home practice over the entire course of the trial (mean and median TC exposure hours were 59.9 and 62.4 h, respectively).For those randomized to TC, 13 subjects were trained at a TC school teaching Yang style and the remaining 18 subjects were trained at a school teaching Wu style.General effects of dual task challengesCompared to undisturbed walking, gait speed decreased during DT walking in both TC expert (p = 0.003) and TC naïve (p &lt; 0.001) adults. Stride time variability also increased with the addition of a DT in both TC expert (p = 0.004) and TC naïve (p &lt; 0.001) adults (see Table 2).Table 2Cross-sectional comparison of gait parameters for Tai Chi expert and Tai Chi naïve older adults during undisturbed single task (ST) and dual task (DT) walking.Outcome measureTai Chi expert (n = 27)Tai Chi naïve (n = 60)Between groupsMean (95% CI)Mean (95% CI)Effect sizeMean difference (95% CI)p-ValueGait speed ST (m/s)1.12 (1.1, 1.2)1.12 (1.1, 1.2)0.008−0.001 (−0.08, 0.07)0.97Gait speed DT (m/s)1.01 (1.0, 1.1)a0.97 (0.9, 1.1)*0.280.041 (−0.03, 0.1)0.26Stride time variability ST (CV %)1.75 (1.5, 2.0)b1.90 (1.8, 2.0)**0.29−0.15 (−0.4, 0.1)0.25Stride time variability DT (CV %)2.11 (1.8, 2.4)2.55 (2.3, 2.8)0.57−0.44 (−0.8, −0.5)0.027Abs. DT cost speed−0.11 (−0.2, −0.1)−0.15 (−0.2, −0.1)0.340.042 (−0.02, 0.1)0.18% DT cost speed−9.50 (−13.9, −5.1)−13.24 (−16.1, −10.4)0.343.74 (−1.7, 9.1)0.17Abs. DT cost variability0.36 (0.03, 0.7)0.65 (0.4, 0.9)0.35−0.29 (−0.7, 0.1)0.16% DT cost variability23.49 (3.3, 43.7)40.82 (27.7, 54.0)0.35−17.33 (−42.3, 7.6)0.17Means and 95% confidence intervals predicted from linear model adjusting for age, gender, BMI, and physical activity.ST, single task; DT, dual task; CV, coefficient of variation.aWithin-group comparisons between undisturbed and DT walking speed among Tai Chi experts (p = 0.003) and *Tai Chi naïve (p &lt; 0.001).bWithin-group comparisons between undisturbed and DT walking stride time variability among Tai Chi experts (p = 0.004) and **Tai Chi naïve (p &lt; 0.001).Gait performance in Tai Chi experts vs. Tai Chi naïve older adultsLinear models adjusting for variation due to age, gender, BMI, and activity revealed that average walking speeds were very similar in the TC naïve vs. TC expert groups during both undisturbed single task and DT walking. Group differences in these outcomes, as well as derived differences in absolute or percent DT costs, were not statistically significant (see Table 2; Figure 2). By contrast, stride time variability was lower in the TC expert vs. the TC naïve group, significantly so during DT walking (2.11 vs. 2.55%, respectively; p = 0.027). Absolute and percent DT costs of stride time variability also trended toward being lower in TC experts, but these differences were not statistically significant (recall Table 2). Of note, the two groups did not differ on performance of the serial subtractions during the DT walking trial. The number of serial subtractions attempted and their accuracy were 31 and 90%, respectively, in TC naïve group and 35 and 90%, respectively, in the TC expert group (p = 0.81). Age did not directly impact any gait variable, and treatment × age interactions for all cross-sectional comparisons were not statistically significant.Figure 2Comparison of gait parameters between Tai Chi expert and Tai Chi naïve older adults. Estimated mean and 95% confidence intervals for gait speed during undisturbed (A) and dual task walking (B), and gait stride time variability during undisturbed (C) and dual task walking (D). Values based on a linear mixed model accounting for variations in age, gender, BMI, and physical activity. *Indicates p &lt; 0.05.The impact of short-term Tai Chi training on gait performanceRandom-slopes model with shared baseline adjusting for variation due to age, gender, BMI, and activity also revealed trends toward reduced stride time variability following 6 months of TC. A small improvement in DT stride time variability (effect size = 0.2) was estimated with TC training, but no significant differences between groups were observed (see Table 3). Potentially important improvements after TC training could not be excluded in this small study. The estimated 95% CI for DT stride time variability includes a 20% improvement from short-term TC training. Effects of TC on stride time variability during quiet walking were negligible (ES &lt; 0.1).Table 3Longitudinal change in gait parameters for older adults randomly assigned to 6 months of Tai Chi vs. usual care during undisturbed single task (ST) and dual task (DT) walking.Outcome measureTai Chi (n = 31)Usual care (n = 29)Between groupsBaseline6 monthsWithin-group p-valueBaseline6 monthsWithin-group p-valueEffect sizeMean difference (95% CI)p-ValueMean (95% CI)Mean (95% CI)Mean (95% CI)Mean (95% CI)Gait speed ST (m/s)1.12 (1.1, 1.2)1.16 (1.1, 1.2)0.0741.12 (1.1, 1.2)1.17 (1.1, 1.2)0.0320.076−0.011 (−0.07, 0.05)0.71Gait speed DT (m/s)0.97 (0.9, 1.0)1.03 (1.0, 1.1)0.0180.97 (0.9, 1.0)1.03 (1.0, 1.1)0.0280.0160.002 (−0.06, 0.06)0.94Stride time variability ST (CV %)1.96 (1.8, 2.1)1.74 (1.5, 2.0)0.111.96 (1.8, 2.1)1.79 (1.5, 2.0)0.220.079−0.044 (−0.3, 0.3)0.77Stride time variability DT (CV %)2.58 (2.3, 2.9)2.29 (2.0, 2.6)0.0352.58 (2.3, 2.9)2.46 (2.2, 2.8)0.390.19−0.17 (−0.5, 0.1)0.27Abs. DT cost speed−0.15 (−0.2, −0.1)−0.14 (−0.2, −0.1)0.63−0.15 (−0.2, −0.1)−0.14 (−0.2, −0.1)0.650.0020.0 (−0.06, 0.06)0.99% DT cost speed−12.92 (−16.7, −9.2)−11.32 (−15.0, −7.7)0.43−12.92 (−16.7, −9.2)−11.33 (−16.0, −6.7)0.520.0010.014 (−5.4, 5.4)&gt;0.99Abs. DT cost variability0.62 (0.3, 0.9)0.61 (0.3, 0.9)0.950.62 (0.3, 0.9)0.62 (0.3, 0.9)0.980.007−0.007 (−0.4, 0.4)0.97% DT cost variability39.48 (20.9, 58.1)38.00 (20.7, 55.4)0.9039.48 (20.9, 58.1)40.13 (22.1, 58.2)0.960.037−2.13 (−23.8, 19.6)0.85Means and 95% confidence intervals predicted from shared baseline linear model adjusting for age, gender, BMI, and activity. No between-group comparisons (i.e., no tests of group × time interactions) were statistically significant. Within-group significant changes (p &lt; 0.05) are highlighted in bold.ST, single task; DT, dual task; CV, coefficient of variation.Both the TC and usual care group increased DT walking speed (p = 0.018 and p = 0.028), but the difference between groups in changes over 6 months were not significant (p = 0.94). No within- or between-group differences were observed for single task walking speed (see Table 3). Post hoc per-protocol analyses (i.e., limited to participants that were TC compliant) did not substantially change within- and between-group observed patterns and trends. Changes over 6 months in absolute and percent DT costs for both gait speed and stride time variability were small and largely uninfluenced by treatment assignment (recall Table 3). As in the cross-sectional comparisons, these groups did not differ on performance of the serial subtractions. The number of serial subtractions attempted and their accuracy at the final 6-month visit was 33 (95%) in usual care group and 33 (92%) in the Tai expert group (p = 0.58). Age did not directly impact longitudinal changes in any gait variable, and treatment × age interactions for all outcomes were not statistically significant.ConclusionIn healthy active older adults, trends toward positive TC effects on gait were most obvious only under cognitively challenging DT conditions, and only for stride time variability. DT stride variability offers a potentially sensitive metric for monitoring the impact of TC on fall risk with healthy aging. These findings also support the value of neurophysiological research evaluating how mind–body exercises like TC impact cognitive–motor interactions and confirm previous findings, which suggest that TC reduces the risk of falls in older adults (Wolf et al., 1996; Gillespie et al., 2012). Future adequately powered studies are required to confirm these preliminary findings.Author ContributionsPW, JH, LL, CP, and BM conceived and designed the study. ML acquired the study data with oversight from VN. ML and BG analyzed the study data. BG and EM performed statistical analysis. PW drafted and revised the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript and approved the final version.Conflict of Interest StatementPeter M. Wayne is the founder and sole owner of the Tree of Life Tai Chi Center. Peter M. Wayne’s interests were reviewed and are managed by the Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Partners HealthCare in accordance with their conflict of interest policies. The Tree of Life Tai Chi Center did not provide payment or services for any aspect of this study. The other co-authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.We thank Danielle Berkowitz. This work was supported by grant R21 AT005501-01A1 from the National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (NCCAM), National Institutes of Health (NIH). Dr. LL was supported by grant R03-AG25037 from the National Institute on Aging (NIA) and the Irving and Edyth S. Usen and Family Chair in Geriatric Medicine at Hebrew SeniorLife. Dr. VN was supported by R21 AT005501-01A1. Dr. CP was supported by a grant (NSC 102-2911-I-008-001) from Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan. Dr. BM was supported by grant 5 KL2 RR025757-04 from the Harvard Catalyst and grant 1K01 AG044543-01A1 from the National Institute on Aging. Its contents are solely the responsibility of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official views of NCCAM, NIA, or NIH.ReferencesAmanoS.NoceraJ. R.VallabhajosulaS.JuncosJ. L.GregorR. J.WaddellD. E. (2013). The effect of Tai Chi exercise on gait initiation and gait performance in persons with Parkinson’s disease. Parkinsonism Relat. Disord.19, 955–960.10.1016/j.parkreldis.2013.06.00723835431ArbuthnottK.FrankJ. (2000). Trail making test, part B as a measure of executive control: validation using a set-switching paradigm. J. Clin. Exp. Neuropsychol.
22, 518–528.10.1076/1380-3395(200008)22:4;1-0;FT51810923061BowieC. R.HarveyP. D. (2006). Administration and interpretation of the trail making test. Nat. Protoc.
1, 2277–2281.10.1038/nprot.2006.39017406468FeingoldA. (2013). A regression framework for effect size assessments in longitudinal modeling of group differences. Rev. Gen. Psychol.
17, 111–121.10.1037/a003004823956615GabellA.NayakU. S. (1984). The effect of age on variability in gait. J. Gerontol.
39, 662–666.10.1093/geronj/39.6.6626491179GattsS. K.WoollacottM. H. (2006). Neural mechanisms underlying balance improvement with short term Tai Chi training. Aging Clin. Exp. Res.
18, 7–19.10.1007/BF0332463516608131GattsS. K.WoollacottM. H. (2007). How Tai Chi improves balance: biomechanics of recovery to a walking slip in impaired seniors. Gait Posture
25, 205–214.10.1016/j.gaitpost.2006.03.01116672187GillespieL. D.RobertsonM. C.GillespieW. J.SherringtonC.GatesS.ClemsonL. M. (2012). Interventions for preventing falls in older people living in the community. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
9, CD00714610.1002/14651858.CD007146.pub322972103HallC. D.MiszkoT.WolfS. L. (2009). Effects of Tai Chi intervention on dual-task ability in older adults: a pilot study. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.
90, 525–529.10.1016/j.apmr.2008.09.56619254623HalsbandU.LangeR. K. (2006). Motor learning in man: a review of functional and clinical studies. J. Physiol. Paris
99, 414–424.10.1016/j.jphysparis.2006.03.00716730432HassC. J.GregorR. J.WaddellD. E.OliverA.SmithD. W.FlemingR. P. (2004). The influence of Tai Chi training on the center of pressure trajectory during gait initiation in older adults. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.
85, 1593–1598.10.1016/j.apmr.2004.01.02015468016HausdorffJ. M. (2005). Gait variability: methods, modeling and meaning. J. Neuroeng. Rehabil.
2, 19.10.1186/1743-0003-2-1916033650HausdorffJ. M.BalashJ.GiladiN. (2003). Effects of cognitive challenge on gait variability in patients with Parkinson’s disease. J. Geriatr. Psychiatry Neurol.
16, 53–58.10.1177/089198870225058012641374HausdorffJ. M.EdelbergH. K.MitchellS. L.GoldbergerA. L.WeiJ. Y. (1997). Increased gait unsteadiness in community-dwelling elderly fallers. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.
78, 278–283.10.1016/S0003-9993(97)90034-49084350HausdorffJ. M.RiosD. A.EdelbergH. K. (2001). Gait variability and fall risk in community-living older adults: a 1-year prospective study. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.
82, 1050–1056.10.1053/apmr.2001.2489311494184HawkesT. D.ManselleW.WoollacottM. H. (2014). Tai Chi and meditation-plus-exercise benefit neural substrates of executive function: a cross-sectional, controlled study. J. Complement. Integr. Med.
11, 279–288.10.1515/jcim-2013-003125294719HeilD. P.FreedsonP. S.AhlquistL. E.PriceJ.RippeJ. M. (1995). Nonexercise regression models to estimate peak oxygen consumption. Med. Sci. Sports Exerc.
27, 599–606.10.1249/00005768-199504000-000207791593HermanT.MirelmanA.GiladiN.SchweigerA.HausdorffJ. M. (2010). Executive control deficits as a prodrome to falls in healthy older adults: a prospective study linking thinking, walking, and falling. J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
65, 1086–1092.10.1093/gerona/glq07720484336JacksonA. S.BeardE. F.WierL. T.RossR. M.StutevilleJ. E.BlairS. N. (1995). Changes in aerobic power of men, ages 25-70 yr. Med. Sci. Sports Exerc.
27, 113–120.10.1249/00005768-199501000-000207898326KayamaH.OkamotoK.NishiguchiS.YamadaM.KurodaT.AoyamaT. (2014). Effect of a kinect-based exercise game on improving executive cognitive performance in community-dwelling elderly: case control study. J. Med. Internet Res.
16, e61.10.2196/jmir.310824565806LiF.HarmerP.FisherK. J.McAuleyE.ChaumetonN.EckstromE. (2005). Tai Chi and fall reductions in older adults: a randomized controlled trial. J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
60, 187–194.10.1093/gerona/60.2.18715814861LiF.HarmerP.FitzgeraldK.EckstromE.StockR.GalverJ. (2012). Tai Chi and postural stability in patients with Parkinson’s disease. N. Engl. J. Med.
366, 511–519.10.1056/NEJMoa110791122316445LiL.ManorB. (2010). Long term Tai Chi exercise improves physical performance among people with peripheral neuropathy. Am. J. Chin. Med.
38, 449–459.10.1142/S0192415X1000797X20503464LiR.ZhuX.YinS.NiuY.ZhengZ.HuangX. (2014). Multimodal intervention in older adults improves resting-state functional connectivity between the medial prefrontal cortex and medial temporal lobe. Front. Aging Neurosci.
6:39.10.3389/fnagi.2014.0003924653698LoggheI. H.VerhagenA. P.RademakerA. C.Bierma-ZeinstraS. M.Van RossumE.FaberM. J. (2010). The effects of Tai Chi on fall prevention, fear of falling and balance in older people: a meta-analysis. Prev. Med.
51, 222–227.10.1016/j.ypmed.2010.06.00320558197LordS.BakerK.NieuwboerA.BurnD.RochesterL. (2011). Gait variability in Parkinson’s disease: an indicator of non-dopaminergic contributors to gait dysfunction?
J. Neurol.
258, 566–572.10.1007/s00415-010-5789-821052710LordS.GalnaB.RochesterL. (2013a). Moving forward on gait measurement: toward a more refined approach. Mov. Disord.
28, 1534–1543.10.1002/mds.2554524132841LordS.GalnaB.VergheseJ.ColemanS.BurnD.RochesterL. (2013b). Independent domains of gait in older adults and associated motor and nonmotor attributes: validation of a factor analysis approach. J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
68, 820–827.10.1093/gerona/gls25523250001LuX.SiuK. C.FuS. N.Hui-ChanC. W.TsangW. W. (2013). Tai Chi practitioners have better postural control and selective attention in stepping down with and without a concurrent auditory response task. Eur. J. Appl. Physiol.
113, 1939–1945.10.1007/s00421-013-2624-923494549MacphersonH. (2004). Pragmatic clinical trials. Complement. Ther. Med.
12, 136–140.10.1016/j.ctim.2004.07.04315561524ManorB.LipsitzL. A.WayneP. M.PengC. K.LiL. (2013). Complexity-based measures inform Tai Chi’s impact on standing postural control in older adults with peripheral neuropathy. BMC Complement. Altern. Med.
13:87.10.1186/1472-6882-13-8723587193ManorB.LoughM.GagnonM. M.CupplesA.WayneP. M.LipsitzL. A. (2014). Functional benefits of Tai Chi training in senior housing facilities. J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.
62, 1484–1489.10.1111/jgs.1294625116984MarkettS.ReuterM.MontagC.VoigtG.LachmannB.RudorfS. (2014). Assessing the function of the fronto-parietal attention network: insights from resting-state fMRI and the attentional network test. Hum. Brain Mapp.
35, 1700–1709.10.1002/hbm.2228523670989MbourouG. A.LajoieY.TeasdaleN. (2003). Step length variability at gait initiation in elderly fallers and non-fallers, and young adults. Gerontology
49, 21–26.10.1159/00006650612457046McGibbonC. A.KrebsD. E.ParkerS. W.ScarboroughD. M.WayneP. M.WolfS. L. (2005). Tai Chi and vestibular rehabilitation improve vestibulopathic gait via different neuromuscular mechanisms: preliminary report. BMC Neurol.
5:3.10.1186/1471-2377-5-315717934McGibbonC. A.KrebsD. E.WolfS. L.WayneP. M.ScarboroughD. M.ParkerS. W. (2004). Tai Chi and vestibular rehabilitation effects on gaze and whole-body stability. J. Vestib. Res.
14, 467–478.15735329MirelmanA.GurevichT.GiladiN.Bar-ShiraA.Orr-UrtregerA.HausdorffJ. M. (2011). Gait alterations in healthy carriers of the LRRK2 G2019S mutation. Ann. Neurol.
69, 193–197.10.1002/ana.2216521280089MirelmanA.HermanT.BrozgolM.DorfmanM.SprecherE.SchweigerA. (2012). Executive function and falls in older adults: new findings from a five-year prospective study link fall risk to cognition. PLoS ONE
7:e40297.10.1371/journal.pone.004029722768271MirelmanA.MaidanI.Bernad-ElazariH.NieuwhofF.ReelickM.GiladiN. (2014). Increased frontal brain activation during walking while dual tasking: an fNIRS study in healthy young adults. J. Neuroeng. Rehabil.
11, 85.10.1186/1743-0003-11-8524886198MirelmanA.RochesterL.ReelickM.NieuwhofF.PelosinE.AbbruzzeseG. (2013). V-TIME: a treadmill training program augmented by virtual reality to decrease fall risk in older adults: study design of a randomized controlled trial. BMC Neurol.
13:15.10.1186/1471-2377-13-1523388087Montero-OdassoM.VergheseJ.BeauchetO.HausdorffJ. M. (2012). Gait and cognition: a complementary approach to understanding brain function and the risk of falling. J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.
60, 2127–2136.10.1111/j.1532-5415.2012.04209.x23110433NakamuraT.MeguroK.SasakiH. (1996). Relationship between falls and stride length variability in senile dementia of the Alzheimer type. Gerontology
42, 108–113.10.1159/0002137809138973RosengrenK. S.ChristouE.YangY.KassD.BouleA. (2003). Quantification of taiji learning in older adults. J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.
51, 1186–1187.10.1046/j.1532-5415.2003.51376.x12890093Sanchez-CubilloI.PerianezJ. A.Adrover-RoigD.Rodriguez-SanchezJ. M.Rios-LagoM.TirapuJ. (2009). Construct validity of the trail making test: role of task-switching, working memory, inhibition/interference control, and visuomotor abilities. J. Int. Neuropsychol. Soc.
15, 438–450.10.1017/S135561770909062619402930ShemaS. R.BrozgolM.DorfmanM.MaidanI.Sharaby-YeshayahuL.Malik-KozuchH. (2014). Clinical experience using a 5-week treadmill training program with virtual reality to enhance gait in an ambulatory physical therapy service. Phys. Ther.
94, 1319–1326.10.2522/ptj.2013030524786944ShenC. L.JamesC. R.ChyuM. C.BixbyW. R.BrismeeJ. M.ZumwaltM. A. (2008). Effects of Tai Chi on gait kinematics, physical function, and pain in elderly with knee osteoarthritis – a pilot study. Am. J. Chin. Med.
36, 219–232.10.1142/S0192415X0800573418457357SocieM. J.SosnoffJ. J. (2013). Gait variability and multiple sclerosis. Mult. Scler. Int.
2013, 645197.10.1155/2013/64519723533759SpringerS.GiladiN.PeretzC.YogevG.SimonE. S.HausdorffJ. M. (2006). Dual-tasking effects on gait variability: the role of aging, falls, and executive function. Mov. Disord.
21, 950–957.10.1002/mds.2084816541455SrygleyJ. M.MirelmanA.HermanT.GiladiN.HausdorffJ. M. (2009). When does walking alter thinking? Age and task associated findings. Brain Res.
1253, 92–99.10.1016/j.brainres.2008.11.06719084511TessitoreA.EspositoF.VitaleC.SantangeloG.AmboniM.RussoA. (2012). Default-mode network connectivity in cognitively unimpaired patients with Parkinson disease. Neurology
79, 2226–2232.10.1212/WNL.0b013e31827689d623100395VallabhajosulaS.RobertsB. L.HassC. J. (2014). Tai Chi intervention improves dynamic postural control during gait initiation in older adults: a pilot study. J. Appl. Biomech.
30, 697–706.10.1123/jab.2013-025625010527VergheseJ.HoltzerR.LiptonR. B.WangC. (2009). Quantitative gait markers and incident fall risk in older adults. J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
64, 896–901.10.1093/gerona/glp03319349593VerhaeghenP.CerellaJ.SemenecS. C.LeoM. A.BoppK. L.SteitzD. W. (2002). Cognitive efficiency modes in old age: performance on sequential and coordinative verbal and visuospatial tasks. Psychol. Aging
17, 558–570.10.1037/0882-7974.17.4.55812507354VisserH. (1983). Gait and balance in senile dementia of Alzheimer’s type. Age Ageing
12, 296–301.10.1093/ageing/12.4.2966660138WayneP. M.FuerstM. L. (2013). The Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi: 12 Weeks to a Healthy Body, Strong Heart &amp; Sharp Mind. Boston: Shambhala Publications Inc.WayneP. M.GowB. J.CostaM. D.PengC. K.LipsitzL. A.HausdorffJ. M. (2014a). Complexity-based measures inform effects of Tai Chi training on standing postural control: cross-sectional and randomized trial studies. PLoS ONE
9:e114731.10.1371/journal.pone.011473125494333WayneP. M.WalshJ. N.Taylor-PiliaeR. E.WellsR. E.PappK. V.DonovanN. J. (2014b). Effect of Tai Chi on cognitive performance in older adults: systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.
62, 25–39.10.1111/jgs.1261124383523WayneP. M.ManorB.NovakV.CostaM. D.HausdorffJ. M.GoldbergerA. L. (2013). A systems biology approach to studying Tai Chi, physiological complexity and healthy aging: design and rationale of a pragmatic randomized controlled trial. Contemp. Clin. Trials
34, 21–34.10.1016/j.cct.2012.09.00623026349WeiG. X.XuT.FanF. M.DongH. M.JiangL. L.LiH. J. (2013). Can Taichi reshape the brain? A brain morphometry study. PLoS ONE
8:e61038.10.1371/journal.pone.006103823585869WolfS. L.BarnhartH. X.KutnerN. G.McNeelyE.CooglerC.XuT. (1996). Reducing frailty and falls in older persons: an investigation of Tai Chi and computerized balance training. Atlanta FICSIT group. Frailty and injuries: cooperative studies of intervention techniques. J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.
44, 489–497.10.1111/j.1532-5415.1996.tb01432.x8617895WolfS. L.O’gradyM.EasleyK. A.GuoY.KressigR. W.KutnerM. (2006). The influence of intense Tai Chi training on physical performance and hemodynamic outcomes in transitionally frail, older adults. J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
61, 184–189.10.1093/gerona/61.2.18416510864WoollacottM.Shumway-CookA. (2002). Attention and the control of posture and gait: a review of an emerging area of research. Gait Posture
16, 1–14.10.1016/S0966-6362(01)00156-412127181WuG. (2012). Biomechanical characteristics of stepping in older Tai Chi practitioners. Gait Posture
36, 361–366.10.1016/j.gaitpost.2012.03.02922560715WuG.HittJ. (2005). Ground contact characteristics of Tai Chi gait. Gait Posture
22, 32–39.10.1016/j.gaitpost.2004.06.00515996589WuG.MillonD. (2008). Joint kinetics during Tai Chi gait and normal walking gait in young and elderly Tai Chi Chuan practitioners. Clin. Biomech. (Bristol, Avon)
23, 787–795.10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2008.02.00118342415YehG. Y.WoodM. J.LorellB. H.StevensonL. W.EisenbergD. M.WayneP. M. (2004). Effects of Tai Chi mind-body movement therapy on functional status and exercise capacity in patients with chronic heart failure: a randomized controlled trial. Am. J. Med.
117, 541–548.10.1016/j.amjmed.2004.04.01615465501ZegerS. L.LiangK. Y. (1986). Longitudinal data analysis for discrete and continuous outcomes. Biometrics
42, 121–130.10.2307/25312483719049ZhangC.MaoD.RiskowskiJ. L.SongQ. (2011). Strategies of stepping over obstacles: the effects of long-term exercise in older adults. Gait Posture
34, 191–196.10.1016/j.gaitpost.2011.04.00821601460ZhangJ. G.Ishikawa-TakataK.YamazakiH.MoritaT.OhtaT. (2006). The effects of Tai Chi Chuan on physiological function and fear of falling in the less robust elderly: an intervention study for preventing falls. Arch. Gerontol. Geriatr.
42, 107–116.10.1016/j.archger.2005.06.00716125805ZhengZ.ZhuX.YinS.WangB.NiuY.HuangX. (2015). Combined cognitive-psychological-physical intervention induces reorganization of intrinsic functional brain architecture in older adults. Neural Plast.
2015, 713104.10.1155/2015/71310425810927ZhouJ.HaoY.WangY.Jor’danA.Pascual-LeoneA.ZhangJ. (2014). Transcranial direct current stimulation reduces the cost of performing a cognitive task on gait and postural control. Eur. J. Neurosci.
39, 1343–1348.10.1111/ejn.1249224443958
