<?xml version="1.0"?>
Afr J Tradit Complement Altern MedAfr J Tradit Complement Altern MedAJTCAMAfrican Journal of Traditional, Complementary, and Alternative Medicines0189-60162505-0044African Traditional Herbal Medicine Supporters Initiative (ATHMSI)Nigeria5412207AJTCAM-13-9010.21010/ajtcam.v13i6.14ArticleIMAGING OF BRAIN FUNCTION BASED ON THE ANALYSIS OF FUNCTIONAL CONNECTIVITY - IMAGING ANALYSIS OF BRAIN FUNCTION BY FMRI AFTER ACUPUNCTURE AT LR3 IN HEALTHY INDIVIDUALSZhengYu1WangYuying1LanYujun1QuXiaodong1LinKelin1ZhangJiping1QuShanshan1WangYanjie1TangChunzhi2HuangYong11School of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, Guangdong Province 510515, China2Clinical Medical College of Acupuncture, Moxibustion and Rehabilitation, Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, Guangdong Province 510405, China*Corresponding author E-mail:nanfanglihuang@163.com*Co-corresponding author E-mail:jordan664@163.com2016299201613690100Copyright: © 2016 Afr. J. Traditional Complementary and Alternative Medicines2016This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International LicenseObjective:This Study observed the relevant brain areas activated by acupuncture at the Taichong acupoint (LR3) and analyzed the functional connectivity among brain areas using resting state functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) to explore the acupoint specificity of the Taichong acupoint.Methods:A total of 45 healthy subjects were randomly divided into the Taichong (LR3) group, sham acupuncture group and sham acupoint group. Subjects received resting state fMRI before acupuncture, after true (sham) acupuncture in each group. Analysis of changes in connectivity among the brain areas was performed using the brain functional connectivity method.Results:The right cerebrum temporal lobe was selected as the seed point to analyze the functional connectivity. It had a functional connectivity with right cerebrum superior frontal gyrus, limbic lobe cingulate gyrus and left cerebrum inferior temporal gyrus (BA 37), inferior parietal lobule compared by before vs. after acupuncture at LR3, and right cerebrum sub-lobar insula and left cerebrum middle frontal gyrus, medial frontal gyrus compared by true vs. sham acupuncture at LR3, and right cerebrum occipital lobe cuneus, occipital lobe sub-gyral, parietal lobe precuneus and left cerebellum anterior lobe culmen by acupuncture at LR3 vs. sham acupoint.Conclusion:Acupuncture at LR3 mainly specifically activated the brain functional network that participates in visual function, associative function, and emotion cognition, which are similar to the features on LR3 in tradition Chinese medicine. These brain areas constituted a neural network structure with specific functions that had specific reference values for the interpretation of the acupoint specificity of the Taichong acupoint.acupunctureTaichong(LR3)functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI)functional connectivityData and MethodsGeneral Data90 healthy subjects were randomly selected from universities and colleges in Guangzhou city, China. The inclusion criteria: (1) age between 21 and 28 years; right handedness; (2) regular diet with minimal liquor, tobacco, tea, and coffee consumption; normal sleeping patterns (before 12 a.m.); moderate-sized body mass index of 18.5–23.9 (Chinese); no history of nervous system disease; (3) no pain (including dysmenorrheal) or insomnia within 1 month before the test; (4) no metallic substances in the body, such as stents; (5) no noise exposure and hypothermia; no fear of confined spaces; and (6) no acupuncture procedure within 1 month before the test. The subjects were informed about the experiment and voluntarily signed informed consent in advance. There were only 45 subjects completed our study. This experiment was approved by the Chinese Ethics Review Committee (ChiECRCT-2012011) and was registered at the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (ChiCTR-TRC-12002427).According to the complete randomized design, the 45 subjects were distributed into three groups, with each group consisting of 15 people. There were no statistically significant differences between the groups in terms of age, height, and weight (P &gt; 0.05; Table 1).Table 1Basic information of the volunteers (χ̅ ± 5)GroupLR3 Group (n=15)Sham acupuncture Group (n=15)Sham acupoint Group (n=15)χ2PAge in years21.80±0.5621.80±0.8621. 87± 1.180.0480.976Height in cm168.60±6.81167.60±8.58170.07±4.520.3970.820Weight in kg55.40±8.3456.40±9.1861.20±7.843.4650.177MethodsTrials and Processing MethodsThe LR3 group subjects underwent true acupuncture at LR3 acupoint, while the sham acupuncture group underwent sham acupuncture at LR3 acupoint. The subjects in sham acupoint group underwent true acupuncture at the sham point. Subjects were asked to pass urine and stool prior to treatment. The volunteers’ eyes were masked with eyeshades, and earplugs were simultaneously worn so that their audiovisual system could not be stimulated. The flowchart is as followed (Figure 1).Figure 1Flowchart2.2.2 Acupuncture Methods2.2.2.1 Acupoints LocalizationLR3 : On the dorsum of the foot, in the depression anterior to the junction of the first and second metatarsal bones (Chinese National Standards GB/T12346) (Figure 2).Figure 2The location of the acupointsSham point: On the midpoint of the line connecting the anterior superior iliac spine and lateral border of the patella, 2 cm inside.Acupuncture OperationThe physician’s hands and volunteers’ skin around the acupoints were sterilized with alcohol before needling. DONGBANG needles (0.30 × (25–15 mm); DONGBANG AcuPrime, Exeter, UK) were used in this study. The acuponits are stimulated bilaterally.① Sham acupuncture at the LR3 acupoint: In accordance with a previously published method of sham acupuncture (Huang Y, et al., 2012), the auxiliary part of the tube was applied to the skin, with a sham needle placed in the tube over the acupoint. The sham needle was then tapped to make its tip touch the skin without puncturing it and was maintained in place for 30 min.② True acupuncture at the LR3 acupoint: The tube needling technique was used; the needle handle was tapped softly using a forefinger. The puncturing depth was controlled. After removal of the tube, the needle was vertically punctured at 15±2 mm. After developing needle sensation, twirling at an angle of 90–180° and a frequency of 60–90 times/min and lifting and thrusting at a range of 0.3–0.5 cm and a frequency of 60–90 times/min were conducted. After manipulating the needle for 1 min, the needle was held in place for 30 min. During the 30 min, the physician repeated this manipulation for 1 min every 10 min.③ True acupuncture at the sham point: The same procedure was followed as that of true acupuncture at the LR3 acupoint.Resting-state fMRI ScanThe subjects were awake, with normal respiration, and lay supine on an examination bed. The head was placed in a foam headrest for maximum restriction of passive and active movements of the head. The subjects were instructed to avoid any systematic mental activity, and visual and audio stimulations were minimized with earplugs and eyeshades. Scanning was initiated once the subjects were familiarized with the circumstances.Experiments were performed using a GE 3.0T MRI scanner with an 8-channel head coil. The MRI data (resting-state BOLD sequence) were collected at before needling and 15 min after withdrawing the needle. The scanning parameters are the same as those in our previous study (Wu C, et al., 2014). (Figure 3)Figure 3The scan flowchartImage Processing and Analytical MethodsPreprocessing was carried out using Data Processing Assistant for Resting-State fMRI (DPARSF) (Yan &amp; Zang, 2010, http://www.restfMRI.net), which is based on Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM8) (http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm) and the Resting-State fMRI Data Analysis Toolkit (REST, Song et al., 2011. http://www.restfMRI.net) (Yan CC, et al., 2010; Song XW, et al., 2011). This includes DICOM format conversion, removal of 10 time points before image scanning, time correction, correction of the head movement, space standardization and space smoothing. After preprocessing, all 45 subjects were included in the statistical analysis. ReHo AnalysisThe parameters are the same as those in our previous study (Wu C, et al., 2014). ALFF analysis: using REST1.8 software, linear tendency of the data after preprocessing (space smoothing was completed) was removed by linear regression. Time and curve were convolved using Hamming bandpass filtering. ALFF was obtained (0.01–0.08 Hz). ALFF of each subject was computed, so ALFF maps were obtained. ALFF value was divided by the mean of the whole brain, and standardized ALFF was obtained. ROI IdentificationRegarding our ALFF results, comparing these three groups, the highest peak scores were in the right cerebrum temporal lobe [36, -45, 9]. In the present study, we followed the work of Greicius et al (Grecius MD, et al., 2003) to select our region of interest (ROI). We chose the above three regions as our seed points, which is the center of a sphere with a radius of 1 mm. fMRI AnalysesWe used the REST1.8 software and ROIs mentioned above to analyze functional connectivity.Statistical AnalysesData were analyzed using REST1.8 software. In the statistical analysis, t-test was used to explore the differences between before and after acupuncture in LR3, true and sham acupuncture in LR3, between acupuncture in LR3 and sham acupoint. Rest1.8 software Viewer was employed to identify the precise anatomical position in the brain with statistical significance on the corresponding MNI coordinate (AlphaSim correction P &lt; 0.05, continuous voxel &gt; 85). The results are presented as images visualized with the BrainNet Viewer (Xia et al., 2013, http://www.nitrc.org/projects/bnv/).AcknowledgementsWe are very grateful to the healthy volunteers and staff from the MRI Center of the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine in China.Conflict of interest statement None declared.References1AcupunctureNIH Consens Statement Online199715512AndersenDLosslKNyboe AndersenAFürbringerJBachHSimonsenJLarsenECAcupuncture on the day of embryo transfer: a randomized controlled trial of 635 patientsReprod Biomed Online201021336672206383383BermanBMLaoLLangenbergPLeeWLGilpinAMHochbergMCEffectiveness of acupuncture as adjunctive therapy in osteoarthritis of the knee: a randomized, controlled trialAnn Intern Med20041411290110156114874BrodmannKVergleichende Lokalisationslehre der GroBhirnrinde1909LeipzigJohann Ambrosius Barth5ChenHDaiJZhangXWangKHuangSCaoQWangHLiangYShiCLiMHaTAiLLiSMaJWeiWYouYLiuZTianJBaiLHypothalamus-related resting brain network underlying short-term acupuncture treatment in primary hypertension[J]Evid Based Complement Alternat Med20138089716ChenJWangJHuangYLaiXTangCYangJWuJZengTQuSModulatory effect of acupuncture at Waiguan (TE5) on the functional connectivity of the central nervous system of patients with ischemic stroke in the left basal ganglia [J]PLoS One201496e96777249272757CordesDHaughtonV MArfanakisKWendtGJTurskiPAMotitzCHQuigleyMAMeyerandMEMapping functionally related regions of brain with functional connectivity MR imaging[J]AJNR Am J Neuroradiol2000219163644110393428DaiXJPengDCGongHHWanALNieXLiHJWangYXAltered intrinsic regional brain spontaneous activity and subjective sleep quality in patients with chronic primary insomnia: a resting-state fMRI studyNeuropsychiatr Dis Treat201410216375254845859EbischSJBelloASpitoniGFPerrucciMGGalleseVCommitteriGPastorelliCPizzamiglioLEmotional susceptibility trait modulates insula responses and functional connectivity in flavor processingFront Behav Neurosci201592972659415910EngelenTde GraafTASackATde GelderBA causal role for inferior parietal lobule in emotion body perceptionCortex2015731952022646086811GreiciusMDKrasnowBReissALMenonVFunctional connectivity in the resting brain: A network analysis of the default mode hypothesis [J]Proc Natl Acad Sci USA200310012532581250619412GreiciusMDKrasnowBBoyett-AndersonJMEliezSSchatzbergAFReissALMenonVRegional analysis of hippocampal activation during memory encoding and retrieval: fMRI study [J]Hippocampus2003131164741262546613HuangYTangCWangSLuYShenWYangJChenJLinRCuiSXiaoHQuSLaiXShanBAcupuncture regulates the glucose metabolism in cerebral functional regions in chronic stage ischemic stroke patients-a PET-CT cerebral functional imaging study [J]BMC Neuroscience201213752273827014JiangYHaoYZhangYLiuJWangXHanJFangJZhangJCuiCThirty minute transcutaneous electric acupoint stimulation modulates resting state brain activities: a perfusion and BOLD fMRI study [J]Brain Res2012145713252254116715JiangYWangHLiuZDongYXiangXXiangXBaiLTianJWuLHanJCuiCManipulation of and sustained effects on the human brain induced by different modalities of acupuncture: an fMRI study [J]PLoS One201386e668152384053316KwanCLCrawleyAPMikulisDJDavisKDAn fMRI study of the anterior cingulate cortex and surrounding medial wall activations evoked by noxious cutaneous heat and cold stimuliPain2000853359741078190917LaiXHuangYA cerebral functional definition on the specificity of acupoints, needling sensation and association of acupoints based on the “acupoints-brain relation hypothesis” [J]Chinese Acupuncture &amp; Moxibustion200727107777801825735918LiGMaXBianHSunXZhaiNYaoMQuHJiSTianHZhuoCA pilot fMRI study of the effect of stressful factors on the onset of depression in female patientsBrain Imaging Behav201510119520219LiangPWangZQianTLiKAcupuncture Stimulation of Taichong (Liv3) and Hegu (LI4) Modulates the Default Mode Network Activity in Alzheimer’s Disease [J]Am J Alzheimers Dis Other Demen2014298739482490696820LindeK1WeidenhammerWStrengAHoppeAMelchartDAcupuncture for osteoarthritic pain: an observational study in routine careRheumatology (Oxford)200645222271636873121LiuQLiRZhouRLiJGuQAbnormal Resting-State Connectivity at Functional MRI in Women with Premenstrual SyndromePLoS One2015109e01360292632551022McPhersonMJBarrettFSLopez-GonzalezMJiradejvongPLimbCJEmotional Intent Modulates The Neural Substrates Of Creativity: An fMRI Study of Emotionally Targeted Improvisation in Jazz MusiciansSci Rep20166184602672592523PotvinSTikàszALunguODumaisAStipEMendrekAEmotion processing in treatment-resistant schizophrenia patients treated with clozapine: An fMRI studySchizophr Res20151681-2377802625508224RenYBaiLFengYTianJLiKInvestigation of acupoint specificity by functional connectivity analysis based on graph theory[J]Neurosci Lett20104822951002061931725SiedentopfCMGolaszewskiSMMottaghyFMRuffCCFelberSSchiagerAFunctional magnetic resonance imaging detects activation of the visual association cortex during laser acupuncture of the foot in humans [J]Neurosci Lett2002327153561209849926SongXWDongZYLongXYLiSFZuoXNZhuCZHeYYanCGZangYFREST: A toolkit for resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging data processing[J]PLoS ONE201169Article ID e2503127TownsendJDTorrisiSJLiebermanMDSugarCABookheimerSYAltshulerLLFrontal-amygdala connectivity alterations during emotion downregulation in bipolar I disorderBiol Psychiatry2013732127352285815128WuCQuSZhangJChenJZhangSLiZChenJOuyangHHuangYTangCCorrelation between the Effects of Acupuncture at Taichong (LR3) and Functional Brain Areas: A Resting-State Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging Study Using True versus Sham Acupuncture[J]Evid Based Complement Alternat Med: 729091201429YanBLiKXuJWangWLiKLiuHShanBTangXAcupoint-specific fMRI patterns in human brain[J]Neurosci Lett200538332362401587649130YanCCZangYFDPARSF: A MATLAB toolbox for Pipeline Data Analysis of Resting-State fMRI. [J]Frontiers in Systems Neuroscience20104132057759131YangWChenQLiuPChengHCuiQWeiDZhangQQiuJAbnormal brain activation during directed forgetting of negative memory in depressed patientsJ Affect Disord201619088082663945232YouYBaiLDaiRChengHLiuZWeiWTianJAltered hub configurations within default mode network following acupuncture at ST36: a multimodal investigation combining fMRI and MEG [J]PLoS One201385e645092369123733ZhangGQuSZhengYChenJDengGYangCHuangYKey regions of the cerebral network are altered after electroacupuncture at the Baihui (GV20) and Yintang acupoints in healthy volunteers: an analysis based on resting fcMRI[J]Acupunct Med201331438382388651234ZhangQLiAYueJZhangFSunZLiXUsing functional magnetic resonance imaging to explore the possible mechanism of the action of acupuncture at Dazhong (KI 4) on the functional cerebral regions of healthy volunteers[J]Intern Med J 2015201545666967135ZhongCBaiLDaiRXueTWangHFengYLiuZYouYChenSTianyaJModulatory effects of acupuncture on resting-state networks: a functional MRI study combining independent component analysis and multivariate Granger causality analysis[J]J Magn Reson Imaging20122012353572812206907836ZyloneyCEJensenKPolichGLoiotileRECheethamALaViolettePSTuPKaptchukTJGollubRLKongJImaging the functional connectivity of the Periaqueductal Gray during genuine and sham electroacupuncture treatment [J]Mol Pain201068021080967
