<?xml version="1.0"?>
960783520545Mol PsychiatryMol. PsychiatryMolecular psychiatry1359-41841476-557855894682826511910.1038/mp.2017.34nihpa842435ArticleEvidence for Neuroplastic Compensation in the Cerebral Cortex of Persons with Depressive IllnessBansalRaviPh.D.12HellersteinDavid J.M.D.34PetersonBradley S.M.D.151Institute for the Developing Mind, Children’s Hospital Los Angeles, CA, USA 900272Department of Pediatrics, Keck School of Medicine at the University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, USA 900333Depression Evaluation Service, Division of Clinical Therapeutics, New York State Psychiatric Institute, New York, NY 100324Department of Psychiatry, Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, NY 100325Department of Psychiatry, Keck School of Medicine at the University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, USA 90033Corresponding Author: Ravi Bansal, Ph.D., 4650 Sunset Blvd, MS # 135, Los Angeles, CA 90027, Phone: 323-361-7558, Fax: 323-361-5309, rabansal@chla.usc.edu14120170732017220182712018232375383Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#termsWe yoked anatomical brain Magnetic Resonance Imaging to a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial (RCT) of antidepressant medication for 10-week’s duration in patients with dysthymia. The RCT study design mitigated ascertainment bias by randomizing patients to receive either duloxetine or placebo, and it supported true causal inferences about treatment effects on the brain by controlling treatment assignment experimentally. We acquired 121 anatomical scans: at baseline and endpoint in 41 patients, and once in 39 healthy controls. At baseline, patients had diffusely thicker cortices than did healthy participants, and patients who had thicker cortices had proportionately less severe symptoms. During the trial, symptoms improved significantly more in medication- compared with placebo-treated patients; concurrently, thicknesses in medication-treated patients declined toward values in healthy controls, but they increased slightly, away from control values, in placebo-treated patients. Changes in symptom severity during the trial mediated the association of treatment assignment with the change in thickness, suggesting that the beneficial effects of medication on symptom severity were at least partially responsible for normalizing cortical thickness. Together our findings suggest that baseline cortical hypertrophy in medication-free patients likely represented a compensatory, neuroplastic response that attenuated symptom severity. Medication then reduced symptoms and lessened the need for compensation, thereby normalizing thickness. This is to the best of our knowledge the first study to report within an RCT a differential change in cortical morphology during medication treatment for depressive illness and the first to provide within an RCT in vivo evidence for the presence of neuroanatomical plasticity in humans.Trial Registration: ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT00360724CONFLICT OF INTERESTDr. Bansal reports no financial relationships with commercial interests.Supplementary information is available at Molecular Psychiatry’s website.This study was supported by NIH grant K02-74677 (PI, Dr. Bradley S. Peterson), an Investigator-Initiated Grant from Eli Lilly company to Drs. Hellerstein and Peterson, and funding from Children’s Hospital Los Angeles and the University of Southern California. We are grateful to Zachary Toth, MS, Giancarlo Nati, MA, and Ming Qian, MS, for their technical assistance in data processing, archiving, and maintenance. The research was made possible by the provision of data by New York State Psychiatric Institute and Columbia University.Drs. Hellerstein and Peterson received an investigator-initiated grant from Eli Lilly to support in part the costs of this study. Neither received salary support from that grant.REFERENCES1SansoneRASansoneLADysthymic disorder: forlorn and overlooked?Psychiatry (Edgmont)2009654651Epub 2009/09/032American Psychiatric AssociationDiagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders2000FourthDSM-IV-TR: American Psychiatric Pub3HellersteinDJEipperJWMannJRooseSPMcGrathPJDysthymia and chronic depressionThe Clinical Handbook for the Management of Mood Disorders2013New YorkCambridge University Press20364AnismanHRavindranAVGriffithsJMeraliZEndocrine and cytokine correlates of major depression and dysthymia with typical or atypical featuresMol Psychiatry199942182188Epub 1999/04/20102084515SchlatterJOrtunoFCervera-EnguixSDifferences in interleukins' patterns between dysthymia and major depressionEur Psychiat20011653173196GriffithsJRavindranAVMeraliZAnismanHDysthymia: a review of pharmacological and behavioral factorsMol Psychiatr2000532422617WeissmanMMLeafPJBruceMLFlorioLThe epidemiology of dysthymia in five communities: rates, risks, comorbidity, and treatmentAm J Psychiatry19881457815819Epub 1988/07/0133819248KellerMBKleinDNHirschfeldRMAKocsisJHMcculloughJPMillerIResults of the Dsm-Iv Mood Disorders Field TrialAmerican Journal of Psychiatry1995152684384977551129SolomonAHaagaDAFArnowBAIs clinical depression distinct from subthreshold depressive symptoms? A review of the continuity issue in depression researchJournal of Nervous and Mental Disease200118984985061153120110MalykhinNVCarterRHegadorenKMSeresPCouplandNJFronto-limbic volumetric changes in major depressive disorderJ Affect Disorders20121363110411132213404111McEwenBSMood disorders and allostatic loadBiological Psychiatry20035432002071289309612SchmaalLVeltmanDJvan ErpTGMPenninxBWJHThompsonPMHibarDPSubcortical Brain Alterations in Major Depressive Disorder: Findings from the ENIGMA Major Depressive Disorder Working GroupBiological Psychiatry201577913PetersonBSWarnerVBansalRZhuHHaoXLiuJCortical thinning in persons at increased familial risk for major depressionProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20091061562736278Epub 2009/03/311932949014van ElstLTWoermannFGLemieuxLTrimbleMRAmygdala enlargement in dysthymia - A volumetric study of patients with temporal lobe epilepsyBiological Psychiatry19994612161416231062454215RavindranAVSmithACameronCBhatlaRCameronIGeorgescuTMToward a functional neuroanatomy of dysthymia: A functional magnetic resonance imaging studyJ Affect Disorders20091191-39151935157216PosnerJHellersteinDJGatIMechlingAKlahrKWangZSAntidepressants Normalize the Default Mode Network in Patients With DysthymiaJama Psychiat201370437338217HorgaGKaurTPetersonBSAnnual research review: Current limitations and future directions in MRI studies of child- and adult-onset developmental psychopathologiesJournal of child psychology and psychiatry, and allied disciplines2014556659680Epub 2014/01/2118PetersonBSFrom correlations to causation: the value of preventive interventions in studying pathogenic mechanisms in childhood psychiatric disordersJournal of child psychology and psychiatry, and allied disciplines2013548813815Epub 2013/07/2019HellersteinDJStewartJWMcGrathPJDeliyannidesDABatchelderSTBlackSRA randomized controlled trial of duloxetine versus placebo in the treatment of nonmajor chronic depressionThe Journal of clinical psychiatry2012737984991Epub 2012/08/212290134820HamiltonMA rating scale for depressionJ Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry1960235662Epub 1960/02/011439927221HellersteinDJBatchelderSTLeeABorisovskayaMRating dysthymia: an assessment of the construct and content validity of the Cornell Dysthymia Rating ScaleJ Affect Disorders2002711-385961216750422SledGJZijdenbosAPEvansACA Nonparametric Method for Automatic Correction of Intensity Nonuniformity in MRI DataIEEE Trans of Medical Imaging19981718797961791023ShattuckDWLeahyRMBrainSuite: An Automated Cortical Surface Identification ToolMedical Image Analysis20028212914224ShroutPEFleissJLIntraclass correlations: uses in assessing rater reliabilityPsychol Bull1979864204281883948425HaralickRShapiroLComputer and Robot Vision, volume 1: Addison-Wesley Publishing Company199226QiuLLuiSKuangWHuangXLiJLiJRegional increases of cortical thickness in untreated, first-episode major depressive disorderTranslational Psychiatry2014427KemptonMJSalvadorZMunafoMRGeddesJRSimmonsAFrangouSStructural Neuroimaging Studies in Major Depressive Disorder Meta-analysis and Comparison With Bipolar DisorderArch Gen Psychiat20116876756902172725228MillerLBansalRWickramaratnePHaoXTenkeCEWeissmanMMNeuroanatomical correlates of religiosity and spirituality: a study in adults at high and low familial risk for depressionJama Psychiat2014712128135Epub 2013/12/2729Pascual-LeoneAAmediAFregniFMerabetLBThe plastic human brain cortexAnnu Rev Neurosci200528377401Epub 2005/07/191602260130ZatorreRJFieldsRDJohansen-BergHPlasticity in gray and white: neuroimaging changes in brain structure during learningNature Neuroscience20121545285362242625431FoxKCRNijeboerSDixonMLFlomanJLEllamilMRumakSPIs meditation associated with altered brain structure? A systematic review and meta-analysis of morphometric neuroimaging in meditation practitionersNeurosci Biobehav R201443487332HottingKRoderBBeneficial effects of physical exercise on neuroplasticity and cognitionNeurosci Biobehav R20133792243225733Stine-MorrowEALBasakCSchaieKWWillisSLCognitive InterventionsHandbook of the Psychology of Aging2011SeventhAcademic Press15317134GreenougWtVolkmarFRJuraskaJMEffects of Rearing Complexity on Dendritic Branching in Frontolateral and Temporal Cortex of RatExperimental Neurology1973412371378412687635KozorovitskiyYGrossCGKopilCBattagliaLMcBreenMStranahanAMExperience induces structural and biochemical changes in the adult primate brainP Natl Acad Sci USA200510248174781748236Blumenfeld-KatzirTPasternakODaganMAssafYDiffusion MRI of Structural Brain Plasticity Induced by a Learning and Memory TaskPLoS One20116637NilssonMPerfilievaEJohanssonUOrwarOErikssonPSEnriched environment increases neurogenesis in the adult rat dentate gyrus and improves spatial memoryJ Neurobiol19993945695781038007838RamachandranVSHirsteinWThe perception of phantom limbs - The D.O. Hebb lectureBrain199812116031630976295239TaubEUswatteGElbertTNew treatments in neurorehabilitation founded on basic researchNature Reviews Neuroscience2002332282361199475440KaysJLHurleyRATaberKHThe dynamic brain: neuroplasticity and mental healthJ Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci2012242118124Epub 2012/07/102277266041PlessenKJRoyalJMPetersonBSNeuroimaging of tic disorders with co-existing attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorderEur Child Adolesc Psychiatry200716Suppl 16070Epub 2007/09/051766528442PetersonBSChoiHAHaoXJAmatJAZhuHWhitemanRMorphologic features of the amygdala and hippocampus in children and adults with Tourette syndromeArch Gen Psychiat20076411128112911798439743PlessenKJBansalRZhuHTWhitemanRAmatJQuackenbushGAHippocampus and amygdala morphology in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorderArch Gen Psychiat20066377958071681886944SobelLJBansalRMaiaTVSanchezJMazzoneLDurkinKBasal ganglia surface morphology and the effects of stimulant medications in youth with attention deficit hyperactivity disorderAm J Psychiatry20101678977986Epub 2010/07/032059541445MillerAMBansalRHaoXJSanchez-PenaJPSobelLJLiuJEnlargement of Thalamic Nuclei in Tourette SyndromeArch Gen Psychiat20106799559642081998946ApfelBARossJHlavinJMeyerhoffDJMetzlerTJMarmarCRHippocampal volume differences in Gulf War veterans with current versus lifetime posttraumatic stress disorder symptomsBiol Psychiatry2011696541548Epub 2010/11/262109493747VitaADe PeriLDesteGBarlatiSSacchettiEThe Effect of Antipsychotic Treatment on Cortical Gray Matter Changes in Schizophrenia: Does the Class Matter? A Meta-analysis and Meta-regression of Longitudinal Magnetic Resonance Imaging StudiesBiological Psychiatry201578640341225802081Figure 1Baseline Data AnalysesWe compared cortical thickness in the 41 dysthymic patients with thickness in the 39 age- and sex-matched healthy participants, and we correlated cortical thickness with symptom severity within the dysthymic patients. We covaried for age and sex, and controlled for multiple hypothesis testing using a procedure for False Discovery Rate (FDR), with the FDR set at 0.05. We color-coded and displayed the P-values smaller than 0.05 across the surface of a template brain using the color bar shown at the bottom. The findings were unchanged when we covaried for a lifetime history of MDD in dysthymic patients.Left Panel: Dysthymic patients compared to healthy controls had a thicker cortex bilaterally across large portions of the brain, especially in the superior and middle temporal gyrus, cingulate gyrus, inferior parietal lobule, supramarginal gyrus, and pre- and post-central gyrus. In addition, the patients had thinner lateral and mesial prefrontal cortices bilaterally. Warm colors (red and orange) represent thicker, cool colors (blue and purple) represent thinner, cortices in patients compared with healthy participants, and gray shows voxels where thickness did not differ between patients and controls.Right Panel: Symptom severity correlated inversely with cortical thickness bilaterally across the parietal and temporal cortices, indicating that patients with thicker cortices had proportionately lower symptom severity scores. Warm colors (red and orange) show positive correlations, cool colors (blue and purple) show inverse correlations, and grey shows no significant correlations between thickness and symptom severity. Findings were similar for the correlations of cortical thickness with symptom severity measured using the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (not shown).DD=Dysthymic Disorder; HC=Healthy Controls; CDRS=Cornell Dysthymia Rating Scale; PFC=Prefrontal Cortex; mPFC=mesial Prefrontal Cortex; CG=Cingulate Gyrus; MTG=Middle Temporal Gyrus; STG=Superior Temporal Gyrus; IPL=Inferior Parietal Lobule; SMAR=Supramarginal Gyrus; PoG=Postcentral Gyrus; PCG=Precentral Gyrus; A=Anterior; P=PosteriorFigure 2Longitudinal Data Analyses to Assess Change in Thickness with TimeWe used linear mixed models to assess the change in cortical thickness with time in the 41 dysthymic patients. Findings showed a significant treatment-by-time interaction on the cortical thickness (left panel), which was driven primarily by a decline in cortical thickness over the trial in the duloxetine-treated patients (middle panel) and a slight increase in thickness in the placebo-treated patients, especially in the occipital cortex bilaterally (right panel). Warm colors (orange and red) show thickening, cool colors (purple and blue) show thinning, and gray shows no significant change in thickness with time. We showed time effects only in voxels where we detected significant effects of treatment-by-time interaction on cortical thickness to understand better treatment effects over the 10-week period of the clinical trial. See Supplementary Figure 1 for maps of time effects across the entire cortical surface. Line graphs for representative locations in the right occipital cortex and right mesial parietal cortex illustrate the opposing change in thickness with time for patients in the two treatment arms. At baseline, the variance of the cortical thickness did not differ between duloxetine-treated patients and placebo-treated patients (scatterplot at mesial location: F-statistic=1.11; df1=19; df2=20; p=0.81; scatterplot at lateral location: F-statistic=0.65; df1=19; df2=20; p=0.36). At the end of the trial, the variance did differ between the two treatment arms for the lateral location (F-statistic=1.53; df1=19; df2=20; p=0.35) but was significantly different for the mesial location (F-statistic=0.31; df1=19; df2=20; p=0.016).DULX=Duloxetine; PBO=PlaceboFigure 3Repeated Measures Analyses Associating Symptom Severity with Cortical ThicknessWe assessed how cortical thickness in duloxetine-treated patients was associated with symptom severity across individuals, as well as how cortical thickness changed with the change in symptom severity within individuals over time. Symptom severity was measured with the Cornell Dysthymic Rating scale (CDRS). We covaried for age and sex effects and generated scatterplots using age- and sex-adjusted cortical thickness measures. We displayed findings only in voxels where the interaction of treatment-by-time on cortical thickness was statistically significant (Figure 2). Maps of findings across the entire brain are shown in Supplementary Figure 3 of the Supplementary Information.Left Panel: The cross-sectional, across-individual correlation of cortical thickness with severity showed that thickness correlated inversely with CDRS values, averaged over pretreatment baseline (Time1) and end of trial (Time2), in large expanses of the lateral and mesial surfaces of both hemispheres, especially in regions where the dysthymic patients had thicker cortices than healthy participants at baseline (Figure 1). Scatterplots for representative voxels where inverse correlations were located illustrate that patients with thicker cortices generally had less severe symptoms. In contrast, cortical thickness correlated positively with symptom severity bilaterally in the anterior prefrontal and posterior parietal cortex.Right Panel: The longitudinal, within-individual, correlation of change in thickness with the change in severity over the course of the trial showed positive associations (indicating that cortical thickness decreased as symptom severity decreased, as shown in orange and red) located bilaterally in the parietal and posterior temporal cortex, and inverse associations (indicating that cortical thickness increased as symptom severity decreased, shown in blue and violet) located bilaterally in the occipital, anterior cingulate, and anterior prefrontal cortex.Note that the cross-sectional, across-individual maps generally show color codings for correlations that are opposite from those in the longitudinal, within-individual maps: In the left panel, individuals with fewer symptoms had thicker cortices in voxels shown in blue; in the right panel, cortical thickness decreased over the 10-week period of the trial within individuals for whom treatment with antidepressants reduced symptom severity. Thus, the findings in both panels, taken together, suggest that a thicker cortex at baseline is associated with fewer symptoms, likely representing a compensatory, neuroplastic hypertrophy of the cortex. Successful treatment and a decline in symptoms over the course of the trial seems to obviate the need for that compensatory hypertrophy and thereby produces a relative thinning and normalization of the cortical mantle.Figure 4Longitudinal Mediation AnalysesWe applied a longitudinal mediation analysis to assess whether the change in symptom severity mediated the association between treatment arm and the change in cortical thickness in our 41 dysthymic patients. We covaried for age and sex and controlled for multiple hypothesis testing using a procedure for false discovery rate (FDR) with FDR=0.05. Here we display findings only for those voxels where we detected significant treatment-by-time interaction effects on cortical thickness (Figure 2). The findings across the entire brain are shown in Supplementary Figure 5.Left Panel: At each voxel on the template surface we color-coded and plotted P-values in warm colors (red and orange) where the test statistic was positive and in cool colors (violet and blue) where the test statistic was negative for the mediation analyses. These plots showed that the decline in symptom severity over the trial significantly mediated the associations between treatment and change in cortical thickness across large portions of the brain where dysthymic patients at baseline had thicker cortices than healthy controls. We used cortical thickness from the brain region pointed to by the arrow for the scatterplot shown in the right panel.Right Panel: We generated scatterplot for the associations among treatment, change in symptom severity, and change in cortical thickness variables for a representative voxel where the mediating effects of symptom severity were statistically significant. These plots showed that symptom severity declined significantly (p=4×10−6) in the duloxetine-treated patients, the decrease in symptom severity was significantly (p=0.01) associated with a decrease in cortical thickness, and treatment was significantly (p=0.045) associated with the decrease in cortical thickness. The overall P-value was &lt; 0.008 for the mediating effect of change in symptom severity on the association of treatment with change in cortical thickness.* = P-value&lt;0.05; ** = P-value&lt;0.01; *** = P-value&lt;0.00001.Table 1Demographics and Symptom Severity of the Participants in this StudyThe 41 dysthymic patients did not differ significantly from the 39 healthy controls in age (p=0.97) or sex (χ2=0.508, df=1, p=0.47). At baseline, patients randomized to the duloxetine arm did not differ significantly from those randomized the placebo arm in age (p=0.44), symptom severity measured using either the HDRS (p=0.26) or the CDRS (p=0.76) scale, or lifetime history of Major Depressive Disorder (χ2=1.17, df=1, p=0.27). However, the sex composition differed significantly in the two treatment arms (χ2=7.152, df=1, p&lt;0.01). By the end of the trial (i.e. Week 10), symptom severity had decreased significantly for both the duloxetine-treated patients (p&lt;1.0*10−15 for HDRS scores and p&lt;4.0*10−13 for CDRS scores) and placebo-treated patients (p&lt;0.002 for HDRS scores and p&lt;0.01 for CDRS scores). However, the duloxetine-treated compared with placebo-treated patients had significantly lower symptom severity (p&lt;9.0*10−6 for HDRS scores and p&lt;2.0*10−5 for CDRS scores). Furthermore, a significantly (χ2=15.14, df=1, p&lt;0.0001) greater proportion of the duloxetine-treated patients had a remission of illness by the end of the trial. The average and standard deviation of age and symptom severity are shown in the table.Age(Years)SexSymptom Severity(At Baseline)Symptom Severity(At Week 10)LifetimeMDDRemitted atWeek 10HDRSCDRSHDRSCDRSHealthy, N=3939.55±10.2622 MalesN/AN/AN/AN/A0N/ADuloxetine Arm, N=2139.08±10.007 Males20.66±4.0937.62±8.165.76±3.12*12.14±7.37*1315Placebo Arm, N=2040.82±10.8115 Males22.23±4.7938.38±8.2215.76±7.7129.04±13.0992HDRS = Hamilton Depression Rating Scale; CDRS = Cornell Dysthymia Rating Scale; N/A = not applicable; MDD = Major Depressive disorderTable 2Comorbid Illnesses in the Dysthymic PatientsThe table lists the number of dysthymic patients who had a comorbid illness either previously or at the time of study entry; 10 patients in the duloxetine arm and 10 patients in the placebo arm had a comorbid illness other than Major Depressive Disorder in their lifetimes.Comorbid IllnessesPreviousAt Study EntryDuloxetine ArmPlacebo ArmMajor Depressive Disorder220139Generalized Anxiety Disorder9054Post Traumatic Stress Disorder1212Panic Disorder2222Social Phobia1753Specific Phobia3443Obsessive Compulsive Disorder2231
