<?xml version="1.0"?>
PLoS OnePLoS ONEplosplosonePLoS ONE1932-6203Public Library of ScienceSan Francisco, CA USA47267932680851910.1371/journal.pone.0147357PONE-D-15-37503Research ArticleBiology and Life SciencesBehaviorBiology and Life SciencesPsychologyEmotionsSocial SciencesPsychologyEmotionsPeople and PlacesPopulation GroupingsAge GroupsAdolescentsBiology and Life SciencesBehaviorAnimal BehaviorCollective Animal BehaviorBiology and Life SciencesZoologyAnimal BehaviorCollective Animal BehaviorMedicine and Health SciencesMental Health and PsychiatryBiology and Life SciencesAnatomyBrainCerebral HemispheresRight HemisphereMedicine and Health SciencesAnatomyBrainCerebral HemispheresRight HemisphereResearch and Analysis MethodsBioassays and Physiological AnalysisElectrophysiological TechniquesBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyBiology and Life SciencesPhysiologyElectrophysiologyNeurophysiologyBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyMedicine and Health SciencesPhysiologyElectrophysiologyNeurophysiologyBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceNeurophysiologyBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceBrain MappingElectroencephalographyMedicine and Health SciencesDiagnostic MedicineClinical NeurophysiologyElectroencephalographyResearch and Analysis MethodsImaging TechniquesNeuroimagingElectroencephalographyBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceNeuroimagingElectroencephalographyResearch and Analysis MethodsBioassays and Physiological AnalysisElectrophysiological TechniquesBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsBiology and Life SciencesPhysiologyElectrophysiologyNeurophysiologyBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsMedicine and Health SciencesPhysiologyElectrophysiologyNeurophysiologyBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceNeurophysiologyBrain ElectrophysiologyElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceBrain MappingElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsMedicine and Health SciencesDiagnostic MedicineClinical NeurophysiologyElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsResearch and Analysis MethodsImaging TechniquesNeuroimagingElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsBiology and Life SciencesNeuroscienceNeuroimagingElectroencephalographyEvent-Related PotentialsPsychosocial Intervention Is Associated with Altered Emotion Processing: An Event-Related Potential Study in At-Risk AdolescentsPsychosocial Intervention in At-Risk AdolescentsPinchamHannah L.12BryceDonna3KokorikouDanae1FonagyPeter12FearonR. M. Pasco12*1Developmental Neuroscience Unit, The Anna Freud Centre, 12 Maresfield Gardens, London, United Kingdom, NW3 5SU2Research Department of Clinical, Educational and Health Psychology, University College London, 1–19 Torrington Place, London, United Kingdom, WC1E 7HB3Department of Psychology, University of Tübingen, Schleichstrasse 4, 72076, Tubingen, GermanyHashimotoKenjiEditorChiba University Center for Forensic Mental Health, JAPANCompeting Interests: The authors have read the journal's policy and have the following competing interests: Kids Company delivered the psycho-social intervention, and also supported the recruitment of participants from their services, and provided lab space, equipment and top-up funding. Kids Company had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. R.M.P. Fearon received an honorarium from Shire Pharmaceuticals for giving a workshop on attachment in March 2014.Conceived and designed the experiments: DB PF RMPF. Performed the experiments: HLP DB DK. Analyzed the data: HLP DB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HLP DB. Wrote the paper: HLP DB DK PF RMPF.* E-mail: p.fearon@ucl.ac.uk25120162016111e01473572682015412016© 2016 Pincham et al2016Pincham et alThis is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.Emotion processing is vital for healthy adolescent development, and impaired emotional responses are associated with a number of psychiatric disorders. However, it is unclear whether observed differences between psychiatric populations and healthy controls reflect modifiable variations in functioning (and thus could be sensitive to changes resulting from intervention) or stable, non-modifiable, individual differences. The current study therefore investigated whether the Late Positive Potential (LPP; a neural index of emotion processing) can be used as a marker of therapeutic change following psycho-social intervention. At-risk male adolescents who had received less than four months intervention (minimal-intervention, N = 32) or more than nine months intervention (extended-intervention, N = 32) passively viewed emotional images whilst neural activity was recorded using electroencephalography. Significant differences in emotion processing, indicated by the LPP, were found between the two groups: the LPP did not differ according to valence in the minimal-intervention group, whereas the extended-intervention participants showed emotion processing in line with low risk populations (enhanced LPP for unpleasant images versus other images). Further, an inverse relationship between emotional reactivity (measured via the LPP) and antisocial behaviour was observed in minimal-intervention participants only. The data therefore provide preliminary cross-sectional evidence that abnormal neural responses to emotional information may be normalised following psychosocial intervention. Importantly, this study uniquely suggests that, in future randomised control trials, the LPP may be a useful biomarker to measure development and therapeutic change.This work was supported by the Waterloo Foundation (grant code 564/709; http://www.waterloofoundation.org.uk), which had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. Kids Company (http://www.kidsco.org.uk) supported the recruitment of participants from their services, and provided lab space, equipment and top-up funding. Kids Company had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.Data AvailabilityDue to the clinical nature of the data with high-risk adolescent participants, and our existing ethics arrangements, data cannot be made freely available. However, we are happy to make anonymised data available to appropriate individuals upon request. Please contact Pasco Fearon at p.fearon@ucl.ac.uk.Data AvailabilityDue to the clinical nature of the data with high-risk adolescent participants, and our existing ethics arrangements, data cannot be made freely available. However, we are happy to make anonymised data available to appropriate individuals upon request. Please contact Pasco Fearon at p.fearon@ucl.ac.uk.<sec xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials &amp; Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Participants</title><p>Participants were 80 male adolescents (aged 13–18 years). All participants were initially assessed by charity staff as being ‘at-risk’. To qualify as at-risk, the following criteria must have been met: the individual displayed emotional turmoil, serious risk-taking behaviours, homelessness, criminal behaviour, signs of neglect and/or abuse [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Of these participants, 9 were excluded due to poor EEG data quality. Given that ERP amplitudes are strongly correlated with age, we carefully matched participant ages across the minimal-intervention and extended-intervention groups, excluding 15 participants that could not be age-matched across the groups. This resulted in 32 participants per group.</p><p>All participants in the minimal-intervention group had received less than 4 months intervention (mean = 1.79, SD = 1.55, range = 0–3.87), and all participants in the extended-intervention group had received more than 9 months intervention (mean = 16.57, SD = 8.07, range = 9.4–36.13). For the extended-intervention group, all participants had engaged in the intervention program on a regular basis. Degree of engagement in the program was rated by participants’ key-workers.</p><p>Socio-economic status was determined using a freely available tool from the Office for National Statistics (UK). This tool provides estimates for the percentage of households living in poverty, where poverty is defined as living below 60% median income. The estimates are derived using survey, census and administrative data in order to produce accurate data for small geographic area statistics. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0147357.t001">Table 1</xref>, the minimal-intervention and extended-intervention groups did not differ in age or socio-economic status.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0147357.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147357.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic and behavioural characteristics (mean and standard deviations) for the minimal-intervention and extended-intervention groups (N = 32 per group).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0147357.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0147357.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimal-Intervention</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extended-Intervention</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect size</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.28 (1.23)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.39 (1.27)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.088</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Households in Poverty (%)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.53 (7.87)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.22 (10.13)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.762</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.078</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRYB</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84 (0.49)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (0.47)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.913</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.028</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDQ</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pro-Social Behaviour</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38 (2.01)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.78 (1.74)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.220</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hyperactivity</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88 (2.52)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.97 (2.86)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.890</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.035</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Emotional Symptoms</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78 (1.98)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44 (1.81)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.184</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Conduct Problems</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63 (2.01)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 (2.03)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.503</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Peer Problems</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 (1.61)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38 (1.74)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.057</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" colspan="3" rowspan="1">KW Ratings</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Internalising behaviour</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14 (0.89)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44 (0.72)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.068</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Externalising behaviour</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (0.93)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 (0.91)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.807</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.382</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Life Stressors</italic></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 (0.94)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 (0.92)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.403</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p><italic>Note</italic>: The groups did not differ on any measure except for reduced conduct problems in the minimal-intervention group. Effect sizes using Cohen’s d for independent samples t-tests are shown.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee at University College London (ID: 3064/001). Written, informed consent was provided by all participants, and was also obtained from parents or legal guardians for participants under 16 years of age, but not for participants aged over 16 years. The ethics committee specifically approved these consent procedures. Participants had normal or corrected-to-normal vision, and none had been diagnosed with a developmental disability. All participants were compensated with a £30 shopping voucher.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Intervention</title><p>Psychosocial intervention was independently provided using the key-worker model detailed in the Introduction. Key-workers receive regular, on-going training in attachment theory, therapeutic engagement skills and other areas of clinical practice relevant for at-risk youth (for example, dealing with antisocial behaviour, responding to trauma, improving educational attainment).</p><p>Semi-structured interviews were conducted with each participant’s key-worker to characterise the participants’ initial emotional and behavioural difficulties. In this manner, we aimed to assess how well matched the two groups were prior to intervention. Key-workers were asked whether–prior to intervention–their client had been excluded from school due to poor conduct, had been involved in criminal activity or had experienced a trauma (for example, witnessed or been exposed to violence, physical, emotional or sexual abuse, maltreatment or neglect, bereavement of a close caregiver, raised in foster care). Key-workers were also asked to rate on a three-point scale, the degree to which–prior to intervention–their client exhibited externalising behaviours (for example, extreme aggression, conduct problems), internalising behaviours (for example, anxiety or depression), and whether they had major stressors impacting on their lives (for example, homelessness or extreme poverty). Ten participants in the minimal-intervention group had not yet been assigned to a key-worker. For these participants, assessment case file records were consulted in order to establish the presence or absence of the above intake characteristics. Missing scores were recorded if the case files were inconclusive. Key-workers of extended-intervention clients also described the nature of intervention received by their client and indicated which of the following types of intervention had been received: educational, emotional, housing, legal and/or physical health.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Stimuli &amp; Measures</title><sec id="sec006"><title>Picture Viewing Task</title><p>The task consisted of three blocks of 69 images from the International Affective Picture System (IAPS), which equated to 207 stimuli in total [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In each block, 23 images were pleasant (for example, families, animals), 23 were unpleasant (for example, illness, aggression) and 23 were neutral (for example, household objects, transport). Pleasant images were the following IAPS images: 1441, 1920, 2080, 2154, 2303, 2306, 4007, 4250, 4622, 5210, 5700, 5760, 5780, 5825, 5833, 8080, 8190, 8300, 8370, 8380, 8420, 8490, 8510. Neutral images were the following IAPS images: 1560, 1670, 2032, 2038, 2122, 2271, 2309, 2411, 2487, 2575, 2749, 2880, 5740, 7021, 7036, 7092, 7461, 7476, 7496, 7632, 9210, 9331, 9411. Unpleasant images were the following IAPS images: 2095, 2205, 2345, 2375, 2800, 3180, 3301, 3350, 3500, 3530, 3550, 6313, 9000, 9001, 9050, 9183, 9325, 9421, 9520, 9560, 9901, 9910, 9925.</p><p>Only age-appropriate stimuli were used and images of erotica and mutilation did not form part of the stimulus set. Based on normative adult data, the pleasant images (mean valence = 7.56, SD = 0.48) were higher in valence than the neutral images (mean valence = 5.09, SD = 0.62; <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) and unpleasant images (mean valence = 2.47, SD = 0.38, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001), and the neutral images were higher in valence than the unpleasant images (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). The pleasant (mean arousal = 5.34, SD = 1.23) and unpleasant images (mean arousal = 5.35, SD = 0.83) were rated as more arousing than the neutral images (mean arousal = 3.87, SD = 0.89; <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). Arousal did not differ between the pleasant and unpleasant images (<italic>p</italic> = .967). Although the normative values reflect adult responses, developmental research using the IAPS images has confirmed that children distinguish similarly between pleasant, unpleasant and neutral images [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Following completion of the three passive viewing blocks, participants rated the valence of each image using a 9-point scale. Participants were asked to rate each image for how much pleasure it gave them. To assist with this task, images of sad, neutral and happy faces were positioned above the beginning, middle and end points of the scale respectively.</p><p>Previous work has highlighted that the LPP can be driven by perceptual features of the stimuli, rather than valence or arousal per se [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147357.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0147357.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. We therefore matched images to ensure that any observed differences in the LPP were driven by stimulus meaning and not visual features of the task. The visual complexity of each image was categorised as either simple (figure-ground composition) or complex (scenes with no main focus). Forty-eight per cent of the unpleasant images, 52% of the neutral images, and 35% of the pleasant images were simple compositions. Furthermore, an attempt was made to match the groups of images for the number of images that featured people (78, 70, and 61%, respectively) and animals (10, 13, 10%, respectively).</p><p>Each image was presented once per block in a randomised order. Images were presented in colour on a Dell E2009W monitor and the task was programmed using E-Prime 2.0 software (Psychology Software Tools, Pittsburgh, PA). Images appeared on a black background, 10cm x 12cm in size, for 1000 msec with a variable inter-stimulus interval ranging between 2300–2700 msec. Each image was shown once per block (hence, three times over the entire experiment).</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</title><p>Participants completed the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. This measure is suitable for use in community samples and provides sub-scale scores for pro-social behaviour, hyperactivity, emotional symptoms, conduct problems and peer problems.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Self-Report of Youth Behaviour</title><p>Antisocial behaviour was assessed using this validated questionnaire, which measures the prevalence and recent frequency of delinquent behaviours including vandalism, theft and fraud [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Three additional questions were added to ask about school exclusion, weapon use and police arrests. Based on the guidance from Jessor and Jessor [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], total scores were derived, which take into account whether each behaviour has ever been committed, as well as frequency of the behaviour in the last six months. Higher total scores are indicative of more frequent, recent involvement in criminal activities and/or delinquent behaviour.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec009" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Experimental Procedure</title><p>The participants were administered the IAPS task and self-report questionnaires in one session in a therapy room within a youth centre complex. Using a portable EEG set-up, we were able to conduct these measurements in the community, rather than relying on university or hospital based equipment and testing facilities, which no doubt aided participation in this group of adolescents, who are notoriously difficult to engage in research. During the IAPS task, participants passively viewed images whilst EEG was recorded. Participants were asked to think about how the images made them feel. Blinking was encouraged during the inter-stimulus interval to avoid artifacts contaminating the data. Participants rated the images for pleasantness and completed the two self-report measures after the passive viewing task.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>EEG Acquisition and Pre-processing</title><p>EEG was recorded using the HGSN Electrical Geodesics system. The sampling rate was 250 Hz. An anti-aliasing low-pass filter of 70 Hz was applied during data acquisition. Offline, the data were band-pass filtered between 0.1 and 30 Hz and recomputed to an average reference. The continuous EEG was segmented into epochs between –200 and 2000 ms relative to the onset of each image. Spline interpolation was carried out on individual channels if required. For the minimal-intervention group, the mean percentage and range of interpolated channels was 2.90% (range: 0.78–7.81%). For the extended-intervention group, the mean percentage and range of interpolated channels was 2.83% (range: 0.78–6.25%). Independent component analysis was run using FASTER to remove stereotyped artifacts [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Epochs were excluded from analysis if they met either of the following artifact rejection criteria: voltage deviations exceeded 100μV relative to baseline or the peak to peak moving amplitude exceeded 100μV in a 200msec moving window.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>The two groups were contrasted across each self-report measure using independent-sample t-tests. To confirm that the groups were initially matched for severity of need, key-worker ratings of internalising behaviours, externalising behaviours and life stressors were compared using independent samples t-tests. The proportion of participants who had experienced school exclusion, criminal engagement and trauma were compared across the groups using chi-square tests. Participants’ mean valence ratings for the images were compared using an image valence (pleasant vs. neutral vs. unpleasant) x group (pre- intervention vs. extended-intervention) ANOVA. For all behavioural and ERP analyses, post-hoc contrasts were corrected for multiple comparisons using the Sidak procedure, where required.</p><sec id="sec012"><title>EPN</title><p>Using the same definition as Schupp, Junghöfer, et al. [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], the EPN was defined as the mean amplitude in the window 240-280msec after stimulus onset, in lateral temporo-occipital regions. These data were analysed using an ANOVA with hemisphere (left vs. right) and image valence (pleasant vs. neutral vs. unpleasant) as within-subjects factors and group (minimal-intervention vs. extended-intervention) as the between-subjects factor. The left lateral temporo-occipital region comprised electrodes 56, 63, 64 (P9), 65 (PO7), 66, 68, 69, 70 (O1), 73, 74. The right lateral occipito-temporal region comprised electrodes 82, 83 (O2), 84, 88, 89, 90 (PO8), 94, 95 (P10), 99, 107. All electrode numbers are taken from the Electrical Geodesics sensor net.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>LPP</title><p>Following Hajcak and Dennis [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], mean LPP amplitudes were calculated in parietal-occipital scalp locations. Electrodes used were O1, O2, P3, P4, P7, P8, which correspond to electrodes 70, 83, 52, 92, 58, 96 in the Electrical Geodesics sensor net. Difference topographies confirmed that, in the current study, observed effects were strongest in this same parietal-occipital region. To examine neural processing across time, mean amplitudes were calculated at two consecutive time windows, as per Cuthbert, et al. [<xref rid="pone.0147357.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]: 400-700msec and 700-1000msec. Mean amplitudes in each time window were analysed using a repeated-measures ANOVA, with hemisphere, image valence and group as factors.</p><p>Importantly, none of the ERP effects reported below could result from differences in the number of trials accepted across image valence categories or across groups. For the minimal-intervention group, the mean numbers of accepted epochs (out of a maximum of 69 per category) were 54.94 (unpleasant), 55.03 (neutral) and 52.78 (pleasant). For the extended-intervention group, the mean numbers of accepted epochs were 54.41 (unpleasant), 56.03 (neutral) and 55.66 (unpleasant). An image valence x group ANOVA confirmed that accepted trial counts were statistically equivalent across the valence categories and between the groups (largest <italic>F</italic> = 1.969).</p></sec></sec></sec>We would like to thank all of the participants, schools and Kids Company key workers who took part in this study. We would like to especially thank the following individuals for their assistance with data collection and/or preparing the data for Analysis: Charlotte Bargus, Elizabeth Harding, Jodie Walman and Anna Zonderman.References1PinchamHL, BryceD, PascoFearon R. The neural correlates of emotion processing in juvenile offenders. Developmental Science. 2014doi: 10.1111/desc.12262
254401132SterzerP, StadlerC, KrebsA, KleinschmidtA, PoustkaF. Abnormal neural responses to emotional visual stimuli in adolescents with conduct disorder. Biological Psychiatry. 2005;57(1):7–15. 156072943GaffreyMS, BarchDM, SingerJ, ShenoyR, LubyJL. Disrupted amygdala reactivity in depressed 4-to 6-year-old children. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry. 2013;52(7):737–46.238004874GollanJK, HoxhaD, ChihadeD, PfliegerME, RosebrockL, CacioppoJ. Frontal alpha EEG asymmetry before and after behavioral activation treatment for depression. Biological psychology. 2014;99:198–208. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsycho.2014.03.003
246747085KavianiH, GrayJ, CheckleyS, RavenP, WilsonG, KumariV. Affective modulation of the startle response in depression: influence of the severity of depression, anhedonia, and anxiety. Journal of affective disorders. 2004;83(1):21–31. 155466426FairchildG, Van GoozenSH, StollerySJ, GoodyerIM. Fear conditioning and affective modulation of the startle reflex in male adolescents with early-onset or adolescence-onset conduct disorder and healthy control subjects. Biological Psychiatry. 2008;63(3):279–85. 177652057SebastianCL, McCroryEJ, CecilCA, LockwoodPL, De BritoSA, FontaineNM, et al
Neural Responses to Affective and Cognitive Theory of Mind in Children With Conduct Problems and Varying Levels of Callous-Unemotional TraitsNeural Responses to Affective and Cognitive ToM. Archives of General Psychiatry. 2012;69(8):814–22. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2011.2070
228689358CecilCAM, VidingE, BarkerED, GuineyJ, McCroryEJ. Double disadvantage: The influence of childhood maltreatment and community violence exposure on adolescent mental health. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry. 2014.9ShawDS, ShellebyEC. Early-Starting Conduct Problems: Intersection of Conduct Problems and Poverty. Annual Review of Clinical Psychology. 2014;10.10ShonkoffJP, GarnerAS. Committee on Psychosocial Aspects of Child and Family Health; Committee on Early Childhood, Adoption, and Dependent Care; Section on Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics. The lifelong effects of early childhood adversity and toxic stress. Pediatrics. 2012;129(1):e232–e46. doi: 10.1542/peds.2011-2663
2220115611FairchildG, StobbeY, van GoozenS, CalderAJ, GoodyerIM. Facial expression recognition, fear conditioning, and startle modulation in female subjects with conduct disorder. Biological Psychiatry. 2010;68(3):272–9. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2010.02.019
2044761612PassamontiL, FairchildG, GoodyerIM, HurfordG, HaganCC, RoweJB, et al
Neural abnormalities in early-onset and adolescence-onset conduct disorder. Archives of General Psychiatry. 2010;67(7):729–38. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.75
2060345413van GoozenS, SnoekH, MatthysW, RossumI, EngelandH. Evidence of fearlessness in behaviourally disordered children: a study on startle reflex modulation. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry. 2004;45(4):884–92. 1505631814RaineA, VenablesPH, WilliamsM. Relationships between central and autonomic measures of arousal at age 15 years and criminality at age 24 years. Archives of General Psychiatry. 1990;47(11):1003–7. 224150215JunghöferM, BradleyMM, ElbertTR, LangPJ. Fleeting images: a new look at early emotion discrimination. Psychophysiology. 2001;38(2):175–8. 1134786216SchuppHT, MarkusJ, WeikeAI, HammAO. Emotional facilitation of sensory processing in the visual cortex. Psychological science. 2003;14(1):7–13. 1256474717SchuppHT, ÖhmanA, JunghöferM, WeikeAI, StockburgerJ, HammAO. The facilitated processing of threatening faces: an ERP analysis. Emotion. 2004;4(2):189
1522285518SchuppHT, FlaischT, StockburgerJ, JunghöferM. Emotion and attention: event-related brain potential studies. Progress in brain research. 2006;156:31–51. 1701507319BradleyMM, HambyS, LöwA, LangPJ. Brain potentials in perception: picture complexity and emotional arousal. Psychophysiology. 2007;44(3):364–73. 1743309520CuthbertBN, SchuppHT, BradleyMM, BirbaumerN, LangPJ. Brain potentials in affective picture processing: covariation with autonomic arousal and affective report. Biological psychology. 2000;52(2):95–111. 1069935021NaumannE, BartussekD., DiedrichO., LauferM.E.
Assessing cognitive and affective information processing functions of the brain by means of the late positive complex of the event-related potential. Journal of Psychophysiology. 1992;6(4):285–98.22LangPJ, BradleyMM, CuthbertBN. International affective picture system (IAPS): Technical manual and affective ratings
Gainesville, FL: NIMH Center for the Study of Emotion and Attention, University of Florida; 1997.23LangPJ, BradleyMM, FitzsimmonsJR, CuthbertBN, ScottJD, MoulderB, et al
Emotional arousal and activation of the visual cortex: an fMRI analysis. Psychophysiology. 1998;35(2):199–210. 952994624SchuppHT, JunghöferM, WeikeAI, HammAO. The selective processing of briefly presented affective pictures: An ERP analysis. Psychophysiology. 2004;41(3):441–9. 1510213025LiuY, HuangH, McGinnis-DeweeseM, KeilA, DingM. Neural substrate of the late positive potential in emotional processing. The Journal of Neuroscience. 2012;32(42):14563–72. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3109-12.2012
2307704226GaskellC. Kids Company helps with the whole problem
London: Kids Company; 2008.27Jovchelovitch S, Concha N. Kids Company: a diagnosis of the organisation and its interventions. 2013.28ChoH, HallforsDD, SánchezV. Evaluation of a high school peer group intervention for at-risk youth. Journal of abnormal child psychology. 2005;33(3):363–74. 1595756329MillsRC, DunhamRG, AlpertGP. Working with high-risk youth in prevention and early intervention programs: toward a comprehensive wellness model. Adolescence. 1988.30PodorefskyDL, McDonald-DowdellM, BeardsleeWR. Adaptation of preventive interventions for a low-income, culturally diverse community. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry. 2001;40(8):879–86.1150168631KidsCompany. Key Worker Tool Kit. London: Kids Company; 2010.32LangPJ, BradleyMM, CuthbertBN. International affective picture system (IAPS): Affective ratings of pictures and instruction manual: University of Florida, Gainesville, FL; 2008.33McManisMH, BradleyMM, BergWK, CuthbertBN, LangPJ. Emotional reactions in children: Verbal, physiological, and behavioral responses to affective pictures. Psychophysiology. 2001;38(2):222–31. 1134786834SchuppHT, CuthbertBN, BradleyMM, CacioppoJT, ItoT, LangPJ. Affective picture processing: the late positive potential is modulated by motivational relevance. Psychophysiology. 2000;37(2):257–61. 1073177635WeinbergA, HajcakG. Beyond good and evil: the time-course of neural activity elicited by specific picture content. Emotion. 2010;10(6):767
doi: 10.1037/a0020242
2105884836GoodmanR. The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire: a research note. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry. 1997;38(5):581–6. 925570237OlweusD. Prevalence and incidence in the study of antisocial behavior: definitions and measurements In: KleinMW, editor. Cross-national research in self-reported crime and delinquency. Dordrecht, Netherlands: Kluwer-Nijhoff; 1989 p. 187–201.38JessorR, JessorSL. Problem behavior and psychosocial development: A longitudinal study of youth
New York: Academic Press; 1977.39NolanH, WhelanR, ReillyR. FASTER: Fully Automated Statistical Thresholding for EEG artifact Rejection. Journal of Neuroscience Methods. 2010;192(1):152–62. doi: 10.1016/j.jneumeth.2010.07.015
2065464640HajcakG, DennisTA. Brain potentials during affective picture processing in children. Biological psychology. 2009;80(3):333–8. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsycho.2008.11.006
1910324941De CesareiA, CodispotiM. When does size not matter? Effects of stimulus size on affective modulation. Psychophysiology. 2006;43(2):207–15. 1671259142LewisMD, GranicI, LammC, ZelazoPD, StiebenJ, ToddRM, et al
Changes in the neural bases of emotion regulation associated with clinical improvement in children with behavior problems. Development and psychopathology. 2008;20(03):913–39.1860603843SyngelakiEM, FairchildG, MooreSC, SavageJC, van GoozenSHM. Affective startle potentiation in juvenile offenders: The role of conduct problems and psychopathic traits. Social Neuroscience. 2013;8(2):112–21. doi: 10.1080/17470919.2012.712549
2285645444PastorMC, BradleyMM, LöwA, VersaceF, MoltóJ, LangPJ. Affective picture perception: Emotion, context, and the late positive potential. Brain research. 2008;1189:145–51. 1806815045CodispotiM, FerrariV, BradleyMM. Repetitive picture processing: Autonomic and cortical correlates. Brain research. 2006;1068(1):213–20. 1640347546CodispotiM, FerrariV, BradleyMM. Repetition and event-related potentials: Distinguishing early and late processes in affective picture perception. Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience. 2007;19(4):577–86. 1738124947GainottiG. Emotional behavior and hemispheric side of the lesion. Cortex. 1972;8(1):41–55. 503125848LevyJ, HellerW, BanichMT, BurtonLA. Asymmetry of perception in free viewing of chimeric faces. Brain and cognition. 1983;2(4):404–19. 654603449PreteG, LaengB, FabriM, FoschiN, TommasiL. Right hemisphere or valence hypothesis, or both? The processing of hybrid faces in the intact and callosotomized brain. Neuropsychologia. 2015;68:94–106. doi: 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2015.01.002
2557545150SyngelakiEM, FairchildG, MooreSC, SavageJC, van GoozenSHM. Fearlessness in juvenile offenders is associated with offending rate. Developmental Science. 2013;16(1):84–90. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-7687.2012.01191.x
2327892951BauerLO, HesselbrockVM. P300 decrements in teenagers with conduct problems: implications for substance abuse risk and brain development. Biological Psychiatry. 1999;46(2):263–72. 1041870252GaoY, RaineA, VenablesPH, MednickSA. The Association Between P3 Amplitude at Age 11 and Criminal Offending at Age 23. Journal of Clinical Child &amp; Adolescent Psychology. 2013;42(1):120–30.2296308353HicksBM, BernatE, MaloneSM, IaconoWG, PatrickCJ, KruegerRF, et al
Genes mediate the association between P3 amplitude and externalizing disorders. Psychophysiology. 2007;44(1):98–105. 1724114554IaconoWG, CarlsonSR, MaloneSM, McGueM. P3 event-related potential amplitude and the risk for disinhibitory disorders in adolescent boys. Archives of General Psychiatry. 2002;59(8):750
1215065255NagaVenkatesha Murthy P, GangadharB, JanakiramaiahN, SubbakrishnaD. Normalization of P300 amplitude following treatment in dysthymia. Biological Psychiatry. 1997;42(8):740–3. 932556956ItoTA, CacioppoJT. Electrophysiological evidence of implicit and explicit categorization processes. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology. 2000;36(6):660–76.
