<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Pharmacol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1663-9812</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5838009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.00154</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Associations Between Oxytocin and Trauma in Humans: A Systematic Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Donadon</surname><given-names>Mariana Fortunata</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/465815/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin-Santos</surname><given-names>Rocio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Os&#x000f3;rio</surname><given-names>Fl&#x000e1;via de Lima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/177480/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Neuroscience and Behavior, Medical School of Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto, University of S&#x000e3;o Paulo</institution>, <addr-line>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Psychiatry and Psychology, Hospital Cl&#x000ed;nic, Institut d'Investigacions Biom&#x000e8;diques August Pi i Sunyer (IDIBAPS), Centro de Investigaci&#x000f3;n en Red de Salud Mental (CIBERSAM)</institution>, <addr-line>Barcelona</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Medicine, University of Barcelona</institution>, <addr-line>Barcelona</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Technology Institute for Translational Medicine (INCT), National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq)</institution>, <addr-line>Bras&#x000ed;lia</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Xinhua Qu, Shanghai Ninth People's Hospital, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Marijn Lijffijt, Baylor College of Medicine, United States; Gail A. Alvares, Telethon Kids Institute, Australia</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Fl&#x000e1;via de Lima Os&#x000f3;rio <email xlink:type="simple">flaliosorio@ig.com.br</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Translational Pharmacology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Pharmacology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>154</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Donadon, Martin-Santos and Os&#x000f3;rio.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Donadon, Martin-Santos and Os&#x000f3;rio</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Studies have shown that traumatic experiences may affect hormonal systems mediated by the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and the oxytocinergic system. This effect is the result of long-term impairments in hypothalamic structures and negative feedback mechanisms within the HPA axis, structures that mediate the response to stress. This deregulation reduces the production and release of cortisol and oxytocin (OXT), which may alter stress responses and lead to increased vulnerability to impairments from stressful experiences. The presence of gene polymorphisms might also have an impact on the vulnerability to psychopathology. We made a systematic review of articles dealing with the relationship between OXT and traumatic emotional experiences in humans. Thirty-five studies were reviewed and significant associations between experiences of emotional trauma (ET) and OXT were found. The main results showed that the presence of ET and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is strongly associated with reductions in endogenous OXT, and also that the acute effects of OXT administrations in individuals with ET tend to be anxiolytic only in less severe forms. In victims of recent traumatic experiences (RTE), OXT increased the re-experience of traumas and restored the function of different neural networks associated with fear control/extinction in PTSD patients. The results available also suggest that gene receptor polymorphisms may have a protective function in different outcomes after the experience of traumatic events. We conclude that the relationship between ET and OXT is multifaceted, complex, and mediated by contextual and individual factors. Directions for future studies are suggested considering the gaps in the available literature.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>oxytocin</kwd><kwd>early trauma</kwd><kwd>current trauma</kwd><kwd>PTSD</kwd><kwd>systematic review</kwd><kwd>PRISMA</kwd><kwd>qualitative assessment</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="105"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="12326"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Traumatic and stressful experiences throughout life, whether acute or chronic, may lead to changes in different bodily systems that increase the vulnerability to psychopathology (Meewisse et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; McQuaid et al., <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). One of the most well-known of such changes concerns hormonal systems, including the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis. The HPA axis plays a fundamental role in responding to both external and internal stimuli, including psychological stressors, and is also believed to be implicated in vulnerability to mental illnesses (Heinrichs et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Juruena et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Boyce and Ellis, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Neumann and Landgraf, <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Olff, <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Kuhlman et al., <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p><p>When facing stressful situations, especially during the early stages of development, the HPA axis can be either hypo- or hyperactived, with the possibility of excessive exposure to glucocorticoids and their deleterious effects. These effects can persist throughout the lifespan because as the HPA axis may remain unstable, hypersensitive, or dysfunctional. This contributes to the weakening of the immune system, to increased vulnerability to different physical and mental illnesses, and to the inability to cope with subsequent stressful/traumatic events that may lead to exhaustion of the organism (Mirescu et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Smith and Vale, <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Faravelli et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>Several neurotransmitters and neuropeptides also affect the function of the HPA axis, including oxytocin (OXT). OXT is a neurohormone produced in the hypothalamus by the supraoptic and paraventricular nuclei. It is sent to the posterior pituitary or neurohypophysis and, from there, it is secreted into the bloodstream to produce its effects (Gimpl and Fahrenholz, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). OXT has peripheral and central functions and its action in breastfeeding, childbirth and maternal behavior is well established (Ring et al., <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Yoshida et al., <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Neumann and Landgraf, <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>In addition to these functions, OXT has therapeutic potential associated with the promotion of pro-social behaviors such as increased self-confidence, positive social memories, and affiliative behavior. Furthermore, previous studies have investigated the possibility that the administration of OXT may lead to reductions in anxiety and stress levels (Savaskan et al., <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Guastella et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Rimmele et al., <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Ross and Young, <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Fischer-Shofty et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>Existing evidence suggests that central OXT release contributes to the modulation and maintenance of cortisol levels that favor the rapid return of the body to its pre-stress baseline state (Amico et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Gulpinar and Yegen, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Heinrichs et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) to minimize the response of the HPA axis to psychologically stressful stimuli. However, stressful experiences might also alter the functioning of the suprachiasmatic nucleus, decreasing the synthesis and release of endogenous OXT (Ozbay et al., <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Gonzalez et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Nicolson et al., <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). As result, the negative feedback mechanism of the HPA axis may be affected, leading to hypercortisolemia (Yehuda et al., <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Brown et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). On the behavioral level, the decrease in endogenous OXT levels reduces the multiple pro-social functions of this hormone, thereby reducing coping and resiliency responses (Opacka-Juffry and Mohiyeddini, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Frijling et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p><p>In light of the above findings, the release of exogenous administration of OXT can reduce hormonal and subjective responses to stress, reduce cortisol release in the blood stream, and reestablish bodily homeostasis, therefore placing OXT as a potential therapeutic agent (Cardoso et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Another line of research deals with the role that genetic polymorphisms play in OXT receptor genes, which might alter the individual vulnerability to stress since changes in receptor configuration can reduce or prevent the binding of OXT and its consequent effects in the body (Champagne and Curley, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Skuse and Gallagher, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Unternaehrer et al., <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Bakermans-Kranenburg and van IJzendoorn, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>As seen, a number of recent studies have attempted to provide a detailed understanding of the multiple and complex associations between OXT and different traumatic and stressful situations, whether chronic or acute (Myers et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Seltzer et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Mizushima et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Van Zuiden et al., <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The objective of the current study was to systematically review this literature to highlight the major contributions of the studies conducted to date dealing with the associations between OXT and traumatic emotional experiences in humans.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><p>The guidelines of the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA&#x02014;Moher et al., <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) were adopted as the methodological framework of this study. The electronic databases PsycINFO, PubMed, Scielo, Web of Science, and LILACS were searched without limitations in terms of time, language, or publication date (last search conducted on December 3, 2017). A manual search of the reference lists of the selected articles was also performed. The following keywords were used followed by &#x0201c;AND&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;OR:&#x0201d; oxytocin; PTSD; post-traumatic stress; early trauma; childhood maltreatment; emotional trauma; emotional stress; neglect; adversity; sexual abuse; emotional abuse; and physical abuse.</p><p>Articles that evaluated associations between OXT and the experience of early trauma (ET), recent traumatic experiences (RTE), and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in men and women, regardless of age, were eligible for inclusion. ET experiences were considered as those that occurred before 18 years of age (Bremner et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), and RTEs were considered as those that occurred over the last few days or months (Chatzittofis et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>Studies of endogenous OXT that did not involve participants with ET, RTE, or PTSD; those investigating OXT and psychiatric disorders excluding PTSD; those involving OXT and social behavior, resilience, social cognition, genetic analysis, and the physiological aspects of the HPA axis among participants without ET, RTE, or PTSD; those involving treatment for ET or PTSD but not involving OXT; and animal studies, letters to the editor, case studies, and reviews unrelated to this topic were excluded.</p><p>Two researchers made independent decisions regarding whether to include a study, and divergences in data extraction were discussed until a consensus was reached.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows the search results as well the reasons for article exclusion.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart based on PRISMA/(OXT, Oxytocin; ET, Early trauma; HPA, Hypothalamic Legend Pituitary Adrenal Axis; PTSD, Post traumatic stress disorder; RTE, Recent trauma event).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-g0001"/></fig><p>The methodological quality of the studies was evaluated using the following references: (a) Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies (STROBE; Von Elm et al., <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>); (b) Transparent Reporting of Evaluations with Non-Randomized Designs (TREND; Des Jarlais et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>); and (c) the Revised Recommendations for Improving the Quality of Reports of Parallel-Group Randomized Trials (CONSORT; Moher et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). The quality percentage of each study was calculated by dividing the number of items scored by the total number of items.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 1,244 articles were found, and 35 articles were selected after applying the inclusion and exclusion criteria (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> below presents the main characteristics of the included studies in relation to the samples, outcomes assessment, and methodological quality. For more details, see the Excel dataset in the Supplementary Material (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the studies included in this review.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Author/Year</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study design</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Interest sample</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Comparison sample</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Outcomes assessment</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quality assessment<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>**</sup></xref></bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N/</bold><break/>
<bold>Sex</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age Mean/range</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Type</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Trauma</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N/</bold><break/>
<bold>Sex</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold><break/>
<bold>Mean/range</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Type</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Trauma</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>[OXT]<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>*</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Other variables/</bold><break/>
<bold>Instrument</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Trauma tool</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="13" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>1 - OBSERVATIONAL STUDIES&#x02014;ENDOGENOUS OXYTOCIN</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean: 76.28%</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heim et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-45</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Healthy Institution</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF/EIA kit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opacka-Juffry and Mohiyeddini, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-56</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood /RIA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELS-C, ELS-A, RSLEs</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chatzittofis et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatients<break/> Suicide Attempters</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET+ RTE /Non- RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF/RIA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIVS, Interview</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mohiyeddini et al., <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-56</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood/RIA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELS- C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mizuki and Fujiwara, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31<bold>M</bold><break/> 49<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-48</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine/ASKA kit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frijling et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21<bold>M</bold><break/> 19<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22-59</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Police Personal Clinic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD +<break/> ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20<bold>M</bold><break/> 20<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#x02013;59</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Police officers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE +<break/> ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva/RIA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, SCID<break/> ETI</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mizushima et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<bold>M</bold><break/> 19<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 (2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residential Child Care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14<bold>M</bold><break/> 12<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva/Elisa Kit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSCC, IES-R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nishi et al., <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134<bold>M</bold><break/> 51<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-69</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatients<break/> Intensive care unit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>#</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood/ELISA Kit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IES-R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reijnen et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">907 <bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.38 (8.91)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Military after combat</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET<break/> PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood/ ELISA Kit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETIS-SR,<break/> DSRI</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="13" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>2 - EXPERIMENTAL STUDIES - STRESS REACTIVITY</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean: 87.83%</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pierrehumbert et al., <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre/Post</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13<bold>M</bold> 16<bold>F</bold><break/> 20<bold>M</bold> 26<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.96 (5.86)<break/> 25.08 (4.96)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients/<break/> Health<break/> Healthy/ Cancer<break/> Survivors</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>##</sup></xref>+ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>###</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14<bold>M</bold><break/> 12<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.63 (8.50)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood/RIA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress Test/ TSST-C</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Munro et al., <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre/Post</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 <bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> University Students</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET /<break/> PTSD/Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood/RIA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress Test / Film Protocol</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELS<break/> PCL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seltzer et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre/Post</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17<bold>M</bold><break/> 21<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-11.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltreatment Child<break/> Protective Services</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>###</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18<bold>M</bold><break/> 36<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-11.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heathy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine/RIA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress Test/ TSST-C</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="13" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>3 - CLINICAL TRIALS, RANDOMIZED, DOUBLE-BLIND, PLACEBO-CONTROLLED - EXOGENOUS ADMINISTRATION</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean: 77.04%</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meinlschmidt and Heim, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 <bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20-28</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> University Students</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 <bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20-28</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> University Students</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> intranasal (24UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Cortisol]/saliva<break/> [OXT] Blood</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSRQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grimm et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21-37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21-37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> Intranasal (40UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain activation<break/> Stress test/MIST<break/> [Cortisol]/saliva</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fan et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 <bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21-36</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heathy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> intranasal (24UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain connectivity<break/> Stress test<italic>/</italic> MIST<break/> Anxiety/ STAI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eidelman-Rothman et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 <bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">War Veterans<break/> Israel Defense Force</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">War Veterans<break/> Israel Defense Force</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> intranasal (24 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEG/Brain activation<break/> [OXT]/blood/saliva</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koch et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 <bold>M</bold><break/> 16 <bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Police Personnel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20<bold>M</bold><break/> 20<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heathy<break/> Police officers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> Intranasal (40 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain connectivity<break/> Facial Task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, SCID</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koch et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21<bold>M</bold><break/> 16 <bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18- 65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Police Personnel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20<bold>M</bold><break/> 20<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> Police officers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> intranasal (40 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain activation<break/> Resting State</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, SCID<break/> ETIS-SR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palgi et al., <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23<bold>M</bold><break/> 9 <bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22-60</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Healthy Institute</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<bold>M</bold><break/> 11F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21-59</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> intranasal (24 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compassion task/listen four Recorded Stories</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, SCID</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frijling et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parallel Group</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 <bold>M</bold><break/> 10 <bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Emergency Department</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9<bold>M</bold><break/> 9<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Emergency Department</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. PLA<break/> intranasal (40 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain connectivity<break/> Accident images vs. neutral Images Task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, SCID-IV, PDI, TSQ, ETIS-SR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frijling et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parallel Group</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9<bold>M</bold><break/> 14<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Emergency Department</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8<bold>M</bold><break/> 10<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients/<break/> Emergency Department</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vsPLA<break/> intranasal (40 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain activation<break/> Facial Task/EFMT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, PDI, TSQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nawijn et al., <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 <bold>M</bold><break/> 14 <bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Police<break/> Personnel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<bold>M</bold><break/> 18<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Police officers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT x PLA<break/> Intranasal (40 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain connectivity<break/> PTSD<break/> Task Monetary/MID</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, SCID</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Van Zuiden et al., <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parallel Group</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53<bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trauma<break/> centers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 <bold>F</bold>/<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trauma<break/> centers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT x PLA<break/> intranasal (40 UI)/<break/> 8 days</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression/ HADS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, MNI, IES-R, ETIS-R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sack et al., <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 <bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8 (11.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Psychosomatic Clinic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.08 (8.56)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT x PLA<break/> intranasal<break/> (24 UI)/ 2 weeks</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trauma Script Challenge/ RSDS/ HR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM-IV, SCID</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nawijn et al., <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21<bold>M</bold><break/> 19<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Police Personnel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20<bold>M</bold><break/> 20<bold>F</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Police officers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT x PLA<break/> intranasal (40 UI)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain connectivity<break/> Social incentive delay task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, SCID</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="13" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>4-OBSERVATIONAL STUDIES &#x02013; ASSOCIATION WITH POLYMORPHISMS OXYTOCIN RECEPTOR GENE</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean: 76.27%</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradley et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1347<bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.36 (13.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatients<break/> Primary Care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attachment/APQ<break/> Emotional Deregulation/EDS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTQ, TEI</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cicchetti and Rogosch, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313<bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> Sumer Camp Program</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">282 <bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> Sumer Camp Program</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resilience/PEI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lucas-Thompson and Holman, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">704<bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-101</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/11 Attack</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD/ RTE Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McQuaid et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213<bold>F</bold><break/> 75<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (3.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> University Students</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression/ BDI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hostinar et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263 <bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13-15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltreatment Child Protective Services</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 <bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Int/Ext/ YSR<break/> Social Support/NRI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myers et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306<bold>F</bold> 347<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy<break/> General Population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 139832701<break/> 11131147</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression/<break/> DASS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunn et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205<bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recent Trauma<break/> Hurricane Katrina</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD/ RTE Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576/<break/> 2254298</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTG, IES-R</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dannlowski et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309<bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-59</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fMRI/Brain activation<break/> Facial Task/EFMT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTQ</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tollenaar et al., <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2567<bold>F/M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 2254298/<break/> 53576/<break/> 2268498</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression and Anxiety/ DSM-IV/ CIDI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTQ + Interview</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sippel et al., <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.50(15.51)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">War Veterans</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010<bold>M</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.80(14.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE /No PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXTR 53576</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attachment Style Questionnaire</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM-IV; PLC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p>Technique Used For Measuring and/or Test Kit And Dose And Via Administration;</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>**</label><p>Quality Assessment According To STROBE, CONSORT, and TREND;</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>#</label><p>, Current trauma by motor or vehicle accident;</p></fn><fn id="TN4"><label>##</label><p>, ET by cancer survival in childhood;</p></fn><fn id="TN5"><label>###</label><p><italic>;:ET by physical abuse; APQ, Attachment Prototype Questionnaire; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; CAN, Canada; CAPS, Clinician Administered; CIDI, Composite Interview Diagnostic Instrument; PTSD Scale; CES, Center For Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale; CMQ, Childhood Maltreatment Questionnaire; Cross, Cross Sectional; CSF, Cerebrospinal Fluid; CTQ, Childhood Trauma Questionnaire; DSRI, Dutch Self-rating Inventory; DASS, Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale; DCP, Dependent Children Program; DHS, Department of Human Services; DSRSC, Depression Self Rating Scale For Children; DSM-IV, Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders; EDS, Emotional Deregulation Scale; EFMT, Emotional Face Matching Task; ELS, Early Life Stress Questionnaire; ELS-A, Early Life Stressful Adolescence; ELS-C, Early Life Stressful Experiences In Childhood; EDS, Emotional Dysregulation Scale; ENG, England; EPS, Parental Early Separation; ET, Early Trauma; ETIS, Early Trauma Inventory; ETISR-SF, Early Trauma Inventory Self Report -Short Form; ETI, Early Trauma Inventory; fMRI, Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging; F, Female; GER, Germany; IES, Impact of Event Scale Revised; IN/ EXT, Internalizing/ Externalizing Symptoms; HR, Heart Hate; ISR, Israel; JAN, Japan; KIVS, The Karolinska Interpersonal Violence Scale; MEG, Magnetoencephalography; MID, Monetary Incentive Delay; MIST, Montreal Image Task; NETH, Netherland; M, Male; MINI, Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview; NRI, Network Relationships Inventory; OXT, Oxytocin; PCL, Checklist Civilian Version for DSM-IV; PDI, Peritraumatic Distress Inventory; PDS, Post Traumatic Stress Diagnostic; PEI, Pupil Evaluation Inventory; PG, Parallel Group; PLA, Placebo; PSC, Parental Child Conflict Scale; PTG, Post Traumatic Growth; PTSD, Post Traumatic Stress Disorder; Rsles, Recent Stressful Life Events; RIA, Radioimmunoassay; RSLE, Recent Stressful Life Events; RSDS, Dissociative Symptoms Scale; RTE, Recent traumatic experiences; SCID, Clinical Interview And Structured (DMS-IV); SDS, Social Disability Scale; SSRQ, Standardized Self Report Questionnaire; STAI, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory; SWI, Switzerland; TEI, Traumatic Events Inventory; TSCC, Trauma Symptoms Check List For Children; TSQ, Trauma Screening Questionnaire; TSST-C, Trier Social Stress Test; UI, International Units; USA, United States of America; YSR, Youth SelfReport; [OXT], Oxytocin Concentration Endogenous; 9/11 Attack = terrorist attack USA</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Importantly, regarding the methodological quality evaluation, all of the studies included in this review had at least 64% of their essential items included in the STROBE (observational studies), TREND (experimental studies) or CONSORT [experimental or randomized controlled trials (RCTs)].</p><p>Depending on their designs or objectives, the studies were divided into four distinct groups: (a) observational studies evaluating endogenous OXT levels; (b) experimental studies related to the reactivity of the oxytocinergic system; (c) RCTs of OXT administration and the experience of either ET, RTE, or PTSD; and (d) observational studies investigating the effect of polymorphisms of the OXT receptor gene.</p><p>The major results of each study group are presented below.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(a) Observational studies evaluating endogenous OXT levels.</p></list-item></list><p>The association between endogenous OXT levels and ET situations was evaluated by six studies as a major outcome. Four of these studies found significant correlations between endogenous OXT levels and ET, with values ranging from &#x02212;0.54 to &#x02212;0.23 (Heim et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Opacka-Juffry and Mohiyeddini, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Chatzittofis et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Mohiyeddini et al., <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). On the contrary, Mizushima et al. (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) did not find an association between OXT levels and experiencing ET (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e;0.05; <italic>d</italic> = 0.19; insignificant effect size). Importantly, however, OXT secretions were markedly increased in adolescents who suffered abuse and lived in a stable environment (e.g., a social welfare institution) at the time of the experiment from awakening to bedtime compared with those who had a history of abuse and lived in unstable environments. Mizuki and Fujiwara (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) showed that only less severe forms of ET were associated with increased OXT levels.</p><p>Heim et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) also performed complementary analyses to evaluate the effect of the recurrence of traumatic events. These authors found that experiencing three or more types of traumatic events during childhood was related with reduced endogenous OXT levels, with a moderate effect size (n<sub><italic>p</italic></sub><sup>2</sup> = 0.45). Opacka-Juffry and Mohiyeddini (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) also conducted complementary analyses and found associations between decreased endogenous OXT levels and increased emotional suppression (r = &#x02212;0.30, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) during adulthood.</p><p>Studies that evaluated participants with RTEs failed to find any significant correlations. For example, Opacka-Juffry and Mohiyeddini (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) found that the correlation between OXT and RTE was 0.01 (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). Chatzittofis et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) also failed to find an association between endogenous OXT levels and RTEs (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.30, <italic>p</italic> = 0.18); however, these authors found that endogenous OXT levels were lower in individuals with RTEs who also experienced ET (i.e., were re-victimized) than in those who only experienced trauma during childhood (<italic>p</italic> = 0.04).</p><p>Nishi et al. (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) also failed to find an association between PTSD symptoms and endogenous OXT levels (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.08 to &#x02212;0.00, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.57). However, these authors showed interesting differences between the genders: In women, endogenous OXT levels were positively correlated with cooperativeness (<italic>r</italic> = 0.41, <italic>p</italic> = 0.01), whereas in men these levels were negatively correlated with C-reactive protein (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02212;0.22, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01), which indicates that OXT plays a role in the coping strategies for PTSD symptoms among women.</p><p>The findings of Frijling et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) also indicated gender differences. Regarding endogenous OXT levels in highly traumatized police officers, only men with PTSD showed lower levels of OXT than those without PTSD (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <italic>d</italic> = 0.60; moderate effect size). No differences were observed in women (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; <italic>d</italic> = 0.10; insignificant effect size).</p><p>Finally, a recent study by Reijnen et al. (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) found that pre-deployment OXT levels in soldiers sent to Afghanistan did not predict PTSD development. However, the experience of an ET predicted the development of PTSD, even though no associations were found between OXT levels and the presence/absence of ET in these individuals.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(b) Experimental studies relating to the reactivity of the oxytocinergic system.</p></list-item></list><p>Three studies evaluated OXT levels (reactivity patterns) in acute stressful situations, although these results should be interpreted with caution because of their small sample sizes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Major results of endogenous OXT during experimental studies (reactivity to stress) of participants who experienced trauma (<italic>n</italic> = 3).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Type of stress test</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Results</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>[OXT] situation</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Reactivity to stress</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>r</italic></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>p</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pierrehumbert et al., <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSST-C</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-Stress [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET sexual abuse = ET cancer childhood = control</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-Stress (+20 min) [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET sexual abuse &#x0003c; control</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seltzer et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSST-C</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post- Stress (+ 30 min) [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02640; ET physical abuse &#x0003e; &#x02640; control</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02642; ET physical abuse = &#x02642; control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Munro et al., <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Film Protocol (Abandonment and Bond scenes)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bonding [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basal &#x02192; Bonding = no alterations Dissociation symptoms x higher levels [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39<break/> 0.018<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Somatization symptoms x higher levels [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abandonment [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basal &#x02192; Abandonment = &#x02193;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD x lower levels [OXT]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>[OXT], oxytocin; ET, Early trauma; PTSD, Post-traumatic stress disorder; &#x02642;, Men; &#x02640;, Women; TSST-C, Trier Social Stress Test; &#x0003c; Minor; &#x0003e; Major</p><fn id="TN6"><label>*</label><p><italic>Difference statistically significant</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Girls who experienced physical abuse during childhood showed increased reactivity to stress. In other words, they presented with higher levels of endogenous OXT after undergoing an acute stress test (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02), whereas OXT levels in boys with and without a history of physical abuse did not change after stress induction (Seltzer et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). On the other hand, adults with a history of sexual abuse (regardless of gender) showed decreasing OXT levels after acute stress (Pierrehumbert et al., <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>Munro et al. (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) also found a decrease in OXT levels after exposure to abandonment scenes (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01) but not after exposure to bonding scenes (<italic>p</italic> = 0.39). However, associations were observed between increased OXT levels and increased dissociative, somatic, and attachment symptoms during bonding scenes as well as between decreased OXT levels and PTSD symptoms during abandonment scenes.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(c) RCTs of OXT administration and trauma.</p></list-item></list><p>The results of these trials were grouped by the type of trauma experienced and are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Major results of RCTs that administered OXT to participants who experienced early or current trauma <italic>(N</italic> = 13).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Outcomes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Main results</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Treatment</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Comparison groups</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Brain activation/ Connectivity/[cortisol]/ Symptomatology results</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(1) EARLY TRAUMA</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meinlschmidt and Heim, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[Cortisol]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. Placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET / Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attenuated the <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/> [cortisol] after OTX in subjects with ET</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grimm et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain activation<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Voxel wise<break/> MIST (Stress task)<break/> [Cortisol]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT<break/> OXT vs. placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET vs. Non-ET<break/> Non-ET<break/> ET<break/> ET vs. Non-ET<break/> Non-ET<break/> ET<break/> ET<break/> Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Activation left hippocampus and dorsomedial thalamus <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>[cortisol] after stress task <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> [cortisol] after stress task <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Activation at right insula, anterior ACC, PCC, left parahippocampal gyrus<break/> No effect on the [cortisol] after stress task <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> [cortisol] after stress task <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/><bold>Hormonal limbic reactivity</bold> (pgACC, left amygdala, left parahippocampal gyrus, left insula, bilateral putamen and bilateral caudate), during the stress test <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/>
<bold>Hormonal limbic reactivity</bold> (pgACC, left amygdala, left parahippocampal gyrus, left insula, bilateral putamen and bilateral caudate), during the stress test</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fan et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain connectivity<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Voxel/<break/> wise<break/> Seed/based approach<break/> Resting state<break/> MIST (Stress task)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT<break/> OXT x ET<break/> Placebo<break/> OXT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>(severity)ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref>
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>(severity)ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref>
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>(severity)ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref><break/> ET <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref> &#x00026; pgACC-amygdala rs/FC <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref> &#x00026; an increased pgACC-amygdala rs/FC <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref> &#x00026; an increased pgACC-amygdala rs/FC <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref>
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> ET<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>*</sup></xref>
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Resting state</bold>
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> pgACC-amygdala rs/FC<break/> It was not significant effect of OXT<break/> It was no significant effect of OXT &#x00026; ET interaction<break/>
<bold>Psychosocial Stress</bold><break/> Correlated with state anxiety, that correlate with [cortisol]<break/> Negatively predicted anxiety<break/> Predicted stronger pgACC deactivation during stress<break/> Predicted weaker pgACC deactivation<break/> Attenuated rest-task interaction between pgACC-amygdala rs/FC and pgACC deactivation</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(2) CURRENT TRAUMA</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frijling et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain connectivity<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Voxel/bold<break/> Accident images vs. Neutral images Task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT<break/> OXT vs. Placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE<break/> RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Connectivity left amygdala and PFC for trauma images vs. neutral images <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Connectivity left amygdala and PFC for trauma images vs. neutral images <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Amygdala connectivity to the left insula for trauma images vs. neutral images <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Amygdala connectivity vmPFC for trauma images vs. neutral images <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Flashbacks of memory during accident images</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frijling et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain activation<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Voxel/bold<break/> Facial task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. Placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>BL amygdala activation for fearful faces &#x02642; <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/> Left amygdala to neutral faces</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Van Zuiden et al., <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD symptoms</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>High PTSD symptoms</bold><break/>
<bold>Low PTSD symptoms</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT &#x0003c; Placebo<break/> OXT = Placebo</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(3) PTSD</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eidelman-Rothman et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEG<break/> Frequency/Hz<break/> Alpha Resting State activation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD vs. Non-PTSD<break/> PTSD vs. Non-PTSD<break/> PTSD and Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>&#x003b1; resting-state activity in left dPFC, SFG and MFG <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> &#x003b1; resting-state activity in left SFG e MFG <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>&#x003b1; resting-state activity in left SFG and MFG correlated with re-experience symptoms</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palgi et al., <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compassion task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT vs. placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Compassion toward women protagonist<break/> No effect on compassion toward masculine protagonist</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koch et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain activation<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Voxel/bold<break/> Facial task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT<break/> OXT vs. placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD<break/> RTE<break/> PTSD<break/> RTE<break/> RTE<break/> PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valence-dependent amygdala reactivity was absent for the left amygdala <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Reactivity of amygdala to fearful-angry faces compared with happy -neutral faces <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Reactivity of left amygdala all emotions <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Increased reactivity of the left amygdala <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Activation of left amygdala for all emotions <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Activation of left amygdala</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koch et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain connectivity<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Voxel/bold<break/> Resting State</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02642;PTSD vs. &#x02642; RTE<break/> &#x02640;PTSD vs. &#x02640; RTE<break/> &#x02642;PTSD vs. &#x02642; RTE<break/> &#x02640;PTSD vs. &#x02640; RTE<break/> PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Connectivity right CeM amygdala to left vmPFC <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Connectivity right BLA to bilateral dACC <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Connectivity right CeM to left vmPFC <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Connectivity right BLA to right dACC <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Anxiety and nervousness but not happiness and sadness</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nawijn et al., <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain activation<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Voxel/bold<break/> Task/Monetary</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT vs. placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD and RTE Non-PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Reaction time on MID task for reward/loss vs. neutral trials <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Brain activation at ventral striatum, amygdala, insula, CPF orbitofrontal <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Brain activation at right striatum, dACC, and insula during reward and loss</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sack et al., <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trauma Script Challenge</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OXT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> reduced avoidance symptoms<break/> No effect on re-experiencing and dissociative symptoms <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Heart rate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nawijn et al., <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain activation<break/> fMRI/ 3T<break/> Social Task</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo<break/> OXT<break/> OXT vs. Placebo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD vs. RTE Non-PTSD<break/> PTSD vs. RTE Non-PTSD<break/> PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0002.jpg"/> Activation insula anterior left during social incentive <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Activation bilateral putamen, right dACC and right insula during social incentive <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Activation right Putamen during social incentive <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-i0001.jpg"/>Activation left striatum; right striatum and insula, and right dorsal ACC</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN11"><label>*</label><p><italic>Early trauma of emotional abuse; &#x003b1;, alpha; ACC, Anterior cingulate cortex; BLA, Amygdala basolateral; BL, Basolateral; CeM, central medial amygdala; CAPS, Clinician-administered PTSD Scale; DMPFC, Dorsomedial pre-frontal cortex; dACC, Dorsal anterior cingulate cortex; dPFC, Dorsolateral pre-frontal cortex; MFG, Middle frontal gyrus; MEG, Magnetoencephalography; MID, Monetary incentive delay task; MIST, Montreal Image Task; PTSD, Post traumatic stress disorder; OXT, Oxytocin; rs/FC, resting state/ functional connectivity; VmPFC, Ventral medial pre frontal cortex; VlPFC, Ventral lateral pre frontal cortex; SFG, Superior frontal gyrus; MFG, Middle frontal gyrus; ET, Early trauma; [Cortisol], concentration of cortisol; fMRI, Functional magnetic resonance imaging; pgACC, Pregenual cortex cingulate anterior; RTE, Recent traumatic experiences; SPG, superior frontal gyrus; sgACC, Subgenual anterior cingulate cortex</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Three studies evaluated participants with just ET. In the first, Meinlschmidt and Heim (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) measured endogenous cortisol and demonstrated that intranasal OXT attenuated the cortisol decrease in participants with ET compared with controls, suggesting the presence of amortization effects related to HPA-axis activities. In the other two studies, participants with ET were assessed in the context of a psychosocial stress situation, and the results indicated that negative outcomes were associated with acute OXT administration.</p><p>In one of these studies, Grimm et al. (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) found that participants with ET, regardless of severity, presented with greater hormonal and limbic reactivity after the use of OXT. However, Fan et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) found that the activation of the connectivity between the amygdala and the pregenual anterior cingulate cortex (pgACC) during stress was only attenuated by OXT in individuals with less severe ET. The use of OXT did not favor this anxiolytic effect in patients with moderate-to-severe ET.</p><p>Two studies by Frijling et al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) reported the adverse effects of exogenous OXT administration in individuals with RTEs. In one such study (Frijling et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>), OXT administration during threatening situations reduced the functional connectivity between the left amygdala and the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex (vlPFC) as well as between the amygdala and the ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) circuits responsible for cognitive-emotional regulation and fear extinction. These findings were also accompanied by an increased connectivity between the amygdala and the insula as well as increased episodes of traumatic flashbacks. In the other study (Frijling et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref>), increased amygdala reactivity was elicited by fearful faces, indicating that OXT favors an increase in the processing of fear salience and, consequently, anxiogenic effects.</p><p>A single study administered OXT for eight subsequent days and showed that it did not attenuate PTSD symptoms in the short term (45 days). However, only participants with high symptom severity reported improvement after 6 months, which suggests that OXT may has a protective effect in the long term which is mediated by symptom severity (Van Zuiden et al., <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In this study, as well as at Fan et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), it is evident the influence of the severity of experience/symptoms of trauma.</p><p>Contrary to the effects observed in subjects with RTE, in those with a PTSD installed, the related effects to acute OXT administration were favorable. Eidelman-Rothman et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) examined veterans with PTSD and showed that OXT normalized the resting-state brain functioning of these individuals, which was similar to those of controls (i.e., veterans not exposed to trauma). Prior to exogenous OXT administration, an increase in resting-state alpha activity was observed in the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (dPFC), especially in the superior frontal gyrus (SFG) and middle frontal gyrus (MFG). These regions are associated with memory and cognitive control, which are important for emotional control.</p><p>Koch et al. (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>,<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) and Nawijn et al. (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) examined the same sample of participants (i.e., trauma-exposed police officers with or without PTSD), in different paradigms outcomes and showed positive effects during acute OXT administration. In a resting state paradigm the acute OXT effects were different between genders. In men with PTSD, OXT decreased subjective anxiety and nervousness as well as restored the connectivity between right amygdala (CeM) and the left vmPFC. In women, OXT restored the connectivity between the right basolateral amygdala (BLA) and the anterior cingulate dorsal cortex (dACC), which decreased the anxiety and fear expression originating from the amygdala (Koch et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref>). In an emotional face-matching task, the acute effects of OXT in subjects with PTSD were the same, regardless of gender: OXT reduced amygdala reactivity to all emotional expressions. In those without RTE, however, reactivity was increased, which indicates the presence of the anxiolytic effects of OXT only in trauma-exposed individuals who develop PTSD (i.e., an interdependence of inter-individual factors; Koch et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>). During a monetary task, OXT increases neural responses during anticipation of reward or loss in key regions of the brain's reward circuit (i.e., the striatum, dACC, and insula) and decreases motivational anhedonia. These effects were positively associated with those of OXT in the ventral striatum (Nawijn et al., <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Similarly, during a social incentive delay task, the administration of OXT normalized the aberrant insula response and increased the putamen response, indicating increased neural sensitivity to social reward (Nawijn et al., <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Finally, it was observed as positive effects related to OXT, an increase in compassion toward women with PTSD (Palgi et al., <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and a decrease in the avoidance symptoms during trauma script exposure (Sack et al., <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(d) Observational studies investigating the effect of the polymorphisms of the OXT receptor gene.</p></list-item></list><p>The major polymorphism studied was OXTR rs53576, which was evaluated in 88.8% of the included studies. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> shows the main results found.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Main results of the association studies of early or current trauma with regard to OXT receptor gene polymorphisms (<italic>N</italic> = 10).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Phenotype</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Results genetic association with ET, RTE and PTSD</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Statistics</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Effect size</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>POLYMORPHISM OXTR rs53576</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bradley et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional deregulation Problematic attachment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 ET or more Non-ET ET Non-ET</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG &#x0003e; AA/AG GG = AA/AG GG &#x0003e; AA/AG GG = AA/AG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001 0.49 0.02 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>d</italic> = &#x02212;0.052</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cicchetti and Rogosch, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resilience</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET+AA/AG ET+GG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x0003c;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-ET +AA/AG Non-ET +GG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.01 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n<italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.083 n<italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lucas-Thompson and Holman, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD symptoms</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>*</sup></xref>+GG RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>*</sup></xref>+GA/AA RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>**</sup></xref>+GG RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>**</sup></xref>+GA/AA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; = &#x0003e; &#x0003e;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>*</sup></xref>+GG Non-RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>*</sup></xref>+GA/AA Non-RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>**</sup></xref>+GG Non-RTE<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>**</sup></xref>+GA/AA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.01 0.12 &#x0003c; 0.01 &#x0003c; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McQuaid et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression symptoms</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low ET+GG/GA High ET+GG/GA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= &#x0003e;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low ET+AA High ET+AA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 &#x0003c; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hostinar et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perception of social support Internalizing behavioral problems Externalizing behavioral problems</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET+GG Non-ET+GG ET+GG ET+GG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; = &#x0003e; =</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET+GA/AA Non-ET+GA/AA ET +AA/AG ET +AA/AG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 0.35 0.01 0.11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n<italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.02 n<italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunn et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD symptoms PTSD development</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG = AG = AA GG = AG = AA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dannlowski et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral striatum gray matter volume Enhanced activation of amygdala to positive and negative emotional</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET+GG Non-ET+GG/GA ET/Non-ET+GG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; &#x0003e; &#x0003e;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA AA ET/Non-ET+ AA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.01 &#x0003e;0.05 &#x0003c; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tollenaar et al., <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression symptoms Anxiety symptoms</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG = AG = AA GG = AG = AA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.90 &#x0003e;0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sippel et al., <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insecure attachment style</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">A allele + insecure attachment = risk factor for PTSD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>POLYMORPHISM OXTR rs2254298</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunn et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD symptoms</td><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">RTE+GG&#x000a0; = &#x000a0;RTE+AG&#x000a0; = &#x000a0;RTE+AA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD development</td><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">RTE+GG&#x000a0; = &#x000a0;RTE+AG&#x000a0; = &#x000a0;RTE+AA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>POLYMORPHISM OXTR rs2254298</bold> + <bold>rs2268498</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tollenaar et al., <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression Symptoms Anxiety Symptoms</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET/Non-ET</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG = AG = AA GG = AG = AA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.08 &#x0003e;0.21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013; &#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>POLYMORPHISM OXTR rs139832701</bold> + <bold>rs11131147</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myers et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression symptoms Stress symptoms</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ET &#x0003e;Non-ET ET &#x0003e;Non-ET</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004 0.0016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN8"><label>*</label><p>Recent traumatic experiences by economic stress;</p></fn><fn id="TN9"><label>**</label><p><italic>Recent traumatic experiences by negative environment; A, A allele; d, Cohen's d; ET, early trauma; G, G allele; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, partial eta squared; PTSD, post-traumatic stress disorder; p, level of significance; Non-ET, absence of early trauma; RTE, Recent traumatic experiences</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Regarding the results linked to the OXTR rs53576 gene polymorphism, participants who exhibited the GG genotype and experienced ET, PTSD, or both reported a series of impairments including emotional dysregulation and problematic attachment (Bradley et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), PTSD symptoms (Lucas-Thompson and Holman, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), symptoms of depression (McQuaid et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), lower levels of perceived social support, and internalized behavioral problems (Hostinar et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Using structural magnetic resonance, Dannlowski et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) showed that the presence of the G allele (GG/GA) was associated with increased amygdala responsiveness to all emotional facial expressions (negative and positive), constituting a higher vulnerability to alterations in the limbic brain structure in individuals with ET. Furthermore, a negative correlation was found between ventral striatum gray matter volume and participants with ET and the GG genotype.</p><p>Cicchetti and Rogosch (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) showed that the presence of ET and the AA/AG genotype was associated with increased resiliency; therefore, the presence of the AA/AG genotype appears to have a protective function. On the other hand, Tollenaar et al. (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) indicated that the OXTR53576 gene polymorphism does not interact with ET and predict risk factor and/or vulnerability toward the development of depression or anxiety. In addition, Sippel et al. (<xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) found that the presence of a minor allele associated with an insecure attachment style was associated with a higher prevalence of PTSD among war veterans.</p><p>Other polymorphisms studied included OXTR rs2254298 and rs2268498, but neither Dunn et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) nor Tollenaar et al. (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) found changes or association among the presence of ET or PTSD, a single nucleotide polymorphism, and the development of symptoms. In addition, Dunn et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) investigated the role of rs53576 and did not find a difference between the presence of the AA allele and the AG or GG alleles as risk factors for the development of PTSD or its symptoms.</p><p>Finally, one study evaluated the polymorphisms OXTR rs139832701 and rs11131147. This study showed that participants who experienced ET and had these polymorphisms exhibited higher levels of depression and more symptoms of stress (Myers et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present review revealed associations between traumatic experiences in humans and the neuropeptide OXT that involve polymorphisms on OXT receptor genes. These associations are multiple and complex and are mediated by contextual and inter-individual factors. A stronger association with OXT was found with regard to the experience of early or chronic trauma as well as with recurrent, severe, or intense traumatic events. Regarding RTEs, the association was strong among individuals who developed psychopathological conditions (e.g., PTSD).</p><p>The findings of the group of studies that evaluated endogenous OXT levels showed a moderate association between reduced OXT levels and the experience of trauma. This finding supports the hypothesis that early adversity persistently, even up to adulthood, alters the functioning of the suprachiasmatic nucleus, which is responsible for the production and release of OXT (Ozbay et al., <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Gonzalez et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Nicolson et al., <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Goldman-Mellor et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). This change might favor vulnerability to stress during adulthood and impair the social functioning associated with OXT. Moreover, it might reduce coping and resiliency responses (Opacka-Juffry and Mohiyeddini, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Frijling et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Interestingly, Munro et al. (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) showed that an increase in endogenous OXT was associated with symptoms of social detachment, which might not always result in favorable outcomes (Seng, <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>However, an increase in endogenous OXT occurred in participants with ET and specific conditions such as less severe forms of ET and social environmental change (from a threatening environment to a protective environment with the establishment of stable social relationships). This finding shows the role of OXT in the development and maintenance of resiliency (Elzinga et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Carpenter et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Heim et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Authors such as Mizuki and Fujiwara (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and Mizushima et al. (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) suggested that an increase in OXT occurs as a response to social stress, thereby promoting the regulation of the oxytocinergic system and an increase in pro-social behaviors under challenging and less unfavorable situations. These findings also reinforce Veenema (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) views concerning the high plasticity of the oxytocinergic system and its dependence on social cues.</p><p>Studies have indicated the mediating role that other variables play in traumatic situations during adulthood because OXT is reduced only in subjects with ET and/or PTSD, demonstrating decreased resiliency responses. It has also been suggested that stress affects the oxytocinergic system in a sex-dependent manner (see especially Nishi et al., <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), which has been extensively documented in animals (Ebner et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Cameron et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p><p>The studies related to stress reactivity have also shown gender dependence because only women with a history of physical abuse show increased OXT secretion under acute stress (Seltzer et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). When gender was not experimentally controlled, a decrease in OXT secretion was observed (Munro et al., <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Previous studies have shown that men and women differ with regard to the release of endogenous OXT following behavioral paradigms. They also differ behaviorally after exogenous OXT administration (Finkelhor et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Heim et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Seng et al., <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Feng et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Koch et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>,<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>).</p><p>One possible explanation of the above gender effects might involve the biochemical differences in the number of available OXT receptors between men and women as well as the binding affinity of these receptors in specific neural networks (Uhl-Bronner et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Hoge et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Furthermore, the different phases of the menstrual cycle can also influence OXT levels as well as the HPA axis, conferring more or less impairment (Altemus et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). This effect is seen because of the role of estrogen, which regulates the production of OXT receptors and the possible release of this hormone (Williams et al., <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>; Wigger and Neumann, <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). In contrast, evidence also shows that androgens inhibit OXT release under stress (Young et al., <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). According to Taylor et al. (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), OXT might also favor the &#x0201c;tend and befriend&#x0201d; response in women and the &#x0201c;fight or flight&#x0201d; response in men.</p><p>The results of the studies that focused on exogenous OXT administration varied by the type of stressor. Regarding ET, the effect of this stressor on the functioning of the brain circuits was demonstrated. ET favored functional changes in the brain circuits, especially those associated with limbic regions (e.g., the hypothalamus, pgACC, amygdala, and parahippocampal gyrus), which are HPA axis-modulating regions. In this sense, OXT modulates the neural networks to favor an improved response to stress (Meinlschmidt and Heim, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p><p>Other studies that examined severe ET, however, seemed to show a null or differential response to exogenous OXT administration that assumes anxiogenic characteristics. This effect might occur because of previous changes in the oxytocinergic circuit as a consequence of the traumatic experience or because of unregulated interactions between the oxytocinergic system and the other neurotransmitter systems (Fan et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Grimm et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>The effects of exogenous OXT in individuals with RTE at risk for PTSD were unfavorable because they tended to promote anxiogenic effects and did not reduce the risk of developing different pathologies, including PTSD. The results generally showed that OXT favors fear-related responses; this fact is also an accepted finding in studies conducted with healthy participants (Domes et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>The above inconsistency can be understood in light of Heinrichs et al. (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). These authors argue that OXT can produce an extinction effect on aversive memories among healthy participants, depending on the test type used and the relevance of the stimuli to the evaluated patient. According to their findings and the previous literature (Kirsch et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Domes et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Gamer et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), the effects of OXT on amygdala reactivity might differ not only because of inter-individual factors such as gender and level of psychopathology but also because of the context (i.e., the emotional content/valence of the stimulus).</p><p>The increased number of flashbacks suggests that the administration of OXT in individuals who experienced recent trauma impedes the functioning of the emotional regulation network in response to exposure to situations reminiscent of the trauma. This finding is contrary to the previous literature (Koch et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref>; Sack et al., <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) showing the potential role that OXT plays in the extinction of traumatic memories. In previous studies, postpartum women (i.e., those with increased OXT production) experience temporary deficits in memory that contribute to the extinction of the aversive memories associated with childbirth (Brindle et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Brett and Baxendale, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>).</p><p>On the other hand, the continuous use of OXT for 8 days had positive effects only for individuals with severe symptoms/traumas, again suggesting an interdependence of inter-individual variables. Thus, the studies of the use of OXT to prevent PTSD suggest the need for caution because of the possible negative/anxiogenic effects on the one hand and the presence of benefits resulting from OXT administration that occur selectively only in highly symptomatic individuals on the other.</p><p>Finally, for individuals with PTSD, the effects of acute OXT administration were favorable. Considering that PTSD is associated with hyperactivity in the amygdala and other limbic brain structures when presented with negative emotional stimuli (Brunetti et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Frijling, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), OXT favored the reestablishment of the functioning of different neural networks associated with fear control and extinction responses, thereby favoring better emotional control and cognitive performance through the reduction of hypervigilance, avoidance, anhedonia, and emotional salience to fear.</p><p>Importantly, these studies showed weak effects for the control groups that were composed mostly of participants with RTEs (i.e., those exposed to trauma but without PTSD). This result reinforces the findings of the previous group of studies that indicated the lack of benefits for this specific sample. These data also reinforce the positions of Koch et al. (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>,<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>) and Bartz et al. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) who argued that OXT is beneficial only for individuals with impaired fear regulation and social functioning. However, Palgi et al. (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) examined participants exposed to trauma, with or without PTSD, and found that they benefited from the administration of OXT in terms of their compassion response.</p><p>Regarding the studies related to the different polymorphisms, the present review suggested that variations and polymorphisms are intrinsically associated with the changes in the stress resilience mechanism and the experience of traumatic experiences (Cicchetti and Rogosch, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). One possible explanation is that individuals with polymorphic variations in the OXT receptor gene due to random changes in the position of the amino acids are more vulnerable to the development of disorders resulting from traumatic experiences throughout the lifespan (Feldman et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>The genetic polymorphisms that showed more damage were those associated with the GG genotype at the OXT genetic receptors rs53576, rs139832701, and rs11131147. These genetic variations might alter receptor configuration and develop changes at density, alter the number of receptors available in the central nervous system (Champagne and Curley, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Skuse and Gallagher, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), and might develop alterations on OXT binding affinity to the receptor, thereby altering the effects/functions of OXT in the body.</p><p>Interestingly, Dannlowski et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) found that the presence of the GG genotype allied with ET might increase the vulnerability to the greater activation of limbic areas during the visualization of positive/negative faces; however, these authors indicated that such a vulnerability would also depend on environmental experiences and the complex interaction between genes and environment. Therefore, stable environments should provide more positive signals and lead to beneficial development, whereas threatening environments should result in detrimental effects on emotional development and lead to vulnerability to psychiatric disorders.</p><p>Champagne and Curley (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) also suggested that participants exposed to stressful environments undergo DNA methylation processes that modify the positions of nitrogenous bases, thereby resulting in the modification of certain gene expression. Therefore, the binding affinity of OXT to the receptor might be altered, thereby reducing the amount of bound OXT and leading to a reduction in the function of OXT in the organism. This effect would alter the individual's vulnerability to the effects of stress (Jack et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>On the other hand, one study (Sippel et al., <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) indicated that polymorphisms on the OXTR rs53576 receptor gene with the presence of a single A' allele might contribute to the formation of insecure attachments among individuals with PTSD. This finding is relevant because this attachment style is associated with a reduced response to PTSD treatment. Such dysfunction might translate into a neural mechanism that could predispose individuals to negative assessments of their social environment stimuli, which might compromise the stress-reducing effects of social support and exacerbate the effect of cognitive representations of relationships as threatening, mistrustful, or unstable.</p><p>Finally, the other genetic polymorphisms (OXTR rs2254298 and rs2268498) had no effect on PTSD symptoms or their development (Dunn et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) nor on the depression or anxiety symptoms of participants with ET (Tollenaar et al., <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). One possible explanation is that the participants were recruited from a specific population of low-income non-Hispanics blacks who were exposed to Hurricane Katrina (Dunn et al. 2014) or healthy participants with ET (Tollenaar et al., <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Large samples are required for candidate gene studies.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>This systematic review regarding the relationship between OXT and emotional trauma in humans revealed that reductions in endogenous OXT levels are more strongly associated with the presence of severe and recurrent ET and PTSD.</p><p>The results also show that the acute effect of OXT in victims of ET tends to be anxiolytic, but only in those with less severe forms of ET. Among individuals with severe ET, OXT does not seem to have anxiolytic properties and may even increase anxiety. The same holds true for victims of RTE, since OXT has been reported to increase the re-experience of traumatic symptoms. In patients with PTSD, OXT reestablished the function of different neural networks associated with fear control and extinction.</p><p>Genetic studies showed that the presence of the GG genotype in the OXTR rs53576 gene polymorphism associated with the experience of ET or PTSD is related to more negative outcomes, whereas the presence of the AA genotype appears to have a protective role.</p><p>It should be noted that the relationship between OXT and traumatic situations is mediated by different contextual and inter-individual variables that might predict more or less favorable outcomes. Thus, a stable environment, less severe forms of trauma, and the female gender are associated with resiliency responses.</p><p>The studies included in the review have limitations that call for caution in the interpretation and generalization of their findings, including (a) small sample sizes recruited from extremely specific contexts; (b) poor control of confounding variables such as gender and ET severity; (c) highly variable age groups; (d) cross-sectional designs; (e) possible differences between chronic and acute administration of OXT in RCT; and (f) lack of evaluation of both central and peripheral levels of OXT to determine whether differences exist [most of the studies on this topic assessed endogenous levels in peripheral fluids (e.g., blood plasma, urine, saliva) and the methodological validity of these techniques is controversial (Wotjak et al., <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Seltzer et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Valstad et al., <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)].</p><p>For future studies, we suggest the adoption of longitudinal designs to establish causal relationships; the recruitment of large samples to control for gender, age, and sex hormones; the conduction of RCTs with chronic and/or prolonged administration of OXT; the investigation of other polymorphisms that might interfere with or contribute to increased susceptibility to the harmful effects of traumatic experiences; and the performance of epigenetic investigations on the association between ET, RTE, and PTSD with OXT.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors listed have made a substantial, direct and intellectual contribution to the work, and approved it for publication.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The National Council for Technological and Scientific Development (CNPq grant numbers 2015/12548-6 and 301321/2016-7), the Spanish Biomedical Research Networking Center for Mental Health (CIBERSAM), and the Comission at per a Universitats i Recerca del DIUE, Generalitat de Catalunya, Spain (grant number 2014SGR1435) supported this study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2018.00154/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2018.00154/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="DataSheet1.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altemus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galliven</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deuster</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Increased vasopressin and adrenocorticotropin responses to stress in the midluteal phase of the menstrual cycle</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metabol.</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>2525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2530</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jcem.86.6.7596</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11397850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11397850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amico</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantella</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Anxiety and stress responses in female oxytocin deficient mice</article-title>. <source>J. Neuroendocrinol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>324</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0953-8194.2004.01161.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15089969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15089969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakermans-Kranenburg</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van IJzendoorn</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>A sociability gene? Meta-analysis of oxytocin receptor genotype effects in humans</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr. Genet.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/YPG.0b013e3283643684</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23921259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23921259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartz</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollander</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>N. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolevzon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin selectively improves empathic accuracy</article-title>. <source>Psychol. Sci.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1426</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1428</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956797610383439</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20855907?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20855907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Biological sensitivity to context: I. An evolutionary&#x02013;developmental theory of the origins and functions of stress reactivity</article-title>. <source>Dev. Psychopathol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0954579405050145</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16761546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16761546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jovanovic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Association between childhood maltreatment and adult emotional dysregulation in a low-income, urban, African American sample: moderation by oxytocin receptor gene</article-title>. <source>Dev. Psychopathol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>452</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0954579411000162</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23786688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23786688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermetten</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazure</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Development and preliminary psychometric properties of an instrument for the measurement of childhood trauma: the early trauma inventory</article-title>. <source>Depress Anxiety</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1520-6394(2000)12:1&#x0003c;1::AID-DA1&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-W</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10999240?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10999240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxendale</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Motherhood and memory: a review</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4530(01)00003-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11259856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11259856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Objective and subjective memory impairment in pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Psychol. Med.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>653</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291700022285</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1946853?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1946853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenbogen</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A meta-analytic review of the correlation between peripheral oxytocin and cortisol concentrations</article-title>. <source>Front. Neuroendocrinol.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yfrne.2016.11.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27836673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27836673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepede</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mingoia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Catani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Elevated response of human amygdala to neutral stimuli in mild post traumatic stress disorder: neural correlates of generalized emotional response</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>168</volume>, <fpage>670</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>679</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.04.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20416363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20416363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meaney</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Maternal influences on the sexual behavior and reproductive success of the female rat</article-title>. <source>Horm. Behav.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yhbeh.2008.02.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18417127?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenbogen</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joober</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin attenuates the cortisol response to physical stress: a dose&#x02013;response study</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2012.07.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22889586?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22889586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingdon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenbogen</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>A meta-analytic review of the impact of intranasal oxytocin administration on cortisol concentrations during laboratory tasks: moderation by method and mental health</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2014.07.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25086828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25086828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyrka</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Effect of childhood emotional abuse and age on cortisol responsivity in adulthood</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.02.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19375070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19375070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curley</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Epigenetic mechanisms mediating the long-term effects of maternal care on development</article-title>. <source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>600</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2007.10.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18430469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18430469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatzittofis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uvn&#x000e4;s-Moberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c5;sberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jokinen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>CSF and plasma oxytocin levels in suicide attempters, the role of childhood trauma and revictimization</article-title>. <source>Neuro Endocrinol. Lett.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>217</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 24977971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24977971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogosch</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Gene and Environment interaction and resilience: effects of child maltreatment and serotonin, corticotropin releasing hormone, dopamine, and oxytocin genes</article-title>. <source>Dev. Psychopathol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>427</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0954579412000077</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22559122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22559122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dannlowski</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kugel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grotegerd</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Redlich</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Opel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohm</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Disadvantage of social sensitivity: interaction of oxytocin receptor genotype and child maltreatment on brain structure</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>405</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.12.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26858213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26858213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Des Jarlais</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyles</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crepaz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Improving the reporting quality of nonrandomized evaluations of behavioral and public health interventions: the TREND statement</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Public Health</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.94.3.361</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14998794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gl&#x000e4;scher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000fc;chel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braus</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herpertz</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin attenuates amygdala responses to emotional faces regardless of valence</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>1187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1190</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2007.03.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17617382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17617382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lischke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauenstein</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Effects of intranasal oxytocin on emotional face processing in women</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.06.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19632787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19632787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solovieff</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaponis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosand</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Interaction between genetic variants and exposure to Hurricane Katrina on post-traumatic stress and post-traumatic growth: a prospective analysis of low income adults</article-title>. <source>J. Affect. Disord.</source>
<volume>152</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>249</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2013.09.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24161451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24161451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wotjak</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>A single social defeat experience selectively stimulates the release of oxytocin, but not vasopressin, within the septal brain area of male rats</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>872</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(00)02464-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10924679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eidelman-Rothman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisman</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneiderman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mankuta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin affects spontaneous neural oscillations in trauma-exposed war veterans</article-title>. <source>Front. Behav. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnbeh.2015.00165</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26175673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26175673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elzinga</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollenaar</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakvis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Pelt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinhoven</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Diminished cortisol responses to psychosocial stress associated with lifetime adverse events: a study among healthy young subjects</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2007.11.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18096322?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18096322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera-Melendez</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pestke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeser</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aust</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Early life stress modulates amygdala-prefrontal functional connectivity: implications for oxytocin effects</article-title>. <source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>5328</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5339</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.22553</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24862297?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24862297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faravelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauro</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benni</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietrini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Childhood stressful events, HPA axis and anxiety disorders</article-title>. <source>World J. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5498/wjp.v2.i1.13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24175164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24175164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monakhov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebstein</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin pathway genes: evolutionary ancient system impacting on human affiliation, sociality, and psychopathology</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>79</volume>, <fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.08.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26392129?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26392129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMarco</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stair</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haroon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin and vasopressin effects on the neural response to social cooperation are modulated by sex in humans</article-title>. <source>Brain Imaging Behav.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>764</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11682-014-9333-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25416642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25416642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finkelhor</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotaling</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Sexual abuse in a national survey of adult men and women: prevalence, characteristics, and risk factors</article-title>. <source>Child Abuse Negl.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0145-2134(90)90077-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2310970?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2310970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer-Shofty</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamay-Tsoory</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harari</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levkovitz</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The effect of intranasal administration of oxytocin on fear recognition</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2009.09.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19747930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19747930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Preventing PTSD with oxytocin: effects of oxytocin administration on fear neurocircuitry and PTSD symptom development in recently trauma-exposed individuals</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Psychotraumatol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1302652</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20008198.2017.1302652</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28451068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28451068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016a</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin affects amygdala functional connectivity after trauma script-driven imagery in distressed recently trauma-exposed individuals</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1286</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1296</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2015.278</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26346640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26346640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016b</year>). <article-title>Effects of intranasal oxytocin on amygdala reactivity to emotional faces in recently trauma-exposed individuals</article-title>. <source>Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>336</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nsv116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Salivary oxytocin and vasopressin levels in police officers with and without post traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>J. Neuroendocrinol.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>743</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>751</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jne.12300</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26184739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26184739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gamer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zurowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000fc;chel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Different amygdala subregions mediate valence-related and attentional effects of oxytocin in humans</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>9400</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9405</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1000985107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20421469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20421469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gimpl</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahrenholz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The oxytocin receptor system: structure, function, and regulation</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>683</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.2001.81.2.629</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11274341?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman-Mellor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steptoe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Early-life stress and recurrent psychological distress over the lifecourse predict divergent cortisol reactivity patterns in adulthood</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1755</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1768</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2012.03.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22475549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22475549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The relation between early life adversity, cortisol awakening response and diurnal salivary cortisol levels in postpartum women</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.08.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18835661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18835661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pestke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeser</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aust</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigand</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Early life stress modulates oxytocin effects on limbic system during acute psychosocial stress</article-title>. <source>Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1835</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nsu020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24478326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24478326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guastella</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dadds</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of intranasal oxytocin as an adjunct to exposure therapy for social anxiety disorder</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>917</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>923</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.01.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19246160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19246160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gulpinar</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yegen</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The physiology of learning and memory: role of peptides and stress</article-title>. <source>Curr. Protein Pept. Sci.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>473</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389203043379341</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15581416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15581416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newport</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heit</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>Y. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonsall</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Pituitary-adrenal and autonomic responses to stress in women after sexual and physical abuse in childhood</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Med. Assoc.</source>
<volume>284</volume>, <fpage>592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.284.5.592</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10918705?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10918705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newport</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mletzko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemeroff</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Lower CSF oxytocin concentrations in women with a history of childhood abuse</article-title>. <source>Mol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>954</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>958</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2008.112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18957940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschbaum</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlert</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Social support and oxytocin interact to suppress cortisol and subjective responses to psychosocial stress</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1398</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(03)00465-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14675803?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14675803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinlschmidt</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wippich</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlert</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellhammer</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Selective amnesic effects of oxytocin on human memory</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Behav.</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9384(04)00346-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15501488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khadge</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Gender moderates the effect of oxytocin on social judgments</article-title>. <source>Hum. Psychopharmacol. Clin. Exp.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hup.2402</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24911580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24911580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hostinar</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogosch</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin receptor gene polymorphism, perceived social support, and psychological symptoms in maltreated adolescents</article-title>. <source>Dev. Psychopathol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0954579414000066</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24621832?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24621832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>DNA methylation of the oxytocin receptor gene predicts neural response to ambiguous social stimuli</article-title>. <source>Front. Hum. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2012.00280</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23087634?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23087634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juruena</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clearea</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pariantea</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>O eixo hipot&#x000e1;lamo-pituit&#x000e1;ria-adrenal, a fun&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o dos receptores de glicocortic&#x000f3;ides e sua import&#x000e2;ncia na depress&#x000e3;o The hypothalamic pituitary adrenal axis, glucocorticoid receptor function and relevance to</article-title>. <source>Rev. Bras. Pisquiatr.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1516-44462004000300009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esslinger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddhanti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin modulates neural circuitry for social cognition and fear in humans</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>11489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11493</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3984-05.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16339042?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16339042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016a</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin administration dampens amygdala reactivity towards emotional faces in male and female PTSD patients</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1504</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2015.299</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26404844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26404844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016b</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin normalizes amygdala functional connectivity in post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>2041</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2051</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2016.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26741286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhlman</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiss</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Duran</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Age of trauma onset and HPA axis dysregulation among trauma exposed youth</article-title>. <source>J. Trauma. Stress</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>579</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.22054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26556544?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26556544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucas-Thompson</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Environmental stress, oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) polymorphism, and mental health following collective stress</article-title>. <source>Horm. Behav.</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>624</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yhbeh.2013.02.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23470776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23470776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McQuaid</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McInnis</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paric</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Yawer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anisman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Relations between plasma oxytocin and cortisol: the stress buffering role of social support</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol. Stress</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynstr.2016.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27981177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27981177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McQuaid</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McInnis</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stead</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anisman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A paradoxical association of an oxytocin receptor gene polymorphism: early-life adversity and vulnerability to depression</article-title>. <source>Front. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2013.00128</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23898235?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23898235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meewisse</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reitsma</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gersons</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Cortisol and post-traumatic stress disorder in adults</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>191</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.bp.106.024877</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17978317?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17978317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meinlschmidt</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Sensitivity to intranasal oxytocin in adult men with early parental separation</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>1109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2006.09.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17141739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17141739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirescu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Early life experience alters response of adult neurogenesis to stress</article-title>. <source>Nat. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>846</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn1290</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15273691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15273691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Association of oxytocin level and less severe forms of childhood maltreatment history among healthy Japanese adults involved with child care</article-title>. <source>Front. Behav. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnbeh.2015.00138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26157369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26157369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takiguchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumazaki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomoda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Effect of the nature of subsequent environment on oxytocin and cortisol secretion in maltreated children</article-title>. <source>Front. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2015.00173</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26696910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26696910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1000097</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19621072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The CONSORT statement: revised recommendations for improving the quality of reports of parallel-group randomised trials</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>357</volume>, <fpage>1191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1194</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(00)04337-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11323066?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11323066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohiyeddini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Opacka-Juffry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Emotional suppression explains the link between early life stress and plasma oxytocin</article-title>. <source>Anxiety Stress Coping</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>466</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>475</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10615806.2014.887696</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24479658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24479658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pournajafi-Nazarloo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seng</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>In search of an adult attachment stress provocation to measure effect on the oxytocin system a pilot validation study</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Psychiatr. Nurses Assoc.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>180</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078390313492173</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23950541?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23950541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatt</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuley-Clark</surname><given-names>E. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobson-Stone</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Variation in the oxytocin receptor gene is associated with increased risk for anxiety, stress and depression in individuals with a history of exposure to early life stress</article-title>. <source>J. Psychiatr. Res.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2014.08.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25262417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25262417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin enhances neural processing of monetary reward and loss in post-traumatic stress disorder and traumatized controls</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2016.01.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26851698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26851698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veltman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin increases neural responses to social reward in post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>212</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nsw123</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27614769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27614769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Balance of brain oxytocin and vasopressin: implications for anxiety, depression, and social behaviors</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>659</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2012.08.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22974560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruszewski</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zautra</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Childhood maltreatment and diurnal cortisol patterns in women with chronic pain</article-title>. <source>Psychosom. Med.</source>
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>480</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181d9a104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20467005?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20467005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Serum oxytocin, posttraumatic coping and C-reactive protein in motor vehicle accident survivors by gender</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychobiology</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000382021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26044751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26044751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Bonding after trauma: on the role of social support and the oxytocin system in traumatic stress</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Psychotraumatol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>18597</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ejpt.v3i0.18597</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22893838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22893838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opacka-Juffry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohiyeddini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Experience of stress in childhood negatively correlates with plasma oxytocin concentration in adult men</article-title>. <source>Stress</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10253890.2011.560309</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21682649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21682649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozbay</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitterling</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Social support and resilience to stress across the life span: a neurobiologic framework</article-title>. <source>Curr. Psychiatry Rep.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>310</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-008-0049-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18627668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18627668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palgi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamay-Tsoory</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin improves compassion toward women among patients with PTSD</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2015.11.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26671007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26671007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pierrehumbert</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torrisi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laufer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halfon</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansermet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popovic</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin response to an experimental psychosocial challenge in adults exposed to traumatic experiences during childhood or adolescence</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>166</volume>, <fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>177</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2009.12.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20018229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reijnen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geuze</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermetten</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Individual variation in plasma oxytocin and vasopressin levels in relation to the development of combat-related PTSD in a large military cohort</article-title>. <source>J. Psychiatr. Res.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2017.06.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28689067?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28689067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rimmele</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hediger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaver</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin makes a face in memory familiar</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4260-08.2009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19129382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19129382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malberg</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Potestio</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boikess</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Anxiolytic-like activity of oxytocin in male mice: behavioral and autonomic evidence, therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology</source>
<volume>185</volume>, <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-005-0293-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16418825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin and the neural mechanisms regulating social cognition and affiliative behavior</article-title>. <source>Front. Neuroendocrinol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>547</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yfrne.2009.05.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19481567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19481567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cillien</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Acute dissociation and cardiac reactivity to script-driven imagery in trauma-related disorders</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Psychotraumatol.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>17419</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ejpt.v3i0.17419</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23198029?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23198029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spieler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wizelman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Epple</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stich</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin reduces provoked symptoms in female patients with posttraumatic stress disorder despite exerting sympathomimetic and positive chronotropic effects in a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Med.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-017-0801-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28209155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28209155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savaskan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrhardt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;chinger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Post-learning intranasal oxytocin modulates human memory for facial identity</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2007.12.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18221838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18221838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seltzer</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prososki</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollak</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Stress-induced elevation of oxytocin in maltreated children: evolution, neurodevelopment, and social behavior</article-title>. <source>Child Dev.</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>512</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cdev.12136</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23865588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23865588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seng</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Posttraumatic oxytocin dysregulation: is it a link among posttraumatic self disorders, posttraumatic stress disorder, and pelvic visceral dysregulation conditions in women?</article-title>. <source>J. Trauma Dissoc.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>406</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15299732.2010.496075</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20938865?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20938865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seng</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>D'andrea</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Complex mental health sequelae of psychological trauma among women in prenatal care</article-title>. <source>Psychol. Trauma</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0031467</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25558308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25558308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sippel</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harpaz-Rotem</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krystal</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Oxytocin receptor gene polymorphisms, attachment, and PTSD: results from the national health and resilience in veterans study</article-title>. <source>J. Psychiatr. Res.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2017.07.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28715704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28715704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skuse</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Genetic influences on social cognition</article-title>. <source>Pediatr. Res.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1203/PDR.0b013e318212f562</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21289535?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21289535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The role of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis in neuroendocrine responses to stress</article-title>. <source>Dialog. Clin. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>395</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17290797?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17290797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzaga</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greendale</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeman</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Relation of oxytocin to psychological stress responses and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical axis activity in older women</article-title>. <source>Psychosom. Med.</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.psy.0000203242.95990.74</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16554389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16554389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tollenaar</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molendijk</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninx</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milaneschi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antypa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The association of childhood maltreatment with depression and anxiety is not moderated by the oxytocin receptor gene</article-title>. <source>Eur. Arch. Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci</source>. <volume>267</volume>, <fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>526</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00406-017-0784-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uhl-Bronner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waltisperger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Lorenzana</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Condes</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freund-Mercier</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Sexually dimorphic expression of oxytocin binding sites in forebrain and spinal cord of the rat</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>154</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2005.05.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16084653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16084653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unternaehrer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dempster</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staehli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Dynamic changes in DNA methylation of stress-associated genes (OXTR, BDNF) after acute psychosocial stress</article-title>. <source>Transl. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e150</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2012.77</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22892716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22892716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valstad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvares</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egknud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matziorinis</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreassen</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westlye</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The correlation between central and peripheral oxytocin concentrations: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev</source>. <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.04.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28442403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28442403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Zuiden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frijling</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawijn</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goslings</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luitse</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Intranasal oxytocin to prevent posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms: a randomized controlled trial in emergency department patients</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1030</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1040</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.11.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28087128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28087128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veenema</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Toward understanding how early-life social experiences alter oxytocin-and vasopressin-regulated social behaviors</article-title>. <source>Horm. Behav.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yhbeh.2011.12.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22197269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22197269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Von Elm</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotzsche</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title>. <source>Prev. Med.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>251</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2007.08.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17950122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17950122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Periodic maternal deprivation induces gender-dependent alterations in behavioral and neuroendocrine responses to emotional stress in adult rats</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Behav.</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9384(98)00300-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10336157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10336157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T. D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lightman</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in the posterior pituitary response to stress in the rat</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>738</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>740</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/endo-116-2-738</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3967625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3967625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wotjak</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganster</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holsboer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Dissociated central and peripheral release of vasopressin, but not oxytocin, in response to repeated swim stress: new insights into the secretory capacities of peptidergic neurons</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>1209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1222</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(97)00683-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9681958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yehuda</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bierer</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmeidler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aferiat</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breslau</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Low cortisol and risk for PTSD in adult offspring of holocaust survivors</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>157</volume>, <fpage>1252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1259</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.157.8.1252</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10910787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10910787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayanagi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Evidence that oxytocin exerts anxiolytic effects via oxytocin receptor expressed in serotonergic neurons in mice</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>2259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2271</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5593-08.2009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19228979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19228979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muns</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Changes in oxytocin receptor mRNA in rat brain during pregnancy and the effects of estrogen and interleukin</article-title>. <source>J. Neuroendocrinol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>859</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>865</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2826.1997.00654.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9419837?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9419837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>