<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front PharmacolFront PharmacolFront. Pharmacol.Frontiers in Pharmacology1663-9812Frontiers Media S.A.583800910.3389/fphar.2018.00154PharmacologyReviewThe Associations Between Oxytocin and Trauma in Humans: A Systematic ReviewDonadonMariana Fortunata1Martin-SantosRocio234OsórioFlávia de Lima14*1Department of Neuroscience and Behavior, Medical School of Ribeirão Preto, University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil2Department of Psychiatry and Psychology, Hospital Clínic, Institut d'Investigacions Biomèdiques August Pi i Sunyer (IDIBAPS), Centro de Investigación en Red de Salud Mental (CIBERSAM), Barcelona, Spain3Department of Medicine, University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain4Technology Institute for Translational Medicine (INCT), National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq), Brasília, BrazilEdited by: Xinhua Qu, Shanghai Ninth People's Hospital, ChinaReviewed by: Marijn Lijffijt, Baylor College of Medicine, United States; Gail A. Alvares, Telethon Kids Institute, Australia*Correspondence: Flávia de Lima Osório flaliosorio@ig.com.brThis article was submitted to Translational Pharmacology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Pharmacology01320182018915414820171322018Copyright © 2018 Donadon, Martin-Santos and Osório.2018Donadon, Martin-Santos and OsórioThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Studies have shown that traumatic experiences may affect hormonal systems mediated by the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and the oxytocinergic system. This effect is the result of long-term impairments in hypothalamic structures and negative feedback mechanisms within the HPA axis, structures that mediate the response to stress. This deregulation reduces the production and release of cortisol and oxytocin (OXT), which may alter stress responses and lead to increased vulnerability to impairments from stressful experiences. The presence of gene polymorphisms might also have an impact on the vulnerability to psychopathology. We made a systematic review of articles dealing with the relationship between OXT and traumatic emotional experiences in humans. Thirty-five studies were reviewed and significant associations between experiences of emotional trauma (ET) and OXT were found. The main results showed that the presence of ET and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is strongly associated with reductions in endogenous OXT, and also that the acute effects of OXT administrations in individuals with ET tend to be anxiolytic only in less severe forms. In victims of recent traumatic experiences (RTE), OXT increased the re-experience of traumas and restored the function of different neural networks associated with fear control/extinction in PTSD patients. The results available also suggest that gene receptor polymorphisms may have a protective function in different outcomes after the experience of traumatic events. We conclude that the relationship between ET and OXT is multifaceted, complex, and mediated by contextual and individual factors. Directions for future studies are suggested considering the gaps in the available literature.oxytocinearly traumacurrent traumaPTSDsystematic reviewPRISMAqualitative assessment<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><p>The guidelines of the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA—Moher et al., <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) were adopted as the methodological framework of this study. The electronic databases PsycINFO, PubMed, Scielo, Web of Science, and LILACS were searched without limitations in terms of time, language, or publication date (last search conducted on December 3, 2017). A manual search of the reference lists of the selected articles was also performed. The following keywords were used followed by “AND” or “OR:” oxytocin; PTSD; post-traumatic stress; early trauma; childhood maltreatment; emotional trauma; emotional stress; neglect; adversity; sexual abuse; emotional abuse; and physical abuse.</p><p>Articles that evaluated associations between OXT and the experience of early trauma (ET), recent traumatic experiences (RTE), and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in men and women, regardless of age, were eligible for inclusion. ET experiences were considered as those that occurred before 18 years of age (Bremner et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), and RTEs were considered as those that occurred over the last few days or months (Chatzittofis et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>Studies of endogenous OXT that did not involve participants with ET, RTE, or PTSD; those investigating OXT and psychiatric disorders excluding PTSD; those involving OXT and social behavior, resilience, social cognition, genetic analysis, and the physiological aspects of the HPA axis among participants without ET, RTE, or PTSD; those involving treatment for ET or PTSD but not involving OXT; and animal studies, letters to the editor, case studies, and reviews unrelated to this topic were excluded.</p><p>Two researchers made independent decisions regarding whether to include a study, and divergences in data extraction were discussed until a consensus was reached.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows the search results as well the reasons for article exclusion.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart based on PRISMA/(OXT, Oxytocin; ET, Early trauma; HPA, Hypothalamic Legend Pituitary Adrenal Axis; PTSD, Post traumatic stress disorder; RTE, Recent trauma event).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-00154-g0001"/></fig><p>The methodological quality of the studies was evaluated using the following references: (a) Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies (STROBE; Von Elm et al., <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>); (b) Transparent Reporting of Evaluations with Non-Randomized Designs (TREND; Des Jarlais et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>); and (c) the Revised Recommendations for Improving the Quality of Reports of Parallel-Group Randomized Trials (CONSORT; Moher et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). The quality percentage of each study was calculated by dividing the number of items scored by the total number of items.</p></sec>Concluding remarksThis systematic review regarding the relationship between OXT and emotional trauma in humans revealed that reductions in endogenous OXT levels are more strongly associated with the presence of severe and recurrent ET and PTSD.The results also show that the acute effect of OXT in victims of ET tends to be anxiolytic, but only in those with less severe forms of ET. Among individuals with severe ET, OXT does not seem to have anxiolytic properties and may even increase anxiety. The same holds true for victims of RTE, since OXT has been reported to increase the re-experience of traumatic symptoms. In patients with PTSD, OXT reestablished the function of different neural networks associated with fear control and extinction.Genetic studies showed that the presence of the GG genotype in the OXTR rs53576 gene polymorphism associated with the experience of ET or PTSD is related to more negative outcomes, whereas the presence of the AA genotype appears to have a protective role.It should be noted that the relationship between OXT and traumatic situations is mediated by different contextual and inter-individual variables that might predict more or less favorable outcomes. Thus, a stable environment, less severe forms of trauma, and the female gender are associated with resiliency responses.The studies included in the review have limitations that call for caution in the interpretation and generalization of their findings, including (a) small sample sizes recruited from extremely specific contexts; (b) poor control of confounding variables such as gender and ET severity; (c) highly variable age groups; (d) cross-sectional designs; (e) possible differences between chronic and acute administration of OXT in RCT; and (f) lack of evaluation of both central and peripheral levels of OXT to determine whether differences exist [most of the studies on this topic assessed endogenous levels in peripheral fluids (e.g., blood plasma, urine, saliva) and the methodological validity of these techniques is controversial (Wotjak et al., 1998; Seltzer et al., 2014; Valstad et al., 2017)].For future studies, we suggest the adoption of longitudinal designs to establish causal relationships; the recruitment of large samples to control for gender, age, and sex hormones; the conduction of RCTs with chronic and/or prolonged administration of OXT; the investigation of other polymorphisms that might interfere with or contribute to increased susceptibility to the harmful effects of traumatic experiences; and the performance of epigenetic investigations on the association between ET, RTE, and PTSD with OXT.Author contributionsAll authors listed have made a substantial, direct and intellectual contribution to the work, and approved it for publication.Conflict of interest statementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.The National Council for Technological and Scientific Development (CNPq grant numbers 2015/12548-6 and 301321/2016-7), the Spanish Biomedical Research Networking Center for Mental Health (CIBERSAM), and the Comission at per a Universitats i Recerca del DIUE, Generalitat de Catalunya, Spain (grant number 2014SGR1435) supported this study.ReferencesAltemusM.RocaC.GallivenE.RomanosC.DeusterP. (2001). Increased vasopressin and adrenocorticotropin responses to stress in the midluteal phase of the menstrual cycle. J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metabol.
86, 2525–2530. 10.1210/jcem.86.6.759611397850AmicoJ. A.MantellaR. C.VollmerR. R.LiX. (2004). Anxiety and stress responses in female oxytocin deficient mice. J. Neuroendocrinol.
16, 319–324. 10.1111/j.0953-8194.2004.01161.x15089969Bakermans-KranenburgM. J.van IJzendoornM. H. (2014). A sociability gene? Meta-analysis of oxytocin receptor genotype effects in humans. Psychiatr. Genet.
24, 45–51. 10.1097/YPG.0b013e328364368423921259BartzJ. A.ZakiJ.BolgerN.HollanderE.LudwigN. N.KolevzonA.. (2010). Oxytocin selectively improves empathic accuracy. Psychol. Sci.
21, 1426–1428. 10.1177/095679761038343920855907BoyceW. T.EllisB. (2005). Biological sensitivity to context: I. An evolutionary–developmental theory of the origins and functions of stress reactivity. Dev. Psychopathol.
17, 271–301. 10.1017/S095457940505014516761546BradleyB.WestenD.MercerK. B.BinderE. B.JovanovicT.CrainD.. (2011). Association between childhood maltreatment and adult emotional dysregulation in a low-income, urban, African American sample: moderation by oxytocin receptor gene. Dev. Psychopathol.
23, 439–452. 10.1017/S095457941100016223786688BremnerJ. D.VermettenE.MazureC. M. (2000). Development and preliminary psychometric properties of an instrument for the measurement of childhood trauma: the early trauma inventory. Depress Anxiety
12, 1–12. 10.1002/1520-6394(2000)12:1&lt;1::AID-DA1&gt;3.0.CO;2-W10999240BrettM.BaxendaleS. (2001). Motherhood and memory: a review. Psychoneuroendocrinology
26, 339–362. 10.1016/S0306-4530(01)00003-811259856BrindleP. M.BrownM. W.BrownJ.GriffithH. B.TurnerG. M. (1991). Objective and subjective memory impairment in pregnancy. Psychol. Med.
21, 647–653. 10.1017/S00332917000222851946853BrownC. A.CardosoC.EllenbogenM. A. (2016). A meta-analytic review of the correlation between peripheral oxytocin and cortisol concentrations. Front. Neuroendocrinol.
43, 19–27. 10.1016/j.yfrne.2016.11.00127836673BrunettiM.SepedeG.MingoiaG.CataniC.FerrettiA.MerlaA.. (2010). Elevated response of human amygdala to neutral stimuli in mild post traumatic stress disorder: neural correlates of generalized emotional response. Neuroscience
168, 670–679. 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.04.02420416363CameronN. M.FishE. W.MeaneyM. J. (2008). Maternal influences on the sexual behavior and reproductive success of the female rat. Horm. Behav.
54, 178–184. 10.1016/j.yhbeh.2008.02.01318417127CardosoC.EllenbogenM. A.OrlandoM. A.BaconS. L.JooberR. (2013). Intranasal oxytocin attenuates the cortisol response to physical stress: a dose–response study. Psychoneuroendocrinology
38, 399–407. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2012.07.01322889586CardosoC.KingdonD.EllenbogenM. A. (2014). A meta-analytic review of the impact of intranasal oxytocin administration on cortisol concentrations during laboratory tasks: moderation by method and mental health. Psychoneuroendocrinology
49, 161–170. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2014.07.01425086828CarpenterL. L.TyrkaA. R.RossN. S.KhouryL.AndersonG. M.PriceL. H. (2009). Effect of childhood emotional abuse and age on cortisol responsivity in adulthood. Biol. Psychiatry
66, 69–75. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.02.03019375070ChampagneF. A.CurleyJ. P. (2009). Epigenetic mechanisms mediating the long-term effects of maternal care on development. Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
33, 593–600. 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2007.10.00918430469ChatzittofisA.NordströmP.Uvnäs-MobergK.ÅsbergM.JokinenJ. (2014). CSF and plasma oxytocin levels in suicide attempters, the role of childhood trauma and revictimization. Neuro Endocrinol. Lett.
35, 213–217. 24977971CicchettiD.RogoschF. A. (2012). Gene and Environment interaction and resilience: effects of child maltreatment and serotonin, corticotropin releasing hormone, dopamine, and oxytocin genes. Dev. Psychopathol.
24, 411–427. 10.1017/S095457941200007722559122DannlowskiU.KugelH.GrotegerdD.RedlichR.OpelN.DohmK.. (2016). Disadvantage of social sensitivity: interaction of oxytocin receptor genotype and child maltreatment on brain structure. Biol. Psychiatry
80, 398–405. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.12.01026858213Des JarlaisD. C.LylesC.CrepazN. (2004). Improving the reporting quality of nonrandomized evaluations of behavioral and public health interventions: the TREND statement. Am. J. Public Health
94, 361–366. 10.2105/AJPH.94.3.36114998794DomesG.HeinrichsM.GläscherJ.BüchelC.BrausD. F.HerpertzS. C. (2007). Oxytocin attenuates amygdala responses to emotional faces regardless of valence. Biol. Psychiatry
62, 1187–1190. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2007.03.02517617382DomesG.LischkeA.BergerC.GrossmannA.HauensteinK.HeinrichsM.. (2010). Effects of intranasal oxytocin on emotional face processing in women. Psychoneuroendocrinology
35, 83–93. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.06.01619632787DunnE. C.SolovieffN.LoweS. R.GallagherP. J.ChaponisJ.RosandJ.. (2014). Interaction between genetic variants and exposure to Hurricane Katrina on post-traumatic stress and post-traumatic growth: a prospective analysis of low income adults. J. Affect. Disord.
152, 243–249. 10.1016/j.jad.2013.09.01824161451EbnerK.WotjakC. T.LandgrafR.EngelmannM. (2000). A single social defeat experience selectively stimulates the release of oxytocin, but not vasopressin, within the septal brain area of male rats. Brain Res.
872, 87–92. 10.1016/S0006-8993(00)02464-110924679Eidelman-RothmanM.GoldsteinA.LevyJ.WeismanO.SchneidermanI.MankutaD.. (2015). Oxytocin affects spontaneous neural oscillations in trauma-exposed war veterans. Front. Behav. Neurosci.
9:165. 10.3389/fnbeh.2015.0016526175673ElzingaB. M.RoelofsK.TollenaarM. S.BakvisP.van PeltJ.SpinhovenP. (2008). Diminished cortisol responses to psychosocial stress associated with lifetime adverse events: a study among healthy young subjects. Psychoneuroendocrinology
33, 227–237. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2007.11.00418096322FanY.Herrera-MelendezA. L.PestkeK.FeeserM.AustS.OtteC.. (2014). Early life stress modulates amygdala-prefrontal functional connectivity: implications for oxytocin effects. Hum. Brain Mapp.
35, 5328–5339. 10.1002/hbm.2255324862297FaravelliC.SauroC. L.GodiniL.LelliL.BenniL.PietriniF.. (2012). Childhood stressful events, HPA axis and anxiety disorders. World J. Psychiatry
2, 13–25. 10.5498/wjp.v2.i1.1324175164FeldmanR.MonakhovM.PrattM.EbsteinR. P. (2016). Oxytocin pathway genes: evolutionary ancient system impacting on human affiliation, sociality, and psychopathology. Biol. Psychiatry
79, 174–184. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.08.00826392129FengC.HackettP. D.DeMarcoA. C.ChenX.StairS.HaroonE.. (2015). Oxytocin and vasopressin effects on the neural response to social cooperation are modulated by sex in humans. Brain Imaging Behav.
9, 754–764. 10.1007/s11682-014-9333-925416642FinkelhorD.HotalingG.LewisI.SmithC. (1990). Sexual abuse in a national survey of adult men and women: prevalence, characteristics, and risk factors. Child Abuse Negl.
14, 19–28. 10.1016/0145-2134(90)90077-72310970Fischer-ShoftyM.Shamay-TsooryS. G.HarariH.LevkovitzY. (2010). The effect of intranasal administration of oxytocin on fear recognition. Neuropsychologia
48, 179–184. 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2009.09.00319747930FrijlingJ. L. (2017). Preventing PTSD with oxytocin: effects of oxytocin administration on fear neurocircuitry and PTSD symptom development in recently trauma-exposed individuals. Eur. J. Psychotraumatol.
8:1302652. 10.1080/20008198.2017.130265228451068FrijlingJ. L.van ZuidenM.KochS. B.NawijnL.VeltmanD. J.OlffM. (2016a). Intranasal oxytocin affects amygdala functional connectivity after trauma script-driven imagery in distressed recently trauma-exposed individuals. Neuropsychopharmacology
41, 1286–1296
10.1038/npp.2015.27826346640FrijlingJ. L.van ZuidenM.KochS. B.NawijnL.VeltmanD. J.OlffM. (2016b). Effects of intranasal oxytocin on amygdala reactivity to emotional faces in recently trauma-exposed individuals. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
17, 327–336. 10.1093/scan/nsv116FrijlingJ. L.ZuidenM.NawijnL.KochS. B. J.NeumannI. D.VeltmanD. J.. (2015). Salivary oxytocin and vasopressin levels in police officers with and without post traumatic stress disorder. J. Neuroendocrinol.
27, 743–751. 10.1111/jne.1230026184739GamerM.ZurowskiB.BüchelC. (2010). Different amygdala subregions mediate valence-related and attentional effects of oxytocin in humans. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
107, 9400–9405. 10.1073/pnas.100098510720421469GimplG.FahrenholzF. (2001). The oxytocin receptor system: structure, function, and regulation. Physiol. Rev.
81, 629–683. 10.1152/physrev.2001.81.2.62911274341Goldman-MellorS.HamerM.SteptoeA. (2012). Early-life stress and recurrent psychological distress over the lifecourse predict divergent cortisol reactivity patterns in adulthood. Psychoneuroendocrinology
37, 1755–1768. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2012.03.01022475549GonzalezA.JenkinsJ. M.SteinerM.FlemingA. S. (2009). The relation between early life adversity, cortisol awakening response and diurnal salivary cortisol levels in postpartum women. Psychoneuroendocrinology
34, 76–86. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.08.01218835661GrimmS.PestkeK.FeeserM.AustS.WeigandA.WangJ.. (2014). Early life stress modulates oxytocin effects on limbic system during acute psychosocial stress. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
9, 1828–1835. 10.1093/scan/nsu02024478326GuastellaA. J.HowardA. L.DaddsM. R.MitchellP.CarsonD. S. (2009). A randomized controlled trial of intranasal oxytocin as an adjunct to exposure therapy for social anxiety disorder. Psychoneuroendocrinology
34, 917–923. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.01.00519246160GulpinarM. A.YegenB. C. (2004). The physiology of learning and memory: role of peptides and stress. Curr. Protein Pept. Sci.
5, 457–473. 10.2174/138920304337934115581416HeimC.NewportD. J.HeitS.GrahamY. P.WilcoxM.BonsallR.. (2000). Pituitary-adrenal and autonomic responses to stress in women after sexual and physical abuse in childhood. J. Am. Med. Assoc.
284, 592–597. 10.1001/jama.284.5.59210918705HeimC.YoungL. J.NewportD. J.MletzkoT.MillerA. H.NemeroffC. B. (2009). Lower CSF oxytocin concentrations in women with a history of childhood abuse. Mol. Psychiatry
14, 954–958. 10.1038/mp.2008.11218957940HeinrichsM.BaumgartnerT.KirschbaumC.EhlertU. (2003). Social support and oxytocin interact to suppress cortisol and subjective responses to psychosocial stress. Biol. Psychiatry
54, 1389–1398. 10.1016/S0006-3223(03)00465-714675803HeinrichsM.MeinlschmidtG.WippichW.EhlertU.HellhammerD. H. (2004). Selective amnesic effects of oxytocin on human memory. Physiol. Behav.
83, 31–38. 10.1016/S0031-9384(04)00346-415501488HogeE. A.AndersonE.LawsonE. A.BuiE.FischerL. E.KhadgeS. D.. (2014). Gender moderates the effect of oxytocin on social judgments. Hum. Psychopharmacol. Clin. Exp.
29, 299–304. 10.1002/hup.240224911580HostinarC. E.CicchettiD.RogoschF. A. (2014). Oxytocin receptor gene polymorphism, perceived social support, and psychological symptoms in maltreated adolescents. Dev. Psychopathol.
26, 465–477. 10.1017/S095457941400006624621832JackA.ConnellyJ. J.MorrisJ. P. (2012). DNA methylation of the oxytocin receptor gene predicts neural response to ambiguous social stimuli. Front. Hum. Neurosci.
6:280. 10.3389/fnhum.2012.0028023087634JuruenaM. F.CleareaA. J.ParianteaC. M. (2004). O eixo hipotálamo-pituitária-adrenal, a função dos receptores de glicocorticóides e sua importância na depressão The hypothalamic pituitary adrenal axis, glucocorticoid receptor function and relevance to. Rev. Bras. Pisquiatr.
26, 189–201. 10.1590/S1516-44462004000300009KirschP.EsslingerC.ChenQ.MierD.LisS.SiddhantiS.. (2005). Oxytocin modulates neural circuitry for social cognition and fear in humans. J. Neurosci.
25, 11489–11493. 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3984-05.200516339042KochS. B.van ZuidenM.NawijnL.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM. (2016a). Intranasal oxytocin administration dampens amygdala reactivity towards emotional faces in male and female PTSD patients. Neuropsychopharmacology
41, 1495–1504. 10.1038/npp.2015.29926404844KochS. B.van ZuidenM.NawijnL.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM. (2016b). Intranasal oxytocin normalizes amygdala functional connectivity in post-traumatic stress disorder. Neuropsychopharmacology
41, 2041–2051. 10.1038/npp.2016.126741286KuhlmanK. R.VargasI.GeissE. G.Lopez-DuranN. L. (2015). Age of trauma onset and HPA axis dysregulation among trauma exposed youth. J. Trauma. Stress
28, 572–579. 10.1002/jts.2205426556544Lucas-ThompsonR. G.HolmanE. A. (2013). Environmental stress, oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) polymorphism, and mental health following collective stress. Horm. Behav.
63, 615–624. 10.1016/j.yhbeh.2013.02.01523470776McQuaidR. J.McInnisO. A.ParicA.Al-YawerF.MathesonK.AnismanH. (2016). Relations between plasma oxytocin and cortisol: the stress buffering role of social support. Neurobiol. Stress
3, 52–60. 10.1016/j.ynstr.2016.01.00127981177McQuaidR. J.McInnisO. A.SteadJ. D.MathesonK.AnismanH. (2013). A paradoxical association of an oxytocin receptor gene polymorphism: early-life adversity and vulnerability to depression. Front. Neurosci.
7:128. 10.3389/fnins.2013.0012823898235MeewisseM. L.ReitsmaJ. B.De VriesG. J.GersonsB. P.OlffM. (2007). Cortisol and post-traumatic stress disorder in adults. Br. J. Psychiatry
191, 387–392. 10.1192/bjp.bp.106.02487717978317MeinlschmidtG.HeimC. (2007). Sensitivity to intranasal oxytocin in adult men with early parental separation. Biol. Psychiatry
61, 1109–1111. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2006.09.00717141739MirescuC.PetersJ. D.GouldE. (2004). Early life experience alters response of adult neurogenesis to stress. Nat. Neurosci.
7, 841–846. 10.1038/nn129015273691MizukiR.FujiwaraT. (2015). Association of oxytocin level and less severe forms of childhood maltreatment history among healthy Japanese adults involved with child care. Front. Behav. Neurosci.
9:138. 10.3389/fnbeh.2015.0013826157369MizushimaS. G.FujisawaT. X.TakiguchiS.KumazakiH.TanakaS.TomodaA. (2015). Effect of the nature of subsequent environment on oxytocin and cortisol secretion in maltreated children. Front. Psychiatry
6:173. 10.3389/fpsyt.2015.0017326696910MoherD.LiberatiA.TetzlaffJ. (2009). Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. PLoS Med.
6:e1000097
10.1371/journal.pmed.100009719621072MoherD.SchulzK. F.AltmanD. G. (2001). The CONSORT statement: revised recommendations for improving the quality of reports of parallel-group randomised trials. Lancet
357, 1191–1194. 10.1016/S0140-6736(00)04337-311323066MohiyeddiniC.Opacka-JuffryJ.GrossJ. J. (2014). Emotional suppression explains the link between early life stress and plasma oxytocin. Anxiety Stress Coping
27, 466–475. 10.1080/10615806.2014.88769624479658MunroM. L.BrownS. L.Pournajafi-NazarlooH.CarterC. S.LopezW. D.SengJ. S. (2013). In search of an adult attachment stress provocation to measure effect on the oxytocin system a pilot validation study. J. Am. Psychiatr. Nurses Assoc.
19, 180–191. 10.1177/107839031349217323950541MyersA. J.WilliamsL.GattJ. M.McAuley-ClarkE. Z.Dobson-StoneC.SchofieldP. R.. (2014). Variation in the oxytocin receptor gene is associated with increased risk for anxiety, stress and depression in individuals with a history of exposure to early life stress. J. Psychiatr. Res.
59, 93–100. 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2014.08.02125262417NawijnL.van ZuidenM.KochS. B.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM. (2016). Intranasal oxytocin enhances neural processing of monetary reward and loss in post-traumatic stress disorder and traumatized controls. Psychoneuroendocrinology
66, 228–237. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2016.01.02026851698NawijnL.van ZuidenM.KochS. B.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM. (2017). Intranasal oxytocin increases neural responses to social reward in post-traumatic stress disorder. Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
12, 212–223. 10.1093/scan/nsw12327614769NeumannI. D.LandgrafR. (2012). Balance of brain oxytocin and vasopressin: implications for anxiety, depression, and social behaviors. Trends Neurosci.
35, 649–659. 10.1016/j.tins.2012.08.00422974560NicolsonN. A.DavisM. C.KruszewskiD.ZautraA. J. (2010). Childhood maltreatment and diurnal cortisol patterns in women with chronic pain. Psychosom. Med.
72, 471–480. 10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181d9a10420467005NishiD.HashimotoK.NoguchiH.KimY.MatsuokaY. (2015). Serum oxytocin, posttraumatic coping and C-reactive protein in motor vehicle accident survivors by gender. Neuropsychobiology
71, 196–201. 10.1159/00038202126044751OlffM. (2012). Bonding after trauma: on the role of social support and the oxytocin system in traumatic stress. Eur. J. Psychotraumatol.
3:18597. 10.3402/ejpt.v3i0.1859722893838Opacka-JuffryJ.MohiyeddiniC. (2012). Experience of stress in childhood negatively correlates with plasma oxytocin concentration in adult men. Stress
15, 1–10. 10.3109/10253890.2011.56030921682649OzbayF.FitterlingH.CharneyD.SouthwickS. (2008). Social support and resilience to stress across the life span: a neurobiologic framework. Curr. Psychiatry Rep.
10, 304–310. 10.1007/s11920-008-0049-718627668PalgiS.KleinE.Shamay-TsooryS. G. (2016). Oxytocin improves compassion toward women among patients with PTSD. Psychoneuroendocrinology
64, 143–149. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2015.11.00826671007PierrehumbertB.TorrisiR.LauferD.HalfonO.AnsermetF.PopovicM. B. (2010). Oxytocin response to an experimental psychosocial challenge in adults exposed to traumatic experiences during childhood or adolescence. Neuroscience
166, 168–177. 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2009.12.01620018229ReijnenA.GeuzeE.VermettenE. (2017). Individual variation in plasma oxytocin and vasopressin levels in relation to the development of combat-related PTSD in a large military cohort. J. Psychiatr. Res.
94, 88–95. 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2017.06.01028689067RimmeleU.HedigerK.HeinrichsM.KlaverP. (2009). Oxytocin makes a face in memory familiar. J. Neurosci.
29, 38–42. 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4260-08.200919129382RingR. H.MalbergJ. E.PotestioL.PingJ.BoikessS.LuoB.. (2006). Anxiolytic-like activity of oxytocin in male mice: behavioral and autonomic evidence, therapeutic implications. Psychopharmacology
185, 218–225. 10.1007/s00213-005-0293-z16418825RossH. E.YoungL. J. (2009). Oxytocin and the neural mechanisms regulating social cognition and affiliative behavior. Front. Neuroendocrinol.
30, 534–547. 10.1016/j.yfrne.2009.05.00419481567SackM.CillienM.HopperJ. W. (2012). Acute dissociation and cardiac reactivity to script-driven imagery in trauma-related disorders. Eur. J. Psychotraumatol.
3:17419. 10.3402/ejpt.v3i0.1741923198029SackM.SpielerD.WizelmanL.EppleG.StichJ.ZabaM.. (2017). Intranasal oxytocin reduces provoked symptoms in female patients with posttraumatic stress disorder despite exerting sympathomimetic and positive chronotropic effects in a randomized controlled trial. BMC Med.
15:40. 10.1186/s12916-017-0801-028209155SavaskanE.EhrhardtR.SchulzA.WalterM.SchächingerH. (2008). Post-learning intranasal oxytocin modulates human memory for facial identity. Psychoneuroendocrinology
33, 368–374. 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2007.12.00418221838SeltzerL. J.ZieglerT.ConnollyM. J.PrososkiA. R.PollakS. D. (2014). Stress-induced elevation of oxytocin in maltreated children: evolution, neurodevelopment, and social behavior. Child Dev.
85, 501–512. 10.1111/cdev.1213623865588SengJ. S. (2010). Posttraumatic oxytocin dysregulation: is it a link among posttraumatic self disorders, posttraumatic stress disorder, and pelvic visceral dysregulation conditions in women?. J. Trauma Dissoc.
11, 387–406. 10.1080/15299732.2010.49607520938865SengJ. S.D'andreaW.FordJ. D. (2014). Complex mental health sequelae of psychological trauma among women in prenatal care. Psychol. Trauma
6, 41–49. 10.1037/a003146725558308SippelL. M.HanS.WatkinsL. E.Harpaz-RotemI.SouthwickS. M.KrystalJ. H.. (2017). Oxytocin receptor gene polymorphisms, attachment, and PTSD: results from the national health and resilience in veterans study. J. Psychiatr. Res.
94, 139–147. 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2017.07.00828715704SkuseD. H.GallagherL. (2011). Genetic influences on social cognition. Pediatr. Res.
69, 85–91. 10.1203/PDR.0b013e318212f56221289535SmithS. M.ValeW. W. (2006). The role of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis in neuroendocrine responses to stress. Dialog. Clin. Neurosci.
8, 383–395. 17290797TaylorS. E.GonzagaG. C.KleinL. C.HuP.GreendaleG. A.SeemanT. E. (2006). Relation of oxytocin to psychological stress responses and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical axis activity in older women. Psychosom. Med.
68, 238–245. 10.1097/01.psy.0000203242.95990.7416554389TollenaarM. S.MolendijkM. L.PenninxB. W.MilaneschiY.AntypaN. (2017). The association of childhood maltreatment with depression and anxiety is not moderated by the oxytocin receptor gene. Eur. Arch. Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci. 267, 517–526. 10.1007/s00406-017-0784-zUhl-BronnerS.WaltispergerE.Martínez-LorenzanaG.CondesL. M.Freund-MercierM. J. (2005). Sexually dimorphic expression of oxytocin binding sites in forebrain and spinal cord of the rat. Neuroscience
135, 147–154. 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2005.05.02516084653UnternaehrerE.LuersP.MillJ.DempsterE.MeyerA. H.StaehliS. (2012). Dynamic changes in DNA methylation of stress-associated genes (OXTR, BDNF) after acute psychosocial stress. Transl. Psychiatry
2:e150. 10.1038/tp.2012.7722892716ValstadM.AlvaresG. A.EgknudM.MatziorinisA. M.AndreassenO. A.WestlyeL. T.. (2017). The correlation between central and peripheral oxytocin concentrations: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev. 78, 117–124. 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.04.01728442403Van ZuidenM.FrijlingJ. L.NawijnL.KochS. B.GoslingsJ. C.LuitseJ. S.. (2017). Intranasal oxytocin to prevent posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms: a randomized controlled trial in emergency department patients. Biol. Psychiatry
81, 1030–1040. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.11.01228087128VeenemaA. H. (2012). Toward understanding how early-life social experiences alter oxytocin-and vasopressin-regulated social behaviors. Horm. Behav.
61, 304–312. 10.1016/j.yhbeh.2011.12.00222197269Von ElmE.AltmanD. G.EggerM.PocockS. J.GotzscheP. C.VandenbrouckeJ. P. (2007). The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. Prev. Med.
45, 247–251. 10.1016/j.ypmed.2007.08.01217950122WiggerA.NeumannI. D. (1999). Periodic maternal deprivation induces gender-dependent alterations in behavioral and neuroendocrine responses to emotional stress in adult rats. Physiol. Behav.
66, 293–302. 10.1016/S0031-9384(98)00300-X10336157WilliamsT. D. M.CarterD. A.LightmanS. L. (1985). Sexual dimorphism in the posterior pituitary response to stress in the rat. Endocrinology
116, 738–740. 10.1210/endo-116-2-7383967625WotjakC. T.GansterJ.KohlG.HolsboerF.LandgrafR.EngelmannM. (1998). Dissociated central and peripheral release of vasopressin, but not oxytocin, in response to repeated swim stress: new insights into the secretory capacities of peptidergic neurons. Neuroscience
85, 1209–1222. 10.1016/S0306-4522(97)00683-09681958YehudaR.BiererL. M.SchmeidlerJ.AferiatD. H.BreslauI.DolanS. (2000). Low cortisol and risk for PTSD in adult offspring of holocaust survivors. Am. J. Psychiatry
157, 1252–1259. 10.1176/appi.ajp.157.8.125210910787YoshidaM.TakayanagiY.InoueK.KimuraT.YoungL. J.OnakaT.. (2009). Evidence that oxytocin exerts anxiolytic effects via oxytocin receptor expressed in serotonergic neurons in mice. J. Neurosci.
29, 2259–2271. 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5593-08.200919228979YoungL. J.MunsS.WangZ.InselT. R. (1997). Changes in oxytocin receptor mRNA in rat brain during pregnancy and the effects of estrogen and interleukin. J. Neuroendocrinol.
9, 859–865. 10.1046/j.1365-2826.1997.00654.x9419837
