<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC Med Res MethodolBMC Med Res MethodolBMC Medical Research Methodology1471-2288BioMed CentralLondon470061910510.1186/s12874-015-0105-zResearch ArticleCreating a literature database of low-calorie sweeteners and health studies: evidence mappingWangDing Dingdeenawang@gmail.comShams-WhiteMarissaMarissa.Shams_White@tufts.eduBrightOliver John M.oliver-john.bright@tufts.eduParrottJ. Scottparrotja@shrp.rutgers.eduChungMeiMei_Chun.Chung@tufts.eduDepartment of Public Health and Community Medicine, Tufts University School of Medicine, Boston, MA USA Department of Interdisciplinary Studies, Rutgers University School of Health Related Professions, Newark, NJ USA 512016512016201616139201521122015© Wang et al. 2015Open AccessThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundEvidence mapping is an emerging tool used to systematically identify, organize and summarize the quantity and focus of scientific evidence on a broad topic, but there are currently no methodological standards. Using the topic of low-calorie sweeteners (LCS) and selected health outcomes, we describe the process of creating an evidence-map database and demonstrate several example descriptive analyses using this database.MethodsThe process of creating an evidence-map database is described in detail. The steps include: developing a comprehensive literature search strategy, establishing study eligibility criteria and a systematic study selection process, extracting data, developing outcome groups with input from expert stakeholders and tabulating data using descriptive analyses. The database was uploaded onto SRDR™ (Systematic Review Data Repository), an open public data repository.ResultsOur final LCS evidence-map database included 225 studies, of which 208 were interventional studies and 17 were cohort studies. An example bubble plot was produced to display the evidence-map data and visualize research gaps according to four parameters: comparison types, population baseline health status, outcome groups, and study sample size. This plot indicated a lack of studies assessing appetite and dietary intake related outcomes using LCS with a sugar intake comparison in people with diabetes.ConclusionEvidence mapping is an important tool for the contextualization of in-depth systematic reviews within broader literature and identifies gaps in the evidence base, which can be used to inform future research. An open evidence-map database has the potential to promote knowledge translation from nutrition science to policy.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12874-015-0105-z) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.KeywordsEvidence mapEvidence-based methodologyLow-calorie sweetenersArtificial sweetenersHigh intensity sweetenersInternational Life Sciences Institutes (ILSI) North Americaissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2016<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Seven steps were used to construct a LCS evidence-map database: 1) Identify the Scope of the Evidence Map; 2) Define the Roles and Responsibilities of Different Parties: Stakeholder Panel and Research Team; 3) Develop a Comprehensive Search Strategy; 4) Establish Study Eligibility Criteria and a Systematic Study Selection Process; 5) Carry Out Abstract Screening and Selection; 6) Carry Out Data Extraction; and 7) Classify Outcome Categories. Details are described as follows.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Identify the scope of the evidence map</title><p>The initial scope of work was developed by the sponsor of this project in a request-for- proposals. The following five areas of research regarding the potential health effects of LCS were all considered and included: 1) energy sensing by the brain; 2) gut hormones that may influence energy homeostasis; 3) satiety and preference for taste; 4) eating behavior; and 5) body weight and composition. It is important to note that, aside from their initial feedback on our funded research proposal, the sponsor was not involved in the later refinement of the work scope or the process of creating the evidence-map database other than providing a list of selective citations for cross-referencing purposes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Establish roles and responsibilities of different parties: stakeholder panel and research team</title><p>A diverse stakeholder panel was recruited across eight areas of expertise: one physician, two dietitians, three policymakers, a research funder, academic researchers from five different fields, two representatives from the food industry, one journalist and one lay person. The panel served as a steering committee to guide the research team through the process of building the LCS evidence-map database. Specifically, the stakeholder panel helped refine the search strategy, finalize study eligibility criteria and define outcome groups for evidence map analysis and charting. Data screening, collection and analyses were performed by the research team. The research team included a methodologist with expertise in conducting and leading systematic reviews and meta-analyses, two team members with graduate-level epidemiology training and a research coordinator.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Develop a comprehensive search strategy</title><p>The research team collected key search terms from previous reviews and systematic reviews on relevant topics to formulate the initial search strategy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The search strategy was developed using both keywords and the National Library of Medicine’s Medical Subject Headings (MeSH). Duplicated citations were removed in MEDLINE® and Endnote®. The search was also cross-referenced with published systematic reviews to make sure all of the relevant articles were included. Publication citations were exported from electronic search interfaces and stored in a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet. The relevance of the publications was determined based on pre-determined inclusion and exclusion criteria using a two-step screening process: 1) title and abstract screening and 2) full-text article screening, which is described later in detail. The initial literature search and abstract screening were conducted by the research team. After the screening was completed, the panel provided input and suggested additional key terms to refine the search strategy. The research team then carried out this supplemental search, retrieved the citations and screened this additional round of abstracts. Included abstracts from both screening rounds were then merged into the same pool for full-text screening. The final search strategy of the LCS evidence map is described in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Establish study eligibility criteria and a systematic study selection process</title><p>The research team used an iterative process to establish study eligibility criteria, with input from the stakeholder panel collected via webinars and online surveys. After 2 iterations, the stakeholders and research team decided that for studies to be included, they needed to be: 1) randomized or non-randomized, controlled, clinical trials or prospective cohort study designs, which are considered the strongest study designs for causal inferences; 2) investigating orally administered, FDA-approved LCS or LCS that are generally recognized as safe (GRAS); 3) reporting at least one health outcome within the five categories in our scope of work; 4) an English publication; and 5) human subjects research. Articles with study populations including adults, children, adolescents, pregnant women and infants greater than 6 months old were included, whereas studies in cancer patients and cancer outcomes were excluded because the project scope includes only FDA-approved LCS that have passed FDA’s toxicological safety assessment as food additives, which includes assessment for cancer risks. A search of systematic reviews and meta-analyses was also conducted in addition to the main search for reference-mining purposes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Carry out abstract screening and study selection</title><p>The titles, abstracts and keywords of all identified articles were screened using Abstrackr™, an open source, web-based, citation screening tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The research team screened study abstracts using inclusion and exclusion criteria and assigned a decision (“yes”, “maybe” or “no”) to each abstract. Two rounds of pilot tests for a total of 1000 abstracts were screened by all reviewers to calibrate screening accuracy between reviewers. Discrepancies of the pilot abstracts were discussed among reviewers until complete agreement was reached and team members fully understood the selection criteria. The remainder of the abstracts (<italic>n</italic> = 11,830) were single-screened due to the large number of abstracts and budgetary constraints. Abstracts with a “yes” or “maybe” label were both included in step 1 of the evidence map and the full-text articles of these abstracts were retrieved for full-text screening. Citations with a “no” label were saved for record. Because of the single screening process, it is possible that a few abstracts were mistakenly rejected during this screening phase. In an effort to ensure all key studies were included, all included citations were cross-referenced with the reference list of relevant systematic reviews and meta-analyses. In step 2 (full-text screening), we followed the predefined study eligibility criteria (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) and recorded the reasons for rejection of each rejected article. About 5 % (<italic>n</italic> = 571) of the original citations were screened in for full-text review. Each full-text article was screened by one reviewer, and the screening decision of the first reviewer was then confirmed or disputed by a second reviewer. Discrepancies were resolved through consensus among all research team members.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Study eligibility criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Inclusion criteria</th><th>Exclusion criteria</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>• English language<break/>• Human subjects<break/>• Interventions studies (randomized or non-randomized control trials or single)<break/>• Adults; Pregnant women and infants (&gt;6 months)<break/>• Prospective cohort studies<break/>• FDA-approved sweeteners</td><td>• Animal studies<break/>• In vitro cell studies<break/>• Case–control, cross-sectional studies; Reviews, interviews, bibliographies, letters, or guidelines<break/>• Systematic reviews and meta-analysis<break/>• Cancer patients<break/>• Non-oral intake</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Carry out data extraction</title><p>The research team extracted data on a customized extraction form shared via Google Drive to facilitate collaboration among research team members and allow for simultaneous data entry. The minimal data to collect for an evidence-map database are the information related to the PI(E)COS (Population, Intervention/Exposure, Comparator, Outcome and Study design). The extraction form for the LCS evidence-map database was designed to collect the following data from each study: study design characteristics (study design, study duration), study population characteristics (baseline health status, age, sample size, anthropometrics), study interventions/exposures and comparisons (type of LCS, comparison or control group, number of people analyzed, form of administration), outcome information (all outcomes or endpoints of interest), the aim or hypothesis of the study and funding source of the study. The extraction form was designed and finalized by the research team lead, who has expertise in evidence-based research and methods. The evidence-map database was uploaded onto SRDR™, an open public data repository, and a database codebook is included in the supplemental material (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Classifications of outcome categories</title><p>One of the most important features of an evidence map is the cataloging of the large number and variety of outcomes reported in the published literature. This step typically occurs after data extraction since the scope of an evidence-map database is large. Thus, it is often difficult to pre-define all outcome categories of interest. The research team worked with the stakeholder panel to classify outcomes into clinically and biologically meaningful outcome categories that could be used in evidence-map analyses. The research team recorded outcomes reported in each publication and took the first attempt in identifying clinically and biologically relevant groups. Standardized coding was then developed for each outcome category. Feedback was sought from the stakeholder panel, and the outcome categories and coding were modified based on the final consensus of the stakeholder panel. Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the final list of outcomes for each outcome category that are reported in the studies included in the LCS evidence-map database. Specifically, outcomes related to appetite or satiety ratings such as hunger score and desire to eat were often rated by a visual analog scale (VAS) and were classified under the ‘Appetite’ category. Outcomes focused on neurological measurements and sensing signals by the brain were classified under the ‘Energy Sensing’ category. Body weight, body composition and changes in weight-related outcomes were classified under the ‘Body Weight or Composition’ category. The ‘Dietary Intake’ category included outcomes such as energy intake, dietary intake, food intake and carbohydrate intake, and finally the ‘Glycemic’ category included glucose, insulin and gastric hormones. Our stakeholder panel did not identify additional outcomes that were not reported in the literature. Both outcome categories and full outcome lists were included in the evidence-map database, which can be used in future analyses with current or new outcome category coding.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Outcomes of interest by outcome groups in the LCS evidence-map database</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Outcome groups</th><th>Outcomes of interest</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Appetite</td><td>Appetite ratings using a visual analog scale (VAS), hunger, desire to eat, fullness, prospective consumption, thirst, motivational and behavioral factors reported through questionnaire</td></tr><tr><td>Energy sensing by brain</td><td>Neurological measurements (fMRI, EEG), sensory rating (sweetness, intensity, pleasantness, sensory specific satiation), taste, perception and preference, taste reaction time</td></tr><tr><td>Body weight or body composition</td><td>Body weight, body composition, BMI, waist circumferences, weight or BMI changes</td></tr><tr><td>Dietary intake</td><td>Energy intake, dietary intake, food intake, carbohydrate intake, sugar intake, salt intake, water intake</td></tr><tr><td>Glycemic</td><td>Glucose, Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c), insulin concentration, insulin sensitivity, hypoglycemia, glucagon, glucose-dependent insulinotropic peptide (GIP), glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1), peptide tyrosine tyrosine (PYY), cholecystokinin (CCK), enterostatin, ghrelin, leptin, somatostatin, oxyntomodulin</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec>Additional filesAdditional file 1: Table S1.LCS search strategy and supplemental search strategy. Supplemental material. Low-calorie sweetener database manual and codebook. (DOCX 75 kb)Additional file 2:
LCS Database Manual and Codebook. (DOCX 56 kb)AbbreviationLCSlow-calorie-sweetenersCompeting interestsThe authors have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsDW and MC drafted the manuscript. MC designed and conceptualized this project, obtained funding, and provided administrative support. DW conducted the data analysis. MSW, OB and DW collected and extracted study data. OB coordinated the stakeholder engagement. MC, JPS, MSW and OB critically commented and revised the manuscript. JPS is one of the stakeholder panel members. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.AcknowledgementWe thank our stakeholder panel for their tremendous contribution toward this project. Panel members include: Sara Bleich, Andrew Bremer, Marion Franz, John Foreyt, Guy Johnson, Beth Manning, Rick Mattes, Allison Sylvetsky Meni, Scott Parrott, Xavier Pi-Sunyer, Babara Schneeman, Joanne Spahn, Dan Steffen, and Paula Ziegler. This study was supported by the International Life Sciences Institutes (ILSI) North America.References1.AlthuisMDWeedDLEvidence mapping: methodologic foundations and application to intervention and observational research on sugar-sweetened beverages and health outcomesAm J Clin Nutr20139837556810.3945/ajcn.113.058917238247222.HetrickSEParkerAGCallahanPPurcellREvidence mapping: illustrating an emerging methodology to improve evidence-based practice in youth mental healthJ Eval Clin Pract201016610253010.1111/j.1365-2753.2008.01112.x203378333.DahabrehIJHadarNChungMEmerging magnetic resonance imaging technologies for musculoskeletal imaging under loading stress: scope of the literatureAnn Intern Med201115596162410.7326/0003-4819-155-9-201111010-00009220419504.Sniltsveit BVM, Bhavsar A, Gaarder M. Evidence gap maps–a tool for promoting evidence-informed policy and prioritizing future research. The World Bank 2013.5.3Ie. International Initiative for Impact Evaluation. Evidence Gap Maps. 2015. http://www.3ieimpact.org/en/evaluation/evidence-gap-maps/. Accessed 8 Aug 2015.6.BraggePClavisiOTurnerTTavenderECollieAGruenRLThe Global Evidence Mapping Initiative: scoping research in broad topic areasBMC Med Res Methodol2011119210.1186/1471-2288-11-92216828707.GrantMJBoothAA typology of reviews: an analysis of 14 review types and associated methodologiesHealth Inf Libr J20092629110810.1111/j.1471-1842.2009.00848.x8.ChapmanEReveizLChamblissASangalangSBonfillXCochrane systematic reviews are useful to map research gaps for decreasing maternal mortalityJ Clin Epidemiol20136611051210.1016/j.jclinepi.2012.09.005231778999.HempelSTaylorSLMarshallNJMiake-LyeIMBeroesJMShanmanRVA evidence-based synthesis program reports. Evidence map of mindfulness2014Washington (DC)Department of Veterans Affairs (US)10.HempelSTaylorSLSollowayMRMiake-LyeIMBeroesJMShanmanRVA evidence-based synthesis program reports. Evidence map of Tai Chi2014Washington (DC)Department of Veterans Affairs (US)11.ArkseyHO’MalleyLScoping studies: towards a methodological frameworkInt J Soc Res Methodol20058193210.1080/136455703200011961612.SchmuckerCMotschallEAntesGMeerpohlJJMethods of evidence mapping. A systematic reviewBundesgesundheitsblatt, Gesundheitsforschung, Gesundheitsschutz201356101390710.1007/s00103-013-1818-y2397898413.DaudtHMvan MosselCScottSJEnhancing the scoping study methodology: a large, inter-professional team’s experience with Arksey and O’Malley’s frameworkBMC Med Res Methodol2013134810.1186/1471-2288-13-482352233314.SwithersSEArtificial sweeteners produce the counterintuitive effect of inducing metabolic derangementsTrends Endocrinol Metab20132494314110.1016/j.tem.2013.05.0052385026115.MillerPEPerezVLow-calorie sweeteners and body weight and composition: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials and prospective cohort studiesAm J Clin Nutr201410037657710.3945/ajcn.113.0828262494406016.GibsonSDHillJRabenABTuorilaHWidstromEConsensus statement on benefits of low-calorie sweetenersNutr Bull2014394386910.1111/nbu.1211617.WallaceBCSmallKBrodleyCELauJTrikalinosTADeploying an interactive machine learning system in an evidence-based practice center: abstrackrProc of the ACM International Health Informatics Symposium (IHI)20128192418.WangDDShams-WhiteMBrightOJChungMLow calorie-sweeteners and health201519.McKeownNChungMLivingstonKSawickiCWangDDBrownCDietary fiber database, version 1201520.ChungMBergerSWangDDBrownCMaJSackeyJSugars and health–evidence map201421.CottrellEWhitlockEKatoEUhlSBelinsonSChangCDefining the benefits of stakeholder engagement in systematic reviews2014Rockville (MD)AHRQ Methods for Effective Health Care22.CareyTSSandersGDViswanathanMTrikalinosTAKatoEChangSFramework for considering study designs for future research needs. Rockville (MD)2012
