<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMJ OpenBMJ OpenbmjopenbmjopenBMJ Open2044-6055BMJ Publishing GroupBMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR5168503bmjopen-2016-01257310.1136/bmjopen-2016-012573Complementary MedicineProtocol150616851710Keeping Weight Off: study protocol of an RCT to investigate brain changes associated with mindfulness-based stress reductionhttp://orcid.org/0000-0001-7292-6257FulwilerCarl1SiegelJulia A2AllisonJeroan3RosalMilagros C4BrewerJudson1KingJean A51Departments of Psychiatry and Medicine and Center for Mindfulness, University of Massachusetts Medical School,Shrewsbury, Massachusetts, USA2University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA3Department of Quantitative Health Sciences, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA4Department of Medicine, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA5Departments of Psychiatry, Neurology and Radiology, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USACorrespondence to Dr Carl Fulwiler; carl.fulwiler@umassmed.edu201630112016611e0125739520169920165102016Published by the BMJ Publishing Group Limited. For permission to use (where not already granted under a licence) please go to http://www.bmj.com/company/products-services/rights-and-licensing/2016This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/IntroductionObesity is a growing epidemic fuelled by unhealthy behaviours and associated with significant comorbidities and financial costs. While behavioural interventions produce clinically meaningful weight loss, weight loss maintenance is challenging. This may partially be due to failure to target stress and emotional reactivity. Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) reduces stress and emotional reactivity and may be a useful tool for behaviour change maintenance. This study seeks to provide a mechanistic understanding for clinical trials of the benefits of MBSR for weight loss maintenance by examining changes in functional connectivity (FC) and the association of these changes with clinical outcomes.Methods and analysisCommunity-dwelling individuals (n=80) who intentionally lost ≥5% of their body weight in the past year will be recruited and randomised to an MBSR programme or educational control. FC using resting-state functional MRI will be measured at baseline and 8 weeks. Psychological factors, health behaviours, body mass index and waist circumference will be measured at baseline, 8 weeks and 6 months post intervention. A 12-month telephone follow-up will assess self-reported weight. Analyses will characterise FC changes in response to MBSR in comparison with a control condition, assess the relationship between baseline FC status and pre–post MBSR changes in FC and investigate the association of FC change with changes in psychological factors and weight loss maintenance.Ethics and disseminationThe University of Massachusetts Medical School Institutional Review Board has approved this study, Declaration of Helsinki protocols are being followed, and patients will give written informed consent. The Independent Monitoring Committee will monitor protocol adherence. Results from the study will be disseminated to the medical community at conferences and submitted for publication in peer-reviewed journals when the last patient included has been followed up for 12 months.Trial registration numberNCT02189187.mindfulnessweight lossbehavior change maintenanceneuroimagingNational Center for Complementary and Integrative Healthhttp://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100008460R34 AT006963-01A1R34AT006963Strengths and limitations of this studyThis is a timely and innovative study that will advance the field of mindfulness research and increase understanding of its mechanisms of action, setting the stage for a comprehensive clinical trial.The intervention is low-risk, highly accessible, low-cost and is implemented in a real-world clinical population and community setting. The control course was specifically designed to serve as an attention control for mindfulness-based stress reduction.The cost of a neuroimaging biomarker could be considered a limitation for large-scale clinical trials, but the insights about neural mechanisms of change cannot be obtained with other methods.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Study design</title><p>The ‘Keeping Weight Off’ study is a randomised, prospective, two-armed, controlled trial. A sample of 80 participants from the community, who have intentionally lost at least 5% of their body weight during the previous year, will be equally randomised into two groups: an MBSR programme and a healthy living course (HLC)—an attention control specifically designed to be structurally equivalent to MBSR.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> The HLC uses the same format of 8-weekly classes lasting 2.5 hours, and controls for attention and other non-specific factors including staff interactions, psychoeducation about health and stress management, classroom format, homework, group process and data collection.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Our main outcome measures are resting-state FC, depression symptoms, BMI and waist circumference. FC, psychological factors, health behaviours, BMI and waist circumference will be measured at baseline and 8 weeks. Psychological factors, health behaviours, BMI and waist circumference will also be measured at 6 months. In addition, a telephone follow-up will be attempted on participants at 12 months to assess weight.</p><p>Total planned enrolment is 80 participants. Screening for eligibility criteria, baseline visits and follow-up visits will take place at University of Massachusetts Medical School (UMMS), Worcester, Massachusetts. All MBSR classes will be conducted at the UMMS Center for Mindfulness in Shrewsbury, Massachusetts.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Study participants</title><p>We will recruit participants who range in age from 25 to 60 (chosen to minimise age-related changes in FC), have intentionally lost ≥5% of their body weight during the previous year and are motivated to maintain this weight loss. Individuals will be excluded if they have participated in an MBSR course, regular meditation practice or any other form of meditative practice (such as yoga, Tai Chi or contemplative prayer), for more than an average of 20 min per week within the past 2 years. Full inclusion and exclusion criteria are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="BMJOPEN2016012573TB1">table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="BMJOPEN2016012573TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Eligibility criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inclusion criteria:</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exclusion criteria:</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Men and women</p></list-item><list-item><p>Right or left handed</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ages 25–60</p></list-item><list-item><p>Intentionally lost ≥5% of body weight during the previous year</p></list-item><list-item><p>Intending to maintain weight loss</p></list-item><list-item><p>BMI &gt;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> in the past 2 years and greater than 20.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup> at time of study entry</p></list-item><list-item><p>Under the care of a primary care physician for at least the last year prior to screening</p></list-item><list-item><p>Able to communicate by telephone with research staff</p></list-item><list-item><p>Have a healthcare provider, personal trainer or weight-loss counsellor who can complete and sign a form indicating the amount and timing of their weight loss OR have a dated photograph</p></list-item><list-item><p>or weight loss diary<xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Weight &gt;300 lbs (limitation of MRI scanner)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Prior participation in an MBSR course</p></list-item><list-item><p>Regular meditation practice (or any other form of meditative practice, such as yoga, Tai Chi, or contemplative prayer) for more than an average of 20 min/week within the past 2 years</p></list-item><list-item><p>Serious psychiatric, cognitive or medical disorder</p></list-item><list-item><p>Alcohol/substance abuse or dependence in past 6 months</p></list-item><list-item><p>Any conditions that are incompatible with MRI</p></list-item><list-item><p>Structural brain damage as determined by an independent neuroradiologist, based on T1W 3D TFE sagittal and T1W FFE axial images</p></list-item><list-item><p>History of an eating disorder, diabetes mellitus or medications for diabetes mellitus</p></list-item><list-item><p>Medication that affects weight (weight loss medications, corticosteroids, antipsychotics)</p></list-item><list-item><p>History of weight loss surgery</p></list-item><list-item><p>Participation in another weight management research study</p></list-item><list-item><p>Regain of &gt;3% of total body weight in the 2 months prior to study entry</p></list-item><list-item><p>Childbirth in the past 6 months</p></list-item><list-item><p>Claustrophobia, or any MRI incompatible implants</p></list-item><list-item><p>Pregnant or planning to become pregnant</p></list-item><list-item><p>Unable to consent</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>3D, three dimensional; BMI, Body Mass Index; FFE, Turbo Flash Field Echo; MBSR, mindfulness-based stress reduction; T1W, T1 weighted; TFE, Turbo Field Echo.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Eligible participants will proceed with the baseline visit prior to randomisation, including collection of demographic information about age, education, marital status, occupation and current employment status, followed by questionnaires and fMRI scan. The full study schedule of recruitment, treatment and assessments is described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="BMJOPEN2016012573TB2">table 2</xref>. All participants will provide informed consent. This process will be conducted by the study coordinator in person prior to the baseline visit, following the protocol established by the University of Massachusetts Institutional Review Board (IRB). Study staff will keep in touch with participants regarding attendance and homework completion and provide support and encouragement to continue with the intervention if participants express dissatisfaction. Participants who drop out of the intervention will be asked to return for all follow-up visits to complete all outcome data collection.</p><table-wrap id="BMJOPEN2016012573TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Study schedule of recruitment, treatment and assessments as a function of time points (according to the SPIRIT 2013 figure guidelines)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Duration of the study<hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recruitment</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment (8 weeks)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up (6 months)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up (12 months)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIME POINT</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>0</sub></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>1</sub></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>2</sub></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>3</sub></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t<sub>4</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">RECRUITMENT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Screening for inclusion/exclusion criteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Informed consent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Assignment to treatment arms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">TREATMENT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MBSR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HLC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">ASSESSMENT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SCID-IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> fMRI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Weight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Height (and BMI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Waist circumference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CES-D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PSS-14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> STAI-T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> STAXI-II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Satisfaction with life</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Emotion Regulation Questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Eating Behaviour Inventory</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Internal Disinhibition Subscale of the Eating Inventory</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Paffenbarger Physical Activity Scale</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CES-D, Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale; HLC, healthy living course; MBSR, mindfulness-based stress reduction; PSS-14, Perceived Stress Scale; SCID-IV, Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV; SPIRIT, Standard Protocol Items: Recommendations for Interventional Trials; STAI-T, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory—trait version; STAXI-II, State-Trait Anger Expression Inventory-II.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Study recruitment</title><p>Recruitment will be conducted using advertising in the community (internet, flyers and social media) of Worcester County, which has a population of over 800 000, as well as a two-stage process to recruit outpatients from the UMass Memorial Medical Center using the electronic medical record. The largest healthcare system in Central and Western Massachusetts, the medical centre has a large population from which to draw, with nearly 70 000 patient visits for primary care alone, and a Weight Center that sees nearly 1000 new patients per year. Our team has an excellent record of recruitment and retention in our previous overweight/obese subjects using these methods.</p><p>First, with a Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) waiver authorisation a search query will be conducted with basic eligibility criteria, and second, identified records will be reviewed to exclude causes of weight loss such as serious illness or weight loss medications. Web-based and telephone screening will determine whether they meet inclusion criteria. Further screening will be done in person to gather a medical history and complete the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV (SCID) to exclude participants with a serious psychiatric, cognitive or medical disorder or a history of alcohol or substance abuse or dependence in the past 6 months.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Randomisation and study blinding</title><p>Study participants will be equally randomised to either the MBSR intervention arm or HLC arm based on a permuted blocks randomisation scheme. In this procedure, treatment allocations will be made within blocks so that the numbers assigned to each arm are equal after each block has been filled. Blocks of various sizes (2, 4, 6) will be used in random order, to facilitate allocation concealment, that is, to make it nearly impossible to determine the treatment assignment based on a pattern of previous treatment allocations. Randomisation will be implemented using sealed envelopes by the study coordinator who will be the only member of the research team who is not blind to treatment assignment. A unique identification number will help to ensure that blindness is maintained throughout the study. All members of the research team involved in data analysis will be blind to treatment assignment.</p><p>To address the possibility that an imbalanced distribution of baseline FC could mask important findings, we will employ a non-stratified permuted-block randomised design with an interim analysis of the distribution of baseline FC. If important imbalances are found, we will implement recruitment strategies to increase enrolment of participants who have baseline FC with a specified range combined with covariate-adaptive randomisation techniques. Residual imbalances will be addressed with post hoc statistical adjustment.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Assessments</title><sec id="s2e1"><title>Resting-state FC</title><p>In contrast to task-evoked functional and effective connectivity studies, resting-state fMRI enables examination of the brain's intrinsic functional connections in the absence of externally controlled stimuli or tasks.<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> FC is responsive to changing levels of stress,<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> intense training on a task<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> and recently, meditation practice including MBSR.<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> FC has been shown to have remarkable consistency and moderate-to-high test–test reliability over periods of months to a year as well.<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>
<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> All MRIs will be acquired on the 3T scanner (Philips Achieva) in the UMMS Advanced MRI Center. Three-dimensional high-resolution structural T1-weighted MR images will be obtained to provide anatomical landmarks. Following the structural imaging, resting-state fMRI data will be collected. Participants will be instructed to remain relaxed with eyes closed as fMRI images are continuously collected for 10 min. The duration of the entire MRI procedure will be 30 min.</p></sec><sec id="s2e2"><title>Psychological symptoms</title><p>The Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D)<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> depression symptom score is a primary outcome. Additional outcomes include perceived stress, anxiety, anger, positive affect and emotion regulation, which will be assessed using the following measures, respectively: the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS-14),<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory—trait version (STAI-T),<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> the State-Trait Anger Expression Inventory-II (STAXI-II) trait anger subscale,<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> the Satisfaction with Life Scale<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> and the Emotion Regulation Questionnaire.<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></p></sec><sec id="s2e3"><title>Health behaviours</title><p>Health behaviours will be assessed using the Eating Behaviour Inventory,<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> the Internal Disinhibition Subscale of the Eating Inventory,<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> the Paffenbarger Physical Activity Scale<xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> and the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI),<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s2e4"><title>Anthropometrics</title><p>Procedures are adapted from the Centers for Disease Control (CDC)'s Anthropometry Procedures Manual.<xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> For the measurement of height and weight, the Seca 213 Portable stadiometer and the tanita, BWB-800 electronic scale will be used and measurements will be taken twice and averaged to assure reliability. Measurement of waist circumference will be taken directly on the skin using measuring tape placed just above top of the iliac crest on each side.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Potential mediators and confounders</title><p>Intervention engagement will be assessed with class attendance and a home practice log. Treatment expectancy and credibility will be assessed with the Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ)<xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> modified slightly to substitute the word ‘Class’ for ‘Therapy’ in the instructions. Secondary analyses will examine how change in FC is explained by (1) class attendance, (2) self-reported time in homework practice, (3) self-reported time for each specific component of the multifaceted training programme and (4) trait mindfulness as measured by the Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ).<xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Interventions</title><sec id="s2g1"><title>Experimental condition: MBSR</title><p>MBSR, described above, is taught in eight weekly classes and one all-day retreat. Homework assignments include formal meditation practices and informal practices during daily life. Classroom activities teach formal meditation practices including sitting meditation, body scan, mindful yoga and walking meditation. Participants also learn to bring awareness in the present moment to aspects of daily life and apply this practice to stressful experiences in order to avoid reflexive or conditioned reactions. The goal of MBSR is to provide participants with these skills for lifelong self-management.</p><p>The MBSR classes are taught by certified teachers from the UMass Center for Mindfulness. All teachers have completed the rigorous training and certification for MBSR through the Center for Mindfulness. To further assure fidelity, each class will be reviewed in weekly sessions with a coinvestigator. In addition, the principal investigators will routinely convene the entire clinical research team to monitor the overall fidelity of the MBSR intervention.</p></sec><sec id="s2g2"><title>Attention control: HLC</title><p>The HLC was specifically designed to serve as a control condition for MBSR.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> HLC consists of eight weekly 2-hour classes. Sessions consist of lectures and discussion on the following topics: healthy living, healthy eating, physical activity and health, sleep and health, stress management, time management and unhealthy behaviours (smoking, drinking). The HLC is designed to control for attention and other non-specific factors including staff interactions, psychoeducation about health and stress management, classroom format, homework, group process and data collection.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Data collection</title><p>Electronic data capture (EDC, Research Electronic Data Capture (REDCap)) will be used for all data collection except imaging. Surveys for psychological symptoms, health behaviours and potential mediators and confounders are programmed into the EDC system. During research visits, participants will enter survey responses directly into this system and research staff will enter screening and anthropometric data with periodic checks for quality assurance. All data will be maintained in a secure location accessible only to study personnel. For MRI measures, data will be analysed blind to intervention group by two fMRI experts who perform cross-validity checks.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Data analysis and sample size considerations</title><p>We based the study sample size on Hypothesis 1, powered to detect an effect size of 0.32 SDs. This moderate Cohen effect size<xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref> represents differential overtime change for the intervention versus comparison group cast in SD units. The study design calls for a baseline measurement and two follow-up measurements. In addition, we assumed a two-tailed α error of 0.05, and a within-person correlation for overtime measurement of 0.8.<xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> With these assumptions, 40 participants in each group are needed for 80% power. We will enrol 100 participants (50 randomised to each arm) and allow for up to 20% loss to follow-up, for an effective sample size of 80.</p><p>Statistical analysis will begin with univariate summaries of data distributions and examination of longitudinal trends with graphic displays. Bivariate associations will then be examined using the χ<sup>2</sup> test, analysis of variance (ANOVA), and the Spearman correlation test. Hypotheses 1 and 2 focus on overtime differences between the two study groups, while Hypotheses 2 and 3 focus on overtime differences for the combined sample. Hypotheses will be formally tested using generalised linear mixed models that represent the clustering of observations within participants as a random intercept, adopt an appropriate link and distribution for the specific outcome and parameterise the intervention effect as a group-time intervention, when appropriate.<xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> To preserve the power of randomisation, hypothesis testing will be performed on an intent-to-treat basis. As a secondary aim, mediation analysis will determine how change in FC is explained by markers of intervention adherence using techniques as described by MacKinnon.<xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>
<xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> Sensitivity analyses with multiple imputation with chained equations will address missing data.</p><p>Imaging data is preprocessed using Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM8) software (Wellcome Department of Cognitive Neurology, London, UK) running under the MATLAB environment (Mathworks, Sherborn, Massachusetts, USA). The data are initially corrected for motion (threshold of 2 mm). Further preprocessing of the data includes (1) slice scan time correction, (2) spatial smoothing using a three-dimensional Gaussian filter (4-mm full width at half maximum (FWHM)) and (3) voxel-wise linear detrending and 0.01–0.08 Hz band-pass filtering. Structural and functional data of each participant are then be transformed to standard stereotaxic space<xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref> to facilitate group analysis.</p><p>Following the preprocessing steps, FC will be generated using correlational analysis. Left and right amygdalae are used as separate seed regions of interest (ROI). FC maps from each individual seed will then be calculated for each individual subject using Resting-State fMRI Data Analysis Toolkit (REST, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.restfmri.net">http://www.restfmri.net</ext-link>). Each seed ROI will be evaluated using two-way repeated measures ANOVA on a voxel-by-voxel basis (factors: group and imaging day) at the threshold of p&lt;0.05 after accounting for multiple comparisons using the criteria of false discovery rate (FDR).<xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref> Voxels with significantly changed FC within each ROI will then be averaged to generate the FC change for the ROI. This procedure will yield a single value of amygdala-orbitofrontal FC for each participant at each point in time. All ROI definitions are based on Automated Anatomical Labelling (AAL)<xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> built in the MARSeille Boîte À Région (MarsBAR) toolbox of SPM8. Image analysis will be done blind to group membership.</p><p>As a secondary analysis, we will explore FC changes in other brain networks following MBSR using other seed regions. For example, other cortical regions that have been implicated in modulation of limbic reactivity (eg, anterior cingulate) will be examined using a hypothesis-driven approach.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Ethical considerations and dissemination plans</title><p>This study is registered as a national clinical trial (NCT02189187) and Declaration of Helsinki protocols are being followed, and patients will give written informed consent. Protocol adherence will be monitored by the Independent Monitoring Committee (for full WHO Trial Registration Data Set information see online <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">supplementary appendix</xref>). Results from the study will be disseminated to the medical community at conferences and submitted for publication in peer-reviewed journals when the last patient included has been followed up for 12 months. Negative and inconclusive as well as positive results will be published or made publicly available through the study website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.umassmed.edu/keepingweightoff">http://www.umassmed.edu/keepingweightoff</ext-link>.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-012573.supp1</object-id><label>Supplementary appendix</label><p><inline-supplementary-material id="ss1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2016-012573supp_appendix.pdf" content-type="local-data"/></p></supplementary-material></sec></sec>The authors thank Dr Nanyin Zhang and Dr Wei Huang for technical assistance with study design. We also extend our sincere gratitude to Dr Saki Santorelli, Executive Director of the Center for Mindfulness at the University of Massachusetts Medical School, for his support and contributions, and the staff and teachers of the Center for Mindfulness for their assistance. The project was conducted at the UMMS Advanced MR Imaging Center with support from Dr Shaokuan Zheng.Contributors: CF conceptualised the study, and JAK, JA, MCR and JB participated in the study design. CF, JAK, and JAS collected data. CF and JAS wrote and all authors revised the article and approved the final version to be published.Funding: The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)) provided funding for this trial (grants R34AT006963 and R34 AT006963-01A1 to CF and JAK). The design of this trial was reviewed and approved by NCCIH's Office of Clinical and Regulatory Affairs. Support was also provided by an award from the UMMS Department of Radiology.Disclaimer: The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health or the UMMS Department of Radiology Advanced MR Imaging Center.Competing interests: None declared.Ethics approval: University of Massachusetts Medical School Institutional Review Board.Provenance and peer review: Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.Data sharing statement: For investigators expressing interest in data analyses, we will welcome proposals for consideration by the study investigators. If there is no overlap in research interests, necessary data files will be generated and provided, and writing groups identified. We are sensitive to the potential for identification of participants and loss of confidentiality. Consequently, certain sensitive types of data may not be released. However, in these cases analyses may be performed by our group and sent to the investigators for interpretation.References1OgdenC, CarrollM
Prevalence of overweight, obesity, and extreme obesity among adults: United States, trends 1976–1980 through 2007–2008. CDC Natl Cent Heal Stat.
2010
http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/hestat/obesity_adult_11_12/obesity_adult_11_12.htm2SchroederSA
We can do better--improving the health of the American people. N Engl J Med.
2007;357:1221–8. doi:10.1056/NEJMsa073350178817533WangYC, McPhersonK, MarshT
Health and economic burden of the projected obesity trends in the USA and the UK. Lancet.
2011;378:815–25. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60814-3218727504RenehanAG, TysonM, EggerM
Body-mass index and incidence of cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective observational studies. Lancet.
2008;371:569–78. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60269-X182803275KearnsK, DeeA, FitzgeraldAP
Chronic disease burden associated with overweight and obesity in Ireland: the effects of a small BMI reduction at population level. BMC Public Health.
2014;14:143
doi:10.1186/1471-2458-14-143245121516DombrowskiSU, KnittleK, AvenellA
Long term maintenance of weight loss with non-surgical interventions in obese adults: systematic review and meta-analyses of randomised controlled trials. BMJ.
2014;348:g2646
doi:10.1136/bmj.g2646251341007MarcusBH, WilliamsDM, DubbertPM
What we know and what we need to know: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association Council on Nutrition, Physical Activity, and Metabolism (Subcommittee on Physical Activity); Council on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young; and the Interdisciplinary Working Group on Quality of Care and Outcomes Research.
Circulation.
2006;114:2739–52. doi:10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.179683171459958HainerV, ToplakH, MitrakouA
Treatment modalities of obesity: what fits whom?
Diabetes Care.
2008;31(Suppl 2):S269–77. doi:10.2337/dc08-s265182274969HajekP, SteadLF, WestR
Relapse prevention interventions for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev.
2009;(1):CD003999
doi:10.1002/14651858.CD003999.pub31916022810MerrillRM, AldanaSG, GreenlawRL
Can newly acquired healthy behaviors persist? An analysis of health behavior decay. Prev Chronic Dis.
2008;5:A13.1808200211OryMG, Lee SmithM, MierN
The science of sustaining health behavior change: the health maintenance consortium. Am J Health Behav.
2010;34:647–59.2060469112BjörntorpP, RosmondR
Obesity and cortisol. Nutrition.
2000;16:924–36. doi:10.1016/S0899-9007(00)00422-61105459813LattimoreP, MaxwellL
Cognitive load, stress, and disinhibited eating. Eat Behav.
2004;5:315–24. doi:10.1016/j.eatbeh.2004.04.0091548844614O'ConnorDB, JonesF, ConnerM
Effects of daily hassles and eating style on eating behavior. Health Psychol.
2008;27:S20–31. doi:10.1037/0278-6133.27.1.S201824810215WallisDJ, HetheringtonMM
Emotions and eating. Self-reported and experimentally induced changes in food intake under stress. Appetite.
2009;52:355–62. doi:10.1016/j.appet.2008.11.0071907117116CosciF, PistelliF, LazzariniN
Nicotine dependence and psychological distress: outcomes and clinical implications in smoking cessation. Psychol Res Behav Manag.
2011;4:119–28. doi:10.2147/PRBM.S142432211454217ElfhagK, RössnerS
Who succeeds in maintaining weight loss? A conceptual review of factors associated with weight loss maintenance and weight regain. Obes Rev.
2005;6:67–85. doi:10.1111/j.1467-789X.2005.00170.x1565503918WingRR, PapandonatosG, FavaJL
Maintaining large weight losses: the role of behavioral and psychological factors. J Consult Clin Psychol.
2008;76:1015–21. doi:10.1037/a00141591904596919EversKE, ProchaskaJO, JohnsonJL
A randomized clinical trial of a population- and transtheoretical model-based stress-management intervention. Heal Psychol.
2006;25:521–9. doi:10.1037/0278-6133.25.4.52120MansyurCL, PavlikVN, HymanDJ
Self-efficacy and barriers to multiple behavior change in low-income African Americans with hypertension. J Behav Med.
2013;36:75–85. doi:10.1007/s10865-012-9403-72232291021NgDM, JefferyRW
Relationships between perceived stress and health behaviors in a sample of working adults. Health Psychol.
2003;22:638–42. doi:10.1037/0278-6133.22.6.6381464086222BenninghovenD, KadukA, WiegandU
Influence of anxiety on the course of heart disease after acute myocardial infarction—Risk factor or protective function?
Psychother Psychosom.
2006;75:56–61. doi:10.1159/0000892271636187523GariepyG, NitkaD, SchmitzN
The association between obesity and anxiety disorders in the population: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Obes.
2010;34:407–19. doi:10.1038/ijo.2009.25224KuhlEA, FauerbachJA, BushDE
Relation of anxiety and adherence to risk-reducing recommendations following myocardial infarction. Am J Cardiol.
2009;103:1629–34. doi:10.1016/j.amjcard.2009.02.0141953906725CastroY, KendzorDE, BusinelleMS
Structural and predictive equivalency of the Wisconsin smoking withdrawal scale across three racial/ethnic groups. Nicotine Tob Res.
2011;13:548–55. doi:10.1093/ntr/ntr0392145491226KahlerCW, StrongDR, NiauraR
Hostility in smokers with past major depressive disorder: relation to smoking patterns, reasons for quitting, and cessation outcomes. Nicotine Tob Res.
2004;6:809–18. doi:10.1080/14622200420002825461570091627PattersonF, KerrinK, WileytoEP
Increase in anger symptoms after smoking cessation predicts relapse. Drug Alcohol Depend.
2008;95:173–6. doi:10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2008.01.0131832864228OgedegbeGO, Boutin-FosterC, WellsMT
A randomized controlled trial of positive-affect intervention and medication adherence in hypertensive African Americans. Arch Intern Med.
2012;172:322–6. doi:10.1001/archinternmed.2011.13072226959229PetersonJC, CharlsonME, HoffmanZ
A randomized controlled trial of positive-affect induction to promote physical activity after percutaneous coronary intervention. Arch Intern Med.
2012;172:329–36. doi:10.1001/archinternmed.2011.13112226958930Kabat-ZinnJ
Mindfulness-based interventions in context: past, present, and future. Clin Psychol Sci Pract.
2003;10:144–56. doi:10.1093/clipsy.bpg01631OuwensMA, SchifferAA, VisserLI
Mindfulness and eating behaviour styles in morbidly obese males and females. Appetite.
2015;87:62–7. doi:10.1016/j.appet.2014.11.0302547868732GoyalM, SinghS, SibingaEMS
Meditation programs for psychological stress and well-being: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Intern Med.
2014;174:357–68. doi:10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.130182439519633FulwilerC, BrewerJA, SinnottS
Mindfulness-based interventions for weight loss and CVD risk management. Curr Cardiovasc Risk Rep.
2015;9
doi:10.1007/s12170-015-0474-134MasonAE, LustigRH, BrownRR
Acute responses to opioidergic blockade as a biomarker of hedonic eating among obese women enrolled in a mindfulness-based weight loss intervention trial. Appetite.
2015;91:311–20. doi:10.1016/j.appet.2015.04.0622593143335KhouryB, LecomteT, FortinG
Mindfulness-based therapy: a comprehensive meta-analysis. Clin Psychol Rev.
2013;33:
763–71. doi:10.1016/j.cpr.2013.05.0052379685536RolandLT, LenzeEJ, HardinFM
Effects of mindfulness based stress reduction therapy on subjective bother and neural connectivity in chronic tinnitus. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg.
2015;152:919–26. doi:10.1177/01945998155715562571535037KilpatrickLA, SuyenobuBY, SmithSR
Impact of mindfulness-based stress reduction training on intrinsic brain connectivity. Neuroimage.
2011;56:290–8. doi:10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.02.0342133444238TarenAA, GianarosPJ, GrecoCM
Mindfulness meditation training alters stress-related amygdala resting state functional connectivity: a randomized controlled trial. Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci.
2015;10:1758–68. doi:10.1093/scan/nsv0662604817639CreswellJD, TarenAA, LindsayEK
Alterations in resting state functional connectivity link mindfulness meditation with reduced interleukin-6: a randomized controlled trial. Biol Psychiatry.
2016;80:53–61. doi:10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.01.0082702151440KattermanSN, KleinmanBM, HoodMM
Mindfulness meditation as an intervention for binge eating, emotional eating, and weight loss: a systematic review. Eat Behav.
2014;15:197–204. doi:10.1016/j.eatbeh.2014.01.0052485480441PbertL, MadisonJM, DrukerS
Effect of mindfulness training on asthma quality of life and lung function: a randomised controlled trial. Thorax.
2012;67:769–76. doi:10.1136/thoraxjnl-2011-2002532254489242BiswalB, YetkinFZ, HaughtonVM
Functional connectivity in the motor cortex of resting human brain using echo-planar MRI. Magn Reson Med.
1995;34:537–41. doi:10.1002/mrm.1910340409852402143FoxMD, RaichleME
Spontaneous fluctuations in brain activity observed with functional magnetic resonance imaging. Nat Rev Neurosci.
2007;8:700–11. doi:10.1038/nrn22011770481244ListonC, McEwenBS, CaseyBJ
Psychosocial stress reversibly disrupts prefrontal processing and attentional control. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA
2009;106:912–17. doi:10.1073/pnas.08070411061913941245LewisCM, BaldassarreA, CommitteriG
Learning sculpts the spontaneous activity of the resting human brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA
2009;106:17558–63. doi:10.1073/pnas.09024551061980506146BrewerJA, WorhunskyPD, GrayJR
Meditation experience is associated with differences in default mode network activity and connectivity. Proc Natl Acad Sci.
2011;108:20254–9. doi:10.1073/pnas.11120291082211419347KilpatrickLA, SuyenobuBY, SmithSR
Impact of mindfulness-based stress reduction training on intrinsic brain connectivity. Neuroimage.
2011;56:290–8. doi:10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.02.0342133444248ShehzadZ, KellyAMC, ReissPT
The resting brain: unconstrained yet reliable. Cereb Cortex.
2009;19:2209–29. doi:10.1093/cercor/bhn2561922114449ZuoXN, KellyC, AdelsteinJS
Reliable intrinsic connectivity networks: test-retest evaluation using ICA and dual regression approach. Neuroimage.
2010;49:2163–77. doi:10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.0801989653750RadloffL
The CES-D scale: a self-report depression scale for research in the general population. Appl Psychol Meas.
1977;1:385–401. doi:10.1177/01466216770010030651CohenS, KamarckT, MermelsteinR
A global measure of perceived stress. J Health Soc Behav.
1983;24:385–96. doi:10.2307/2136404666841752SpielbergerCD, GorsuchRL, LushenePR
Manual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory. Palo Alto, CA: Consulting Psychologists Press, 1983.53SpielbergerC
State-Trait Anger Expression Inventory-2, Professional Manual. Psychol Assess Resour Inc., 1999:1–7.54DienerE, EmmonsRA, LarsenRJ
The satisfaction with life scale. J Pers Assess.
1985;49:71–5. doi:10.1207/s15327752jpa4901_131636749355GrossJJ, JohnOP
Individual differences in two emotion regulation processes: implications for affect, relationships, and well-being. J Pers Soc Psychol.
2003;85:348–62. doi:10.1037/0022-3514.85.2.3481291657556StunkardAJ, MessickS
The three-factor eating questionnaire to measure dietary restraint, disinhibition and hunger. J Psychosom Res.
1985;29:71–83.398148057NiemeierHM, PhelanS, FavaJL
Internal disinhibition predicts weight regain following weight loss and weight loss maintenance. Obes (Silver Spring).
2007;15:2485–94. doi:10.1038/oby.2007.29558PaffenbargerRSJr, BlairSN, LeeIM
Measurement of physical activity to assess health effects in free-living populations. Med Sci Sport Exerc.
1993;25:60–70.59BuysseDJ, ReynoldsCF, MonkTH
The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry Res.
1989;28:193–213. doi:10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4274877160Anthropometry procedures manual. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES), 2007.61DevillyGJ, BorkovecTD
Psychometric properties of the credibility/expectancy questionnaire. J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry
2000;31:73–86. doi:10.1016/S0005-7916(00)00012-41113211962BaerRA, SmithGT, LykinsE
Construct validity of the five facet mindfulness questionnaire in meditating and nonmeditating samples. Assessment.
2008;15:329–42. doi:10.1177/10731911073130031831059763CohenJ
A power primer. Psychol Bull.
1992;112:155–9. doi:10.1037/0033-2909.112.1.1551956568364FrisonL, PocockSJ
Repeated measures in clinical trials: analysis using mean summary statistics and its implications for design. Stat Med.
1992;11:1685–704. doi:10.1002/sim.4780111304148505365Rabe-HeskethS, SkrondalA
Multilevel and longitudinal modeling using Stata. Am Statistician
2006;60:293–4. doi:10.1198/tas.2006.s5666BaronRM, KennyDA
The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations. J Pers Soc Psychol.
1986;51:1173–82. doi:10.1037/0022-3514.51.6.1173380635467MacKinnonDP
Introduction to statistical mediation analysis. Mahwah, NJ: Erlbaum; 2008.68TalairachJ, TournouxP
Co-Planar Stereotaxic Atlas of the Human Brain: 3-Dimensional Proportional System: an Approach to Cerebral Imaging. Hardcover
1988;39
doi:10.1111/mono.1208369GenoveseCR, LazarNA, NicholsT
Thresholding of statistical maps in functional neuroimaging using the false discovery rate. Neuroimage.
2002;15:870–8. doi:10.1006/nimg.2001.10371190622770Tzourio-MazoyerN, LandeauB, PapathanassiouD
Automated anatomical labeling of activations in SPM using a macroscopic anatomical parcellation of the MNI MRI single-subject brain. Neuroimage.
2002;15:273–89. doi:10.1006/nimg.2001.09781177199571WingRR, TateDF, GorinAA
A self-regulation program for maintenance of weight loss. N Engl J Med.
2006;355:1563–71. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa06188317035649
