<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front Hum NeurosciFront Hum NeurosciFront. Hum. Neurosci.Frontiers in Human Neuroscience1662-5161Frontiers Media S.A.413727810.3389/fnhum.2014.00630NeuroscienceHypothesis and Theory ArticleThe development of an RDoC-based treatment program for adolescent depression: “Training for Awareness, Resilience, and Action” (TARA)Henje BlomEva12*DuncanLarissa G.34HoTiffany C.2ConnollyColm G.2LeWinnKaja Z.2ChesneyMargaret45HechtFrederick M.45YangTony T.21Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska InstitutetStockholm, Sweden2Department of Psychiatry, Division of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University of California San FranciscoSan Francisco, CA, USA3Department of Family and Community Medicine, University of California San FranciscoSan Francisco, CA, USA4Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, University of California San FranciscoSan Francisco, CA, USA5Department of Medicine, University of California San FranciscoSan Francisco, CA, USAEdited by: Laura Schmalzl, University of California San Diego, USAReviewed by: Norman Farb, Baycrest, Canada; Emiliana Simon-Thomas, University of California Berkeley, USA*Correspondence: Eva Henje Blom, Department of Clinical Neuroscience, Karolinska Institutet, Retzius Vag 8, A2:3, 17177 Stockholm, Sweden; Department of Psychiatry, Division of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University of California San Francisco, 401 Parnassus Avenue,San Francisco, CA 94143, USA e-mail: eva.henjeblom@ki.se; eva.henjeblom@ucsf.eduThis article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Human Neuroscience.19820142014863023420142872014Copyright © 2014 Henje Blom, Duncan, Ho, Connolly, LeWinn, Chesney, Hecht and Yang.2014 This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Major depressive disorder (MDD) is one of the current leading causes of disability worldwide. Adolescence is a vulnerable period for the onset of depression, with MDD affecting 8–20% of all youth. Traditional treatment methods have not been sufficiently effective to slow the increasing prevalence of adolescent depression. We therefore propose a new model for the treatment of adolescent depression – Training for Awareness, Resilience, and Action (TARA) – that is based on current understanding of developmental and depression neurobiology. The TARA model is aligned with the Research Domain Criteria (RDoC) of the National Institute of Mental Health. In this article, we first address the relevance of RDoC to adolescent depression. Second, we identify the major RDoC domains of function involved in adolescent depression and organize them in a way that gives priority to domains thought to be driving the psychopathology. Third, we select therapeutic training strategies for TARA based on current scientific evidence of efficacy for the prioritized domains of function in a manner that maximizes time, resources, and feasibility. The TARA model takes into consideration the developmental limitation in top-down cognitive control in adolescence and promotes bottom-up strategies such as vagal afference to decrease limbic hyperactivation and its secondary effects. The program has been informed by mindfulness-based therapy and yoga, as well as modern psychotherapeutic techniques. The treatment program is semi-manualized, progressive, and applied in a module-based approach designed for a group setting that is to be conducted one session per week for 12 weeks. We hope that this work may form the basis for a novel and more effective treatment strategy for adolescent depression, as well as broaden the discussion on how to address this challenge.adolescent depressionRDoCtreatment developmentemotion regulationattention trainingyoga-based movementmindfulnessALIGNMENT WITH THE NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF MENTAL HEALTH’S RESEARCH DOMAIN CRITERIAThe National Institute of Mental Health’s (NIMH) RDoC Project, as described by Insel et al. (2010) intends to “develop a research program which incorporates data on pathophysiology in ways that eventually will help identify new targets for treatment development, detect subgroups for treatment selection, and provide a better match between research findings and clinical decision making” (Insel et al., 2010). It is based on the assumption that mental illnesses are related to dysfunction of relevant brain circuits, which can be identified by clinical neuroscience. The levels of analysis progress from measures of circuitry function upward to clinical manifestations or downward to the genetic and molecular/cellular factors influencing these functions. The RDoC project identifies five broad domains of function, which may contribute to psychopathology in varying degrees across a range of clinically defined psychiatric disorders (Insel et al., 2010): negative valence, positive valence, cognition, social processes and arousal/modulation. The structure of the RDoC is described as “a matrix in which the rows represent various constructs grouped hierarchically into broad domains of function. The columns of the matrix denote different levels of analysis, from genetic, molecular, and cellular levels, proceeding to the circuit-level to the level of the individual, family environment, and social context” (Insel et al., 2010). For a graphic illustration of the RDoC matrix, see (http://www.nimh.nih.gov/research-priorities/rdoc/nimh-research-domain-criteria-rdoc.shtml#toc_matrix).The application of the RDoC approach instead of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM) system is especially relevant in the research field of adolescent depression. The DSM diagnostic criteria for adolescent MDD have low diagnostic validity and specificity, with unclear diagnostic boundaries (Costello et al., 2003; Ford et al., 2003; Korczak and Goldstein, 2009; Alexandrino-Silva et al., 2012; Henje Blom et al., 2014; Schuch et al., 2014). Psychiatric comorbidity is also highly prevalent in adolescent depression (Angold and Costello, 1993; Middeldorp et al., 2005; Spencer, 2006; Hettema, 2008). These factors contribute to heterogeneous sample configurations when recruiting depressed adolescents for research on the basis of DSM criteria and makes it very hard to tailor an effective treatment for the heterogeneous population that the DSM MDD diagnosis will encompass. Consequently, from a neuroscientific research perspective it may be more relevant to study the different brain circuits implicated in adolescent depression, such as those important to emotion regulation, attention, motivation, stress responses, social cognition, reward processing, and neuro-vegetative functions in patients who may potentially span multiple DSM diagnoses (Joormann and Goodman, 2014). Ultimately, brain development should also be taken into account in the RDoC constructs since the implicated brain circuits mature within different time frames and thus give rise to age-dependent symptomatology (Drevets et al., 2008). The neurocircuitry implied in adolescent depression often overlaps between different domains and constructs. Therefore, to maximize time, resources, and feasibility in designing an intervention model for adolescent depression, we suggest specific neural circuits to be targeted in our treatment model rather than all of the neurocircuitry described in each construct. While a RDoC based approach to develop a treatment program for geriatric depression has previously been developed and applied (Alexopoulos and Arean, 2014), our approach to use the RDoC in combination with developmental aspects of the brain as the foundation for creating a treatment model for adolescent depression is the first of its kind.The transition from the DSM system to RDoC is a challenge in our research design, since on the one hand we have adolescent depression as a starting point, which is a diagnostic entity (i.e., MDD) that is constituted of symptoms that may arise from different RDoC constructs and originate in different neural pathways, and on the other hand we try to tease out distinct neurocircuitry that have a behavior or symptom-related feature which is possible to identify across different DSM diagnostic entities. Our solution to this challenge is a pragmatic one: to base our hypothesis on the most common clinical manifestations of adolescent depression, which is not congruent with the MDD DSM categories and which extend beyond one specified RDoC construct. Consequently, both unspecific and specific symptoms according to the DSM will be addressed.In summary, the RDoC approach gives us an opportunity to address specific dimensions of psychopathology in a hierarchical manner according to what we hypothesize drives the pathophysiology of adolescent depression. For instance, giving priority to target anxious arousal, worrying and rumination specifically, allows us to assess these dimensions from a neuroscience perspective. We aim to find out whether this approach will aid the development of a more targeted and efficient treatment for adolescent depressive symptoms.BRAIN DEVELOPMENT AND VULNERABILITY TO DEPRESSIONDuring childhood, the brain undergoes an overproduction of synapses and gray matter. Throughout normal brain development, excess neural connections are then progressively pruned (Giorgio et al., 2010). Subcortical areas, such as the brainstem and limbic structures involved in basic functions and emotional processing mature earlier in life (Gogtay et al., 2004). Higher order cortical regions, specifically the prefrontal and frontal cortices responsible for executive functioning and cognitive control are not fully developed until the mid-20’s (Giorgio et al., 2010; Fjell et al., 2012). Thus, the adolescent brain differs from the adult brain in frontal development and frontolimbic connections (Gogtay et al., 2004). It has been suggested that altered development of these neural circuits increases the risk for depression (Andersen and Teicher, 2008; Pandey et al., 2013). The differing rates between subcortical and cortical maturation during adolescence may increase vulnerability to emotional reactivity, as the absence of effective top-down regulation from prefrontal and frontal regions on limbic reactivity may be a possible contributing mechanism to developing depressive symptoms (Cunningham et al., 2002; Gogtay et al., 2004; Yurgelun-Todd and Killgore, 2006). This neural pattern of development that subserves limited top-down control may translate into behavioral patterns such as impulsivity, risk-taking, novelty-seeking, increased emotional intensity and reactivity in adolescents (Gogtay et al., 2004; Giorgio et al., 2010; Tamura et al., 2012; Rubia, 2013). All of these factors may be functionally adaptive during this developmental period as increased peer-group social focus and orientation toward autonomy is essential in adolescence. However, these factors may simultaneously constitute an increased vulnerability to depressive symptomatology (Ernst and Korelitz, 2009). To alter negative trajectories leading to depressive illness and to avoid the lifelong recurrent pattern of depression, we should intervene with effective prevention and treatment in childhood and adolescence when neuronal plasticity is at its peak and before secondary co-morbidities occur (Hulvershorn et al., 2011).THE NEUROCIRCUITRY CENTRAL TO THE PSYCHOPATHOLOGY OF ADOLESCENT DEPRESSIONTo date, the body of literature on adolescent depression using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) has shown consistent alterations in the amygdala, the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC), in particular the subgenual portion (sgACC) and the medial prefrontal cortex (MPFC). The amygdala is a limbic structure that plays a key role in emotion-processing and memory formation (Morris et al., 1998; LeDoux, 2007). The sgACC acts as an interface between emotion and cognition with evidence of involvement in both emotion generative and regulatory processing (Seminowicz et al., 2004). The MPFC is implicated in many functions, including emotion regulation, reward processing, memory consolidation, and self-referential processing (Buckner et al., 2008). Both adolescent (Buckner et al., 2008; Yang et al., 2010; Perlman et al., 2012) and adult MDD (Sheline et al., 2001; Cunningham et al., 2002) are associated with amygdalar hyperactivation in response to emotional stimuli, and increased amygdalar activation has been shown to correlate positively with depression severity (Price and Drevets, 2010; Lane et al., 2013). The amygdala has reciprocal connections with the sgACC, which has also been demonstrated to exhibit resting-state hyperperfusion (Ho et al., 2013) and task-related hyperactivation in depressed compared to healthy adolescents (Yang et al., 2009). More recently, functional connectivity (FC) of the sgACC during resting-state (Cullen et al., 2009; Davey et al., 2012a; Connolly et al., 2013) and during emotional processing (Ho et al., 2014) has been assessed to investigate the functioning of neural networks in adolescent depression. Two of these studies showed increased sgACC-amygdala FC in depressed compared to healthy adolescents (Connolly et al., 2013; Ho et al., 2014). It is hypothesized that enhanced bottom-up responses to affectively laden stimuli could be linked to deficits in amygdala and sgACC function and represent heightened emotional reactivity to emotional and social stimuli in adolescent MDD. Similar results have been found in MDD patients in remission (Joormann and Gotlib, 2007; Fritzsche et al., 2010) and in high-risk girls (Joormann et al., 2012), thereby suggesting that limbic and cingulate hyperactivation may be a trait which increases vulnerability to depression. These bottom-up processes could potentially also have negative effects on the development of cognitive control mechanisms involved in physiologic and behavioral coping by sustaining negative affect (Fales et al., 2008; Michl et al., 2013). Depressed individuals often ruminate and have difficulties disengaging from the processing of self-focused, often negatively biased thoughts (Cooney et al., 2010; Manoliu et al., 2013; Mandell et al., 2014). It has been proposed that aberrant switching from self-referential processing involving midline prefrontal structures such as the MPFC to interoceptive processes involving the insula or to goal-directed cognitive processes involving the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) might contribute to MDD (Manoliu et al., 2013).The insula is a paralimbic structure implicated in a broad range of different functions (Craig, 2011; Nieuwenhuys, 2012). A dysfunction in the integration of visceral signals to the insular cortex has been suggested in adult depression (Critchley, 2005) and adult MDD is associated with abnormal functional connectivity of the insula (Mutschler et al., 2012; Avery et al., 2013). Interestingly, increased sgACC-insula functional connectivity (Connolly et al., 2013) has been documented in adolescent depression during resting-state, whereas sgACC-insula functional connectivity during emotion processing in this population has been shown to decrease (Ho et al., 2014). This may indicate that altered sgACC-insula connectivity does characterize adolescent MDD, but that the directionality of the functional connections change with brain state (Ho et al., 2014).Cognitive control areas within portions of the PFC, such as the DLPFC and the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex (VLPFC) have been implicated in adult MDD (Rive et al., 2013). It has been suggested that reduced DLPFC recruitment in depressed adults is present only when the amygdala is overactive, indicating that dysfunction in the DLPFC may not the primary mechanism involved in adult MDD but that amygdalar hyperactivity may have a bottom-up influence on the level of activity in DLPFC (Drevets et al., 2008). The DLPFC does not seem to be as strongly implicated in adolescent as compared to adult MDD (Kerestes et al., 2013). This is in line with the lack of evidence for differences between depressed and healthy control adolescents in both behavioral performance and brain activation in DLPFC during tasks of cognitive control (Davey et al., 2012b; Bora et al., 2013). In fact, cognitive deficits in MDD seem to become more severe with recurrent MDD and are more pronounced in late-life depression (Koenig and Butters, 2014). It must be emphasized that adolescents in general, independent of depressive illness, have functional limitations in top-down control systems compared to adults due to differing frontal development and frontolimbic connections (Gogtay et al., 2004; Giorgio et al., 2010; Tamura et al., 2012; Rubia, 2013). Task-dependent DLPFC activation in adolescents has been shown to measures of impulse control, foresight, and resistance to peer pressure (Andrews-Hanna et al., 2011). The limitations in executive function and cognitive control may thus contribute to the increased risk of depression and certain aspects of adolescent depression symptomatology, but we suggest that these mechanisms are not primarily driving the pathophysiology of adolescent MDD.It should be mentioned that the dysfunction of specific brain regions described in adolescent depression should not be regarded in isolation, but rather as part of networks of structures functionally interacting together (Greicius, 2008; Hamilton et al., 2013). Studies of adult MDD suggest dysfunction in an extended medial network involved in emotion processing (Price and Drevets, 2012). This network partly overlaps with and is dynamically interacting with the DMN, which is involved in self-referential processing (Buckner et al., 2008; Greicius, 2008; Hamilton et al., 2013). The extended medial network is also functionally interacting with the executive control network implicated in cognitive control of emotions (Phan et al., 2004). Similar network dysfunctions has been partly suggested in adolescent MDD (Kerestes et al., 2013).Alterations in reward circuitry have also been implicated in the pathophysiology of adolescent MDD (Forbes and Dahl, 2012). Functional MRI studies using reward processing tasks show decreased activation in the striatum and increased activation in MPFC in response to reward in depressed adolescents compared to healthy controls (Forbes and Dahl, 2012). In addition, adolescents with MDD show increased resting-state FC between striatal regions and midline structures (Gabbay et al., 2013). Furthermore, alterations in striatal FC correlate with depression and anhedonic severity (Gabbay et al., 2013). Dysfunctional social reward systems may be particularly implicated in adolescent depression, since depression is often precipitated by social rejection or loss of status in this age-group (Davey et al., 2008). Altered reward circuitry may also be specifically related to anhedonia, which is prevalent but variable among depressed adolescents (Gabbay et al., 2009, 2010, 2012; Geisler et al., 2013). Converging evidence suggests that anhedonia specifically reflects disturbances in a mesolimbic striatum-based reward system in adolescents with MDD, whereas MDD without anhedonia is accompanied by normal function in this circuitry (Gabbay et al., 2013). Anhedonia in adolescence predicts chronicity of MDD (Bennik et al., 2013), is a negative prognostic predictor for treatment response (McMakin et al., 2012), and MDD with anhedonia may constitute more severe type of adolescent depression (Gabbay et al., 2013). The anhedonic form of adolescent depression has a symptom profile similar to adult melancholic depression (Gabbay et al., 2013). In contrast, the adolescent form of depression without anhedonia but with emotion instability/dysregulation, stress reactivity, low impulse control and comorbid anxiety shows a dramatic increase of prevalence at the onset of puberty with a major predominance in girls. This gender effect is hypothesized to be related to estrogen levels and cortisol receptor sensitivity in the brain (Antonijevic, 2006; Paing et al., 2008; Weiser and Handa, 2009; Smith, 2012). The non-anhedonic symptom profile in adolescent depression has similarities with the features of atypical depression in adults according to the DSM system, even though the diagnostic validity is low for atypical depression according to DSM in this age-group (Williamson et al., 2000; Paing et al., 2008). Notably, women have a documented higher frequency of comorbid depression and anxiety disorders, and a threefold higher prevalence of atypical depression compared to men (Silverstein, 2002; Halbreich and Kahn, 2007). The female predominance of depression in adults thus seems to be restricted to the atypical subtype in premenopausal women (Angst et al., 2002; Silverstein, 2002). This contrasts with the pattern seen in postmenopausal women, for whom melancholic MDD is predominant and no gender differences have been identified (Antonijevic, 2006). The literature describes differences in hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis function, serotonin and noradrenaline function, immune system activation and treatment response between MDD and atypical depression (Angst et al., 2006; Antonijevic, 2008). Based on this evidence, we hypothesize that the pathophysiological mechanisms involved in atypical depression in women are similar to those in the most common form of depression in adolescent females.In mid-puberty a 2:1 female to male ratio in depressive disorders emerges (Angold et al., 1998). A large body of literature suggests that an estrogen dependent increase of stress sensitivity and mood instability increases the vulnerability to depression in puberty for girls (Angold et al., 1998, 1999; Steiner et al., 2003; Ter Horst et al., 2009; Weiser and Handa, 2009; Blanton et al., 2012; Smith, 2012).Summarizing these findings, two possible pathophysiological trajectories leading to adolescent depression emerge. One subtype seems to be driven by limbic hyperactivation, related to sustained threat with clinical features such as emotional hyper-reactivity, agitation and dysphoric mood and possible secondary negative effects on the ability to dynamically switch from self-referential processing to interoceptive awareness or goal directed behavior. A second subtype may be driven by compromised positive reward circuitry and may be related to an anhedonic subtype of adolescent depression (Gabbay et al., 2013). Based on clinical experience and the literature of atypical versus melancholic depression according to the DSM system (Antonijevic, 2006; Paing et al., 2008), we suggest that the increased prevalence of MDD seen in puberty is mainly constituted by a subtype that best fits the symptomatology of limbic hyperactivation corresponding to the RDoC construct of “sustained threat.” The subtype of adolescent MDD that may be more related to dysfunction of reward circuitry seems to remain more stable across different age groups and gender (Antonijevic, 2006; Halbreich and Kahn, 2007). When creating the foundation for an intervention for adolescent depression by determining the hierarchy of the domains of function, it is crucial to identify which of these subgroups to target. In our present work, we chose to focus on the most prevalent type of adolescent depression with clinical features of emotional hyper-reactivity, agitation, and dysphoric mood but without major signs of anhedonia. In the future our manual can be adapted for other types of depression as well.THE ROLE OF SUSTAINED THREAT IN RELATION TO SYSTEMIC DYSREGULATION AND THE SOMATIC MANIFESTATIONS OF DEPRESSIONThe PFC and the amygdala are linked via the vagus nerve to the regulation of metabolic systems (Thayer and Sternberg, 2006). It is hypothesized that a predisposition to amygdala and limbic hyperactivation and decreased vagal control, such as is found in depressive illness, will induce a cascade of dysregulation across multiple systems (Juster et al., 2010). Inflammatory processes (Henje Blom et al., 2011; Maes et al., 2011), glucose–insulin homeostasis, glucocorticoid signaling, oxidative stress, and energy biosynthesis (Thayer and Sternberg, 2006; McIntyre et al., 2007) are examples of systems that are often dysregulated in depression. Over time, this dysregulation can build to an increased risk of developing systemic diseases such as atherosclerosis, heart disease, hypertension, stroke, osteoporosis, deterioration of the immune system, obesity, metabolic syndrome, insulin resistance and Type 2 diabetes (Wolkowitz et al., 2011).Early childhood experience may be one pathway through which neural circuits underlying depression may become dysregulated. Childhood maltreatment may cause patterns of limbic hyper-responsiveness and increased rumination (Michl et al., 2013), which may consequently lead to altered and sustained physiological responses to stress, including mechanisms of inflammation, oxidative stress, telomerase activity and regulation of neurotrophic factors, growth factors, and neurosteroids (Taylor et al., 2011; Shonkoff and Garner, 2012; Karatsoreos and McEwen, 2013). The effect of chronic childhood abuse and adverse life events on neurosteroid metabolism during development has been especially well studied and described in the RDoC construct of sustained threat (Heim et al., 2000). The implicated mechanism is HPA dysregulation with persistent corticotropin-releasing factor (CRF) hypersecretion, overproduction of adreno-corticotropic hormone (ACTH) in the anterior pituitary and increased glucocorticoid release from the adrenal glands (Heim et al., 2000). Preclinical studies show that increased glucocorticoid secretion progressively reduces neurogenesis and synaptogenesis in the hippocampus (Andersen and Teicher, 2008). This damage to hippocampal neurons then contributes to hippocampal dysfunction and the eventual development of depression (Heim et al., 2000; Kaymak et al., 2010; Dannlowski et al., 2012; Teicher et al., 2012). Regional differences in synaptic development and the establishment of glucocorticoid receptors may also influence the development of other specific regions and functional connectivity among these regions during adolescence. Early life stress has been shown to increase childhood cortisol levels, which predicts decreased amygdala-ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) connectivity in adolescence (Burghy et al., 2012). Therefore, there may be a temporal delay between early stress exposure and the clinical manifestations of depression (Andersen and Teicher, 2008).Smaller hippocampal volumes have been a consistent finding in depressed adults (Kempton et al., 2011) and in early onset depressed adolescents (Kaymak et al., 2010; Hulvershorn et al., 2011). However, in child- and adolescent depression, hippocampal size is positively correlated with the duration of illness, which is not the case in adult depression (Hulvershorn et al., 2011). This may be a compensatory process in the developing brain aimed at neural recovery (Hulvershorn et al., 2011). This is important from a clinical perspective since it implies that reduction of hippocampal volume may be prevented by effective interventions during the sensitive time-period by which this compensatory mechanism is still at work. This finding is also in line with previous data showing that children who are exposed to maternal depressive symptomatology since birth show increased levels of glucocorticoids but not changes in hippocampal volume (Lupien et al., 2011). On the other hand, these children show increased amygdala volumes, which indicates that the amygdala may be particularly sensitive to early life adversity and stress (Lupien et al., 2011).Based on these findings, we hypothesize that exposure to sustained threat is detrimental to the developing central nervous system. A negative spiral seems to be created wherein amygdala hyperactivity leads to increased metabolic dysfunction, which in turn instigates dysfunction of emotion regulation circuitry and increased sensitivity to threatening cues, further increasing the risk of metabolic consequences (McIntyre et al., 2007). The trajectory of depressive disease starts early and continues unless addressed by effective and targeted interventions (McEwen, 2003; Juster et al., 2010; Dannlowski et al., 2012). We therefore suggest that the first priority in treating pediatric depression should be to normalize amygdala and limbic hyperactivity and ACC dysfunction by specially designed practice as outlined in the later sections of this article.HIERARCHICAL ORGANIZATION OF THE RDoC DOMAINS OF FUNCTIONWe have identified the major RDoC domains of function involved in adolescent depression and organized them in a way that gives priority to domains thought to be driving the psychopathology (see Table 1). We propose that the most important factor driving the pathophysiology of mild to moderate adolescent depression without major signs of anhedonia is limbic hyper-reactivity and dysregulation of the amygdala and ACC as previously described. These neural circuits correspond well to the RDoC construct of sustained threat within the domain of negative valence. The behavioral unit of analysis of the RDoC construct of sustained threat describes several of the core symptoms of the most common type of adolescent depression: anxious arousal, increased conflict detection, attentional bias to threat, helplessness behavior, punishment sensitivity and avoidance. These mechanisms are supported by the extensive body of literature suggesting an increased risk of adolescent depression as a result of childhood trauma (Andersen and Teicher, 2008; Taylor et al., 2011; D’Andrea et al., 2012; Dannlowski et al., 2012; Gulec et al., 2013) and it is also congruent with the findings that anxious symptomatology often precedes the onset of MDD (Stein et al., 2001) and that anxiety disorders are highly comorbid with MDD in this age group (Keller et al., 1992; Angold and Costello, 1993; Seligman and Ollendick, 1998; Costello et al., 2003; Middeldorp et al., 2005; Olino et al., 2008).Table 1A proposed hierarchy of RDoC constructs relevant in treating mild to moderate adolescent depression without major anhedonia.RDoC constructsRDoC domainsImplicated neurocircuitryClinical manifestationsIntervention strategiesDriving depressive pathophysiologySustained threatNegative valenceLimbic hyper-reactivity with dysregulation of the amygdala and the anterior cingulate cortexAnxious arousal; increased conflict detection, attentional bias to threat, helplessness behavior, punishment sensitivity, avoidanceStress-reduction by breathing exercises and yoga-based movementArousal and sleep-wakefulnessArousal and regulatory systemsHypothalamic to thalamic and cortical circuitsSleep-wake dysregulation and sleep dependent behavioral dysfunctions such as affect regulation, emotional reactivity, impulsivityDecrease of daytime hyper- arousal by breathing exercises and yoga-based movement. Psycho-education related to sleepLossNegative valenceSustained amygdala reactivity and decreased DLPFC recruitment. Increased default mode activitySadness, guilt, shame, low self-esteem, worry, rumination, increased self-focus, withdrawal behaviorPractice of dynamic shifting from rumination to interoceptive awareness. Cognitive reappraisal techniquesMaintaining depressive psychopathologyAttention and cognitive controlCognitive systemsCircuitry involving top down cognitive control: DLPFC, VLPFC, PPC, the insula and limbic systemConcentration difficulties, distractibility. Low impulse controlPractice of attention by body-scans and sitting meditationOf interest for treatment approachApproach motivationPositive valenceCircuitry involving MPFC, OFC, dorsal and ventral striatum and amygdalaPractice approach behavior rather than experiential avoidanceReward learningPositive valenceCircuitry involving OFC and ventral striatumCore value identification, practicing value-based decision making for behavioral activationSocial communication, perception and understanding self and others and self knowledgeSocial processesBroad range of brain areas, beyond the scope of this tablePractice to care for oneself and others and to receive care/compassion. Practice to communicate emotions. Practice of understanding one-self in relation to othersSince the implied neurocircuitry often overlaps between different RDoC domains and constructs we suggest that only specific neural circuits are targeted for treatment as suggested in the column “implicated neurocircuitry” rather than all of the neurocircuitry described in each construct.Closely related to the sustained threat mechanism is autonomic nervous system hyper-reactivity and dysfunction in the domain of arousal and regulatory systems both within the RDoC construct of arousal and sleep-wakefulness. Neurocircuits related to sleep and to arousal are reciprocally modulating each other. This is represented by reciprocal connections from the amygdala to other limbic structures such as the thalamus and hypothalamus, as well as to cortical structures (McGinty and Szymusiak, 2003; Szymusiak et al., 2007). Insomnia may be secondary to frequent daytime hyper-arousal (Riemann et al., 2010) and it is hypothesized that sleep disturbances precede and are etiologically linked to the emergence of depressive symptoms (Harvey et al., 2011). Persistent sleep disturbance may cause secondary cognitive dysfunctions, daytime tiredness, concentration difficulties, affect dysregulation, emotional reactivity, impulsivity and dysregulation of neuroendocrine and immunological systems and it is negatively related to depression treatment outcome (Manglick et al., 2013).Dysphoric mood, including sadness, guilt, shame, and low self-esteem are core features of adolescent MDD, which correspond to the construct loss, within the negative valence RDoC domain. Worry, rumination, increased self-focus, withdrawal behavior, and impaired sustained attention are examples of other common features of adolescent depression described in the construct loss, that may be secondary to sustained threat mechanisms as previously described. However, it is important to emphasize that several of the behavioral features described within the RDoC construct of loss such as psychomotor retardation, anhedonia, loss of drive (sleep, appetite, libido), and a lack of motivation may constitute a distinct and less prevalent subtype of adolescent depression in which dysfunctional reward circuitry may be implicated. As previously described, we acknowledge that an aberrant reward circuitry exists in adolescent depression as shown in previous functional MRI (Forbes et al., 2007, 2009; Forbes and Dahl, 2012) and magnetic resonance spectroscopy studies (Gabbay et al., 2007). We suggest that these findings may be related to a more severe form of anhedonic depression and that aberrant reward circuitry may not be driving the pathophysiology of mild to moderate adolescent depression, in which the previously described mechanisms of a hyper-reactive limbic system are more dominant.The DSM-IV definition of MDD includes several more general psychiatric symptoms, which may be part of the DSM diagnostic criteria of other psychiatric disorders as well. These unspecific symptoms may still contribute to and maintain the psychophysiology of depression and be part of the suggested RDoC constructs. Concentration difficulties, for example, are often part of adolescent depression symptomatology and belong to the construct of attention in the domain of cognitive systems (Han et al., 2012). Another unspecific symptom associated with adolescent behavior in general is impaired impulse control (Andrews-Hanna et al., 2011) which is described as a within the cognitive control construct in the domain of cognitive systems in the RDoC matrix as represented by impaired top-down regulation from DLPFC, VLPFC, and posterior parietal cortex (PPC). The decrease of impulse control in combination with dysphoric mood may be driving secondary comorbidities such as behavioral problems, self-harming behavior, drug abuse, and suicidal actions.Constructs within the positive valence system domain may constitute relevant mechanisms to consider when designing a treatment model for adolescent depression. We hypothesize that dysfunction of mechanisms of approach motivation may relate to increased experiential avoidance, which may be involved in sustaining depressive symptomatology. The reward learning construct within the positive valence system also describes value-based decision-making behavior that may increase resilience to depressive symptomatology by contributing with behavioral motivation, meaning and direction in the life of the adolescent. Finally, dysfunction within the domain of social processes such the constructs of social communication, perception and understanding self and others and self knowledge is also important in the treatment of adolescent depression since depressive self-evaluation and extensive negative self-referential processing often impede social connections and a healthy peer group identification that is developmentally important in adolescence.In summary, we propose the following hierarchy of RDoC constructs in treating mild to moderate adolescent depression without major anhedonia (see also Table 1):1. Sustained threat with symptoms of anxious arousal, increased conflict detection, attentional bias to threat and emotion-laden stimuli, helplessness behavior, punishment sensitivity and avoidance.2. Arousal and wakefulness including limbic and autonomic hyperarousal with manifestations such as insomnia and secondary sleep dependent behavioral dysfunctions.3. Loss, including feelings of sadness, guilt, shame, low self-esteem, worry, rumination, increased self-focus, and withdrawal.4. Attention and cognitive control with concentration difficulties, distractibility, and low impulse control.5. Approach motivation, mechanisms of reward learning and social processes such as social communication, perception and understanding self and others and self knowledge are valuable salutogenic life skills which should be addressed in treatment of adolescent depression.Since a clinical application is time-limited and constrained by aspects of feasibility, we propose the following simplification in the translation of the RDoC constructs to a progressive skills-training with clear treatment goals for adolescent depression (see Table 1):1. Improve autonomic regulation and decreased hyper-arousal and limbic hyper-reactivity (with hypothesized secondary effects on sleep disturbances).2. Practice attention and interoceptive awareness to enhance dynamic switching away from self-evaluative processing and rumination.3. Promote emotion recognition by training interoceptive awareness and enhance prefrontal cortical regulation of affect by practicing labeling and communication of emotions.4. Train top-down cognitive control over affective responses such as negatively biased states of attention, processing, thinking, memory, rumination, and dysfunctional attitudes.5. Identify intrinsic values to drive pro-social behavior and increase motivation for committed behavioral activation.PROPOSED THERAPEUTIC TRAINING STRATEGIES BASED ON CURRENT SCIENTIFIC EVIDENCE OF EFFICACYThe first aim of our intervention is to decrease limbic hyper-reactivity and increase autonomic regulation through the promotion of vagal afference. We aim to target neurocircuitry described in the RDoC construct of sustained threat within the domain of negative valence and the dysfunction in the domain of arousal and regulatory systems both within the RDoC constructs of arousal and sleep-wakefulness. [Section “Module 1: Calming Down and Creating a Sense of Safety (Weeks 1–3)” for description of the corresponding section of the manual.]The nervous system is designed to evaluate risk and match neurophysiological state with the actual risk of the environment (McEwen, 2003). Adolescents with emotional dysregulation often perceive the environment as being dangerous or threatening even when it is safe, which could be a result of early life stress exposure as described in section “The Role of Sustained Threat in Relation to Systemic Dysregulation and the Somatic Manifestations of Depression.” This mismatch may result in defensive states, limbic hyperactivation and sympathetic arousal. On the other hand, there is evidence that during the experience of a safe environment, the influence of afferent vagal motor pathways increases, which in turn inhibits the defense mechanisms of the sympathetic nervous system, dampening the stress response (Porges, 2009).In adult depression (Licht et al., 2008), as well as in adolescent depression, amygdala hyperactivity is related to a decrease of vagal inhibitory control (Yang et al., 2007; Henje Blom et al., 2010) and in depressed patients, a direct association between depression symptom severity and the modulation of cardio-vagal activity has been shown (Agelink et al., 2002). It has been proposed that individual differences in heart rate variability (HRV) predict attentional inhibition, which suggests that successful inhibition as well as novelty search may be mediated by cortical inhibitory mechanisms among people with high cardiac vagal tone (Park et al., 2012). Cardiac vagal tone is also associated with both adaptive top-down and bottom-up modulation of emotional processing, which is implicated in depression (Park et al., 2013). From both animal and human neurochemical and neuroimaging studies as well as from studies using vagus nerve stimulation (VNS) – a therapeutic brain stimulation technique sending electrical impulses to the left cervical vagus nerve, which is approved as an adjunct long-term treatment for chronic or recurrent depression – there is considerable evidence that the vagus nerve and its stimulation influence limbic and higher cortical brain regions implicated in mood disorders (Park et al., 2007; Vonck et al., 2014). RSA-biofeedback and breathing training has also been shown to increase vagal modulation and to reduce depressive symptoms (Siepmann et al., 2008; Patron et al., 2012). Increased HRV, and more specifically, respiratory sinus arrhythmia (RSA), has been shown to relate to the level of engagement of coping strategies and social well-being. Moreover, RSA predicts less use of avoidance strategies for regulating negative emotions and more use of socially adaptive emotion-regulation skills in young adults (Geisler et al., 2013).A few small studies of respiratory biofeedback with focus on assessing RSA have indicated beneficial effects on anxious and depressive symptoms (Patron et al., 2012; Sutarto et al., 2012). Several studies have shown that regular practice of breathing techniques also substantially changes respiratory metabolism and produces psychological effects, such as reduction of chemo-reflex sensitivity (Spicuzza et al., 2000), oxidative stress (Sharma et al., 2003), depressive symptoms (Tweeddale et al., 1994) and symptoms of panic disorder (Meuret et al., 2005; Wollburg et al., 2011; Kim et al., 2012).We conclude that breathing exercises may be helpful in increasing vagal afference and improving autonomic regulation and for the purpose of the treatment of adolescent depression, yoga-based breathing and movement practices may improve regulatory skills by recruiting vagal and sensory afferent neurocircuitry. These practices may thus have an effect on limbic hyperactivity, break the negative spiral previously described, and prevent the recurrent course of depression. Despite some methodological limitations, there are some preliminary promising results for yoga-based treatment of depressive symptomatology (Pilkington et al., 2005; Ospina et al., 2008; Uebelacker et al., 2010). Limitations of yoga studies for depression include insufficient description of techniques applied as well as problems with control conditions (Pilkington et al., 2005; Shapiro et al., 2007; Dunn, 2008; Uebelacker et al., 2010; Cabral et al., 2011; Balasubramaniam et al., 2012; Khalsa, 2013). No studies have yet been published on yoga based treatment for adolescent depression but two preliminary RCTs, one in a high-school setting (Noggle et al., 2012) and one in a secondary school setting (Khalsa et al., 2012), have focused on yoga as a school intervention for increased wellness and both suggest preventive effects on mental health. Other strategies to calm a hyperactive limbic system such as sensory activation through sound, light (Canbeyli, 2013), smell (Perry and Perry, 2006; Lv et al., 2013), and touch (Hou et al., 2010) are not within the scope of this review, but may have potential anti-depressive effects that need to be further investigated.The second priority in our intervention is to increase attention skills and shift neural activity from negative self-referencing processing to present-moment sensory and interoceptive awareness. We aim to target parts of the neural circuitry implicated within the RDoC construct of loss in the domain of negative valence and the construct of attention in the domain of cognitive systems. [Section “Module 2: Attending and Caring about Our Inner Experience (Weeks 4–6)” for description of the corresponding section of the manual.]Adults with MDD who paid less attention to their emotions showed better recovery from MDD (Thompson et al., 2013), but paying too little attention to one’s inner state is also thought to be maladaptive for depressed individuals (Thompson et al., 2013). Attending to emotions may be beneficial for individuals with a good capacity to regulate mood, but may be potentially detrimental to those with a low capacity to regulate mood (Lischetzke and Eid, 2003). Consequently, we suggest that practice of attending emotion is prioritized in the intervention, once regulatory skills have been acquired in section “Module 1: Calming Down and Creating a Sense of Safety (Weeks 1–3).”The insula may be involved in integrating diffuse feedback from the viscera into cognitive awareness (Nieuwenhuys, 2012). Functional MRI experiments have demonstrated that the insula plays an important role in the experience of pain and the experience of several emotions, including anger, fear, disgust, happiness, and sadness (Craig, 2009). Internal body states are represented in the insula and contribute to our subjective feeling, with insular activity correlating positively with interoceptive accuracy (Critchley, 2005). Depressed adults show less accurate heartbeat perception compared to healthy controls (Furman et al., 2013) and in adults with depressive disorder, training of interoceptive awareness seems to enhance focused attention, which is a cognitive process supported by the ACC and the lateral PFC (Farb et al., 2012). In the context of emotion regulation, increasing interoceptive awareness requires reducing self-evaluative processing. The corresponding neural events during this transition to present-moment sensory awareness include a shifting from midline structures of the PFC to the thalamus, insula, and primary sensory regions (Farb et al., 2012). Training of interoceptive awareness seems to buffer against rumination and negative emotional bias (Farb et al., 2012) and a reduction of emotional limbic hyperactivity has also been shown to be one consequence of mindfulness interventions (Paul et al., 2013). Based on these data, we propose that disengagement from internal self-focus by increasing sensory and introceptive moment-to-moment awareness may be especially helpful for reducing depressive symptoms and vulnerability to depression for adolescents.As discussed in the previous section, we suggest these skills are cultivated predominantly in contemplative movement practice or in body scans (guided practice of interoceptive awareness) that closely follow a movement practice, rather than in sitting meditation. Four hundred clinical trials on meditation-based interventions for clinical disorders (published between 1956 and 2005) were reviewed in 2007, yet the authors could not make any decisive conclusions with respect to effects on depression due to poor methodological quality (Ospina et al., 2008). In 2007, 15 mindfulness based stress reduction (MBSR) studies for depression and anxiety were also reviewed (Toneatto and Nguyen, 2007). MBSR is 8 week group intervention developed by Kabat-Zinn (1996) containing different components of practice such as body scans, sitting meditation, yoga and informal mindfulness in every day life. Meta-analyses of these studies showed that when active control groups were used, MBSR did not show a reliable effect on depression and anxiety (Toneatto and Nguyen, 2007). More recently, a meta-analyses of mindfulness-based practices for the treatment of adult depression showed relatively small effect sizes on self-assessed depression symptom severity: Cohen’s d = 0.30 [95% CI, 0.00–0.59] at 8 weeks and Cohen’s d = 0.23 [95% CI, 0.05–0.42] at 3–6 months (Goyal et al., 2014). Preliminary results from studies applying modified versions of mindfulness based cognitive therapy (MBCT) for the treatment of acute depression have also been published (Eisendrath et al., 2011, 2014; Munshi et al., 2013). However, the MBCT model does not contain any practices that stimulate the vagal afference such as breathing or movement. The implicated mechanisms of change in the MBCT intervention are rather top-down regulatory skills training and meta-cognition strategies, which we propose should not the primary focus in treating adolescent depression. A recent study by Williams et al. (2013) showed that MBCT provided significant protection against depressive relapse, but only for participants who experienced childhood trauma, which supports the notion that sustained threat neuro-mechanisms may increase the risk for recurrent episodes. In comparison to an active control condition and to treatment as usual (TAU), MBCT did not improve symptoms in patients with recurrent depression.Carmody and Baer (2008) investigated the components contained in the MBSR program and the amount of time these components were practiced between sessions in relation to outcome. Specifically, a strong association was found between yoga and improved mindfulness skills, reduced psychological symptoms (such as anxiety and inter-personal sensitivity), and improved well-being, even though the yoga was practiced on fewer days and for fewer total hours than the other formal practices (Carmody and Baer, 2008). From these reviews, we can conclude that mindfulness-based interventions alone have limited efficacy for treating adult depression, but body-based contemplative practices may be beneficial and warrant further examination.Studies of mindfulness-based interventions for adolescent depression in clinical settings are rare and the possible neural mechanisms involved have not been studied in this population. One RCT showed a decrease in depression and anxiety symptoms after a MBSR course delivered in a group format for adolescents with heterogeneous diagnoses in a clinical outpatient setting (Biegel et al., 2009). A pilot RCT of acceptance and commitment therapy (ACT) for individual treatment of teenage depression demonstrated greater improvement in depressive symptoms as compared to TAU (Hayes et al., 2011). Recent studies of mindfulness-based group interventions in school settings for teenagers and young adults have also yielded reductions in depression and anxiety-related symptoms. In a non-randomized study of secondary school students, Kuyken et al. (2013) showed that relative to children who participated in the usual school curriculum, children who participated in a mindfulness intervention reported significantly fewer depressive symptoms post-treatment and at 3 months follow-up. In a cluster-RCT of a mindfulness group program for an adolescent school-based population (ages 13–20 years), Raes et al. (2013) demonstrated that effects on depressive symptoms from baseline to post-intervention and from baseline to 6 months after treatment ended were small to medium (both Cohen’s d &gt; 0.30). These promising early results suggest potential for improvement with contemplative practices carefully tailored for maximum skill uptake and neural effect among adolescents with depression.The third target is emotion regulation by recognition, labeling and communication of emotions, aiming to improve function in neurocircuits within both the constructs of sustained threat and the construct of loss in the RDoC negative valence domain. [Section “Module 3: Recognizing, Regulating, and Communicating Emotions (Weeks 7–9)” for description of the corresponding section of the manual.]We propose that adolescents need to first achieve bottom-up regulatory skills to calm the limbic system with vagal and sensory afferent techniques prior to engaging effectively in training top-down cognitive control strategies. In the previous modules, participants have practiced breathing exercises, yoga-based movement, and body scans to improve attention, interoceptive awareness, and recognition of emotions and their bodily representations. In this module, we introduce more top-down strategies such as labeling emotions. In traditional mindfulness programs for adults, labeling emotions is an inner process that is recommended during meditation when strong emotions arise. It has been shown in adults that mindfulness is associated with enhanced prefrontal cortical regulation of affect through labeling of negative affective stimuli (Creswell et al., 2007), and that during the labeling of emotions, the VLPFC exhibits a dampening effect on the activity of the amygdala (Lieberman et al., 2007; Torrisi et al., 2013). While emotion recognition and labeling are core practices in most mindfulness programs, the skills of communicating emotion or interpreting emotional states in others are not emphasized. We have addressed this limitation by integrating aspects of psychotherapeutic traditions with some evidence of treatment effect for emotional dysregulation and depressive symptomatology in adolescents such as dialectic behavioral therapy (DBT; Bedics et al., 2013) and ACT (Hayes et al., 2010, 2011).Once the previous regulatory skills have been acquired, the final intervention goal is to introduce practices of top-down cognitive control over affective responses such as negatively biased states of attention, processing, thinking, memory, rumination and dysfunctional attitudes. These functions are related to altered neural circuitry implied in the construct of cognitive control within the RDoC cognitive systems. We also target mechanisms within the RDoC domain of positive valence related to experiential avoidance such as approach motivation and reward learning and within the domain of social processes. [Section “Module 4: Core Values, Goal Setting and Committed Action (Weeks 10–12)” for description of the corresponding section of the manual.]Cognitive-behavioral strategies for managing depressive symptoms seem to rely on improving the function of the PFC and enhancing the cortico-limbic circuits in modulating emotional processing (Mor and Winquist, 2002; Drevets et al., 2008; Beevers et al., 2010; Cooney et al., 2010; Disner et al., 2011). In the TARA intervention, we emphasize the importance of waiting to introduce this approach once the foundation of the previous “bottom-up” regulatory skills have been consolidated. Our rationale for this is that while strategies of cognitive reappraisal can be effective for emotion regulation in healthy and perhaps depressed adults (Denny and Ochsner, 2013), depressed adolescents have fundamental difficulties with cognitively regulating negative emotion due to developmental and possible depression-related limitations in top-down neural circuitry. Top-down cognitive reappraisal training may be maladaptive and increase risk for rumination and contribute to sustained dysphoric mood (Farb et al., 2012). The top-down model of depression treatment does not take into account that the teenage brain has limited capacity for higher-level executive function. These limitations among adolescents may make them less likely to experience long-term anti-depressive benefit from cognitive control strategies as compared to adults, especially under stressful conditions when limbic hyperactivity tends to override top-down cognitive control. Training adults with depression in executive tasks is associated with increased DLPFC activity during cognitive tasks and with decreased amygdala reactivity in response to emotional stimuli (DeRubeis et al., 2008). However, remission of depression after CBT is associated with decreased, basal DLPFC metabolism, suggesting that recovery might involve the lowering of tonic resting-state activity, allowing for greater reactivity when executive control is recruited (Ressler and Mayberg, 2007; DeRubeis et al., 2008). Since adolescents have limited top-down regulation, we suggest that this mechanism may not be the most effective target to reduce depressive symptomatology. Instead, we prioritize an initial bottom-up regulation strategy to help dampen limbic hyper-reactivity and thereby facilitate the DLPFC contribution to emotion regulation. CBT is the recommended choice of psychological treatment for adolescent depression and has yielded modest effect sizes (Weisz et al., 2006; Watanabe et al., 2007; Reinecke et al., 2009). In a large RCT performed for treatment of adolescent depression, CBT showed a response rate of 43% as compared to 35% for placebo during 12 weeks of treatment, which leaves room for future improvement and development of psychological treatments, such as our approach (Reinecke et al., 2009).THE CREATION OF A PROGRESSIVE MODULE-BASED TREATMENT PROGRAM FOR ADOLESCENTS WITH DEPRESSION – TRAINING FOR AWARENESS, RESILIENCE, AND ACTIONTo enhance the translation of neuroplasticity and neurocircuit retraining research into an effective clinical intervention for adolescent depression in line with RDoC principles, we have integrated approaches drawn from several different paradigms and traditions based on their efficacy and congruence with our scientific theory of change (Cramer et al., 2011). We developed a 12-week group treatment program: we do not aspire to teach meditation or yoga as spiritual practices according to any specific tradition or lineage. The TARA treatment program is only informed by Eastern practices such as meditation and yoga and current evidence on their therapeutic efficacy. The practices have been taken out of their original spiritual and cultural context and then simplified and adapted to fit our therapeutic model and current scientific paradigms. The TARA model has been influenced by practice modalities found in MBSR and MBCT based on evidence of their efficacy for the relevant domains of function as previously outlined (Desrosiers et al., 2013). Some components of the TARA have also been inspired by approaches from CBT, Behavioral Activation, DBT, ACT, Compassion Therapy, and expressive arts therapy. In our proposed research design we include adolescents who are seeking psychiatric care or are under treatment for depressive problems and randomize them to the TARA intervention and TAU or only TAU. Potential participants are screened for depressive symptoms based on DSM-IV, but we do not require a primary MDD diagnosis for inclusion, only a cut-off score of depressive symptoms based on the Children’s Depression Rating Scale Revised (CDRS-R; Poznanski, 1996; Guo et al., 2006). It may be argued that this way of identifying participants to the study is paradoxically based on the very same DSM criteria that we are questioning instead of on pure dimensionality. We acknowledge this as a potential limitation in our present design, but find no other solution in the clinical environment in which the study is conducted, and at a time-point when validated self-assessment of RDoC constructs adapted for age and gender are not yet developed. The DSM scheme just allows for a major subtype distinction that will help focus the proposed therapy. We exclude only on the basis of restrictions in the ability to attend the group format and the training content, for example learning disability, psychosis, severe behavioral problems, severe posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and active suicidality but aim in general to be as inclusive as possible when it comes to psychiatric comorbidities.The TARA program is constructed in four modules, which for future clinical applications will allow for flexibility and adaption based on participant needs so that a module can potentially be continued or repeated until skill uptake is consolidated (Weisz et al., 2011). Each of the 12 TARA sessions is 1.5 h in length and designed for an optimal group size of 10–12 participants. Before the program starts, a session is offered for parents/guardians or other adult persons such as relatives or family friends that are important in the young person’s life and who may provide a support system in between sessions. The aim of this introductory session is to outline the overall goals of the program, invite the adults to try some of the practices, and guide them in how they can be of support for the adolescent. Home practice is encouraged and between session treatment support, such as audio-recordings of short, guided meditations, is also provided.The TARA program is interactively designed and relies on understanding participant behavior given their present context and history (Hayes et al., 2010; Levin et al., 2012). A calm, safe, and respectful group climate is essential and promoted by non-judgmental, empathic, and caring attitudes, and predictability and authenticity on the part of the facilitators. The facilitators must be experienced in leading adolescent group processes and committed to personal contemplative practice in order to effectively model the skills and be able to relate to what the participants are experiencing. The content of the program is transmitted both through implicit and explicit learning. New ways of relating are implicitly taught to the participants by employing skillful and authentic ways of dealing with difficult emotions. Brief psycho-educational modules are offered to provide supportive instruction in lifestyle factors that encourage uptake of the core skills in each module, e.g., physical exercise (Cooney et al., 2013), anti-inflammatory diet/nutrition (Lucas et al., 2013), and adequate sleep (Manglick et al., 2013). In this way, adolescents learn core principles drawn from the theoretical and empirical foundation for the program so they can understand how their brains work and thus develop motivation to practice what they are learning.The program has been “semi-manualized” to make it replicable and easily implemented in different cultures and settings. TARA is based on the principles of neurocircuitry dysfunction and does not require a strict manualization, as long as these mechanisms of change are deeply understood by the facilitators. This approach increases authenticity and allows for personal teaching strategies, adaptions, and flexibility (e.g., certain practices such as respiratory biofeedback that are consistent with the framework can be incorporated). Each session follows the same sequence: first is “the opening of the circle” in which the group members gather to share experiences from the previous week and go through the homework. Next, there is brief psycho-education, followed by breathing exercises, yoga-based movement and a meditation practice. The sessions end with “the closing of the circle” in which the participants give feedback on the session and are given home practice instructions for the following week. Each session component has a distinct and independent progression throughout the 12 weeks. It is therefore possible to break out each single component into a separate 12-week independent program, which will facilitate future studies of the efficacy of each component such as is possible in adaptive trial designs.MODULE 1: CALMING DOWN AND CREATING A SENSE OF SAFETY (WEEKS 1–3)We propose that the first target in correcting the pathophysiology of adolescent depression is to address pathological limbic activity through afferent vagal pathways. We instruct adolescents in breathing techniques and movement practices drawn from yoga that can impact those afferent vagal pathways. As opposed to practices of attending to the breath and increasing awareness of the breath as is typically done in mindfulness-based interventions, we include active breathing practice of a soft “yogic” breathing technique. Slowing down the breathing rate and extending the length of exhalation increases vagus tone and improves autonomic regulation. Our clinical experience suggests that controlling breathing rate and the duration of the breath in this manner promotes feelings of relaxation and well-being. We recommend that participants practice this simple down-pacing and softening of the breath on a daily basis.After learning to slow and soften their breathing, participants next receive instruction in the use of the “Ujjayi” breathing technique often used in yoga. Instead of using the Sanskrit term “ujjayi” when describing it to the adolescents, we use the term “ocean breath.” In our experience, adolescents are more receptive to new mind/body practices when the instructor uses developmentally appropriate language. Ocean breath practice in the TARA intervention is presented as a deep slow rhythmic breathing with the instruction to visualize the inhalation starting from the lower belly, continuing in a wave through the ribcage, upper chest and throat, and followed by exhaling in the opposite order. Inhalations and exhalations are usually approximately equal in duration, but for the purpose of calming the mind, this practice involves a slight extension of the exhalation along with a very brief pause at the end of each inhalation and exhalation, but without tension or any holding of the breath. Both inhalation and exhalation are done through the nostrils (versus through the mouth). Concurrently, narrowing of the throat passage at the glottis level creates a soft and soothing sound that can be described as sounding like the ocean. The duration of the breath is controlled by the diaphragm, and gets extended by practice, but should never create tension or distress. Participants are encouraged to be gentle with themselves and not force the breathing. The breath can also be used to direct attention to certain parts of the body, for example, to increase interoceptive or sensatory capability, release tension or extend the range of movement. Ujjayi breathing is often used in synchronization with movement and an advantage to practicing breathing techniques in combination with movement in a group setting is that a generalization to ways of using the breath practices in everyday life situations is facilitated. For example, participants are encouraged to use ocean breath along with their movements while walking between classes in school or in regulating their emotions in everyday situations (see “Stop-Breathe-Act” exercise in Module 3).Following basic instruction in the breathing practices, we offer a series of movement practices drawn from yoga asanas that are intended to promote calmness and “grounding.” The movements are presented in a non-competitive manner that emphasizes experience versus achievement. We do not expect that the hypothesized antidepressant effect of the practice will arise from the intensity of the physical training such as is highlighted in muscle-building, endurance or aerobic fitness. Instead, we promote specific qualities of the movement practices such as posture, balance, and development of equanimity, and non-straining/non-pushing. We support these attitudes and qualities of physical movement to enhance the development of their psychological counterparts. We also emphasize a focus on interoceptive and sensory awareness, along with ways to use the breath to direct the attention toward unpleasant sensations. When participants feel a painful, unpleasant, or stressful physical sensation, we encourage them to use their breathing practices to turn toward the sensation and explore it instead of avoiding the experience. This strategy can thereby lessen the tension related to “holding” emotional pain, stress, or anxiety. At home, a daily practice is preferred as opposed to more extensive training with longer intervals in between practice sessions. Regular, brief practice may be preferable for impacting change in pathophysiological mechanisms.The psycho-education part in Module 1 covers stress, breathing physiology, sleep, and a discussion about what really matters in the lives of the participants, i.e., defining one’s core-values.MODULE 2: ATTENDING AND CARING ABOUT OUR INNER EXPERIENCE (WEEKS 4–6)Module 2 focuses on attention regulation and practices of interoceptive awareness. In these practices, participants receive verbal guidance to practice paying attention to a variety of “objects of attention” (i.e., the stimuli to which one directs attention). The first set of attention objects includes sensory stimuli such as externally oriented sounds, smells and tactile sensations. Progressively, the focus of attention is shifted inward toward more subtle sensations. Interoceptive awareness may include attention to different types of somatic perceptions for example proprioceptive (a sense of where your body is in space), kinesthetic (a sense of body position, weight, muscle tension and movement), pain, and temperature sensations. The practice of attention and interoceptive awareness can be integrated with yoga-based movement and can also be extended to involve any kind of physical activity, such as walking, running or biking, so that it fits with the culture and interests of the adolescent. Gradually, brief practices in stillness, such as body scans and guided sitting meditations are introduced. Focusing on the breath is a traditional meditation practice and shifting from manipulation of the breath to simply attending to it may be a next step after the breathing practice introduced in Module 1.Traditionally, mindfulness-based interventions aim to increase the capacity to experience a full range of emotions and sensations instead of trying to ease or modify the experience. From our clinical experience of teaching mindfulness-based methods to adolescents with depression, this approach is often initially experienced as overwhelming and can be counter-productive for adherence and compliance to training. It is important to introduce attention training in a manner that is engaging, relevant, and manageable for the depressed adolescent in order to empower them and motivate continued practice. We hypothesize this practice of attending to one’s inner sensations may increase the ability to capture early warning signs of stress or depression and prepare the practitioner to become more aware and skillful in handling bodily expressions of emotions, which will be the focus of the next module. Teenagers are often preoccupied with handling peer pressure, are vulnerable to the judgments of others, and seek external reward. Caring for one’s own inner experience may increase the capacity for self-compassion and also facilitate empathy and compassion for others, all of which have been shown to increase resilience to depressive problems (Germer and Neff, 2013; Gilbert, 2014). We suggest that the heavy cultural bias to external stimuli and extrinsic value systems may lead to objectification, loss of internal points of references, and increased vulnerability to depressive illness. Thus, we hypothesize that practices of interoceptive awareness can be used to develop the capability to recognize one’s own intrinsic values, and by practice make them a foundation for behavior and action (see Module 4).The educational topics in Module 2 include basic brain function and how the TARA practices promote the brain’s capacity to regulate feelings of stress, anxiety and depression. The concept of attention is also explained and how attention can improve with practice. Healthy food and eating habits in relation to glucose regulation and mood are also explained.MODULE 3: RECOGNIZING, REGULATING, AND COMMUNICATING EMOTIONS (WEEKS 7–9)The skills training provided in Modules 1 and 2 are continued throughout this module for consolidation and to encourage the application of these practices as a foundation for emotion regulation. Breathing exercises in which exhalation is prolonged are introduced for calming effects and a simple exercise “Stop-Breathe-Act” is practiced with the aim of being able to use breath for emotion regulation in every day life. In Module 3, the practice of interoceptive awareness extends from being focused on body sensation to emotion recognition. The main focus of this module is development of the ability to link bodily sensations to present-moment emotional awareness. As children and adolescents with mood disorders often have alexithymia tendencies (Gulec et al., 2013), externalization techniques and non-verbal forms of describing emotion are included early in this module. For example, emotions can be depicted through artwork so the emotions can be recognized and described in terms of color, texture, shape, and weight. Labeling of emotions is the next step and it is practiced first as a strategy to regulate emotion and then as later as a way to communicate emotion.The next goal of this module is to use the acquired skills to communicate emotions to others in an empathic, responsible and pro-social way. Practices of recognizing and handling emotions in other people will be practiced. Toward the end of Module 3 there is also an introduction to understanding social triggers that cause negative emotions to arise and a focus on one’s own experiential avoidance strategies and how they may impede obtaining desired life-goals.The education portion of Module 3 focuses on explaining a schematic illustration of how the brain functions. To further enhance the participants’ autonomy in their practice and to empower them, they start guiding the breathing, yoga-based movement and brief meditations to each other under supervision of the facilitators.MODULE 4: CORE VALUES, GOAL SETTING AND COMMITTED ACTION (WEEKS 10–12)After basic regulatory skills have been acquired, more conventional cognitive reappraisal techniques to skillfully handle negative emotion regulation are introduced. Habitual thought patterns, assumptions, and cultural bias are tested and perspective shifting is practiced. Participants reassess the previously identified social triggers that cause negative emotions to arise for them and how their own experiential avoidance strategies impact their lives. In this last module, there is also an emphasis on summarizing personal core values. This has been a thread throughout the treatment, but it is now addressed directly through written and experiential activities. Each participant is supported in the process of finding out what they intrinsically value and then extending these values to behavior and action oriented toward future short and long-term life goals. Identifying core values may thus serve as a motivational force for sustainable behavioral activation in a way that is meaningful and relevant to the adolescent.Since adolescents with depression often have social difficulties there are also specific exercises on how to connect and contribute to others, such as teamwork exercises. We investigate different aspects of care and compassion, i.e., toward oneself and others along with the capacity to be able to receive care and compassion. These concepts are practiced in short, guided loving-kindness meditations and by behavioral practices such as “random acts of kindness.” The concepts of caring and compassion are also linked back to core values (i.e., we care about what we value and what is really important to us). Caring is also addressed in a more extended perspective. We hypothesize that explicit practices of how to care for each other will increase a sense of connectedness and decrease the sense of loneliness and separation that depressed adolescents often feel. Furthermore, we hypothesize based on our clinical experience that depressed adolescents often feel disconnected from their environment and lack a sense of purpose and meaning. Adolescents are sometimes left alone with relevant questions and concerns about an uncertain future and without the tools or the knowledge of how to be able to connect and contribute in meaningful ways. Consequently, we have integrated these topics throughout the TARA treatment by practicing care for one another and the world around us. Thus, in this last module, these issues are more explicitly addressed and concrete ways to engage and commit are identified and explored.Finally, great care is given to end the TARA program in a skillful way. Facilitators guide discussions centered on the following questions, among others: “What have I learned?” “How do I move forward from here?” “What do I do if I feel worse again?” The participants are encouraged to create their own personal daily practice aligned with their life goals. In this way, the breathing, yoga-based movement, and meditations are personalized to fit each participant and can be used as a foundation for life as they have been the foundation of the TARA intervention.SUMMARYIn this conceptual article, we describe the design of a semi-structured, progressive, and individually adaptable program based on the NIMH RDoC criteria for the treatment of adolescent depression without major anhedonia. The program prioritizes the core domains of function hypothesized to drive the pathophysiology of adolescent depression and employs straightforward and feasible treatment strategies that have been selected based on current scientific evidence. A limitation of the RDoC matrix is that the developmental aspects of adolescent depression are not well considered and some of the implied neurocircuitry overlaps between domains and constructs. To maximize time, resources, and feasibility, we therefore suggest specific neural circuits to be targeted in our treatment model rather than the full constructs. We hope that this work may form the basis for a novel and more effective treatment strategy for adolescent depression, as well as open up a discussion on how to take on this challenge. We aim to continue the curriculum development of TARA and to test feasibility and efficacy of this program in clinical populations, as well as study the neuroscientific and systemic regulatory mechanisms of change. Finally, we propose this treatment approach will both effectively treat depression and promote more general long-term health and well-being.Conflict of Interest StatementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.This work was supported by the Swedish Research Council (350-2012-303), the Swedish Society of Medicine (SLS244671) and the Sweden American Association to Eva Henje Blom, by the National Institute of Mental Health (R01MH085734, R01MH085734-02S1, and R01MH085734-05S1) to Tony T. Yang, (K01MH097978) to Kaja LeWinn, by the National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (K01AT005270) to Larissa G. Duncan and (1R01AT005820) to Margaret Chesney and (K24AT007827 and P01AT005013) to Frederick M. Hecht. The funding agencies played no role in the design, review, or approval of the manuscript. We wish to thank Dr. Laura Schmalzl for inspiration, Dr. Robert Hendren for his kind support and insightful comments, and Dr. Patricia Moran and Veronica Goldman for their work to support the study.REFERENCESAdegbite-AdeniyiC.GronB.RowlesB. M.DemeterC. A.FindlingR. L. (2012). An update on antidepressant use and suicidality in pediatric depression.Expert Opin. pharmacother.
13
2119–2130
10.1517/14656566.2012.72661322984934AgelinkM. W.BozC.UllrichH.AndrichJ. (2002). Relationship between major depression and heart rate variability. Clinical consequences and implications for antidepressive treatment.
Psychiatry Res.
113
139–149
10.1016/S0165-1781(02)00225-112467953Alexandrino-SilvaC.WangY. P.Carmen VianaM.BulhoesR. S.MartinsS. S.AndradeL. H. (2012). Gender differences in symptomatic profiles of depression: results from the sao paulo megacity mental health survey.
J. Affect. Disord.
147
355–364
10.1016/j.jad.2012.11.04123246363AlexopoulosG. S.AreanP. (2014). A model for streamlining psychotherapy in the RDoC era: the example of Engage.
Mol. Psychiatry
19
14–19
10.1038/mp.2013.15024280983AndersenS. L.TeicherM. H. (2008). Stress, sensitive periods and maturational events in adolescent depression.
Trends Neurosci.
31
183–191
10.1016/j.tins.2008.01.00418329735Andrews-HannaJ. R.Mackiewicz SegheteK. L.ClausE. D.BurgessG. C.RuzicL.BanichM. T. (2011). Cognitive control in adolescence: neural underpinnings and relation to self-report behaviors.
PLoS ONE
6:e21598
10.1371/journal.pone.0021598AngoldA.CostelloE. J. (1993). Depressive comorbidity in children and adolescents: empirical, theoretical, and methodological issues.
Am. J. Psychiatry
150
1779–17918238631AngoldA.CostelloE. J.ErkanliA.WorthmanC. M. (1999). Pubertal changes in hormone levels and depression in girls.
Psychol. Med.
29
1043–1053
10.1017/S003329179900894610576297AngoldA.CostelloE. J.WorthmanC. M. (1998). Puberty and depression: the roles of age, pubertal status and pubertal timing.
Psychol. Med.
28
51–61
10.1017/S003329179700593X9483683AngstJ.GammaA.BenazziF.SilversteinB.Ajdacic-GrossV.EichD. (2006). A typical depressive syndromes in varying definitions.
Eur. Arch. Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.
256
44–54
10.1007/s00406-005-0600-z16041559AngstJ.GammaA.SellaroR.ZhangH.MerikangasK. (2002). Toward validation of atypical depression in the community: results of the Zurich cohort study.
J. Affect. Disord.
72
125–138
10.1016/S0165-0327(02)00169-612200203AntonijevicI. (2008). HPA axis and sleep: identifying subtypes of major depression.
Stress
11
15–27
10.1080/1025389070137896717853067AntonijevicI. A. (2006). Depressive disorders – is it time to endorse different pathophysiologies?
Psychoneuroendocrinology
31
1–15
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2005.04.00415950391AveryJ. A.DrevetsW. C.MosemanS. E.BodurkaJ.BarcalowJ. C.SimmonsW. K. (2013). Major depressive disorder is associated with abnormal interoceptive activity and functional connectivity in the insula.
Biol. Psychiatry
76
258–266
10.1016/j.biopsych.2013.11.02724387823BalasubramaniamM.TellesS.DoraiswamyP. M. (2012). Yoga on our minds: a systematic review of yoga for neuropsychiatric disorders.
Front. Psychiatry
3:117
10.3389/fpsyt.2012.00117BedicsJ. D.KorslundK. E.SayrsJ. H.McFarrL. M. (2013). The observation of essential clinical strategies during an individual session of dialectical behavior therapy.
Psychotherapy
50
454–457
10.1037/a003241824000870BeeversC. G.ClasenP.SticeE.SchnyerD. (2010). Depression symptoms and cognitive control of emotion cues: a functional magnetic resonance imaging study.
Neuroscience
167
97–103
10.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.01.04720116416BennikE. C.NederhofE.OrmelJ.OldehinkelA. J. (2013). Anhedonia and depressed mood in adolescence: course, stability, and reciprocal relation in the TRAILS study.
Eur. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
23
579–586
10.1007/s00787-013-0481-z24154568BiegelG. M.BrownK. W.ShapiroS. L.SchubertC. M. (2009). Mindfulness-based stress reduction for the treatment of adolescent psychiatric outpatients: a randomized clinical trial.
J. Consult. Clin. Psychol.
77
855–866
10.1037/a001624119803566BirmaherB.ArbelaezC.BrentD. (2002). Course and outcome of child and adolescent major depressive disorder.
Child Adolesc. Psychiatr. Clin. N. Am.
11
619–637
10.1016/S1056-4993(02)00011-112222086BlantonR. E.CooneyR. E.JoormannJ.EugeneF.GloverG. H.GotlibI. H. (2012). Pubertal stage and brain anatomy in girls.
Neuroscience
217
105–112
10.1016/j.neuroscience.2012.04.05922569152BoraE.HarrisonB. J.YucelM.PantelisC. (2013). Cognitive impairment in euthymic major depressive disorder: a meta-analysis.
Psychol. Med.
43
2017–2026
10.1017/s003329171200208523098294BucknerR. L.Andrews-HannaJ. R.SchacterD. L. (2008). The brains default network: anatomy, function, and relevance to disease.
Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.
1124
1–38
10.1196/annals.1440.01118400922BurghyC. A.StodolaD. E.RuttleP. L.MolloyE. K.ArmstrongJ. M.OlerJ. A. (2012). Developmental pathways to amygdala-prefrontal function and internalizing symptoms in adolescence.
Nat. Neurosci.
15
1736–1741
10.1038/nn.325723143517CabralP.MeyerH. B.AmesD. (2011). Effectiveness of yoga therapy as a complementary treatment for major psychiatric disorders: a meta-analysis.
Prim. Care Companion CNS Disord.
13:PCC10r01068. 10.4088/PCC.10r01068CanbeyliR. (2013). Sensorimotor modulation of mood and depression: in search of an optimal mode of stimulation.
Front. Hum. Neurosci.
7:428
10.3389/fnhum.2013.00428CarmodyJ.BaerR. A. (2008). Relationships between mindfulness practice and levels of mindfulness, medical and psychological symptoms and well-being in a mindfulness-based stress reduction program.
J. Behav. Med.
31
23–33
10.1007/s10865-007-9130-717899351ConnollyC. G.WuJ.HoT. C.HoeftF.WolkowitzO.EisendrathS. (2013). Resting-state functional connectivity of subgenual anterior cingulate cortex in depressed adolescents.
Biol. Psychiatry
74
898–907
10.1016/j.biopsych.2013.05.03623910949CooneyG. M.DwanK.GreigC. A.LawlorD. A.RimerJ.WaughF. R. (2013). Exercise for depression.
Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
9:CD004366
10.1002/14651858.CD004366CooneyR. E.JoormannJ.EugeneF.DennisE. L.GotlibI. H. (2010). Neural correlates of rumination in depression.
Cogn. Affect. Behav. Neurosci.
10
470–478
10.3758/cabn.10.4.47021098808CostelloE. J.MustilloS.ErkanliA.KeelerG.AngoldA. (2003). Prevalence and development of psychiatric disorders in childhood and adolescence.
Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
60
837–844
10.1001/archpsyc.60.8.83712912767CoxG. R.CallahanP.ChurchillR.HunotV.MerryS. N.ParkerA. G. (2012). Psychological therapies versus antidepressant medication, alone and in combination for depression in children and adolescents.
Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
11:CD008324
10.1002/14651858.CD008324CraigA. D. (2009). How do you feel–now? The anterior insula and human awareness.
Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
10
59–70
10.1038/nrn255519096369CraigA. D. (2011). Significance of the insula for the evolution of human awareness of feelings from the body.
Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.
1225
72–82
10.1111/j.1749-6632.2011.05990.x21534994CramerS. C.SurM.DobkinB. H.O’BrienC.SangerT. D.TrojanowskiJ. Q. (2011). Harnessing neuroplasticity for clinical applications.
Brain
134
1591–609
10.1093/brain/awr03921482550CreswellJ. D.WayB. M.EisenbergerN. I.LiebermanM. D. (2007). Neural correlates of dispositional mindfulness during affect labeling.
Psychosom. Med.
69
560–565
10.1097/PSY.0b013e3180f6171f17634566CritchleyH. D. (2005). Neural mechanisms of autonomic, affective, and cognitive integration.
J. Comp. Neurol.
493
154–166
10.1002/cne.2074916254997CullenK. R.GeeD. G.Klimes-DouganB.GabbayV.HulvershornL.MuellerB. A. (2009). A preliminary study of functional connectivity in comorbid adolescent depression.
Neurosci. Lett.
460
227–231
10.1016/j.neulet.2009.05.02219446602CunninghamM. G.BhattacharyyaS.BenesF. M. (2002). Amygdalo-cortical sprouting continues into early adulthood: implications for the development of normal and abnormal function during adolescence.
J. Comp. Neurol.
453
116–130
10.1002/cne.1037612373778D’AndreaW.FordJ.StolbachB.SpinazzolaJ.van der KolkB. A. (2012). Understanding interpersonal trauma in children: why we need a developmentally appropriate trauma diagnosis.
Am. J. Orthopsychiatry
82
187–200
10.1111/j.1939-0025.2012.01154.x22506521DannlowskiU.StuhrmannA.BeutelmannV.ZwanzgerP.LenzenT.GrotegerdD. (2012). Limbic scars: long-term consequences of childhood maltreatment revealed by functional and structural magnetic resonance imaging.
Biol. Psychiatry
71
286–293
10.1016/j.biopsych.2011.10.02122112927DaveyC. G.HarrisonB. J.YucelM.AllenN. B. (2012a) Regionally specific alterations in functional connectivity of the anterior cingulate cortex in major depressive disorder.
Psychol. Med.
42
2071–2081
10.1017/S0033291712000323DaveyC. G.YucelM.AllenN. B.HarrisonB. J. (2012b). Task-related deactivation and functional connectivity of the subgenual cingulate cortex in major depressive disorder.
Front. Psychiatry
3:14
10.3389/fpsyt.2012.00014DaveyC. G.YucelM.AllenN. B. (2008). The emergence of depression in adolescence: development of the prefrontal cortex and the representation of reward.
Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
32
1–19
10.1016/j.neubiorev.2007.04.01617570526DennyB. T.OchsnerK. N. (2013). Behavioral Effects of Longitudinal Training in Cognitive Reappraisal.
Emotion (Washington, DC)
14
425–433
10.1037/a0035276DeRubeisR. J.SiegleG. J.HollonS. D. (2008). Cognitive therapy versus medication for depression: treatment outcomes and neural mechanisms.
Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
9
788–796
10.1038/nrn234518784657DesrosiersA.VineV.KlemanskiD. H.Nolen-HoeksemaS. (2013). Mindfulness and emotion regulation in depression and anxiety: common and distinct mechanisms of action.
Depress Anxiety
30
654–661
10.1002/da.2212423592556DisnerS. G.BeeversC. G.HaighE. A.BeckA. T. (2011). Neural mechanisms of the cognitive model of depression.
Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
12
467–477
10.1038/nrn302721731066DrevetsW. C.PriceJ. L.FureyM. L. (2008). Brain structural and functional abnormalities in mood disorders: implications for neurocircuitry models of depression.
Brain Struct. Funct.
213
93–118
10.1007/s00429-008-0189-x18704495DunnK. D. (2008). A review of the literature examining the physiological processes underlying the therapeutic benefits of Hatha yoga.
Adv. Mind Body Med.
23
10–1820664144EisendrathS.ChartierM.McLaneM. (2011). Adapting mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for treatment-resistant depression: a clinical case study.
Cogn. Behav. Pract.
18
362–370
10.1016/j.cbpra.2010.05.00422211062EisendrathS. J.GillungE. P.DelucchiK. L.ChartierM.MathalonD. H.SullivanJ. C. (2014). Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) versus the health-enhancement program (HEP) for adults with treatment-resistant depression: a randomized control trial study protocol.
BMC Complement. Alternat. Med.
14:95
10.1186/1472-6882-14-95ErnstM.KorelitzK. E. (2009). Cerebral maturation in adolescence: behavioral vulnerability.
Encephale
35(Suppl. 6)
S182–S1829
10.1016/s0013-7006(09)73469-420141770FalesC. L.BarchD. M.RundleM. M.MintunM. A.SnyderA. Z.CohenJ. D. (2008). Altered emotional interference processing in affective and cognitive-control brain circuitry in major depression.
Biol. Psychiatry
63
377–384
10.1016/j.biopsych.2007.06.01217719567FarbN. A.AndersonA. K.SegalZ. V. (2012). The mindful brain and emotion regulation in mood disorders.
Can. J. Psychiatry
57
70–7722340146FerrariA. J.CharlsonF. J.NormanR. E.PattenS. B.FreedmanG.MurrayC. J. (2013). Burden of depressive disorders by country, sex, age, and year: findings from the global burden of disease study 2010.
PLoS Med.
10:e1001547
10.1371/journal.pmed.1001547FjellA. M.WalhovdK. B.BrownT. T.KupermanJ. M.ChungY.HaglerD. J.Jr. (2012). Multimodal imaging of the self-regulating developing brain.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
109
19620–19625
10.1073/pnas.120824310923150548ForbesE. E.DahlR. E. (2012). Research Review: altered reward function in adolescent depression: what, when and how?
J. Child Psychol. Psychiatry
53
3–15
10.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02477.x22117893ForbesE. E.HaririA. R.MartinS. L.SilkJ. S.MoylesD. L.FisherP. M. (2009). Altered striatal activation predicting real-world positive affect in adolescent major depressive disorder.
Am. J. Psychiatry
166
64–73
10.1176/appi.ajp.2008.0708133619047324ForbesE. E.ShawD. S.DahlR. E. (2007). Alterations in reward-related decision making in boys with recent and future depression.
Biol. Psychiatry
61
633–639
10.1016/j.biopsych.2006.05.02616920074FordT.GoodmanR.MeltzerH. (2003). The British Child and Adolescent Mental Health Survey 1999: the prevalence of DSM-IV disorders.
J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
42
1203–1211
10.1097/01.chi.0000081820.2510714560170FritzscheA.DahmeB.GotlibI. H.JoormannJ.MagnussenH.WatzH. (2010). Specificity of cognitive biases in patients with current depression and remitted depression and in patients with asthma.
Psychol. Med.
40
815826
10.1017/s0033291709990948FurmanD. J.WaughC. E.BhattacharjeeK.ThompsonR. J.GotlibI. H. (2013). Interoceptive awareness, positive affect, and decision making in Major Depressive Disorder.
J. Affect. Disord.
151
780–785
10.1016/j.jad.2013.06.04423972662GabbayV.ElyB. A.LiQ.BangaruS. D.PanzerA. M.AlonsoC. M. (2013). Striatum-based circuitry of adolescent depression and anhedonia.
J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
52
628–641 e13. 10.1016/j.jaac.2013.04.00323702452GabbayV.HessD. A.LiuS.BabbJ. S.KleinR. G.GonenO. (2007). Lateralized caudate metabolic abnormalities in adolescent major depressive disorder: a proton MR spectroscopy study.
Am. J. Psychiatry
164
1881–1889
10.1176/appi.ajp.2007.0612203218056244GabbayV.KleinR. G.KatzY.MendozaS.GuttmanL. E.AlonsoC. M. (2010). The possible role of the kynurenine pathway in adolescent depression with melancholic features.
J. Child Psychol. Psychiatry
51
935–943
10.1111/j.1469-7610.2010.02245.x20406333GabbayV.LiebesL.KatzY.LiuS.MendozaS.BabbJ. S. (2009). The kynurenine pathway in adolescent depression: preliminary findings from a proton MR spectroscopy study.
Prog. Neuropsychopharmacol. Biol. Psychiatry
34
37–44
10.1016/j.pnpbp.2009.09.01519778568GabbayV.MaoX.KleinR. G.ElyB. A.BabbJ. S.PanzerA. M. (2012). Anterior cingulate cortex gamma-aminobutyric acid in depressed adolescents: relationship to anhedonia.
Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
69
139–149
10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2011.13121969419GeislerF. C.KubiakT.SiewertK.WeberH. (2013). Cardiac vagal tone is associated with social engagement and self-regulation.
Biol. Psychol.
93
279–286
10.1016/j.biopsycho.2013.02.01323466587GermerC. K.NeffK. D. (2013). Self-compassion in clinical practice.
J. Clin. Psychol.
69
856–867
10.1002/jclp.2202123775511GilbertP. (2014). The origins and nature of compassion focused therapy.
Br. J. Clin. Psychol.
53
6–41
10.1111/bjc.1204324588760GiorgioA.WatkinsK. E.ChadwickM.JamesS.WinmillL.DouaudG. (2010). Longitudinal changes in grey and white matter during adolescence.
Neuroimage
49
94–103
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.08.00319679191GogtayN.GieddJ. N.LuskL.HayashiK. M.GreensteinD.VaituzisA. C. (2004). Dynamic mapping of human cortical development during childhood through early adulthood.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
101
8174–8179
10.1073/pnas.040268010115148381GoyalM.SinghS.SibingaE. M.GouldN. F.Rowland-SeymourA.SharmaR. (2014). Meditation programs for psychological stress and well-being: a systematic review and meta-analysis.
JAMA Intern. Med.
174
357–368
10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.1301824395196GreiciusM. (2008). Resting-state functional connectivity in neuropsychiatric disorders.
Curr. Opin. Neurol.
21
424–430
10.1097/WCO.0b013e328306f2c518607202GulecM. Y.AltintasM.InancL.BezginC. H.KocaE. K.GulecH. (2013). Effects of childhood trauma on somatization in major depressive disorder: the role of alexithymia.
J. Affect. Disord.
146
137–141
10.1016/j.jad.2012.06.03322884234GuoY.NilssonM. E.HeiligensteinJ.WilsonM. G.EmslieG. (2006). An exploratory factor analysis of the childrens depression rating scale-revised.
J. Child Adolesc. Psychopharmacol.
16
482–491
10.1089/cap.2006.16.48216958573HalbreichU.KahnL. S. (2007). Atypical depression, somatic depression and anxious depression in women: are they gender-preferred phenotypes?
J. Affect. Disord.
102
245–258
10.1016/j.jad.2006.09.02317092565HamiltonJ. P.ChenM. C.GotlibI. H. (2013). Neural systems approaches to understanding major depressive disorder: an intrinsic functional organization perspective.
Neurobiol. Dis.
52
4–11
10.1016/j.nbd.2012.01.01523477309HanG.Klimes-DouganB.JepsenS.BallardK.NelsonM.HouriA. (2012). Selective neurocognitive impairments in adolescents with major depressive disorder.
J. Adolesc.
35
11–20
10.1016/j.adolescence.2011.06.00921782233HarveyA. G.MurrayG.ChandlerR. A.SoehnerA. (2011). Sleep disturbance as transdiagnostic: consideration of neurobiological mechanisms.
Clin. Psychol. Rev.
31
225–235
10.1016/j.cpr.2010.04.00320471738HayesL.BachP. A.BoydC. P. (2010). Psychological treatment for adolescent depression: perspectives on the past, present and future.
Behav. Chang.
27
1–18
10.1375/bech.27.1.1HayesL.BoydC. P.SewellJ. (2011). Acceptance and commitment therapy for the treatment of adolescent depression: a pilot study in a psychaitric outpatient setting.
Mindfulness
2
86–94
10.1007/s12671-011-0046-5HeimC.NewportD. J.HeitS.GrahamY. P.WilcoxM.BonsallR. (2000). Pituitary-adrenal and autonomic responses to stress in women after sexual and physical abuse in childhood.
JAMA
284
592–597
10.1001/jama.284.5.59210918705Henje BlomE.ForsmaM.YangT. T.SerlachiusE.LarssonJ. O. (2014). Latent classes of symptoms related to clinically depressed mood in adolescents.
Scand. J. Child Adolesc. Psychiatr. Psychol.
2
19–28
10.1037/a0015923Henje BlomE.LekanderM.IngvarM.AsbergM.MobarrezF.SerlachiusE. (2011). Pro-inflammatory cytokines are elevated in adolescent females with emotional disorders not treated with SSRIs.
J. Affect. Disord.
136
716–723
10.1016/j.jad.2011.10.00222056230Henje BlomE.OlssonE. M.SerlachiusE.EricsonM.IngvarM. (2010). Heart rate variability (HRV) in adolescent females with anxiety disorders and major depressive disorder.
Acta Paediatr.
99
604–611
10.1111/j.1651-2227.2009.01657.x20121706HetrickS.MerryS.McKenzieJ.SindahlP.ProctorM. (2007). Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) for depressive disorders in children and adolescents.
Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
18 CD004851. 10.1002/14651858.CD004851HettemaJ. M. (2008). What is the genetic relationship between anxiety and depression?
Am. J. Med. Genet. C Semin. Med. Genet. 148C, 140–146
10.1002/ajmg.c.3017118412101HoT. C.WuJ.ShinD. D.LiuT. T.TapertS. F.YangG. (2013). Altered cerebral perfusion in executive, affective, and motor networks during adolescent depression.
J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
52
1076–1091 e2. 10.1016/j.jaac.2013.07.00824074474HoT. C.YangG.WuJ.CasseyP.BrownS. D.HoangN. (2014). Functional connectivity of negative emotional processing in adolescent depression.
J. Affect. Disord.
155
65–74
10.1016/j.jad.2013.10.02524268546HouW. H.ChiangP. T.HsuT. Y.ChiuS. Y.YenY. C. (2010). Treatment effects of massage therapy in depressed people: a meta-analysis.
J. Clin. Psychiatry
71
894–901
10.4088/JCP.09r05009blu20361919HulvershornL. A.CullenK.AnandA. (2011). Toward dysfunctional connectivity: a review of neuroimaging findings in pediatric major depressive disorder.
Brain Imaging Behav.
5
307–328
10.1007/s11682-011-9134-321901425InselT.CuthbertB.GarveyM.HeinssenR.PineD. S.QuinnK. (2010). Research domain criteria (RDoC): toward a new classification framework for research on mental disorders.
Am. J. Psychiatry
167
748–751
10.1176/appi.ajp.2010.0909137920595427JoormannJ.CooneyR. E.HenryM. L.GotlibI. H. (2012). Neural correlates of automatic mood regulation in girls at high risk for depression.
J. Abnorm. Psychol.
121
61–72
10.1037/a002529421895344JoormannJ.GoodmanS. H. (2014). Transdiagnostic processes in psychopathology: in memory of susan nolen-hoeksema.
J. Abnorm. Psychol.
123
49–50
10.1037/a003552524661158JoormannJ.GotlibI. H. (2007). Selective attention to emotional faces following recovery from depression.
J. Abnorm. Psychol.
116
80–85
10.1037/0021-843x.116.1.8017324018JusterR. P.McEwenB. S.LupienS. J. (2010). Allostatic load biomarkers of chronic stress and impact on health and cognition.
Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
35
2–16
10.1016/j.neubiorev.2009.10.00219822172Kabat-ZinnJ. (1996). Full Catastrophe Living: How to Cope with Stress, Pain and Illness Using Mindfulness Meditation.
London: PiaktusKaratsoreosI. N.McEwenB. S. (2013). Resilience and vulnerability: a neurobiological perspective.
F1000prime Rep.
5
13
10.12703/p5-13KaymakS. U.DemirB.SenturkS.TatarI.AldurM. M.UlugB. (2010). Hippocampus, glucocorticoids and neurocognitive functions in patients with first-episode major depressive disorders.
Eur. Arch. Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.
260
217–223
10.1007/s00406-009-0045-x19756819KellerM. B.LavoriP. W.WunderJ.BeardsleeW. R.SchwartzC. E.RothJ. (1992). Chronic course of anxiety disorders in children and adolescents.
J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
31
595–599
10.1097/00004583-199207000-000031644719KemptonM. J.SalvadorZ.MunafoM. R.GeddesJ. R.SimmonsA.FrangouS. (2011). Structural neuroimaging studies in major depressive disorder. Meta-analysis and comparison with bipolar disorder.
Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
68
675–690
10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2011.60.21727252KerestesR.DaveyC. G.StephanouK.WhittleS.HarrisonB. J. (2013). Functional brain imaging studies of youth depression: a systematic review.
Neuroimage Clin.
4
209–231
10.1016/j.nicl.2013.11.00924455472KesslerR. C.AngermeyerM.AnthonyJ. C.DE GraafR.DemyttenaereK.GasquetI. (2007). Lifetime prevalence and age-of-onset distributions of mental disorders in the world health organization’s world mental health survey initiative.
World Psychiatry
6
168–176
10.1192/bjp.188.5.50018188442KhalsaS. B. (2013). Yoga for psychiatry and mental health: an ancient practice with modern relevance.
Indian J. Psychiatry
55(Suppl. 3)
S334–S33624049194KhalsaS. B.Hickey-SchultzL.CohenD.SteinerN.CopeS. (2012). Evaluation of the mental health benefits of yoga in a secondary school: a preliminary randomized controlled trial.
J. Behav. Health Serv. Res.
39
80–90
10.1007/s11414-011-9249-821647811KimS.WollburgE.RothW. T. (2012). Opposing breathing therapies for panic disorder: a randomized controlled trial of lowering vs raising end-tidal P(CO2).
J. Clin. Psychiatry
73
931–939
10.4088/JCP.11m0706822901344KoenigA. M.ButtersM. A. (2014). Cognition in late life depression: treatment considerations.
Curr. Treat. Options Psychiatry
1
1–14
10.1007/s40501-013-0001-224665414KorczakD. J.GoldsteinB. I. (2009). Childhood onset major depressive disorder: course of illness and psychiatric comorbidity in a community sample.
J. Pediatr.
155
118–123
10.1016/j.jpeds.2009.01.06119394039KuykenW.WeareK.UkoumunneO. C.VicaryR.MottonN.BurnettR. (2013). Effectiveness of the mindfulness in schools programme: non-randomised controlled feasibility study.
Br. J. Psychiatry
203
126–131
10.1192/bjp.bp.113.12664923787061LaneR. D.WeidenbacherH.SmithR.FortC.ThayerJ. F.AllenJ. J. (2013). Subgenual anterior cingulate cortex activity covariation with cardiac vagal control is altered in depression.
J. Affect. Disord.
150
565–570
10.1016/j.jad.2013.02.00523473547LeDouxJ. (2007). The amygdala.
Curr Biol
17
R868–R874
10.1016/j.cub.2007.08.00517956742LevinM. E.HildebrandtM. J.LillisJ.HayesS. C. (2012). The impact of treatment components suggested by the psychological flexibility model: a meta-analysis of laboratory-based component studies.
Behav. Ther.
43
741–756
10.1016/j.beth.2012.05.00323046777LichtC. M.de GeusE. J.ZitmanF. G.HoogendijkW. J.van DyckR.PenninxB. W. (2008). Association between major depressive disorder and heart rate variability in the Netherlands Study of Depression and Anxiety (NESDA).
Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
65
1358–1367
10.1001/archpsyc.65.12.135819047522LiebermanM. D.EisenbergerN. I.CrockettM. J.TomS. M.PfeiferJ. H.WayB. M. (2007). Putting feelings into words: affect labeling disrupts amygdala activity in response to affective stimuli.
Psychol. Sci.
18
421–428
10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01916.x17576282LischetzkeT.EidM. (2003). Is attention to feelings beneficial or detrimental to affective well-being? Mood regulation as a moderator variable.
Emotion (Washington, DC)
3
361–377
10.1037/1528-3542.3.4.361LucasM.Chocano-BedoyaP.ShulzeM. B.MirzaeiF.OReillyE. J.OkerekeO. I. (2013). Inflammatory dietary pattern and risk of depression among women.
Brain Behav. Immun.
36
46–53
10.1016/j.bbi.2013.09.01424095894LupienS. J.ParentS.EvansA. C.TremblayR. E.ZelazoP. D.CorboV. (2011). Larger amygdala but no change in hippocampal volume in 10-year-old children exposed to maternal depressive symptomatology since birth.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
108
14324–14329
10.1073/pnas.110537110821844357LvX. N.LiuZ. J.ZhangH. J.TzengC. M. (2013). Aromatherapy and the central nerve system (CNS): therapeutic mechanism and its associated genes.
Curr. Drug Targets
14
872–879
10.2174/138945011131408000723531112MaesM.KuberaM.ObuchowiczwaE.GoehlerL.BrzeszczJ. (2011). Depressions multiple comorbidities explained by (neuro)inflammatory and oxidative &amp; nitrosative stress pathways.
Neuro. Endocrinol. Lett.
32
7–2421407167MandellD.SiegleG. J.ShuttL.FeldmillerJ.ThaseM. E. (2014). Neural substrates of trait ruminations in depression.
J. Abnorm. Psychol.
123
35–48
10.1037/a003583424661157ManglickM.RajaratnamS. M.TaffeJ.TongeB.MelvinG. (2013). Persistent sleep disturbance is associated with treatment response in adolescents with depression.
Aust. N. Z. J. Psychiatry
47
556–563
10.1177/000486741348163023508680ManoliuA.MengC.BrandlF.DollA.TahmasianM.ScherrM. (2013). Insular dysfunction within the salience network is associated with severity of symptoms and aberrant inter-network connectivity in major depressive disorder.
Front. Hum. Neurosci.
7:930
10.3389/fnhum.2013.00930MarchJ. S.VitielloB. (2009). Clinical messages from the treatment for adolescents with depression study (TADS).
Am. J. Psychiatry
166
1118–1123
10.1176/appi.ajp.2009.0810160619723786McEwenB. S. (2003). Mood disorders and allostatic load.
Biol. Psychiatry
54
200–207
10.1016/S0006-3223(03)00177-X12893096McGintyD.SzymusiakR. (2003). Hypothalamic regulation of sleep and arousal.
Front. Biosci.
8:s1074–s1083
10.2741/115912957869McIntyreR. S.SoczynskaJ. K.KonarskiJ. Z.WoldeyohannesH. O.LawC. W.MirandaA. (2007). Should Depressive Syndromes Be Reclassified as “Metabolic Syndrome Type II”?
Ann. Clin. Psychiatry
19
257–264
10.1080/1040123070165337718058283McMakinD. L.OlinoT. M.PortaG.DietzL. J.EmslieG.ClarkeG. (2012). Anhedonia predicts poorer recovery among youth with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor treatment-resistant depression.
J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
51
404–411
10.1016/j.jaac.2012.01.01122449646MerikangasK. R.HeJ. P.RapoportJ.VitielloB.OlfsonM. (2013). Medication use in US youth with mental disorders.
JAMA Pediatr.
167
141–148
10.1001/jamapediatrics.2013.43123403911MeuretA. E.RitzT.WilhelmF. H.RothW. T. (2005). Voluntary hyperventilation in the treatment of panic disorder–functions of hyperventilation, their implications for breathing training, and recommendations for standardization.
Clin. Psychol. Rev.
25
285–306
10.1016/j.cpr.2005.01.00215792851MichlL. C.McLaughlinK. A.ShepherdK.Nolen-HoeksemaS. (2013). Rumination as a mechanism linking stressful life events to symptoms of depression and anxiety: longitudinal evidence in early adolescents and adults.
J. Abnorm. Psychol.
122
339–352
10.1037/a003199423713497MiddeldorpC. M.CathD. C.Van DyckR.BoomsmaD. I. (2005). The co-morbidity of anxiety and depression in the perspective of genetic epidemiology. a review of twin and family studies.
Psychol. Med.
35
611–624
10.1017/S003329170400412X15918338MorN.WinquistJ. (2002). Self-focused attention and negative affect: a meta-analysis.
Psychol. Bull.
128
638–662
10.1037/0033-2909.128.4.63812081086MorrisJ. S.FristonK. J.BuchelC.FrithC. D.YoungA. W.CalderA. J. (1998). A neuromodulatory role for the human amygdala in processing emotional facial expressions.
Brain
121
47–57
10.1093/brain/121.1.479549487MunshiK.EisendrathS.DelucchiK. (2013). Preliminary long-term follow-up of Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy-induced remission of depression.
Mindfulness
4
354–361
10.1007/s12671-012-0135-024443660MutschlerI.BallT.WankerlJ.StrigoI. A. (2012). Pain and emotion in the insular cortex: evidence for functional reorganization in major depression.
Neurosci. Lett.
520
204–209
10.1016/j.neulet.2012.03.09522503725NaickerK.GalambosN. L.ZengY.SenthilselvanA.ColmanI. (2013). Social, demographic, and health outcomes in the 10 years following adolescent depression.
J. Adolesc. Health
52
533–538
10.1016/j.jadohealth.2012.12.01623499382NieuwenhuysR. (2012). The insular cortex: a review.
Prog. Brain Res.
195
123–163
10.1016/b978-0-444-53860-4.00007-622230626NoggleJ. J.SteinerN. J.MinamiT.KhalsaS. B. (2012). Benefits of yoga for psychosocial well-being in a US high school curriculum: a preliminary randomized controlled trial.
J. Dev. Behav. Pediatr.
33
193–201
10.1097/DBP.0b013e31824afdc422343481OlinoT. M.KleinD. N.LewinsohnP. M.RohdeP.SeeleyJ. R. (2008). Longitudinal associations between depressive and anxiety disorders: a comparison of two trait models.
Psychol. Med.
38
353–363
10.1017/S003329170700134117803836OspinaM. B.BondK.KarkhanehM.BuscemiN.DrydenD. M.BarnesV. (2008). Clinical trials of meditation practices in health care: characteristics and quality.
J. Altern. Complement. Med.
14
1199–11213
10.1089/acm.2008.030719123875PaingW. W.WellerR. A.BrennanL.WellerE. B. (2008). Atypical depression in children and adolescents.
Curr. Psychiatry Rep.
10
130–133
10.1007/s11920-008-0023-418474203PandeyG. N.RizaviH. S.RenX.DwivediY.PalkovitsM. (2013). Region-specific alterations in glucocorticoid receptor expression in the postmortem brain of teenage suicide victims.
Psychoneuroendocrinology
38
2628–2639
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2013.06.02023845513ParkG.Van BavelJ. J.VaseyM. W.ThayerJ. F. (2012). Cardiac vagal tone predicts inhibited attention to fearful faces.
Emotion (Washington, DC) 12
1292–1302
10.1037/a002852822642338ParkG.Van BavelJ. J.VaseyM. W.ThayerJ. F. (2013). Cardiac vagal tone predicts attentional engagement to and disengagement from fearful faces.
Emotion (Washington, DC)
13
645–656
10.1037/a0032971ParkM. C.GoldmanM. A.CarpenterL. L.PriceL. H.FriehsG. M. (2007). Vagus nerve stimulation for depression: rationale, anatomical and physiological basis of efficacy and future prospects.
Acta Neurochir.
97 (Suppl. 1)
407–416
10.1007/978-3-211-33081-4_46PatronE.Messerotti BenvenutiS.FavrettoG.ValfreC.BonfaC.GasparottoR. (2012). Biofeedback assisted control of respiratory sinus arrhythmia as a biobehavioral intervention for depressive symptoms in patients after cardiac surgery: a preliminary study.
Appl. Psychophysiol. Biofeedback
38
1–9
10.1007/s10484-012-9202-522829151PaulN. A.StantonS. J.GreesonJ. M.SmoskiM. J.WangL. (2013). Psychological and neural mechanisms of trait mindfulness in reducing depression vulnerability.
Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.
8
56–64
10.1093/scan/nss07022717383PerlmanG.SimmonsA. N.WuJ.HahnK. S.TapertS. F.MaxJ. E. (2012). Amygdala response and functional connectivity during emotion regulation: a study of 14 depressed adolescents.
J. Affect. Disord.
139
75–84
10.1016/j.jad.2012.01.04422401827PerouR.BitskoR. H.BlumbergS. J.PastorP.GhandourR. M.GfroererJ. C. (2013). Mental health surveillance among children–United States, 2005-2011.
MMWR Surveill. Summ.
62(Suppl. 2)
1–3523677130PerryN.PerryE. (2006). Aromatherapy in the management of psychiatric disorders: clinical and neuropharmacological perspectives.
CNS Drugs
20
257–280
10.2165/00023210-200620040-0000116599645PhanK. L.WagerT. D.TaylorS. F.LiberzonI. (2004). Functional neuroimaging studies of human emotions.
CNS Spectr.
9
258–26615048050PilkingtonK.KirkwoodG.RampesH.RichardsonJ. (2005). Yoga for depression: the research evidence.
J. Affect. Disord.
89
13–24
10.1016/j.jad.2005.08.01316185770PorgesS. W. (2009). The polyvagal theory: new insights into adaptive reactions of the autonomic nervous system.
Cleve. Clin. J. Med.
76(Suppl. 2)
S86–S90
10.3949/ccjm.76.s2.1719376991PoznanskiE. O. (1996). Children’s Depression Rating Scale-Revised (CDRS-R) Manual (ASIN: B0006RINEM ed.).
Los Angeles, CA: Western Psychological ServicesPriceJ. L.DrevetsW. C. (2010). Neurocircuitry of mood disorders.
Neuropsychopharmacology
35
192–216
10.1038/npp.2009.10419693001PriceJ. L.DrevetsW. C. (2012). Neural circuits underlying the pathophysiology of mood disorders.
Trends Cogn. Sci.
16
61–71
10.1016/j.tics.2011.12.01122197477RaesF.GriffithJ. WVan der GuchtK.WilliamsJ. M. G. (2013). School-based prevention and reduction of depression in adolescents: a cluster-randomized controlled trial of a mindfulness group program.
Mindfulness
10.1007/s12671-013-0202-1
[Epub ahead of print]ReineckeM. A.CurryJ. F.MarchJ. S. (2009). Findings from the treatment for adolescents with depression study (TADS): what have we learned? What do we need to know?
J. Clin. Child Adolesc.
53
38
761–767
10.1080/15374410903258991ResslerK. J.MaybergH. S. (2007). Targeting abnormal neural circuits in mood and anxiety disorders: from the laboratory to the clinic.
Nat. Neurosci.
10
1116–1124
10.1038/nn194417726478RiemannD.SpiegelhalderK.FeigeB.VoderholzerU.BergerM.PerlisM. (2010). The hyperarousal model of insomnia: a review of the concept and its evidence.
Sleep Med. Rev.
14
19–31
10.1016/j.smrv.2009.04.00219481481RiveM. M.van RooijenG.VeltmanD. J.PhillipsM. L.ScheneA. H.RuheH. G. (2013). Neural correlates of dysfunctional emotion regulation in major depressive disorder. A systematic review of neuroimaging studies.
Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
37
2529–2553
10.1016/j.neubiorev.2013.07.01823928089RubiaK. (2013). Functional brain imaging across development.
Eur. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
22
719–731
10.1007/s00787-012-0291-822729957SchuchJ. J.RoestA. M.NolenW. A.PenninxB. W.de JongeP. (2014). Gender differences in major depressive disorder: results from the Netherlands study of depression and anxiety.
J. Affect. Disord.
156
156–163
10.1016/j.jad.2013.12.01124388685SeligmanL. D.OllendickT. H. (1998). Comorbidity of anxiety and depression in children and adolescents: an integrative review.
Clin. Child Fam. Psychol. Rev.
1
125–144
10.1023/A:102188771287311324302SeminowiczD. A.MaybergH. S.McIntoshA. R.GoldappleK.KennedyS.SegalZ. (2004). Limbic-frontal circuitry in major depression: a path modeling metanalysis.
Neuroimage
22
409–418
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.01.01515110034ShapiroD.CookI. A.DavydovD. M.OttavianiC.LeuchterA. F.AbramsM. (2007). Yoga as a complementary treatment of depression: effects of traits and moods on treatment outcome.
Evid. Based Complement. Altern. Med.
4
493–502
10.1093/ecam/nel114SharmaH.SenS.SinghA.BhardwajN. K.KochupillaiV.SinghN. (2003) Sudarshan Kriya practitioners exhibit better antioxidant status and lower blood lactate levels.
Biol. Psychol.
63
281–291
10.1016/s0301-0511(03)00071-112853172ShelineY. I.BarchD. M.DonnellyJ. M.OllingerJ. M.SnyderA. Z.MintunM. A. (2001). Increased amygdala response to masked emotional faces in depressed subjects resolves with antidepressant treatment: an fMRI study.
Biol. Psychiatry
50
651–658
10.1016/S0006-3223(01)01263-X11704071ShonkoffJ. P.GarnerA. S. (2012). The lifelong effects of early childhood adversity and toxic stress.
Pediatrics
129
e232–e246
10.1542/peds.2011-266322201156SiepmannM.AykacV.UnterdorferJ.PetrowskiK.Mueck-WeymannM. (2008). A pilot study on the effects of heart rate variability biofeedback in patients with depression and in healthy subjects.
Appl. Psychophysiol. Biofeedback
33
195–201
10.1007/s10484-008-9064-z18807175SilversteinB. (2002). Gender differences in the prevalence of somatic versus pure depression: a replication.
Am. J. Psychiatry
159
1051–1052
10.1176/appi.ajp.159.6.105112042198SmithS. S. (2012). The influence of stress at puberty on mood and learning: role of the α4βδ GABAA receptor.
Neuroscience
26
192–213
10.1016/j.neuroscience.2012.09.06523079628SpencerT. J. (2006). ADHD and comorbidity in childhood.
J. Clin. Psychiatry
67(Suppl. 8)
27–3116961427SpicuzzaL.GabuttiA.PortaC.MontanoN.BernardiL. (2000). Yoga and chemoreflex response to hypoxia and hypercapnia.
Lancet
3569240
1495–1496
10.1016/s0140-6736(00)02881-611081541SteinM. B.FuetschM.MullerN.HoflerM.LiebR.WittchenH. U. (2001). Social anxiety disorder and the risk of depression: a prospective community study of adolescents and young adults.
Arch. Gen. Psychiatry
58
251–256
10.1001/archpsyc.58.3.25111231832SteinerM.DunnE.BornL. (2003). Hormones and mood: from menarche to menopause and beyond.
J. Affect. Disord.
74
67–83
10.1016/S0165-0327(02)00432-912646300SutartoA. P.WahabM. N.ZinN. M. (2012). Resonant breathing biofeedback training for stress reduction among manufacturing operators.
Int. J. Occup. Safety Ergon.
18
549–561SzymusiakR.GviliaI.McGintyD. (2007). Hypothalamic control of sleep.
Sleep Med.
8
291–301
10.1016/j.sleep.2007.03.01317468047TamuraM.MoriguchiY.HiguchiS.HidaA.EnomotoM.UmezawaJ. (2012). Neural network development in late adolescents during observation of risk-taking action.
PLoS ONE
7:e39527
10.1371/journal.pone.0039527TaylorS. E.WayB. M.SeemanT. E. (2011). Early adversity and adult health outcomes.
Dev. Psychopathol.
23
939–954
10.1017/s095457941100041121756443TeicherM. H.AndersonC. M.PolcariA. (2012). Childhood maltreatment is associated with reduced volume in the hippocampal subfields CA3 dentate gyrus, and subiculum.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
109
E563–E572
10.1073/pnas.111539610922331913Ter HorstG. J.WichmannR.GerritsM.WestenbroekC.LinY. (2009). Sex differences in stress responses: focus on ovarian hormones.
Physiol. Behav.
97
239–249
10.1016/j.physbeh.2009.02.03619275910ThaparA.CollishawS.PineD. S.ThaparA. K. (2012). Depression in adolescence.
Lancet
3799820
1056–1067
10.1016/s0140-6736(11)60871-422305766ThayerJ. F.SternbergE. (2006). Beyond heart rate variability: vagal regulation of allostatic systems.
Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.
1088
361–372
10.1196/annals.1366.01417192580ThompsonR. J.MataJ.JaeggiS. M.BuschkuehlM.JonidesJ.GotlibI. H. (2013). The role of attention to emotion in recovery from major depressive disorder.
Depress. Res. Treat.
2013:540726
10.1155/2013/540726ToneattoT.NguyenL. (2007). Does mindfulness meditation improve anxiety and mood symptoms? A review of the controlled research.
Can. J. Psychiatry.
52
260–26617500308TorrisiS. J.LiebermanM. D.BookheimerS. Y.AltshulerL. L. (2013). Advancing understanding of affect labeling with dynamic causal modeling.
Neuroimage 82C, 481–488
10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.06.02523774393TweeddaleP. M.RowbottomI.McHardyG. J. (1994). Breathing retraining: effect on anxiety and depression scores in behavioural breathlessness.
J. Psychosom. Res.
38
11–21
10.1016/0022-3999(94)90004-38126685UebelackerL. A.Epstein-LubowG.GaudianoB. A.TremontG.BattleC. L.MillerI. W. (2010). Hatha yoga for depression: critical review of the evidence for efficacy, plausible mechanisms of action, and directions for future research.
J. Psychiatr. Pract.
16
22–33
10.1097/01.pra.0000367775.88388.9620098228VonckK.RaedtR.NaulaertsJ.De VogelaereF.ThieryE.Van RoostD. (2014). Vagus nerve stimulation … 25 years later! What do we know about the effects on cognition?
Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev. 45C, 63–71
10.1016/j.neubiorev.2014.05.00524858008WatanabeN.HunotV.OmoriI. M.ChurchillR.FurukawaT. A. (2007). Psychotherapy for depression among children and adolescents: a systematic review.
Acta Psychiatr. Scand.
116
84–95
10.1111/j.1600-0447.2007.01018.x17650269WeiserM. J.HandaR. J. (2009). Estrogen impairs glucocorticoid dependent negative feedback on the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis via estrogen receptor alpha within the hypothalamus.
Neuroscience
159
883–895
10.1016/j.neuroscience.2008.12.05819166915WeiszJ. R.ChorpitaB. F.FryeA.NgM. Y.LauN.BearmanS. K. (2011). Youth Top Problems: using idiographic, consumer-guided assessment to identify treatment needs and to track change during psychotherapy.
J. Consult. Clin. Psychol.
79
369–380
10.1037/a002330721500888WeiszJ. R.McCartyC. A.ValeriS. M. (2006). Effects of psychotherapy for depression in children and adolescents: a meta-analysis.
Psychol. Bull.
132
132–149
10.1037/0033-2909.132.1.13216435960WilliamsJ. M.CraneC.BarnhoferT.BrennanK.DugganD. S.FennellM. J. (2013). Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for preventing relapse in recurrent depression: a randomized dismantling trial.
J. Consult. Clin. Psychol.
82
275–286
10.1037/a003503624294837WilliamsonD. E.BirmaherB.BrentD. A.BalachL.DahlR. E.RyanN. D. (2000). Atypical symptoms of depression in a sample of depressed child and adolescent outpatients.
J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
39
1253–1259
10.1097/00004583-200010000-0001211026179WolkowitzO. M.ReusV. I.MellonS. H. (2011). Of sound mind and body: depression, disease, and accelerated aging.
Dialogues Clin. Neurosci.
13
25–3921485744WollburgE.RothW. T.KimS. (2011). Effects of breathing training on voluntary hypo- and hyperventilation in patients with panic disorder and episodic anxiety.
Appl. Psychophysiol. Biofeedback
36
81–91
10.1007/s10484-011-9150-521373936YangT. T.SimmonsA. N.MatthewsS. C.TapertS. F.Bischoff-GretheA.FrankG. K. (2007). Increased amygdala activation is related to heart rate during emotion processing in adolescent subjects.
Neurosci. Lett.
428
109–114
10.1016/j.neulet.2007.09.03918029095YangT. T.SimmonsA. N.MatthewsS. C.TapertS. F.FrankG. K.Bischoff-GretheA. (2009). Depressed adolescents demonstrate greater subgenual anterior cingulate activity.
Neuroreport
20
440–444
10.1097/WNR.0b013e3283262e1019218875YangT. T.SimmonsA. N.MatthewsS. C.TapertS. F.FrankG. K.MaxJ. E. (2010). Adolescents with major depression demonstrate increased amygdala activation.
J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
49
42–5120215925Yurgelun-ToddD. A.KillgoreW. D. (2006). Fear-related activity in the prefrontal cortex increases with age during adolescence: a preliminary fMRI study.
Neurosci. Lett.
406
194–199
10.1016/j.neulet.2006.07.04616942837
