<?xml version="1.0"?>
TrialsTrialsTrials1745-6215BioMed CentralLondon5474001201210.1186/s13063-017-2012-6Study ProtocolEffects of digital Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Insomnia on cognitive function: study protocol for a randomised controlled trialKyleSimon D.simon.kyle@ndcn.ox.ac.uk1HurryMadeleine E. D.madeleine.hurry@ndcn.ox.ac.uk12EmsleyRichardrichard.emsley@manchester.ac.uk3LuikAnnemarie I.annemarie.luik@ndcn.ox.ac.uk14OmlinXimenaximena.omlin@ndcn.ox.ac.uk1SpiegelhalderKaikai.spiegelhalder@uniklinik-freiburg.de5EspieColin A.colin.espie@ndcn.ox.ac.uk14SextonClaire E.claire.sexton@psych.ox.ac.uk210000 0004 1936 8948grid.4991.5Nuffield Department of Clinical Neurosciences, Sleep and Circadian Neuroscience Institute, University of Oxford, Sir William Dunn School of Pathology, South Parks Road, Oxford, OX1 3RE UK 20000 0004 1936 8948grid.4991.5Oxford Nuffield Department of Clinical Neurosciences, Centre for Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging of the Brain (FMRIB Centre), University of Oxford, Oxford, UK 30000000121662407grid.5379.8Centre for Biostatistics, School of Health Sciences, The University of Manchester, Manchester Academic Health Science Centre, Manchester, UK 4Big Health Ltd., London, UK 5grid.5963.9Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, Medical Center - University of Freiburg, Faculty of Medicine, University of Freiburg, Freiburg, Germany 1762017176201720171828116220172352017© The Author(s). 2017
Open AccessThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundThe daytime effects of insomnia pose a significant burden to patients and drive treatment seeking. In addition to subjective deficits, meta-analytic data show that patients experience reliable objective impairments across several cognitive domains. While Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Insomnia (CBT-I) is an effective and scalable treatment, we know little about its impact upon cognitive function. Trials of CBT-I have typically used proxy measures for cognitive functioning, such as fatigue or work performance scales, and no study has assessed self-reported impairment in cognitive function as a primary outcome. Moreover, only a small number of studies have assessed objective cognitive performance, pre-to-post CBT-I, with mixed results. This study specifically aims to (1) investigate the impact of CBT-I on cognitive functioning, assessed through both self-reported impairment and objective performance measures, and (2) examine whether change in sleep mediates this impact.Methods/designWe propose a randomised controlled trial of 404 community participants meeting criteria for Insomnia Disorder. In the DISCO trial (D
efining the 
I
mpact of improved 
S
leep on 
CO
gnitive function (DISCO)) participants will be randomised to digital automated CBT-I delivered by a web and/or mobile platform (in addition to treatment as usual (TAU)) or to a wait-list control (in addition to TAU). Online assessments will take place at 0 (baseline), 10 (post-treatment), and 24 (follow-up) weeks. At week 25, all participants allocated to the wait-list group will be offered digital CBT-I, at which point the controlled element of the trial will be complete. The primary outcome is self-reported cognitive impairment at post-treatment (10 weeks). Secondary outcomes include objective cognitive performance, insomnia severity, sleepiness, fatigue, and self-reported cognitive failures and emotional distress. All main analyses will be carried out on completion of follow-up assessments and will be based on the intention-to-treat principle. Further analyses will determine to what extent observed changes in self-reported cognitive impairment and objective cognitive performance are mediated by changes in sleep. The trial is supported by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Oxford Biomedical Research Centre (BRC) based at Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust and University of Oxford, and by the NIHR Oxford Health BRC.DiscussionThis study will be the first large-scale examination of the impact of digital CBT-I on self-reported cognitive impairment and objective cognitive performance.Trial registrationISRCTN, ID: ISRCTN89237370. Registered on 17 October 2016.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13063-017-2012-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.KeywordsSleepInsomniaCognitive impairmentCognitive behavioural therapyInternethttp://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000272National Institute for Health Researchissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2017Methods/designResearch designThe study is a parallel-group, superiority RCT of dCBT-I (+ TAU) versus WLC (+ TAU). The study will be carried out completely online. Participants will be administered screening, informed consent, assessments (tasks and questionnaires), allocation to condition, and intervention through web-based platforms. Online assessment of our primary and secondary dependent variables will take place at 0 (baseline), 10 (post-treatment), and 24 (follow-up) weeks. At week 25 all participants allocated to the WLC will be offered dCBT-I to improve their insomnia (see Fig. 1 for trial design). Ethical approval has been granted from the University of Oxford Medical Sciences Inter-Divisional Research Ethics Committee (R46116/RE001) and the trial is registered at ISRCTN (ISRCTN89237370).Fig. 1Flow chart diagram showing summary of the trial design for the Defining the Impact of improved Sleep on COgnitive function (DISCO) study. DSM-5 Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, version 5, SCI Sleep Condition Indicator, dCBT-I digital Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Insomnia, WLC Wait-list control
ParticipantsWe will recruit 404 community participants who report clinically-significant insomnia. Our inclusion criteria comprise: (a) a positive screen for probable DSM-5 insomnia disorder using items from the Sleep Condition Indicator (SCI) (scoring ≤2 on item 1 (sleep latency) or item 2 (wakefulness during the night) + scoring ≤2 on item 3 (frequency of disturbance) + scoring ≤1 on item 4 (sleep quality) + scoring ≤2 on daytime functioning items 5 or 6 + scoring ≤2 on item 8 (chronicity of problem)) [23], (b) endorsement of difficulties with concentration or memory using items from the Daytime Functioning and Sleep Attribution Scale (selecting ‘somewhat of a problem’ or ‘a very big problem’ on at least one item, when asked how much of a problem ‘difficulty concentrating and focussing on things’ and ‘difficulty remembering things’ has been in the past 2 weeks) [24], (c) being aged 25 years and above (to minimise the possibility that circadian rhythm disruption, which is common in late adolescence/early 20s, is the source of insomnia complaints), (d) having reliable Internet access at home or at work, (e) being able to read and understand English, and (f) currently living in the UK. We will screen for comorbid conditions and medication use via online survey and exclude people with (1) symptoms of a probable additional sleep disorder (e.g. possible obstructive sleep apnoea, restless legs syndrome [25]), (2) diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment or dementia, (3) psychosis or mania, (4) serious physical health concerns necessitating surgery or with a prognosis of under 6 months, (4) those undergoing a psychological treatment programme for insomnia with a health professional, (5) habitual night shift, evening, or rotating shift-workers, (6) those taking prescribed sleeping pills more than 2 nights in the past 2 weeks prior to study entry, and (7) those with suicidal ideation with intent. We will not omit participants for any other physical or mental health problems. The study will recruit through multiple channels. These include online, print and broadcast media advertisements, and the use of contact lists where adults who have agreed to be contacted about future studies will be notified about the DISCO trial. In addition to receiving free access to the dCBT-I programme, participants will also receive payment in the form of Amazon™ gift vouchers for completing each assessment point (£5 for baseline; £10 for post-treatment; £15 for follow-up).Randomisation and allocation concealmentThis study will use simple randomisation with an allocation ratio of 1:1, as recommended for large clinical trials [26]. Randomisation will be carried out using the randomisation function within Qualtrics Survey Software (Qualtrics, Provo, UT, USA). On completion of baseline measures, each subject will be randomly assigned by the software to either dCBT-I or WLC. The research team, therefore, will be unable to influence randomisation and will have no access to future allocations.BlindingSelf-report assessments and performance tasks will be completed entirely online. Participants will be informed of their randomisation outcome (dCBT-I or WLC) via email, and so they will not be blind to treatment allocation. The research team, except the trial coordinator, will be blind to allocation. The trial coordinator will not be blind since they will inform participants of group allocation and monitor completion of assessments. Participant contact with the trial coordinator will be limited to scripted phrases, detailing instructions for dCBT-I access and completion of assessments, and will not cover therapy content or support. Statistical analyses will be conducted by a member of the research team who will have access to all data.Assessment pointsAssessments will take place at weeks 0 (baseline), 10 (post-treatment), and 24 (follow-up) (see Fig. 2). Participants are advised to allow enough time to complete the questionnaires and cognitive tasks in one session, on their home computer or laptop in a quiet, distraction-free environment. On completion of the trial (week 25), all participants in the control arm will be offered access to dCBT-I. Baseline variables include demographic information such as age, gender, ethnic group, partner status, employment status, and education. Frequency of sleep medication use will also be monitored at each assessment point.Fig. 2Standard Protocol Items: Recommendations for Interventional Trials (SPIRIT) figure
InterventiondCBT-I will be delivered using the Sleepio® programme (www.sleepio.com and associated Sleepio® app) [19]. We have previously described the Sleepio® programme in two trial protocols published in this journal [27, 28]. The programme is fully automated and its underlying algorithms drive the delivery of information, support, and advice in a personally tailored manner. Delivery is structured into six weekly sessions, lasting an approximately 20 min each. The full programme can be accessed via the website or iOS app. Treatment content is based on CBT-I manuals and includes a behavioural component (sleep restriction, stimulus control, and relaxation), a cognitive component (paradoxical intention, cognitive restructuring, mindfulness, positive imagery, and putting the day to rest) and an educational component (psychoeducation and sleep hygiene) [29–31].The programme is highly interactive, and content is presented by an animated virtual therapist (‘The Prof’). Before the start of the programme, participants complete a questionnaire to tailor the therapy and to set treatment goals. Participants complete daily sleep diary information throughout the intervention, which is used by the programme to provide tailored, personalised advice. Participants can opt to receive an email and/or SMS reminder each morning to prompt them to fill in their sleep diary. In addition, throughout the course of therapy, participants have access to an online community forum; weekly sleep expert sessions moderated by a clinical psychologist; and online library of information about sleep and sleep disorders. During weekly sleep expert sessions, users may vote on topics and submit questions to be addressed by the clinical psychologist. Questions are answered in such a way as to benefit as many people as possible and no personal medical advice is provided. Participants can view their online ‘case file’, which includes four sections: a progress review, a 'to-do' list, an agreed sleep schedule, and a list of further reading. The system provides online analytics which can be used to monitor adherence by assessing how many sessions were completed and the number of weeks to complete the course. All information gathered during the programme will be stored in encrypted form on secure servers. Participants will have access to the intervention for up to 12 weeks. dCBT-I will in effect be dCBT-I + TAU because there will be no requirement for participants (in either group) to alter their usual care in any way.Outcome measuresOur primary outcome will be self-reported cognitive impairment, assessed using the British Columbia Cognitive Complaints Inventory (BC-CCI) [32]. The BC-CCI comprises six questions scored using a 4-point scale (0–3 points; total score range: 0–18) probing perceived cognitive problems (with concentration, memory, and thinking skills) during the past 7 days. It was originally designed to probe cognitive complaints in those with depression – a disorder highly comorbid with insomnia, and sharing similar cognitive features [33]. Given the absence of a widely used measure of insomnia-related cognitive impairment the BC-CCI was selected based on good face validity, internal consistency data (Cronbach’s alpha = 0.82–0.86), and short (1-week) reference period.Secondary measures
Objective cognitive performance will be assessed through an online battery of tasks and will include measures of simple attention (dependent variable [DV]: simple reaction time [msec] for correct identification of matching pairs [‘snap’]), episodic memory (DV: number of attempts to identify identical pairs of cards within a matrix), working memory (DV: longest sequence of correctly recalled digits), visual attention (DV: time taken [secs] to link numbered circles), and complex processing speed (DV: number of correctly matched digit-symbols within a 2-min interval). The battery was developed by the UK Biobank Cognitive Psychology Sub-Group for Cognitive Assessments. Prior to task commencement, participants are asked which text entry and pointing methods they will use to complete tasks (e.g. on full-sized keyboard, touchscreen, laptop trackpad or mouse).Insomnia severityParticipants will complete the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) [34] to quantify global insomnia severity. The ISI is a seven-item insomnia assessment tool, probing both nighttime and daytime aspects of insomnia disorder, and is sensitive to change following CBT-I. It is a recommended outcome measure in insomnia trials [35]. The ISI will be supplemented with four items from the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) [36] to permit calculation of quantitative sleep parameters, namely: total time in bed, sleep-onset latency, total sleep time, and sleep efficiency.FatigueFatigue will be assessed with the Multidimensional Fatigue Inventory (MFI) [37], a 20-item measure comprising five subscales; general fatigue, physical fatigue, mental fatigue, reduced motivation and reduced activity.SleepinessDaytime somnolence will be assessed with the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) [38], an eight-item measure (score range: 0–24) probing propensity for ‘dosing’ in a range of daytime situations.Cognitive failuresSelf-reported cognitive failures will be assessed with the Cognitive Failures Questionnaire (CFQ) [39]. The CFQ comprises 25 questions scored using a 5-point Likert scale (range: 0–100) to identify frequency of minor cognitive mistakes over the past month.DepressionDepressive symptoms will be measured using the nine-item (score range: 0–27) Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) [40].AnxietySymptoms of anxiety will be assessed using two items [‘Feeling nervous, anxious, or on edge’, ‘not being able to stop or control worrying’; score range: 0–6] from the seven-item Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7 questionnaire (GAD-7) [41].Assessment of safetyThe likelihood of serious adverse events occurring during this trial is low since CBT-I (in any format) has not been reported to cause them. The intervention offered in the trial has previously been tested in a randomised, placebo-controlled trial and no adverse outcomes were reported [20]. Since the trial is completed fully online, without formal participant contact, we are unlikely to become aware of potential adverse events. However, should we do so, we will define serious adverse events as: (1) death, (2) suicide attempt, (3) admission to hospital, and (4) formal complaints about the online intervention.Studies have shown that daytime sleepiness and vigilance impairment may increase during Sleep Restriction Therapy (SRT) (one component of CBT-I), owing to restricted sleep opportunity. At the end of treatment (week 10), we will, therefore, ask participants to complete an adapted version of a previously used measure to assess differential rates of self-reported adverse effects [42].Sample size calculationOur planned primary intention-to-treat analysis will compare dCBT-I + TAU versus WLC + TAU for self-reported cognitive impairment (BC-CCI). A systematic review of the cognitive functioning and CBT-I literature shows a standardised mean difference of 0.42 at post-treatment for self-reported outcomes [15]. We will recruit and randomise 404 participants (202 participants/arm). This sample size will give 90% power to detect a minimum standardised effect size of 0.42 at 5% level of significance, accounting for 40% attrition.Statistical analysisIn accordance with Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) guidelines, we will record and report all participant flow [43]. Descriptive statistics of recruitment, dropout, and completeness of interventions will be provided. The main efficacy analysis will be via intention-to-treat including all participants, with no planned interim analysis for efficacy or futility. Baseline characteristics will be presented by randomised group without formal statistical tests. We will test the primary hypothesis for between-group change in the primary outcome (BC-CCI) at 10 weeks using analysis of covariance with baseline outcome measure and treatment assignment as fixed effects, and apply standard regression diagnostics. The analysis will use statistical techniques for handling missing outcome data under a missing-at-random assumption. Secondary outcomes will be analysed using an analogous method. Analysis of all treatment effects will be undertaken after follow-up (week 24) assessments are completed. Additional exploratory analyses will assess whether age moderates treatment-related effects on cognitive functioning outcomes.We will use modern causal inference methods to investigate the mediation hypothesis. If the efficacy analysis shows significant between-group differences in the ISI and sleep efficiency (based on PSQI items) at 10 weeks, then we will use parametric regression models to test for the indirect effect of ISI/sleep efficiency on primary and secondary cognitive outcomes at 24 weeks, and the residual direct effect of treatment on cognitive outcomes at 24 weeks. Since all the measures are continuous, the indirect effects are calculated by multiplying relevant pathways and bootstrapping is used to produce valid standard errors for the indirect effects. All analyses will adjust for baseline measures of the mediators (ISI/sleep efficiency), outcomes and putative measured confounders. Mediation analyses are potentially biased by measurement error in mediators and hidden confounding between mediators and outcomes and we will investigate the sensitivity of the estimates to these problems. All analyses will be carried out using Stata [44].DisseminationWe will publish the results of this study in peer-reviewed journals, irrespective of magnitude or direction of effect. Findings will also be presented at both national and international scientific meetings. The results will be made available online wherever possible, if permitted by journal policies.Items in this protocol comply with the Standard Protocol Items: Recommendations for Interventional Trials (SPIRIT) Checklist (see SPIRIT Checklist in Additional file 1 and Fig. 2 for the SPIRIT figure).Additional file
Additional file 1:SPIRIT Checklist. (DOCX 51 kb)
AbbreviationsBC-CCIBritish Columbia Cognitive Complaints InventoryCBTCognitive Behavioural TherapyCBT-ICognitive Behavioural Therapy for InsomniaCFQCognitive Failures QuestionnairedCBT-IDigital Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for InsomniaDSM-5Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders,5th editionDVDependent variableESSEpworth Sleepiness ScaleGADGeneralised Anxiety DisorderICSD-3International Classification of Sleep Disorders,3rd editionISIInsomnia Severity IndexMEQMorningness-Eveningness QuestionnaireMFIMultidimensional Fatigue IndexPHQ-9Patient Health QuestionnairePSQIPittsburgh Sleep Quality IndexRCTRandomised controlled trialSCISleep Condition IndicatorSRTSleep restriction therapyTAUTreatment as usualWLCWait-list controlElectronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13063-017-2012-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.AcknowledgementsNot applicable.FundingThis research was supported by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Oxford Biomedical Research Centre (BRC) based at Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust and University of Oxford, and by the NIHR Oxford Health BRC.Availability of data and materialsThe datasets analysed during the current study will be available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.Authors’ contributionsSDK and CES are the chief investigators, conceived of the study, contributed to the design, and drafted the manuscript. MEDH contributed to the design, is the trial coordinator, and helped to draft the manuscript. RE contributed to the design, is responsible for the main statistical outcome analysis and is responsible for the statistical mediation analysis. KS and CAE contributed to the design and helped to draft the manuscript. AIL helped to draft the manuscript and will support recruitment and participant access to digital CBT-I. XO helped to draft the manuscript and will support participant recruitment. All authors approved the final manuscript.Competing interestsCAE is the cofounder and Clinical and Scientific Director of the CBT-I programme (Big Health Ltd., Sleepio®). AIL holds a position at Oxford that is funded by Big Health Ltd. The programme is being provided to all participants at no cost. No other investigators declare potential conflicts of interest. The study will be conducted by the University of Oxford, Sleep and Circadian Neuroscience Institute. The University of Oxford has a Memorandum of Understanding with Big Health Ltd. (Sleepio®) for the conduct of joint research.Consent for publicationNot applicable.Ethics approval and consent to participateAll participants are required to read the information sheet and consent to participate in the study. This included consent for their anonymised data to be published. The study has been granted ethical approval by the University of Oxford Medical Sciences Inter-Divisional Research Ethics Committee (R46116/RE001) and the trial is registered at ISRCTN (ISRCTN89237370).Publisher’s NoteSpringer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.References1.MorinCMBencaRChronic insomniaLancet2012379982111294110.1016/S0140-6736(11)60750-2222657002.Morin CM, Drake LD, Harvey AH, Krystal AD, Manber R, Riemann D, et al. Insomnia disorders. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2015. doi:10.1038/nrdp.2015.26.3.KyleSDEspieCAMorganKNot just a minor thing, it is something major, which stops you from functioning daily’: quality of life and daytime functioning in insomniaBehav Sleep Med.2010831234010.1080/15402002.2010.487450205827564.KyleSDMorganKEspieCAInsomnia and health-related quality of lifeSleep Med Rev2010141698210.1016/j.smrv.2009.07.004199629225.EspieCAKyleSDHamesPCyhlarovaEBenzevalMThe daytime impact of DSM-5 insomnia disorder: comparative analysis of insomnia subtypes from the Great British Sleep SurveyJ Clin Psychiatry2012731214788410.4088/JCP.12m079546.KyleSDCrawfordMRMorganKSpiegelhalderKClarkAAEspieCAThe Glasgow Sleep Impact Index (GSII): a novel patient-centred measure for assessing sleep-related quality of life impairment in Insomnia DisorderSleep Med201314649350110.1016/j.sleep.2012.10.023233479087.Fortier-BrochuÉBeaulieu-BonneauSIversHMorinCMInsomnia and daytime cognitive performance: a meta-analysisSleep Med Rev2012161839410.1016/j.smrv.2011.03.008216362978.ShekletonJAFlynn-EvansEEMillerBEpsteinLJKirschDBrognaLANeurobehavioral performance impairment in insomnia: relationships with self-reported sleep and daytime functioningSleep201437110716244707009.Fortier-BrochuEMorinCMCognitive impairment in individuals with insomnia: clinical significance and correlatesSleep2014371117879810.5665/sleep.41722536407410.AltenaEVan Der WerfYDSanz-ArigitaEJVoornTARomboutsSAKuijerJPPrefrontal hypoactivation and recovery in insomniaSleep2008319127161878865211.StoffersDAltenaEvan der WerfYDSanz-ArigitaEJVoomTAAstillRGThe caudate: a key node in the neuronal network imbalance of insomnia?Brain201413726102010.1093/brain/awt3292428564212.DrummondSPWalkerMAlmklovECamposMAndersonDEStrausLDNeural correlates of working memory performance in primary insomniaSleep20133691307162399736313.SpiegelhalderKRegenWBaglioniCNissenCRiemannDKyleSDNeuroimaging insights into insomniaCurr Neurol Neurosci Rep20151531710.1007/s11910-015-0527-314.American Psychiatric AssociationDiagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders20135WashingtonAmerican Psychiatric Association15.Herbert V, Kyle SD, Pratt D. Does cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia improve cognitive performance? A systematic review and narrative synthesis. Sleep Med Rev.16.LegerDBayonVOhayonMMPhilipPEmentPMetlaineAInsomnia and accidents: cross-sectional study (EQUINOX) on sleep-related home, work and car accidents in 5293 subjects with insomnia from 10 countriesJ Sleep Res20142321435210.1111/jsr.121042423785517.MiroELupianezJMartinezMPSanchezAIDiaz-PiedraCGuzmanMACognitive-behavioral therapy for insomnia improves attentional function in fibromyalgia syndrome: a pilot, randomized controlled trialJ Health Psychol20111657708210.1177/13591053103905442134602018.OmvikSSivertsenBPallesenSBjorvatnBHavikOENordhusIHDaytime functioning in older patients suffering from chronic insomnia: treatment outcome in a randomized controlled trial comparing CBT with zopicloneBehav Res Ther20084656234110.1016/j.brat.2008.02.0131841709919.WilckensKAHallMHNebesRDMonkTHBuysseDJChanges in cognitive performance are associated with changes in sleep in older adults with insomniaBehav Sleep Med201614329531010.1080/15402002.2014.10020342632290420.EspieCAKyleSDWilliamsCOngJCDouglasNJHamesPA randomized, placebo-controlled trial of online cognitive behavioral therapy for chronic insomnia disorder delivered via an automated media-rich web applicationSleep20123567698110.5665/sleep.18722265419621.SeyffertMLagisettyPLandgrafJChopraVPfeifferPNConteMLInternet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy to treat insomnia: a systematic review and meta-analysisPLoS One2016112e014913910.1371/journal.pone.01491392686713922.ZachariaeRLybyMSRitterbandLMO’TooleMSEfficacy of Internet-delivered cognitive-behavioural therapy for insomnia—A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trialsSleep Med Rev.20163011010.1016/j.smrv.2015.10.0042661557223.EspieCAKyleSDHamesPGardaniMFlemingLCapeJThe Sleep Condition Indicator: a clinical screening tool to evaluate insomnia disorderBMJ Open201443e00418310.1136/bmjopen-2013-0041832464316824.Kyle SD, Morgan K, Espie CA. The Daytime Functioning and Sleep Attribution Scale (DFSAS): a new insomnia-specific measure to probe daytime impairment and poor sleep attributions. 2010. Sleep;33, A192–A193). One Westbrook Corporate Ctr., Ste. 920, Westchester, IL 60154 USA: American Academy of Sleep Medicine.25.WilsonSJNuttDJAlfordCArgyropoulosSVBaldwinDSBatesonANBritish Association for Psychopharmacology consensus statement on evidence-based treatment of insomnia, parasomnias and circadian rhythm disordersJ Psychopharmacol20102411157760010.1177/02698811103793072081376226.HewittCETorgersonDJIs restricted randomization necessary?BMJ200633275561506810.1136/bmj.332.7556.15061679381927.FreemanDGoodwinGMYuL-MHarrisonPJEmsleyRBostockSEffects of cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia on the mental health of university students: study protocol for a randomized controlled trialTrials20151623610.1186/s13063-015-0756-42601669728.EspieCLuikAICapeJDrakeCLNiroshan SiriwardenaAOngJCDigital cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia versus sleep hygiene education: the impact of improved sleep on functional health, quality of life and psychological well-being. Study protocol for a randomised controlled trialTrials20161725710.1186/s13063-016-1364-72721611229.EspieCAInglisSJTesslerSHarveyLThe clinical effectiveness of cognitive behavior therapy for chronic insomnia: implementation and evaluation of a sleep clinic in general medical practiceBehav Res Ther.200139456010.1016/S0005-7967(99)00157-61112572330.EspieCAMacMahonKMKellyHLBroomfieldNMDouglasNJEnglemanHMRandomized clinical effectiveness trial of nurse-administered small-group cognitive behavior therapy for persistent insomnia in general practiceSleep.2007305748410.1093/sleep/30.5.5741755237231.EspieCAFlemingLCassidyJSamuelLTaylorLWhiteCRandomized controlled clinical effectiveness trial of cognitive behavior therapy compared with treatment as usual for persistent insomnia in patients with cancerJ Clin Oncol.2008264651810.1200/JCO.2007.13.90061859154932.IversonGLLamRWRapid screening for perceived cognitive impairment in major depressive disorderAnn Clin Psychiatry2013252135402363844433.BencaRMPetersonMJInsomnia and depressionSleep200891S3910.1016/S1389-9457(08)70010-834.MorinCMInsomnia: psychological assessment and management1993New YorkGuilford Press35.BuysseDJAncoli-IsraelSEdingerJDLichsteinKLMorinCMRecommendations for a standard research assessment of insomniaSleep.20062911557310.1093/sleep/29.9.11551704000336.BuysseDJReynoldsCFMonkTHBermanSRKupferDJThe Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and researchPsychiatry Res198928219321310.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4274877137.SmetsEGarssenBBonkeBDDe HaesJThe Multidimensional Fatigue Inventory (MFI) psychometric qualities of an instrument to assess fatigueJ Psychosom Res19953933152510.1016/0022-3999(94)00125-O763677538.JohnsMWA new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth Sleepiness ScaleSleep1991146540510.1093/sleep/14.6.540179888839.BroadbentDECooperPFFitzGeraldPParkesKRThe Cognitive Failures Questionnaire (CFQ) and its correlatesBr J Clin Psychol198221111610.1111/j.2044-8260.1982.tb01421.x712694140.KroenkeKSpitzerRLWilliamsJBLöweBThe PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measureJ Gen Intern Med.2001323455941.SpitzerRLKroenkeKWilliamsJBLöweBA brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: the GAD-7Arch Intern Med200616101092710.1001/archinte.166.10.109242.KyleSDMorganKSpiegelhalderKEspieCANo pain, no gain: an exploratory within-subjects mixed-methods evaluation of the patient experience of sleep restriction therapy (SRT) for insomniaSleep Med20111287354710.1016/j.sleep.2011.03.0162190761643.MoherDHopwellSSchulzKFMontoriVGøtzschePCDevereauxPJCONSORT 2010 Explanation and Elaboration: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trialsBMJ.2010340c86910.1136/bmj.c8692033251144.StataCorpStata Statistical Software: Release 142015College StationStataCorp LP
