<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front PsycholFront PsycholFront. Psychol.Frontiers in Psychology1664-1078Frontiers Media S.A.496360510.3389/fpsyg.2016.01112PsychologyOriginal ResearchSmartphone-Based Psychotherapeutic Micro-Interventions to Improve Mood in a Real-World SettingMeinlschmidtGunther12LeeJong-Hwan3StalujanisEsther4BelardiAngelo4OhMinkyung3JungEun Kyung3KimHyun-Chul3AlfanoJanine1YooSeung-Schik56TegethoffMarion4*1Division of Clinical Psychology and Epidemiology, Department of Psychology, University of BaselBasel, Switzerland2Faculty of Medicine, Ruhr-University BochumBochum, Germany3Department of Brain and Cognitive Engineering, Korea UniversitySeoul, South Korea4Division of Clinical Psychology and Psychiatry, Department of Psychology, University of BaselBasel, Switzerland5Department of Radiology, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical SchoolBoston, MA, USA6Incheon St. Mary's Hospital, The Catholic University of KoreaIncheon, South KoreaEdited by: Angelo Compare, University of Bergamo, ItalyReviewed by: Silvia Serino, Istituto Auxologico Italiano (IRCCS), Italy; Inês Mendes, University of Minho, Portugal*Correspondence: Marion Tegethoff marion.tegethoff@unibas.chThis article was submitted to Psychology for Clinical Settings, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychology287201620167111202520161172016Copyright © 2016 Meinlschmidt, Lee, Stalujanis, Belardi, Oh, Jung, Kim, Alfano, Yoo and Tegethoff.2016Meinlschmidt, Lee, Stalujanis, Belardi, Oh, Jung, Kim, Alfano, Yoo and TegethoffThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Background: Using mobile communication technology as new personalized approach to treat mental disorders or to more generally improve quality of life is highly promising. Knowledge about intervention components that target key psychopathological processes in terms of transdiagnostic psychotherapy approaches is urgently needed. We explored the use of smartphone-based micro-interventions based on psychotherapeutic techniques, guided by short video-clips, to elicit mood changes.Method: As part of a larger neurofeedback study, all subjects—after being randomly assigned to an experimental or control neurofeedback condition—underwent daily smartphone-based micro-interventions for 13 consecutive days. They were free to choose out of provided techniques, including viscerosensory attention, emotional imagery, facial expression, and contemplative repetition. Changes in mood were assessed in real world using the Multidimensional Mood State Questionnaire (scales: good–bad, GB; awake–tired, AT; and calm–nervous, CN).Results: Twenty-seven men participated on at least 11 days and were thus included in the analyses. Altogether, they underwent 335, generally well-tolerated, micro-intervention sessions, with viscerosensory attention (178 sessions, 53.13%) and contemplative repetition (68 sessions, 20.30%) being the most frequently applied techniques. Mixed models indicated that subjects showed better mood [GB: b = 0.464, 95%confidence interval (CI) [0.068, 0.860], t(613.3) = 2.298, p = 0.022] and became more awake [AT: b = 0.514, 95%CI [0.103, 0.925], t(612.4) = 2.456, p = 0.014] and calmer [CN: b = 0.685, 95%CI [0.360, 1.010], t(612.3) = 4.137, p &lt; 0.001] from pre- to post-micro-intervention. These mood improvements from pre- to post-micro-intervention were associated with changes in mood from the 1st day until the last day with regard to GB mood (r = 0.614, 95%CI [0.297, 0.809], p &lt; 0.001), but not AT mood (r = 0.279, 95%CI [−0.122, 0.602], p = 0.167) and CN mood (r = 0.277, 95%CI [0.124, 0.601], p = 0.170).Discussion: Our findings provide evidence for the applicability of smartphone-based micro-interventions eliciting short-term mood changes, based on techniques used in psychotherapeutic approaches, such as mindfulness-based psychotherapy, transcendental meditation, and other contemplative therapies. The results encourage exploring these techniques' capability to improve mood in randomized controlled studies and patients. Smartphone-based micro-interventions are promising to modify mood in real-world settings, complementing other psychotherapeutic interventions, in line with the precision medicine approach. The here presented data were collected within a randomized trial, registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (Identifier: NCT01921088) https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01921088.behavioral intervention technologyehealthhealth information technologyinformation and communication technologyInternet- and mobile-based interventionmental disordermhealthwireless healthSchweizerischer Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung10.13039/501100001711PZ00P1_137023100014_135328National Research Foundation of Korea10.13039/5011000037252013S1A2A2035364Ministry of Health and Welfare10.13039/501100003625HI12C1847Ministry of Science, ICT and Future Planning10.13039/5011000036212015R1A2A2A03004462Author contributionsGM, JL, SY, and MT designed the study; GM, JL, ES, and MT prepared the study material and data acquisition; JL, ES, MO, EJ, and HK recruited participants and acquired the data; ES, AB, and JA entered the data and prepared it for statistical analyses; GM, ES, and AB analyzed the data; GM, JL, and MT interpreted the data; GM wrote the first draft of the manuscript; GM, JL, ES, AB, MO, EJ, HK, JA, SY, and MT critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content; MT obtained funding; All authors gave final approval of the manuscript version to be published and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved.FundingGM, JL, and MT receive funding from the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) within the Global Research Network Program (under project no. 2013S1A2A2035364). MT receives funding from the Swiss National Science Foundation, SNSF (project no. PZ00P1_137023). JL receives funding from the NRF, Ministry of Science, ICT, and Future Planning, Korea (2015R1A2A2A03004462) and the Korean Health Technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Korea (HI12C1847); GM receives funding from the SNSF (project no. 100014_135328).Conflict of interest statementGM acts as consultant for Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC. The other authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.ReferencesAhmedaniB. K.CrottyN.AbdulhakM. M.OndersmaS. J. (2015). Pilot feasibility study of a brief, tailored mobile health intervention for depression among patients with chronic pain. Behav. Med.
41, 25–32. 10.1080/08964289.2013.86782724313728AlkhaldiG.HamiltonF. L.LauR.WebsterR.MichieS.MurrayE. (2016). The effectiveness of prompts to promote engagement with digital interventions: a systematic review. J. Med. Internet Res.
18, e6. 10.2196/jmir.479026747176American Psychiatric Association (2013). Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (dsm-5).
Arlington, TX: American Psychiatric Association.AnderssonG.CuijpersP. (2009). Internet-based and other computerized psychological treatments for adult depression: a meta-analysis. Cogn. Behav. Ther.
38, 196–205. 10.1080/1650607090331896020183695AnderssonG.CuijpersP.CarlbringP.RiperH.HedmanE. (2014). Guided internet-based vs. Face-to-face cognitive behavior therapy for psychiatric and somatic disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. World Psychiatry
13, 288–295. 10.1002/wps.2015125273302AsselbergsJ.RuwaardJ.EjdysM.SchraderN.SijbrandijM.RiperH. (2016). Mobile phone-based unobtrusive ecological momentary assessment of day-to-day mood: an explorative study. J. Med. Internet Res.
18, e72. 10.2196/jmir.550527025287BakkerD.KazantzisN.RickwoodD.RickardN. (2016). Mental health smartphone apps: review and evidence-based recommendations for future developments. JMIR Ment. Health
3, e7. 10.2196/mental.498426932350BatesD.MächlerM.BolkerB.WalkerS. (2014). Fitting linear mixed-effects models using lme4. arXiv preprint arXiv:1406.5823. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/lme4/BaumeisterH.ReichlerL.MunzingerM.LinJ. (2014). The impact of guidance on internet-based mental health interventions—a systematic review. Internet Interv.
1, 205–215. 10.1016/j.invent.2014.08.003Ben KhelilM.TegethoffM.MeinlschmidtG.JameyC.LudesB.RaulJ. S. (2011). Simultaneous measurement of endogenous cortisol, cortisone, dehydroepiandrosterone, and dehydroepiandrosterone sulfate in nails by use of uplc-ms-ms. Anal. Bioanal. Chem.
401, 1153–1162. 10.1007/s00216-011-5172-321720737Ben-ZeevD.BrennerC. J.BegaleM.DuffecyJ.MohrD. C.MueserK. T. (2014). Feasibility, acceptability, and preliminary efficacy of a smartphone intervention for schizophrenia. Schizophr. Bull.
40, 1244–1253. 10.1093/schbul/sbu03324609454Ben-ZeevD.SchuellerS. M.BegaleM.DuffecyJ.KaneJ. M.MohrD. C. (2015). Strategies for mhealth research: lessons from 3 mobile intervention studies. Adm. Policy Ment. Health
42, 157–167. 10.1007/s10488-014-0556-224824311BowerJ. L.ChristensenC. M. (1995). Disruptive technologies: catching the wave. Harv. Bus. Rev.
73, 43–53.BradleyM. M.LangP. J. (1994). Measuring emotion: the self-assessment manikin and the semantic differential. J. Behav. Ther. Exp. Psychiatry
25, 49–59. 10.1016/0005-7916(94)90063-97962581BrakeC. A.Sauer-ZavalaS.BoswellJ. F.GallagherM. W.FarchioneT. J.BarlowD. H. (2016). Mindfulness-based exposure strategies as a transdiagnostic mechanism of change: an exploratory alternating treatment design. Behav. Ther.
47, 225–238. 10.1016/j.beth.2015.10.00826956654ChoiS.KimS.YangJ.-S.LeeJ.-H.JooC.JungH.-I. (2014). Real-time measurement of human salivary cortisol for the assessment of psychological stress using a smartphone. Sens. Bio-Sens. Res.
2, 8–11. 10.1016/j.sbsr.2014.08.001CipressoP.SerinoS.VillaniD.RepettoC.SellittiL.AlbaniG. (2012). Is your phone so smart to affect your state? An exploratory study based on psychophysiological measures. Neurocomputing
84, 23–30. 10.1016/j.neucom.2011.12.027CloughB. A.CaseyL. M. (2015). The smart therapist: a look to the future of smartphones and mhealth technologies in psychotherapy. Prof. Psychol. Res. Pr.
46, 147
10.1037/pro0000011CollinsF. S.VarmusH. (2015). A new initiative on precision medicine. N. Engl. J. Med.
372, 793–795. 10.1056/NEJMp150052325635347CollinsP. Y.PatelV.JoestlS. S.MarchD.InselT. R.DaarA. S.. (2011). Grand challenges in global mental health. Nature
475, 27–30. 10.1038/475027a21734685CuijpersP.DonkerT.van StratenA.LiJ.AnderssonG. (2010). Is guided self-help as effective as face-to-face psychotherapy for depression and anxiety disorders? A systematic review and meta-analysis of comparative outcome studies. Psychol. Med.
40, 1943–1957. 10.1017/S003329171000077220406528deCharmsR. C.MaedaF.GloverG. H.LudlowD.PaulyJ. M.SonejiD.. (2005). Control over brain activation and pain learned by using real-time functional mri. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
102, 18626–18631. 10.1073/pnas.050521010216352728DinakarK.ChenJ.LiebermanH.PicardR.FilbinR. (2015). Mixed-initiative real-time topic modeling &amp; visualization for crisis counseling, in IUI'15 Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces (New York, NY: ACM), 417–426. Available online at: http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2701395DonkerT.PetrieK.ProudfootJ.ClarkeJ.BirchM. R.ChristensenH. (2013). Smartphones for smarter delivery of mental health programs: a systematic review. J. Med. Internet Res.
15, e247. 10.2196/jmir.279124240579EbertD. D.ZarskiA. C.ChristensenH.StikkelbroekY.CuijpersP.BerkingM.. (2015). Internet and computer-based cognitive behavioral therapy for anxiety and depression in youth: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled outcome trials. PLoS ONE
10:e0119895. 10.1371/journal.pone.011989525786025EhrenreichB.RighterB.RockeD. A.DixonL.HimelhochS. (2011). Are mobile phones and handheld computers being used to enhance delivery of psychiatric treatment? A systematic review. J. Nerv. Ment. Dis.
199, 886–891. 10.1097/NMD.0b013e3182349e9022048142Ericsson (2015). Ericsson Mobility Report [Online]. Available online at: http://www.ericsson.com/res/docs/2015/ericsson-mobility-report-june-2015.pdf (Accessed February 14, 2016).FaulF.ErdfelderE.LangA.-G.BuchnerA. (2007). G* power 3: a flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences. Behav. Res. Methods
39, 175–191. 10.3758/BF0319314617695343FoxJ.WeisbergS. (2011). An {r} Companion to Applied Regression. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/car/FrankE. H.Jr.DupontC. (2015). Hmisc: Harrell Miscellaneous. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/Hmisc/FranklinJ. C.FoxK. R.FranklinC. R.KleimanE. M.RibeiroJ. D.JaroszewskiA. C.. (2016). A brief mobile app reduces nonsuicidal and suicidal self-injury: evidence from three randomized controlled trials. J. Consult. Clin. Psychol.
84, 544–557. 10.1037/ccp000009327018530FredricksonB. L. (2004). The broaden-and-build theory of positive emotions. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci.
359, 1367–1377. 10.1098/rstb.2004.151215347528GajeckiM.BermanA. H.SinadinovicK.RosendahlI.AnderssonC. (2014). Mobile phone brief intervention applications for risky alcohol use among university students: a randomized controlled study. Addict. Sci. Clin. Pract.
9:11. 10.1186/1940-0640-9-1124985342GriffithsK. M.FarrerL.ChristensenH. (2010). The efficacy of internet interventions for depression and anxiety disorders: A review of randomised controlled trials. Med. J. Aust.
192, S4–S11. 20528707GrosjeanP.IbanezF. (2014). Pastecs: Package for Analysis of Space-Time Ecological Series. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/pastecs/GustafsonD. H.McTavishF. M.ChihM. Y.AtwoodA. K.JohnsonR. A.BoyleM. G.. (2014). A smartphone application to support recovery from alcoholism: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Psychiatry
71, 566–572. 10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2013.464224671165HarrisonA. M.GoozeeR. (2014). Psych-related iphone apps. J. Ment. Health
23, 48–50. 10.3109/09638237.2013.86957524484194HolmesE. A.ArntzA.SmuckerM. R. (2007). Imagery rescripting in cognitive behaviour therapy: images, treatment techniques and outcomes. J. Behav. Ther. Exp. Psychiatry
38, 297–305. 10.1016/j.jbtep.2007.10.00718035331HolmesE. A.MathewsA.DalgleishT.MackintoshB. (2006). Positive interpretation training: effects of mental imagery versus verbal training on positive mood. Behav. Ther.
37, 237–247. 10.1016/j.beth.2006.02.00216942975InselT. R. (2014). The nimh research domain criteria (rdoc) project: precision medicine for psychiatry. Am. J. Psychiatry
171, 395–397. 10.1176/appi.ajp.2014.1402013824687194IoannidisJ. P. (1998). Effect of the statistical significance of results on the time to completion and publication of randomized efficacy trials. J. Am. Med. Assoc.
279, 281–286. 10.1001/jama.279.4.2819450711IoannidisJ. P. A. (2016). Most psychotherapies do not really work, but those that might work should be assessed in biased studies. Epidemiol. Psychiatr. Sci. [Epub ahead of print]. 10.1017/S204579601500088827355892IshiharaS.ForceR. A. A. (1943). Ishihara Tests for Colour Blindness.
Sydney, NSW: Shephard &amp; Newman.ItoL. M.de AraujoL. A.TessV. L.de Barros-NetoT. P.AsbahrF. R.MarksI. (2001). Self-exposure therapy for panic disorder with agoraphobia: randomised controlled study of external v. Interoceptive self-exposure. Br. J. Psychiatry
178, 331–336. 10.1192/bjp.178.4.33111282812KayM.SantosJ.TakaneM. (2011). Mhealth: New horizons for Health through Mobile Technologies: Based on the Findings of the Second Global Survey on ehealth (Global Observatory for ehealth Series, Volume 3). Geneva: World Health Organization.KazdinA. E.BlaseS. L. (2011). Rebooting psychotherapy research and practice to reduce the burden of mental illness. Perspect. Psychol. Sci.
6, 21–37. 10.1177/174569161039352726162113KimD. Y.YooS. S.TegethoffM.MeinlschmidtG.LeeJ. H. (2015). The inclusion of functional connectivity information into fmri-based neurofeedback improves its efficacy in the reduction of cigarette cravings. J. Cogn. Neurosci.
27, 1552–1572. 10.1162/jocn_a_0080225761006KleeA.StacyM.RosenheckR.HarknessL.TsaiJ. (2016). Interest in technology-based therapies hampered by access: a survey of veterans with serious mental illnesses. Psychiatr. Rehabil. J.
39, 173–179. 10.1037/prj000018026985680KleinkeC. L.PetersonT. R.RutledgeT. R. (1998). Effects of self-generated facial expressions on mood. J. Pers. Soc. Psychol.
74:272
10.1037/0022-3514.74.1.272KostkovaP. (2015). Grand challenges in digital health. Front. Public Health
3:134. 10.3389/fpubh.2015.0013426000272KuesterA.NiemeyerH.KnaevelsrudC. (2016). Internet-based interventions for posttraumatic stress: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
43, 1–16. 10.1016/j.cpr.2015.11.00426655959KumarS.NilsenW. J.AbernethyA.AtienzaA.PatrickK.PavelM.. (2013). Mobile health technology evaluation: the mhealth evidence workshop. Am. J. Prev. Med.
45, 228–236. 10.1016/j.amepre.2013.03.01723867031KuznetsovaA.BrockhoffP. B.ChristensenR. H. B. (2015). Lmertest: Tests in Linear Mixed Effects Models. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/lmerTest/LaneJ. D.SeskevichJ. E.PieperC. F. (2007). Brief meditation training can improve perceived stress and negative mood. Altern. Ther. Health Med.
13, 38–44. 17283740LenthR. V. (2016). Least-squares means: the {r} package {lsmeans}. J. Stat. Softw.
69, 1–33. 10.18637/jss.v069.i01 Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/lsmeans/LinW.HuJ.GongY. (2015). Is it helpful for individuals with minor depression to keep smiling? An event-related potentials analysis. Soc. Behav. Pers.
43, 383–396. 10.2224/sbp.2015.43.3.383LindhiemO.BennettC. B.RosenD.SilkJ. (2015). Mobile technology boosts the effectiveness of psychotherapy and behavioral interventions: a meta-analysis. Behav. Modif.
39, 785–804. 10.1177/014544551559519826187164LyK. H.TopoocoN.CederlundH.WallinA.BergströmJ.MolanderO.. (2015). Smartphone-supported versus full behavioural activation for depression: a randomised controlled trial. PLoS ONE
10:e0126559. 10.1371/journal.pone.012655926010890LyK. H.TrüschelA.JarlL.MagnussonS.WindahlT.JohanssonR.. (2014). Behavioural activation versus mindfulness-based guided self-help treatment administered through a smartphone application: a randomised controlled trial. BMJ Open
4:e003440. 10.1136/bmjopen-2013-00344024413342ManiM.KavanaghD. J.HidesL.StoyanovS. R. (2015). Review and evaluation of mindfulness-based iphone apps. JMIR mHealth and uHealth
3:e82. 10.2196/mhealth.432826290327MartinM. (1990). On the induction of mood. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
10, 669–697. 10.1016/0272-7358(90)90075-L25339980McClernonF. J.Roy ChoudhuryR. (2013). I am your smartphone, and i know you are about to smoke: the application of mobile sensing and computing approaches to smoking research and treatment. Nicotine Tob. Res.
15, 1651–1654. 10.1093/ntr/ntt05423703731MelioliT.BauerS.FrankoD. L.MoessnerM.OzerF.ChabrolH.. (2016). Reducing eating disorder symptoms and risk factors using the internet: a meta-analytic review. Int. J. Eat. Disord.
49, 19–31. 10.1002/eat.2247726607683MohrD. C.BurnsM. N.SchuellerS. M.ClarkeG.KlinkmanM. (2013a). Behavioral intervention technologies: evidence review and recommendations for future research in mental health. Gen. Hosp. Psychiatry
35, 332–338. 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2013.03.00823664503MohrD. C.CheungK.SchuellerS. M.Hendricks BrownC.DuanN. (2013b). Continuous evaluation of evolving behavioral intervention technologies. Am. J. Prev. Med.
45, 517–523. 10.1016/j.amepre.2013.06.00624050429MohrD. C.SchuellerS. M.MontagueE.BurnsM. N.RashidiP. (2014). The behavioral intervention technology model: an integrated conceptual and technological framework for ehealth and mhealth interventions. J. Med. Internet Res.
16:e146. 10.2196/jmir.307724905070MorrisM. E.AguileraA. (2012). Mobile, social, and wearable computing and the evolution of psychological practice. Prof. Psychol. Res. Pr.
43, 622. 10.1037/a002904125587207MorrisM. E.KathawalaQ.LeenT. K.GorensteinE. E.GuilakF.DeLeeuwW.. (2010). Mobile therapy: case study evaluations of a cell phone application for emotional self-awareness. J. Med. Internet Res.
12, e10. 10.2196/jmir.137120439251MurrayC. J.VosT.LozanoR.NaghaviM.FlaxmanA. D.MichaudC.. (2012). Disability-adjusted life years (dalys) for 291 diseases and injuries in 21 regions, 1990-2010: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2010. Lancet
380, 2197–2223. 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61689-423245608NashJ. C.VaradhanR. (2011). Unifying optimization algorithms to aid software system users: optimx for r. J. Stat. Softw.
43, 1–14. 10.18637/jss.v043.i09. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/optimx/
22003319NewbyJ. M.McKinnonA.KuykenW.GilbodyS.DalgleishT. (2015). Systematic review and meta-analysis of transdiagnostic psychological treatments for anxiety and depressive disorders in adulthood. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
40, 91–110. 10.1016/j.cpr.2015.06.00226094079NewbyJ. M.TwomeyC.Yuan LiS. S.AndrewsG. (2016). Transdiagnostic computerised cognitive behavioural therapy for depression and anxiety: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Affect. Disord.
199, 30–41. 10.1016/j.jad.2016.03.01827060430NicholasJ.LarsenM. E.ProudfootJ.ChristensenH. (2015). Mobile apps for bipolar disorder: a systematic review of features and content quality. J. Med. Internet Res.
17, e198. 10.2196/jmir.458126283290OldfieldR. (1971). The assessment and analysis of handedness. Neuropsychologia
9, 97–113. 10.1016/0028-3932(71)90067-45146491OlesenJ.GustavssonA.SvenssonM.WittchenH. U.JonssonB. (2012). The economic cost of brain disorders in europe. Eur. J. Neurol.
19, 155–162. 10.1111/j.1468-1331.2011.03590.x22175760OlffM. (2015). Mobile mental health: a challenging research agenda. Eur. J. Psychotraumatol.
6:27882. 10.3402/ejpt.v6.2788225994025OliverM. I.PearsonN.CoeN.GunnellD. (2005). Help-seeking behaviour in men and women with common mental health problems: cross-sectional study. Br. J. Psychiatry
186, 297–301. 10.1192/bjp.186.4.29715802685OlthuisJ. V.WattM. C.BaileyK.HaydenJ. A.StewartS. H. (2016). Therapist-supported internet cognitive behavioural therapy for anxiety disorders in adults. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
3:CD011565. 10.1002/14651858.CD011565.pub226968204Orme-JohnsonD. W.BarnesV. A. (2014). Effects of the transcendental meditation technique on trait anxiety: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. J. Altern. Complement. Med.
20, 330–341. 10.1089/acm.2013.020424107199PalmqvistB.CarlbringP.AnderssonG. (2007). Internet-delivered treatments with or without therapist input: does the therapist factor have implications for efficacy and cost?
Expert Rev. Pharmacoecon. Outcomes Res.
7, 291–297. 10.1586/14737167.7.3.29120528315ParedesP.Gilad-BachrachR.CzerwinskiM.RosewayA.RowanK.HernandezJ. (2014). Poptherapy: coping with stress through pop-culture, in PervasiveHealth 2014, (Gent: Institute for Computer Sciences, Social-Informatics and Telecommunications Engineering (ICST)), 109–117. Available online at: http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2686909PollatosO.MatthiasE.KellerJ. (2015). When interoception helps to overcome negative feelings caused by social exclusion. Front. Psychol.
6:786. 10.3389/fpsyg.2015.0078626124734R Core Team (2015). R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing.
Vienna.RhodesA. E.GoeringP. N.ToT.WilliamsJ. I. (2002). Gender and outpatient mental health service use. Soc. Sci. Med.
54, 1–10. 10.1016/S0277-9536(01)00002-811820673RichardsD.RichardsonT. (2012). Computer-based psychological treatments for depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
32, 329–342. 10.1016/j.cpr.2012.02.00422466510RichardsD.RichardsonT.TimulakL.McElvaneyJ. (2015). The efficacy of internet-delivered treatment for generalized anxiety disorder: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Internet Interv.
2, 272–282. 10.1016/j.invent.2015.07.003RileyW. T.GlasgowR. E.EtheredgeL.AbernethyA. P. (2013). Rapid, responsive, relevant (r3) research: a call for a rapid learning health research enterprise. Clin. Transl. Med.
2:10. 10.1186/2001-1326-2-1023663660RiperH.BlankersM.HadiwijayaH.CunninghamJ.ClarkeS.WiersR.. (2014). Effectiveness of guided and unguided low-intensity internet interventions for adult alcohol misuse: a meta-analysis. PLoS ONE
9:e99912. 10.1371/journal.pone.009991224937483SchaeferA.NilsF.SanchezX.PhilippotP. (2010). Assessing the effectiveness of a large database of emotion-eliciting films: a new tool for emotion researchers. Cogn. Emotion
24, 1153–1172. 10.1080/02699930903274322SchuellerS. M. (2010). Preferences for positive psychology exercises. J. Posit. Psychol.
5, 192–203. 10.1080/17439761003790948ShallcrossA. J.TroyA. S.BolandM.MaussI. B. (2010). Let it be: accepting negative emotional experiences predicts decreased negative affect and depressive symptoms. Behav. Res. Ther.
48, 921–929. 10.1016/j.brat.2010.05.02520566191ShenN.LevitanM. J.JohnsonA.BenderJ. L.Hamilton-PageM.JadadA. A.. (2015). Finding a depression app: a review and content analysis of the depression app marketplace. JMIR mHealth and uHealth
3, e16. 10.2196/mhealth.371325689790SingerJ. D.WillettJ. B. (2003). Applied Longitudinal Data Analysis.
Oxford: Oxford University Press.SpekV.CuijpersP.NyklícekI.RiperH.KeyzerJ.PopV. (2007). Internet-based cognitive behaviour therapy for symptoms of depression and anxiety: a meta-analysis. Psychol. Med.
37, 319–328. 10.1017/S003329170600894417112400SpijkermanM.PotsW.BohlmeijerE. (2016). Effectiveness of online mindfulness-based interventions in improving mental health: a review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Clin. Psychol. Rev.
45, 102–114. 10.1016/j.cpr.2016.03.00927111302SteyerR. (2014). Mdmq Questionnaire (English Version of Mdbf) [Online]. Jena: Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena, Institut für Psychologie, Lehrstuhl für Methodenlehre und Evaluationsforschung. Available online at: https://www.metheval.uni-jena.de/mdbf.php (Accessed April 4, 2016).SteyerR.SchwenkmezgerP.NotzP.EidM. (1997). Der Mehrdimensionale Befindlichkeitsfragebogen (mdbf): Handanweisung [The Multidimensional Mood State Questionnaire (mdmq): Manual]. Göttingen: Hogrefe.TegethoffM.RaulJ. S.JameyC.KhelilM. B.LudesB.MeinlschmidtG. (2011). Dehydroepiandrosterone in nails of infants: a potential biomarker of intrauterine responses to maternal stress. Biol. Psychol.
87, 414–420. 10.1016/j.biopsycho.2011.05.00721645584ThibaultR. T.LifshitzM.RazA. (2016). The self-regulating brain and neurofeedback: experimental science and clinical promise. Cortex
74, 247–261. 10.1016/j.cortex.2015.10.02426706052Thompson-HollandsJ.Sauer-ZavalaS.BarlowD. H. (2014). Cbt and the future of personalized treatment: a proposal. Depress. Anxiety
31, 909–911. 10.1002/da.2230125407579TorousJ.FirthJ. (2016). The digital placebo effect: mobile mental health meets clinical psychiatry. Lancet Psychiatry
3, 100–102. 10.1016/S2215-0366(15)00565-926851322TorousJ.PowellA. C. (2015). Current research and trends in the use of smartphone applications for mood disorders. Internet Interv.
2, 169–173. 10.1016/j.invent.2015.03.002VeltenE. (1968). A laboratory task for induction of mood states. Behav. Res. Ther.
6, 473–482. 10.1016/0005-7967(68)90028-45714990WattsS.MackenzieA.ThomasC.GriskaitisA.MewtonL.WilliamsA.. (2013). Cbt for depression: a pilot rct comparing mobile phone vs. Computer. BMC Psychiatry
13:49. 10.1186/1471-244x-13-4923391304WhittakerR.McRobbieH.BullenC.RodgersA.GuY. (2016). Mobile phone-based interventions for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
4:CD006611. 10.1002/14651858.CD006611.pub427060875WickhamH. (2015). Tidyr: Easily Tidy Data with “Spread()” and “Gather()” Functions. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/tidyr/WickhamH.FrancoisR. (2015). Dplyr: A Grammar of Data Manipulation. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/dplyr/WickhamH.MillerE. (2015). Haven: Import Spss, Stata and Sas Files. Available online at: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/haven/WilamowskaZ. A.Thompson-HollandsJ.FairholmeC. P.EllardK. K.FarchioneT. J.BarlowD. H. (2010). Conceptual background, development, and preliminary data from the unified protocol for transdiagnostic treatment of emotional disorders. Depress. Anxiety
27, 882–890. 10.1002/da.2073520886609WittchenH.-U.JacobiF.RehmJ.GustavssonA.SvenssonM.JönssonB.. (2011). The size and burden of mental disorders and other disorders of the brain in europe 2010. Eur. Neuropsychopharmacol.
21, 655–679. 10.1016/j.euroneuro.2011.07.01821896369YardleyL.MorrisonL.BradburyK.MullerI. (2015). The person-based approach to intervention development: application to digital health-related behavior change interventions. J. Med. Internet Res.
17, e30. 10.2196/jmir.405525639757YooS. S.LeeJ. H.O'LearyH.PanychL. P.JoleszF. A. (2008). Neurofeedback fmri-mediated learning and consolidation of regional brain activation during motor imagery. Int. J. Imaging Syst. Technol.
18, 69–78. 10.1002/ima.2013919526048ZachariaeR.LybyM. S.RitterbandL. M.O'TooleM. S. (2016). Efficacy of internet-delivered cognitive-behavioral therapy for insomnia–a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Sleep Med. Rev.
30, 1–10. 10.1016/j.smrv.2015.10.00426615572ZeeviD.KoremT.ZmoraN.IsraeliD.RothschildD.WeinbergerA.. (2015). Personalized nutrition by prediction of glycemic responses. Cell
163, 1079–1094. 10.1016/j.cell.2015.11.00126590418
