<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front Hum NeurosciFront Hum NeurosciFront. Hum. Neurosci.Frontiers in Human Neuroscience1662-5161Frontiers Media S.A.432272010.3389/fnhum.2015.00045NeuroscienceOriginal Research ArticleThe effects of a Self-Alert Training (SAT) program in adults with ADHDSalomoneSimona1*FlemingGrainne R.1ShanahanJacqueline M.1CastorinaMarco1BramhamJessica23O’ConnellRedmond G.14RobertsonIan H.141Trinity College Institute of Neuroscience, Lloyd Institute, Trinity College DublinDublin, Ireland2St. Patrick’s University HospitalDublin, Ireland3School of Psychology, University College DublinDublin, Ireland4School of Psychology, Trinity College DublinDublin, IrelandEdited by: Srikantan S. Nagarajan, University of California, San Francisco, USAReviewed by: Mor Nahum, Posit Science Corp., USA; Jyoti Mishra, University of California, San Francisco, USA*Correspondence: Simona Salomone, Trinity College Institute of Neuroscience, Lloyd Institute, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin 2, Ireland e-mail: ssalomon@tcd.ieThis article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Human Neuroscience.10220152015945251120141712015Copyright © 2015 Salomone, Fleming, Shanahan, Castorina, Bramham, O’Connell and Robertson.2015This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution and reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), a neuropsychiatric condition characterized by attention and impulsivity problems, is one of the most common behavioral disorders. The first line of treatment for ADHD is psychostimulant medication, but this has limited effectiveness, particularly in adults, and is often associated with adverse side-effects. Thus, it is imperative that new non-pharmaceutical approaches to treatment are developed. This study aims to evaluate the impact of a non-pharmacological Self-Alert Training (SAT) intervention on ADHD symptom prevalence, psychological and cognitive functioning, and on everyday functional impairment in adults with ADHD. Fifty-one adult participants with a current diagnosis of ADHD were randomized to either SAT or a Control Training (CT) program. They were assessed at baseline, immediately following the 5-week training period, and after 3-months using ADHD symptoms scales, as well as a series of neuropsychological tests and psychological questionnaires. Subjective ratings of everyday life attention and memory problems were also collected. The SAT group showed significant improvements in ADHD inattentive and impulsive symptoms, depressive symptoms and in self-efficacy ratings compared to the CT group at both post-training and at the 3-month assessment. Pre-post improvements in SAT participants on untrained cognitive tasks measuring selective attention and executive functions were also observed. Finally, the SAT group reported improved subjective ratings of everyday life attention at both assessment points. This pattern of results suggests that SAT may be beneficial in treating ADHD symptoms as well as psychological and cognitive impairments in adult ADHD. A large-scale randomized controlled trial (RCT) is needed.ADHDSelf-Alert TrainingCAARSbiofeedbackeveryday lifeattention<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Participants</title><p>Fifty-one participants were recruited from a specialist adult ADHD service, the Dean Clinic at St. Patrick’s Hospital, Dublin. Inclusion criteria were as follows: age between 18–50 years; full scale IQ &gt; 80, assessed using Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale—3rd Edition (WAIS–III, Wechsler, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>); diagnosis of ADHD according to: DSM-IV criteria in both childhood and at present in adulthood using the Conners Adult ADHD Diagnostic Inventory for DSM-IV (CAADID; Epstein et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) and the Conners’ Adult ADHD Rating Scale (CAARS; Conners et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) and the Wender Utah Rating Scale (WURS), a retrospective measure of ADHD symptoms in childhood (Ward et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>). The observer versions of both scales were also administered to a close family member or partner; self-reported clinically significant problems in daily life attributable to attentional, executive or arousal deficits (based on interview by a trained clinical psychologist); provision of informed consent. Exclusion criteria were: history of pervasive developmental disorders (e.g., Asperger’s syndrome, autism) or intellectual disability (IQ &lt; 80); history or current diagnosis of epilepsy or other neurological condition (e.g., multiple sclerosis, motor neuron disease); history or current diagnosis of schizophrenia, bipolar disorder or other equivalently severe psychiatric condition; current primary diagnosis of substance misuse requiring treatment with priority (i.e., dependent on alcohol or illicit substances). However individuals with recreational alcohol and drug use were included as they are representative of the adult ADHD population.</p><p>Participants who met the inclusion criteria were randomly assigned using an automated minimization randomization procedure (Altman and Bland, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) which ensured that the two groups did not differ significantly in (a) gender; (b) prescribed psychotropic medication status; (c) alcohol and illegal drug use (sorted according to: alcohol consumption less than 35 units per week <italic>and</italic> no illegal drug more than once per month use vs. alcohol consumption more than 35 units per week <italic>OR</italic> illegal drug use more than once per month). Eight participants in the SAT group and six participants in the placebo group were taking psychostimulant medication for ADHD. Nine participants in the SAT group had comorbid disorders (one insomnia, one dyslexia and seven anxiety and depression) while four CT participants reported comorbid conditions (one depression and three anxiety and depression). The two groups did not differ in terms of gender, estimated IQ, measured by WAIS–III (Wechsler, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>), mean years of education, and pre-training ADHD symptoms, as measured by the CAARS (Conners et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) and the WURS (Ward et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>).</p><p>Fourteen participants out or the 51 participants who were randomized dropped out during the 5-week training period leaving 18 participants in the SAT group and 19 in the control group who completed the training and pre and post-training assessment. The two groups did not differ in terms of age (<italic>t</italic><sub>(23)</sub> = 0.94, <italic>p</italic> = 0.35), years of education (<italic>t</italic><sub>(23)</sub> = 0.39, <italic>p</italic> = 0.70), estimated IQ (<italic>t</italic><sub>(23)</sub> = 1.56, <italic>p</italic> = 0.96). A further 8 participants dropped out of the study between the post-training and the three-month follow up assessment, leaving 15 participants in the SAT group and 14 participants in the CT group. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> showed the flow of participants through the study. The two groups did not differ for age (<italic>t</italic><sub>(16)</sub> = 0.99, <italic>p</italic> = 0.40), years of education (<italic>t</italic><sub>(16)</sub> = 1.22, <italic>p</italic> = 0.66), and estimated IQ (<italic>t</italic><sub>(16)</sub> = 1.33, <italic>p</italic> = 0.89). Demographic characteristics at each time point as well as CAARS and WURS scores at pre-training of SAT and CT participants are presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Consolidated Standard for Reporting Trials (CONSORT) diagram showing the flow of participants through the trial and reasons for dropout</bold>. SAT = Self-Alert Training; CT = Control Training.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-09-00045-g0001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Demographic characteristics at the three assessment points and measures of ADHD symptoms at pre-training in the SAT group (<italic>n</italic> = 24) and in the CT group (<italic>n</italic> = 27)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-training</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-training</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-month follow-up</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAT group<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT group<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T<sub>(49)</sub></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAT group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAT group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7 (12.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6 (11.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8 (9.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.4 (9.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6 (8.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 (9.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16M; 8F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20M; 7F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12M; 7F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13M; 6F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9M; 6F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9M; 5F</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity: White</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years of education</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9 (10.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7 (11.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7 (9.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 (5.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9 (8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7 (9.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQ</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (9.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (8.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (7.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (10.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (9.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medications</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comordities</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Clinical symptoms of ADHD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAARS E- DSM IV inattention self</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.33 (9.38)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.22 (13.20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAARS F- DSM IV hyperactivity self</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.92 (13.21)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.00 (14.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAARS G- DSM IV total self</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.38 (9.05)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.56 (14.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAARS E- DSM IV inattention other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.05 (10.64)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.90 (11.63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAARS F- DSM IV hyperactivity other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.80 (11.12)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.55 (12.75)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAARS G- DSM IV total other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.20 (10.61)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.05 (12.09)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WURS self</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.43 (19.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.46 (29.45)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WURS other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.82 (6.54)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.11 (7.70)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>T-scores are reported for each variable. <sup>a</sup>Values are mean (SD)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Procedure</title><p>The study included three assessments (pre-training, post-training after 5-weeks of intervention, 3-month follow up), and 2 training sessions. Before starting the pre-training assessment, informed consent was obtained from each participant. During each assessment neuropsychological tests were carried out. A series of questionnaires were administered to participants and informant measures from a close relative or friend were also obtained. Participants’ randomization was conducted by a clinical psychologist based outside Trinity College Dublin using an automated procedure (Altman and Bland, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). ADHD participants were not aware of the type of their group allocation and researchers who conducted pre-training assessments as well as post-training and follow up assessments were blind to participants’ group allocation. Following the pre-training assessment, participants attended Trinity College Institute of Neuroscience for two training sessions, conducted by a trained research assistant. After the completion of both training sessions and assessments, participants were asked to practice the training themselves at home for 5-weeks. Participants in both groups were contacted once a week over the phone by a research assistant to assess their progress with their home-based training over the 5-week training period. All study procedures were approved by the Ethical Review Board of the School of Psychology, Trinity College Dublin in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Measures</title><sec id="s2-3-1"><title>Adult ADHD symptoms</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The <italic>Conners Adult ADHD Rating Scale: Long version</italic> (CAARS-S:L; Conners et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The <italic>Conners Adult ADHD Rating Scale Observer: Long Version</italic> (CAARS-O:L; Conners et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). To note, an insufficient number observer forms were returned to perform a well powered analysis (8 forms in the SAT group and 6 in the CT group); therefore these results are not described.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s2-3-2"><title>Psychological functioning</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The<italic> Generalized Self Efficacy Scale</italic> (GSES; Schwarzer and Jerusalem, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). The GSES is a 10-item scale designed to assess optimistic self-beliefs and copying skills. Participants rate each question on a scale ranging from 0 to 4, with higher scores indicating higher self-efficacy.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The<italic> Beck Anxiety Inventory</italic> (BAI; Beck and Steer, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>). The BAI consists of 21 questions about symptoms of anxiety. Participants rate each question on a scale from 0 to 3, with higher scores corresponding to greater anxiety.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The<italic> Beck Depression Inventory</italic> (BDI-II; Beck et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>). The BDI is a 21 questions inventory about the severity of depression’s symptoms Participants rate each question on a scale ranging from 0 to 3, with higher scores indicating higher depression.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s2-3-3"><title>Cognitive functions</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Two subtests from the<italic> Test of Everyday Attention</italic> (TEA; Robertson et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>) were used: <italic>Elevator Counting with Distraction</italic>, in which participants had to listen to series of tones and count the high-pitched tones only. This task measures auditory selective attention. <italic>Telephone Search While Counting</italic> that involve counting a series of tones while looking for symbols on a telephone directory. This task measures divided attention and its final score is called: “Dual Task Decrement”.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The<italic> Hotel Task</italic> (Manly et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) which measures executive functions and is designed to simulate typical day-to-day activities. The Hotel task is comprised of five distinct activities that would plausibly be completed in the course of running a hotel (i.e., checking guests’ bills, proofreading a leaflet on the hotel’s facilities, ordering labels with guests’ names in alphabetical order, sorting money, etc.,). The participants’ objective in this task is to try to complete as much as they can from each of the five activities over an allocated 10 min period. Performance in the Hotel Task is scored within two categories: Number of Attempted Tasks out of five, and time allocation, measured as the Total Deviation Time from an optimal time allocation of 2 min per activity.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s2-3-4"><title>Subjective measures</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The<italic> Attention-Related Cognitive Errors Questionnaire (</italic>ARCEQ; adapted from Cheyne et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The ARCEQ is a 12 items scale that was used as a self-report measure of attention slips and absentmindness in everyday life. Participants rate the frequency with which they experience such slips in attention on a scale ranging from 1 to 5, with higher scores indicating higher absentmindness.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The <italic>Memory Failures Questionnaire</italic> (EMFQ; adapted from Cheyne et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). It is structured in the same way as the ARCEQ and it is a self-report measure of minor memory failures that occur in everyday life. Participants rate the frequency with which they experience memory failures in a series of 12 items that are rated on a scale ranging from 1 to 5, with higher scores representing higher occurrence of memory failures.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Self-Alert Training and Control Training (CT) protocols</title><p>Participants were asked to attend two training sessions. Each session was carried out on separate days and lasted on average 1 h and 20 min. Training sessions were a means of providing participants with psycho-education regarding sustained attention, arousal, and the role of noradrenaline in mediating levels of cognitive alertness. The role of the trainer was to facilitate and encourage participants’ development over the course of the training. Emphasis was thus placed on the role of the participant in what was essentially a “self-training” scheme.</p><sec id="s2-4-1"><title>Self-Alert Training (SAT)</title><p>SAT program consisted of an initial phase of psycho-education regarding the nature of alertness and attention, following which participants completed two questionnaires regarding their everyday life attention and memory difficulties. Following this, participants were taught to gain volitional control of their EDA using SAT in three main steps: (1) <italic>Eliciting SCR by external alerting</italic>. Participants were allowed to view the EDA readings on line and the meaning of this measurement was briefly explained. Then participants were presented with a loud alerting sound in order to demonstrate the responsiveness of their SCRs to changes in arousal. Participants were shown their SCR to this alert in real time. The experimenter asked participants to try to make a link between what they felt inside and the increase they saw in the line. This step was repeated five times and each time participants were allowed to view increases in their SCR waveforms on line (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Participants were instructed to relax as much as possible in between each alert to reduce the number of non-specific SCRs and thus ensure that increases in arousal were clearly observable in the EDA waveform; (2) <italic>Cued internally generated SCRs</italic>. The alerting sound was removed and the aim was for participants to begin producing internally driven increases in response to a verbal cue from the trainer (the word: “now”). Participants were asked to try to recreate the sudden increase in alertness they felt the first time the experimenter played the loud sound on the laptop. This step was repeated until participants could generate 5 clear increases in their SCR amplitudes. If participants had initial difficulties in generating SCR increases, the trainer guided them through the SAT technique step-by-step and invited them to try this again. There was no time limitation. To note, all our participants were able to learn the SAT technique by the end of the two training sessions. Participants were instructed to relax as much as possible in between each attempt in order to ensure that increases in arousal were readily observable; (3) <italic>Self-initiated control over alertness</italic>. In the final step, participants learned to take complete control of their EDA trace without any external prompt from the trainer. Participants were asked to say the word “now” when they were initiating a self-alert. This step was repeated with visual feedback until participants could generate 5 increases in SCR amplitudes. The same procedure was repeated but without visual feedback and participants were not able to view their EDA trace. Participants were asked to say the word “now” before initiating a self-alert and while the trainer checked their performance. This step was repeated until participants could generate 5 SCR increases. Finally, participants were instructed to save each biofeedback session on the laptop. Participants were instructed to relax as much as possible in between each attempt in order to ensure that increases in arousal were readily observable. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> shows examples of participants’ biofeedback session with several successful alerts.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Examples of participants’ biofeedback session with several successful alerts</bold>. The dots indicate the start of a self-alert episode, which is followed by a clear increase (peak) in participants’ Skin Conductance Response (SCR).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-09-00045-g0002"/></fig><p>A series of attentional exercises were also included in the program. To note, these exercises were included in the SAT program to provide participants additional occasions to practice the self-alert technique without the visual feedback from the biofeedback software. Participants were in fact asked to apply self-alerting strategies while practicing the attentional exercises in order to try and improve their performance. In this way they learned to control their alertness levels without visual feedback from their EDA trace, in a task-independent manner. The exercises consist of:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><italic>Sustained Attention to Response Task</italic> (SART; Robertson et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref><italic>)</italic>. Three versions of this task were included, each lasting 3 min and 10 s (126 trials). These were: Number SART, Auditory SART and Animal SART. In the Number SART, numbers from 1 to 9 were randomly presented in the center of participants’ training laptop and participants had to press the space bar for each number except 3. Similarly, in the Auditory SART, numbers from 1 to 9 were played on the laptop in a random order and participants had to listen to these numbers and press the space bar for every number except 3. In the Animal SART, nine different animal shapes were randomly presented in the center of the laptop’s screen and participants had to press the space bar for each animal shape except the kangaroo shape. At the end of each exercise participants received feedback on their performance in terms of number of correct responses, omission errors and commission errors.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Choice Reaction Time Task</italic> (modeled from Logan et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>). Two versions were included, each lasting 3 min and 45 s (150 trials). In the first version, an arrow pointing either to the left or to the right appeared in the center of the laptop’s screen. Participants had to press the corresponding arrow key on the laptop’s keyboard. In the second version, participants were presented with either the letter “O” or “X” that appeared in the center of the screen and they had to press the corresponding letter key on the laptop’s keyboard. Participants were instructed to answer as fast but also as accurately as possible. At the end of each exercise participants received feedback on their performance in terms of number of correct responses, omission errors and commission errors.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Listening Task</italic> (this task was modeled from the Lottery task of the TEA, Robertson et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). Four different audio recordings were included consisting of recorded weather forecasts (downloaded from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rte.ie">www.rte.ie</ext-link>). The length of each recording was 5 min and 46 s. Participants had to listen carefully and indicate the number of times a particular word was pronounced (for example the word “wind” or “cloud”) by writing this number in a box that was presented on the laptop’s screen at the end of each exercise. Participants did not receive feedback on this task.</p></list-item></list></p><p>Each exercise was briefly demonstrated and participants were encouraged to apply the self-alert technique to improve their performance. Each practice of an attentional exercise was automatically saved by the training software in a database. Finally, participants were also invited to think about high-risk situations for attentional failures in their everyday life were encouraged to apply the SAT techniques in their day-to-day life during these problematic situations to increase their alertness. Participants were then provided with a laptop containing specialized SAT software and an EDA kit to take home. Participants were asked to practice 20 min of SAT-biofeedback exercises and 10 min of computerized exercises and to apply self-alerting during exercises for 5 days out of each week for 5-weeks.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4-2"><title>Control Training (CT)</title><p>The CT session consisted of the same initial phase of psycho-education on sustained attention as well completion of two questionnaires on everyday life attention and memory difficulties, as in the SAT group. After this, the first type of attentional exercise (SART) was explained and participants were told that some studies had demonstrated that practicing certain types of attentional exercises had helped to improve sustained attention (all of this was designed to increase the face validity of the CT paradigm and to ensure participants’ blindness). The same attentional exercises were included in the CT program, as in the SAT program (SART, Choice Reaction Time Task and Listening Task). Participants were familiarized with each of the attentional exercises on the laptop provided. A brief discussion was conducted at the end of the last training session about participants’ experience of day-to-day life problematic situations and participants were invited to try to re-focus their attention during these situations. Participants in this group were asked to practice 20 min of computerized exercises for 5 days a week for 5-weeks. We believed that there was a risk of losing participants by asking them to practice more than 20 min, as the exercises were repetitive and any increase in training time requirements in this case have would likely led to participants’ frustration and loss of motivation to complete the training.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis was used. A mixed analysis of covariance (ANCOVA), including one between subjects variable, Group (two levels: SAT group, CT group), one within subjects variable, Time (three levels: pre-training assessment, post-training assessment, 3-month follow up) and one covariate, pre-training assessment was run for each measure. <italic>Post hoc</italic> comparisons were run using Bonferrorni correction to investigate between groups differences at each assessment session separately. Bonferroni correction accounted for all tests within each domain, as in our analysis it was applied for each outcome measure of ADHD symptoms, cognitive functions, psychological symptoms and everyday life subjective ratings. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> presents the mean values and standard deviations obtained by the SAT group and the CT group at each time points for each measure and interactions effects of the ANCOVAs analysis for each measure.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Mean scores (and Standard Deviations) on ADHD symptom measures, social functioning and psychiatric comorbidities’ scales, neuropsychological tests and subjective attention and memory ratings for the SAT group and CT group, results of the ANCOVAs and between group effect sizes</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">SAT group</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">CT group</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-training</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-training</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-training</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-training</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1. Adult ADHD symptoms (CAARS Self-Report)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inattention and memory problems</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.39 (9.36)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.67 (9.80)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.81 (9.74)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (14.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.79 (14.04)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.33 (20.53)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 1.44, <italic>p</italic> = 0.24, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperactivity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.44 (11.66)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.33 (11.86)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.94 (10.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.74 (9.97)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.26 (11.26)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.53 (12.39)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 0.13, <italic>p</italic> = 0.88, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impulsivity and emotional lability</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.28 (12.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.60 (11.57)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.80 (12.68)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.37 (15.66)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.26 (14.89)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.27 (14.52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 4.06, <italic>p</italic> = 0.022*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problems with self-concept</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.83 (12.35)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.72 (11.57)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.00 (12.96)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.47 (14.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.89 (13.95)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.13 (12.62)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 5.58, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM-IV inattentive symptoms</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.94 (7.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.44 (9.15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.06 (14.60)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.89 (14.68)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.11 (11.21)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.40 (14.04)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 3.96, <italic>p</italic> = 0.035*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup>.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM-IV hyperactive symptoms</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.67 (14.53)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.22 (12.96)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.37 (13.37)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.11 (15.46)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.21 (15.24)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.47 (15.62)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 0.79, <italic>p</italic> = 0.46, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM-IV total ADHD symptoms</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.00 (8.90)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.33 (11.31)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.00 (13.60)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.79 (16.57)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.53 (13.55)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.87 (15.15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 2.90, <italic>p</italic> = 0.13, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup>.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADHD index</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.67 (7.63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.00 (10.04)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.13 (12.44)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.68 (13.56)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.74 (13.14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.27 (12.01)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 7.81, <italic>p</italic> = 0.001*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup>.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2. Psychological functioning</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00 (5.70)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.00 (4.76)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.33 (5.42)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.10 (5.65)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.26 (6.70)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.00 (6.77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 4.55, <italic>p</italic> = 0.016*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup>.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.33 (8.20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22 (5.27)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.73 (5.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.33 (12.20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00 (8.26)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.00 (9.03)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 3.81, <italic>p</italic> = 0.029*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup>.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.67 (6.18)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.72 (5.53)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47 (4.94)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00 (7.41)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32 (6.48)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.86 (4.43)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 0.99, <italic>p</italic> = 0.38, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup>.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3. Cognitive functions</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevator with distraction (TEA)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50 (1.95)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.11 (0.90)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.75 (1.24)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11 (2.51)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.21 (2.88)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.80 (2.60)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 3.22, <italic>p</italic> = 0.038*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup>.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dual task decrement (TEA)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.84)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (0.61)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 (4.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88 (3.26)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08 (1.99)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 (1.86)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 0.74, <italic>p</italic> = 0.48, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of attempted tasks (Hotel task)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.31 (0.79)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56 (1.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 (1.20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27 (0.80)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 (0.91)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47 (0.83)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 0.96, <italic>p</italic> = 0.39, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total deviation time (Hotel task)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.68 (12.11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.61 (13.42)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.02 (14.55)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.54 (11.30)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.12 (10.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.03 (11.22)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 2.02, <italic>p</italic> = 0.12, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4. Subjective measures</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARCEQ</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.67 (8.17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.00 (8.18)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.45 (9.35)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.11 (12.63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.67 (10.97)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.75 (11.09)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 7.16, <italic>p</italic> = 0.003*, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMFQ</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.50 (12.04)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.33 (10.39)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00 (7.99)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.33 (11.62)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.89 (11.32)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.75 (13.64)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 0.47, <italic>p</italic> = 0.63, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.03</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Note. The degrees of freedom are 2,56 for the CAARS, 2,26 for GSES, 2.50 for BDI and BAI, 2,54 for neuropsychological tests and 2,26 for ARCEQ and EMFQ. Confident Interval is 95%. SAT = Self-Alert Training; CT = Control Training. *Indicated statistically significant difference</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec>Authors and contributorsDesign of the work, data acquisition, analysis and interpretation: Simona Salomone (design, data collection, analysis and interpretation), Grainne Ruth Fleming (data collection), Jacqueline Marie Shanahan (data collection), Marco Castorina (programming of the training programs and data collection), Redmond G. O’Connell (design, and data interpretation), Jessica Bramham (design and data interpretation), Ian H. Robertson (design and data interpretation). Drafting the work or revising it critically for important intellectual content: Simona Salomone, Grainne Ruth Fleming, Redmond G. O’Connell, Jessica Bramham, and Ian H. Robertson. Substantial contributions to the conception or design of the work: Simona Salomone, Redmond G. O’Connell, Jessica Bramham, Ian H. Robertson. Final approval of the version to be published: Simona Salomone, Grainne Ruth Fleming, Jacqueline Marie Shanahan, Marco Castorina, Redmond G. O’Connell, Jessica Bramham, Ian H. Robertson. Agreement to be accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved: Simona Salomone, Grainne Ruth Fleming, Jacqueline Marie Shanahan, Marco Castorina, Redmond G. O’Connell, Jessica Bramham, and Ian H. Robertson.Conflict of interest statementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.The authors would like to acknowledge with thanks the funding of the Irish Health Research Board in carrying out this research, grant number: H01352. We would also like to thank Dr. Aisling Parsons, Sophia Kilcullen and all participants who took part in this study.ReferencesAltmanD. G.BlandJ. M. (2005). Treatment allocation by minimisation. BMJ
330:843. 10.1136/bmj.330.7495.84315817555ArnsM.HeinrichH.StrehlU. (2014). Evaluation of neurofeedback in ADHD: the long and winding road. Biol. Psychol.
95, 108–115. 10.1016/j.biopsycho.2013.11.01324321363AshersonP. (2005). Clinical assessment and treatment of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder in adults. Expert Rev. Neurother.
5, 525–539. 10.1586/14737175.5.4.52516026236BarkleyR. A. (2006). Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder: A Handbook for Diagnosis and Treatment.
3rd Edn.
New York: Guilford.BeckA. T.SteerR. A. (1993). Beck Anxiety Inventory.
San Antonio: The Psychological Corporation, Harcourt Brace an Company.BeckA. T.SteerR. A.BrownG. K. (1996). Beck Depression Inventory.
San Antonio: The Psychological Corporation, Harcourt Brace and Company.BiedermanJ. (2005). Attention-deficit/hyiperactivity disorder: a selective overview. Biol. Psychiatry
57, 1215–1220. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.10.02015949990BinkM.van NieuwenhuizenC.PopmaA.BongersI. L.van BoxtelG. J. (2014). Neurocognitive effects of neurofeedback in adolescents with ADHD: a randomized controlled trial. J. Clin. Psychiatry
75, 535–542. 10.4088/jcp.13m0859024922488CastellanosF. X.Sonuga-BarkeE. J.ScheresA.Di MartinoA.HydeC.WaltersJ. R. (2005). Varieties of attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder-related intra-individual variability. Biol. Psychiatry
57, 1416–1423. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.12.00515950016CastellanosF. X.TannockR. (2002). Neuroscience of attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder: the research of endophenotypes. Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
3, 617–628
10.1038/nrn89612154363CheyneJ. A.CarriereJ. S. A.SmilekD. (2006). Absent-mindedness: lapses of conscious awareness and everyday cognitive failures. Conscious. Cogn.
15, 578–592. 10.1016/j.concog.2005.11.00916427318ClareL.van PaasschenJ.EvansS. J.ParkinsonC.WoodsR. T.LindenD. E. (2009). Goal-oriented cognitive rehabilitation for an individual with mild cognitive impairment: behavioral and neuroimaging outcomes. Neurocase
15, 318–331. 10.1080/1355479090278311619291529ConnersC. K.ErhartD.SparrowE. (2003). Conners’ Adult ADHD Rating Scales (CAARS).
Toronto: MHS.CritchleyH. D.MelmedR. N.FeatherstoneE.MathiasC. J.DolanR. J. (2002). Volitional control of autonomic arousal: a functional magnetic resonance study. NeuroImage
16, 909–919. 10.1006/nimg.2002.114712202079DawsonM. E.SchellA. M.FilionD. L. (2000). “The electrodermal system,” in Handbook of Psychophysiology, ed CacioppoJ. T. (USA: Cambridge University Press), 159–181.DupaulG. J. (2006). Academic achievements in children with ADHD. J. Am. Acad. Child Adolesc. Psychiatry
45, 766–767. 10.1016/s0890-8567(09)61520-316832310EpsteinJ. N.JohnsonD.ConnersC. K. (2000). Conners’ Adult ADHD Diagnostic Interview for DSM-IV (CAADID).
North Tonawanda, NY: Multi-Health Systems.FaraoneS. V.BiedermanJ.MickE. (2006). The age-dependent decline of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: a meta-analysis of follow-up studies. Psychol. Med.
36, 159–165. 10.1017/s003329170500471x16420712FischerA. G.BauC. H.GrevetE. H.SalgadoC. A.VictorM. M.KalilK. L.. (2007). The role of comorbid major depressive disorder in the clinical presentation of adult ADHD. J. Psychiatr. Res.
41, 991–996. 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2006.09.00817098256FoucherJ. R.OtzenbergerH.GounotD. (2004). Where arousal meets attention: a simultaneous fMRI and EEG recording study. NeuroImage
22, 688–697. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.01.04815193597KesslerR. C.AdlerL.BarkleyR.BiedermanJ.ConnersC. K.DemlerO.. (2006). The prevalence and correlates of adult ADHD in the United States: results from the National Comorbidity Survey Replication. Am. J. Psychiatry
163, 716–723. 10.1176/appi.ajp.163.4.71616585449KiresukT.SmithA.CardilloJ. E. (2009). Goal Attainment Scaling (GAS) in rehabilitation: a practical guide. Clin. Rehabil.
23, 362–370. 10.1177/026921550810174219179355LoganG. D.CowanW. B.DavisK. A. (1984). On the ability to inhibit simple and choice reaction time responses: a model and a method. J. Exp. Psychol. Hum. Percept. Perform.
10, 276–291. 10.1037//0096-1523.10.2.2766232345LosierB. J.McgrathP. J.KelinR. M. (1996). Error patterns on the continuous performance test in non-medicated and medicated samples of children with and without ADHD: a meta-analytic review. J. Child Psychol. Psychiatry
37, 971–987. 10.1111/j.1469-7610.1996.tb01494.x9119944LubarJ. F. (2003). “Neurofeedback for the management of attention deficits disorders,” in Biofeedback: A Practitioner’s Guide, eds SchwartzM.AndraisckF. (New York: The Guilford Press), 408–438.MadrasB. K.MillerG. M.FischmanA. J. (2005). The dopamine transporter and ADHD. Biol. Psychiatry
57, 1397–1409. 10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.10.01115950014ManlyT.HawkinsK.EvansJ.WoldtK.RobertsonI. H. (2002). Rehabilitation of executive function: facilitation of effective goal management on complex tasks using periodic auditory alerts. Neuropsychologia
40, 271–281. 10.1016/s0028-3932(01)00094-x11684160ManlyT.OwenA. M.McAvinueL.DattaA.LewisG. H.ScottS. K.. (2003). Enhancing the sensitivity of a sustained attention task to frontal damage: convergent clinical and functional imaging evidence. Neurocase
9, 340–349. 10.1076/neur.9.4.340.1555312925947MatzaL. S.ParamoreC.PrasadM. (2005). A review of the economic burden of ADHD. Cost Eff. Resour. Alloc.
9, 3–5. 10.1186/1478-7547-3-515946385McavinueL.VangkildeS.JohnsonK. A.HabekostT.KyllingsbækS.BundesenC.. (2012). A componential analysis of visual attention in children with ADHD. J. Atten. Disord. [Epub ahead of print]. 10.1177/108705471246193523190613Micoulaud-FranchiJ. A.GeoffroyP. A.FondG.LopezR.BioulacS.PhilipP. (2014). EEG neurofeedback treatments in children with ADHD: an updated meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Front. Hum. Neurosci.
13:906. 10.3389/fnhum.2014.0090625431555MillerT. W.NiggJ. T.FaraoneS. V. (2007). Axis I and Axis II comorbidity in adults with ADHD. J. Abnorm. Psychol.
116, 519–528. 10.1037/0021-843x.116.3.51917696708NagaiY.CritchleyH. D.FeatherstoneE.TrimbleM. R.DolanR. J. (2004). Activity in ventromedial prefrontal cortex covaries with sympathetic skin conductance level: a physiological account of a “default mode” of brain function. Neuroimage
22, 243–251. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.01.01915110014O’ConnellR. G.BellgroveM. A.DockreeP. M.LauA.FitzgeraldM.RobertsonI. H. (2008). Self-Alert training: volitional modulation of autonomic arousal improves sustained attention. Neuropsychologia
46, 1379–1390. 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2007.12.01818249419O’ConnellR. G.BellgroveM. A.DockreeP. M.RobertsonI. H. (2006). Cognitive remediation in ADHD: effects of periodic non-contingent alerts on sustained attention to response. Neuropsychol. Rehabil.
16, 653–665. 10.1080/0960201050020025017127571PetersonS. E.PosnerM. I. (2012). The attention system of the human brain: 20 years after. Annu. Rev. Neurosci.
35, 73–89. 10.1146/annurev-neuro-062111-15052522524787RobertsonI. H.ManlyT.AndradeJ.BaddeleyB. T.YiendJ. (1997). ‘Oops!’: performance correlates of everyday attentional failures in traumatic brain injured and normal subjects. Neuropsychologia
35, 747–758. 10.1016/s0028-3932(97)00015-89204482RobertsonI. H.TegnérR.ThamK.LoA.Nimmo-SmithI. (1995). Sustained attention training for unilateral neglect: theoretical and rehabilitation implications. J. Clin. Exp. Neuropsychol.
17, 416–430. 10.1080/016886395084051337650103RobertsonI. H.WardT.RidgewayV.Nimmo-SmithI. (1994). The Test of Everyday Attention.
Bury St. Edmunds: Thames Valley Test Company.SafrenS. A. (2006). Cognitive-behavioral approaches to ADHD treatment in adulthood. J. Clin. Psychiatry
67, 46–50. 16961430SchwarzerR.JerusalemM. (1995). “Generalized self-efficacy scale,” in Measures in Health Psychology: A User’s Portfolio. Causal and Control Beliefs, eds WeinmanJ.WrightS.JohnstonM. (Windsor, UK: NFER-NELSON), 35–37.SimkinD. R.ThatcherR. W.LubarJ. (2014). Quantitative EEG and neurofeedback in children and adolescents: anxiety disorders, depressive disorders, comorbid addiction and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder and brain injury. Child Adolesc. Psychiatr. Clin. N. Am.
23, 427–464. 10.1016/j.chc.2014.03.00124975621SobanskiE.BrüggemannD.AlmB.KernS.DeschnerM.SchubertT.. (2007). Psychiatric comorbidity and functional impairment in a clinically referred sample of adults with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). Eur. Arch. Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.
257, 371–377. 10.1007/s00406-007-0712-817902010SolantoM. V.MarksD. J.MitchellK. J.WassersteinJ.KofmanM. D. (2008). Development of a new psychosocial treatment for adult ADHD. J. Atten. Disord.
11, 728–736. 10.1177/108705470730510017712167Sonuga-BarkeJ. S.BrandeisD.CorteseS.DaleyD.FerrinM.HoltmannM.. (2013). Nonpharmacological interventions for ADHD: systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials of dietary and psychological treatments. Am. J. Psychiatry
170, 275–289. 10.1176/appi.ajp.2012.1207099123360949SteinerN. J.FrenetteE. C.ReneK. M.BrennanR. T.PerrinE. C. (2014). Neurofeedback and cognitive attention training for children with attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder in schools. J. Dev. Behav. Pediatr.
35, 18–27. 10.1097/DBP.000000000000000924399101StevensonC. S.StevensonR. J.WhitmoutS. (2003). A self-directed psychosocial intervention with minimal therapist contact for adults with attention deficit-hyperactivity disorder. Clin. Psychol. Psychother.
10, 93–101
10.1002/cpp.356TreboE.HolznerB.PircherM.PrunnlechnerR.GüntherV. (2007). The effects of a computer based assisted cognitive training on neuropsychological parameters, mood and dysfunctional cognitions in depressive patients. Neuropsychiatr.
21, 207–215. 17915181VidalR.BoschR.NogueiraM.Gómez-BarrosN.ValeroS.PalomarG.. (2013). Psychoeducation for adults with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder vs. cognitive behavioral group therapy: a randomized controlled pilot study. J. Nerv. Ment. Dis.
201, 894–900. 10.1097/nmd.0b013e3182a5c2c524080677WardM. F.WenderP. H.ReimherrF. W. (1993). The Wender Utah rating scale: an aid in the retrospective diagnosis of childhood attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. Am. J. Psychiatry
150, 885–890. 10.1176/ajp.150.6.8858494063WechslerD. (1997). Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale - Third Edition (WAIS-III).
San Antonio: The psychological corporation.WolinskyF. D.Vander WegM. W.MartinR.UnverzagtF. W.BallK. K.JonesR. N.. (2009). The effect of speed-of-processing training on depressive symptoms in ACTIVE. J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
64, 468–472. 10.1093/gerona/gln04419181719WoodsS. P.LovejoyD. W.BallJ. D. (2002). Neuropsychological characteristics of adults with ADHD: a comprehensive review of initial studies. Clin. Neuropsychol.
16, 12–34. 10.1076/clin.16.1.12.833611992223
