<?xml version="1.0"?>
Arch PhysiotherArch PhysiotherArchives of Physiotherapy2057-0082BioMed CentralLondon57599251310.1186/s40945-015-0013-xReviewAction observation training to improve motor function recovery: a systematic reviewSarassoElisabettasarasso.elisabetta@hsr.it12GemmaMariano1AgostaFederica2FilippiMassimo2GattiRoberto31grid.18887.3e0000000417581884Rehabilitation Department, San Raffaele Scientific Institute, Milan, Italy 2grid.18887.3e0000000417581884Neuroimaging Research Unit, INSPE, Division of Neuroscience, San Raffaele Scientific Institute, Vita-Salute San Raffaele University, Milan, Italy 3grid.15496.3fSchool of Physiotherapy, Vita-Salute San Raffaele University, Milan, Italy 21220152122015201551416520159112015© Sarasso et al. 2015
Open AccessThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.Following the discovery of Mirror Neuron System (MNS), Action Observation Training (AOT) has become an emerging rehabilitation tool to improve motor functions both in neurologic and orthopedic pathologies.The aim of this study is to present the state of the art on the use of AOT in experimental studies to improve motor function recovery in any disease.The research was performed in PubMed, PEDro, Embase, CINAHL and Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (last search July 2015). Randomized controlled trials (RCTs) that analyse efficacy of AOT for recovery of motor functions, regardless of the kind of disease, were retrieved. The validity of the included studies was assessed using the Cochrane Collaboration tool for evaluating risk of bias.Twenty RCTs were eligible. Four studies showed AOT efficacy in improving upper limb functional recovery in participants with chronic stroke, two studies in sub-acute ones and one in acute ones. Six articles suggested its effectiveness on walking performance in chronic stroke individuals, and three of them also suggested an efficacy in improving balance. The use of AOT was also recommended in individuals with Parkinson’s disease to improve autonomy in activities of daily living, to improve spontaneous movement rate of self-paced finger movements and to reduce freezing of gait. Other two studies also indicated that AOT improves upper limb motor function in children with cerebral palsy. The last two studies, showed the efficacy of AOT in improving motor recovery in postsurgical orthopedic participants. Overall methodological quality of the considered studies was medium.The majority of analyzed studies suggest the efficacy of AOT, in addition to conventional physiotherapy, to improve motor function recovery in individuals with neurological and orthopedic diseases. However, the application of AOT is very heterogeneous in terms of diseases and outcome measures assessed, which makes it difficult to reach, to date, any conclusion that might influence clinical practice.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s40945-015-0013-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.KeywordsAction observationMotor function recoverySystematic reviewissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2015ReviewObjectivesThe aim of this study is to present a systematic review on the use of AOT in experimental studies to improve motor function recovery in any disease. It was decided to investigate the modality of application and the posology of this technique, the diseases on which it was applied, the objectives and the outcome measures used to assess its efficacy.<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec5"><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p id="Par9">Randomized controlled trials (RCTs) that focused on the effects of a period of AOT on motor rehabilitation were included. There was no restriction on disease, impairment and disability of the participants. The following selection criteria (PICO) were used: a randomized controlled trial design, a patient population including any kind of disease, a rehabilitative intervention focused on AOT, outcomes of motor function recovery. All the articles had to be available in English and full-text.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Search strategy</title><p id="Par10">Pubmed (from 1950), PEDro (from 1929), Embase (from 1980), CINAHL (from 1982) and the Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (from 1929) databases were electronically searched until July 2015. Three key terms – action observation, rehabilitation, and motor function - were used to generate a list of search terms, which were combined into a search strategy adapted to each database: (action OR motor OR movement) AND observation AND (training OR treatment OR therapy OR physical training OR movement execution OR rehabilitation OR neurorehabilitation) AND ((motor AND (function OR recovery OR learning OR activity OR ability)) OR (functional recovery). The extended version is available in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Study selection</title><p id="Par11">Among the articles found by the search (see flowchart in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), 29 were selected according to the titles and abstracts by two independent reviewers (ES, MG). Reference lists of identified studies and published reviews were manually checked for additional RCTs. References retrieved by the electronical search were compared for duplicate entries and were manually cross-checked. Eligible papers were gathered in full-text, independently screened by the same reviewers. A third reviewer (RG) facilitated decision-making when there was disagreement.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of study selection</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40945_2015_13_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Assessment of risk of bias in included studies</title><p id="Par12">The risk of bias of the included studies was independently assessed by two review authors (ES and MG) using the Cochrane Collaboration’s “Risk of bias” tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The assessment was achieved by assigning a judgment of ‘low risk’ of bias when bias was considered unlikely to have altered the results, ‘high risk’ of bias when the potential for bias weakened confidence in the results, or ‘unclear risk’ when there was some doubt about the effect of bias on the results. The following topics were assessed: description of randomization, allocation concealment, blinding, completeness of outcome data, and selective reporting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Considering the nature of the intervention, blinding of the physiotherapists administering the AOT was impractical, so only outcome assessor and participant blinding was considered.</p></sec></sec>ConclusionsIn conclusion, data presented in the analyzed articles would suggest that AOT is more beneficial than a simple motor training, enhancing motor recovery regardless of the disease. It could be helpful to design more RCTs combining clinical, imaging and neurophysiological evaluations with the aim to correlate clinical motor changes and cerebral plasticity over time in order to deeply understand the mechanisms underlying motor learning after AOT. Further studies with larger samples, longer follow up and correlations with instrumental data are necessary to define the best way to apply AOT in clinical practice.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s40945-015-0013-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.References1.di PellegrinoGFadigaLFogassiLGalleseVRizzolattiGUnderstanding motor events: a neurophysiological studyExp Brain Res1992911768010.1007/BF0023002713013722.FadigaLFogassiLPavesiGRizzolattiGMotor facilitation during action observation: a magnetic stimulation studyJ Neurophysiol19957326081176661693.LotzeMMontoyaPErbMHülsmannEFlorHKloseUActivation of cortical and cerebellar motor areas during executed and imagined hand movements: an fMRI studyJ Cogn Neurosci19991149150110.1162/089892999563553105116384.CattaneoLRizzolattiGThe mirror neuron systemArch Neurol2009665576010.1001/archneurol.2009.41194336545.RizzolattiGCraigheroLThe mirror-neuron systemAnnu Rev Neurosci2004271699210.1146/annurev.neuro.27.070203.144230152173306.IacoboniMMolnar-SzakacsIGalleseVBuccinoGMazziottaJCRizzolattiGGrasping the intentions of others with one’s own mirror neuron systemPLoS Biol20053e7910.1371/journal.pbio.0030079157369817.HalsbandULangeRKMotor learning in man: a review of functional and clinical studiesJ Physiol Paris2006994142410.1016/j.jphysparis.2006.03.007167304328.MulderTMotor imagery and action observation: cognitive tools for rehabilitationJ Neural Transm200711412657810.1007/s00702-007-0763-z175798059.GarrisonKAWinsteinCJAziz-ZadehLThe mirror neuron system: a neural substrate for methods in stroke rehabilitationNeurorehabil Neural Repair2010244041210.1177/15459683093545362020785110.CelnikPStefanKHummelFDuqueJClassenJCohenLGEncoding a motor memory in the older adult by action observationNeuroimage2006296778410.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.07.0391612541711.StefanKCohenLGDuqueJMazzocchioRCelnikPSawakiLFormation of a motor memory by action observationJ Neurosci20052593394610.1523/JNEUROSCI.2282-05.20051622184212.WangWCollingerJLPerezMATyler-KabaraECCohenLGBirbaumerNNeural interface technology for rehabilitation: exploiting and promoting neuroplasticityPhys Med Rehabil Clin N Am2010211577810.1016/j.pmr.2009.07.0031995178413.Higgins JPT, Green S. Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 5.1.0 [updated March 2011], 2011.14.ErteltDHemmelmannCDettmersCZieglerABinkofskiFObservation and execution of upper-limb movements as a tool for rehabilitation of motor deficits in paretic stroke patients: protocol of a randomized clinical trialBMC Neurol2012124210.1186/1471-2377-12-422270861215.SgandurraGFerrariACossuGGuzzettaABiagiLTosettiMUpper limb children action-observation training (UP-CAT): a randomised controlled trial in hemiplegic cerebral palsyBMC Neurol2011118010.1186/1471-2377-11-802171152516.AltermannCDMartinsASCarpesFPMello-CarpesPBInfluence of mental practice and movement observation on motor memory, cognitive function and motor performance in the elderlyBraz J Phys Ther201418201910.1590/S1413-355520120050001502483904617.ChaYJYooEYJungMYParkSHParkJHLeeJEffects of mental practice with action observation training on occupational performance after strokeJ Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis20152414051310.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2015.02.0222585134418.EwanLMKinmondKHolmesPSAn observation-based intervention for stroke rehabilitation: experiences of eight individuals affected by strokeDisabil Rehabil201032209710610.3109/09638288.2010.4813452045570719.KimJYKimJMKoEYThe effect of the action observation physical training on the upper extremity function in children with cerebral palsyJ Exerc Rehabil2014101768310.12965/jer.1401142506159820.SuggKMullerSWinsteinCHathornDDempseyADoes action observation training with immediate physical practice improve hemiparetic upper-limb function in chronic stroke?Neurorehabil Neural Repair2015298071710.1177/15459683145655122561398421.TaubeWLorchMZeiterSKellerMNon-physical practice improves task performance in an unstable, perturbed environment: motor imagery and observational balance trainingFront Hum Neurosci2010897222.TiaBMoureyFBallayYSirandreCPozzoTPaizisCImprovement of motor performance by observational training in elderly peopleNeurosci Lett20104801384210.1016/j.neulet.2010.06.0262054720723.ErteltDSmallSSolodkinADettmersCMcNamaraABinkofskiFAction observation has a positive impact on rehabilitation of motor deficits after strokeNeuroimage200736T1647310.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.03.0431749916424.HarmsenWJBussmannJBSellesRWHurkmansHLRibbersGMA mirror therapy-based action observation protocol to improve motor learning after strokeNeurorehabil Neural Repair2015295091610.1177/15459683145585982541673725.KimEKimKEffects of purposeful action observation on kinematic patterns of upper extremity in individuals with hemiplegiaJ Phys Ther Sci20152718091110.1589/jpts.27.18092618032626.LeeDRohHParkJLeeSHanSDrinking behavior training for stroke patients using action observation and practice of upper limb functionJ Phys Ther Sci201325611410.1589/jpts.25.6112425981327.FranceschiniMCeravoloMGAgostiMCavalliniPBonassiSDall'ArmiVClinical relevance of action observation in upper-limb stroke rehabilitation: a possible role in recovery of functional dexterity. A randomized clinical trialNeurorehabil Neural Repair2012264566210.1177/15459683114274062223505928.Sale P, Ceravolo MG, Franceschini M. Action observation therapy in the subacute phase promotes dexterity recovery in right-hemisphere stroke patients. Biomed Res Int. 2014;457538.29.CowlesTClarkAMaresKPeryerGStuckRPomeroyVObservation-to-imitate plus practice could Add little to physical therapy benefits within 31 days of stroke: translational randomized controlled trialNeurorehabil Neural Repair2013271738210.1177/15459683124524702279815130.BangDHShinWSKimSYChoiJDThe effects of action observational training on walking ability in chronic stroke patients: a double-blind randomized controlled trialClin Rehabil20132711182510.1177/02692155135015282408943431.KimJHLeeBHAction observation training for functional activities after stroke: a pilot randomized controlled trialNeuroRehabilitation201333565742402901032.KimJSKimKClinical feasibility of action observation based on mirror neuron system on walking performance in post stroke patientsJ Phys Ther Sci201224597910.1589/jpts.24.59733.ParkECHwangboGThe effects of action observation gait training on the static balance and walking ability of stroke patientsJ Phys Ther Sci201527341410.1589/jpts.27.3412572916334.ParkHRKimJMLeeMKOhDWClinical feasibility of action observation training for walking function of patients with post-stroke hemiparesis: a randomized controlled trialClin Rehabil20142879480310.1177/02692155145231452456965235.ParkCSKangKYThe effects of additional action observational training for functional electrical stimulation treatment on weight bearing, stability and gait velocity of hemiplegic patientsJ Phys Ther Sci2013251173510.1589/jpts.25.11732425993936.BuccinoGGattiRGiustiMCNegrottiARossiACalzettiSAction observation treatment improves autonomy in daily activities in Parkinson’s disease patients: results from a pilot studyMov Disord2011261963410.1002/mds.237452154795237.PelosinEAvanzinoLBoveMStramesiPNieuwboerAAbbruzzeseGAction observation improves freezing of gait in patients with Parkinson’s diseaseNeurorehabil Neural Repair2010247465210.1177/15459683103686852045315538.PelosinEBoveMRuggeriPAvanzinoLAbbruzzeseGReduction of bradykinesia of finger movements by a single session of action observation in Parkinson diseaseNeurorehabil Neural Repair2013275526010.1177/15459683124719052339291939.BuccinoGArisiDGoughPAprileDFerriCSerottiLImproving upper limb motor functions through action observation treatment: a pilot study in children with cerebral palsyDev Med Child Neurol201254822810.1111/j.1469-8749.2012.04334.x2276535240.SgandurraGFerrariACossuGGuzzettaAFogassiLCioniGRandomized trial of observation and execution of upper extremity actions versus action alone in children with unilateral cerebral palsyNeurorehabil Neural Repair2013278081510.1177/15459683134971012388688641.BellelliGBuccinoGBernardiniBPadovaniATrabucchiMAction observation treatment improves recovery of postsurgical orthopedic patients: evidence for a top-down effect?Arch Phys Med Rehabil20109114899410.1016/j.apmr.2010.07.0132087550442.ParkSDSongHSKimJYThe effect of action observation training on knee joint function and gait ability in total knee replacement patientsJ Exerc Rehabil2014101687110.12965/jer.1401122506159643.Abbruzzese G, Marchese R, Avanzino L, Pelosin E. Rehabilitation for Parkinson’s disease: Current outlook and future challenges. Parkinsonism Relat Disord 2015 Epub ahead of print.44.PereraSModySHWoodmanRCStudenskiSAMeaningful change and responsiveness in common physical performance measures in older adultsJ Am Geriatr Soc200654743910.1111/j.1532-5415.2006.00701.x1669673845.BeninatoMGill-BodyKMSallesSStarkPCBlack-SchafferRMSteinJDetermination of the minimal clinically important difference in the FIM instrument in patients with strokeArch Phys Med Rehabil20068732910.1016/j.apmr.2005.08.1301640143546.BuccinoGVogtSRitzlAFinkGRZillesKFreundHJNeural circuits underlying imitation learning of hand actions: an event-related fMRI studyNeuron2004423233410.1016/S0896-6273(04)00181-31509134647.PressCHeyesCKilnerJMLearning to understand others’ actionsBiol Lett201174576010.1098/rsbl.2010.08502108433348.KimSSKimTHLeeBHEffects of action observational training on cerebral hemodynamic changes of stroke survivors: a fTCD studyJ Phys Ther Sci201426331410.1589/jpts.26.3312470707849.GattiRTettamantiAGoughPMRiboldiEMarinoniLBuccinoGAction observation versus motor imagery in learning a complex motor task: a short review of literature and a kinematics studyNeurosci Lett2011540374210.1016/j.neulet.2012.11.03950.LotzeMCohenLGVolition and imagery in neurorehabilitationCogn Behav Neurol2006191354010.1097/01.wnn.0000209875.56060.0616957491
