<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC Musculoskelet DisordBMC Musculoskelet DisordBMC Musculoskeletal Disorders1471-2474BioMed CentralLondon44135272588755053310.1186/s12891-015-0533-2Research ArticleShort-term effect on pain and function of neurophysiological education and sensorimotor retraining compared to usual physiotherapy in patients with chronic or recurrent non-specific low back pain, a pilot randomized controlled trialWältiPhilippphil.waelti@gmail.comKoolJanjan.kool@bluewin.chLuomajokiHannuluom@zhaw.chZurich University of Applied Sciences, School of Health Professions, Institute of Physiotherapy, Winterthur, Switzerland Physiotherapie am Kohlplatz, Heiden, Switzerland Rehabilitation Centre, Valens, Switzerland 104201510420152015168314320141932015© Wälti et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundNon-specific chronic low back pain (NSCLBP) is a major health problem. Identification of subgroups and appropriate treatment regimen was proposed as a key priority by the Cochrane Back Review Group. We developed a multimodal treatment (MMT) for patients with moderate to severe disability and medium risk of poor outcome. MMT includes a) neurophysiological education on the perception of pain to decrease self-limitation due to catastrophizing believes about the nature of NSCLBP, b) sensory training of the lower trunk because these patients predominantly show poor sensory acuity of the trunk, and c) motor training to regain definite movement control of the trunk.A pilot study was conducted to investigate the feasibility of MMT, prior to a larger RCT, with focus on patients’ adherence and the evaluation of short-term effects on pain and disability of MMT when compared to usual physiotherapy.MethodWe conducted a randomised controlled trial (RCT) in a primary care physiotherapy centre in Switzerland. Outcome assessment was 12 weeks after baseline. Patients with NSCLBP, considerable disability (five or more points on the Roland and Morris Disability Questionnaire (RMDQ) and medium or high risk of poor outcome on the Keele Start Back Tool (KSBT) were randomly allocated to either MMT or usual physiotherapy treatment (UPT) by an independent research assistant. Treatment included up to 16 sessions over 8 to 12 weeks. Both groups were given additional home training of 10 to 30 minutes to be performed five times per week. Adherence to treatment was evaluated in order to assess the feasibility of the treatment. Assessments were conducted by an independent blinded person. The primary outcome was pain (NRS 0-10) and the secondary outcome was disability (RMDQ). Between-group effects with Student’s t-test or the Mann-Whitney U test and the standardized mean difference of the primary outcome were calculated.ResultsTwenty-eight patients (46% male, mean age 41.5 years (SD 10.6)) were randomized to MMT (n = 14) or UPT (n = 14). Patients’ adherence to treatment was &gt;80% in both groups. Pain reduction (NRS; [95% CI]) was 2.14 [1.0 to 3.5] in the MMT and 0.69 [-2.0 to 2.5.] in the UPT. The between-group difference was 1.45 [0.0 to 4.0] (p = 0.03), representing a moderate effect size of 0.66 [-0.1 to 1.5]. Reduction in disability on the RMDQ was 6.71 [4.2 to 9.3] in MMT and 4.69 [1.9 to 7.4] in UPT, with a non-significant between-group difference of 2.02 [-1.5 to 5.6] (p = 0.25). The required sample size for a RCT with six months follow-up was estimated at 170 patients.ConclusionsMMT was found to be feasible and to significantly reduce pain in the short term when compared with UPT. A future RCT with a six-month follow-up would require approximately 170 patients.Trial registrationCurrent Controlled Trials ISRCTN66262199. Registered 8 January 2014.Electronic supplementary materialThe online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12891-015-0533-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.KeywordsChronic low back painPatient educationSensory motor trainingPhysiotherapyRandomized controlled trialissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2015<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec3" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Method</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study design</title><p>This was a single-centre, assessor-blinded RCT carried out at the <italic>medbase</italic> centre for health care in Saint Gallen, Switzerland. Assessments were performed at baseline before first treatment and 12 weeks after baseline. Following inclusion, written informed consent and baseline assessment, patients with NSCLBP were randomly allocated to either the multimodal treatment group (MMT) or usual physiotherapy treatment group (UPT). Randomization of the pre-defined number of 28 patients was concealed, using a randomization list with a block size of four, which was generated electronically before start of the trial. Patients were treated by two independent physiotherapists, one in the MMT group and the other in the UPT group. The follow up assessments were conducted by an independent physiotherapist blinded to the group assignment. Treatment was free of charge for all patients participating in the study. The trial was approved by the local ethics committee (ethics committee of the canton Saint Gallen, Switzerland. Ethics committee trial identification number: EKSG 12/149/1B).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Recruitment</title><p>Telephone contact was made with referring general practitioners (GP), chiropractors and rheumatologists. Fifteen received a 20-minute power point presentation on the background of the trial and were supplied with flyers outlining the study. In addition, human resources managers of local companies were contacted and requested to distribute information to their employees. Patient recruitment was also achieved through advertisements in a local newspaper. Interested participants were referred to an online questionnaire for a first eligibility check. Suitable candidates were then contacted and invited for a final eligibility check, informed consent and baseline assessment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Study population</title><p>The inclusion criteria were designed to recruit patients with moderate to severe disability and pain and were in accordance with the definition in the European guidelines for the management of NSCLBP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Eligible were: men and women aged 18 to 60 years; a LBP history of three months or more; at least moderate disability, i.e. five points or more on the RMDQ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]; and medium or high risk of poor outcome, as evaluated with the Keele Start Back Tool (KSBT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Participants were excluded when they had nerve root pain, a diagnosed specific spinal pathology (such as malignancy, fracture, infection, or inflammatory joint or bone disease), were pregnant or less than 6 months postpartum, had a coexisting major medical disease causing a relative or absolute contraindication to general exercise, had undergone spinal surgery within the preceding two years, or had had an intra-articular or perineural steroid injection on the lumbar spine during the previous five months. Participants had to be able to speak and read German, have a person available to assist them with home training, have access to the internet and consent to a time expenditure of 30 minutes, five times per week for eight weeks, to perform a home programme and one/two 30-minute physiotherapy sessions per week.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Treatment dosage</title><p>Physiotherapy treatment dosage in both groups was one or two sessions per week during the 8 week programme, with a maximum of 16 sessions. Patients were given home assignments to be performed for 30 minutes five days per week. An extension to a maximum of twelve weeks was allowed to account for discontinuity, such as holiday or other time issues.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Home training</title><p>Patients from both groups had personalized access to a web-based home training interface (HTI) to guide the home assignments. The HTI recorded adherence to assignments and allowed evaluation of performance (further details outlined in the treatment paragraphs below).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Multimodal treatment group</title><p>MMT included: 1. Education on the neurophysiology of pain; 2. Sensory retraining; and 3. Motor retraining. Treatment was aimed at reducing pain and disability and, potentially, addressing associated abnormal cortical processing in NSCLBP. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> provides a detailed time schedule of each part of the MMT.<list list-type="order"><list-item><p><italic>Patient education</italic> on the neurophysiology of pain was aimed at the reduction of patients’ perception of pain and disability, a reconsideration of protective behaviour and self-limitation resulting from fear of movement, assistance in regaining a confident and positive perspective of their abilities and acknowledgment of the beneficial value of activity. The content of this section was based on a RCT by Moseley et al. that demonstrated a beneficial effect of intensive neurophysiological education in patients with NSCLBP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Our education began with an outline of a bio-psychosocial model of LBP, including cortical dysfunction in pain and body perception. Emphasis was placed on how this model might explain the features of the participants’ LBP experiences. Between two and four education sessions were held. Patients received a copy of the book “Explain Pain” (German translation) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. During the first two weeks, patients were required to read ten pages of the book each day and, using the HTI, answer 18 relevant questions on each section.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The aim of the <italic>sensory retraining</italic> section was to restore discriminate sensory acuity of the lower back and, potentially, to restore normal cortical processing in the sensory cortex, as Flor et al. have shown in patients with phantom limb pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Depending on the patients’ baseline lower back TPD-threshold, each received a set of gauges (like tracing papers) with 16 to 20 numbered dots with equal inter-punctual distance. Patients then had to transfer their appropriate gauge inter-punctual value to a Sensory Retraining Tool (SRT) integrated into their HTI (Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Each patient had an aid person to hold the gauge onto the patient’s back, to plot the dots through the paper, to number them and press the start button on the SRT. The SRT displayed dot numbers in randomized order and the aid had to press the relevant dot onto the patient’s back with a pencil, so that the patient could discern and identify the number of the dot being stimulated (Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The answer was confirmed with true or false on the SRT. When performance reached 80% correct answers, treatment progressed to the next gauge with an inter-punctual distance of five millimetres smaller. Likewise, letters and three-letter words were written directly onto the back. Tactile acuity was shown to be reduced in patients with LBP and correlated with movement control impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. A similar treatment was described by Wand et al. in a multi-baseline study reducing pain and disability in patients with NSCLBP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Sensory Retraining Tool on the home training Interface for the multimodal treatment group.</bold> Example of a gauge plotted on patient’s back. The specifications of the gauge (16 dots, 65 millimetres inter-punctual distance) were imputed on the SRT as visible on laptop-screen, SRT ready to start.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2015_533_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Sensory Retraining Tool on the home training Interface for the multimodal treatment group.</bold> SRT started: The patient has to discern the pressed dot number 14. The aid person then confirms the answer with right or wrong on the SRT and the next number appears on the screen, and so on.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2015_533_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></list-item><list-item><p>The goal of the <italic>motor retraining</italic> was to improve movement control of the lower back [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Patients performed laterality recognition training. They were shown photographs of a human trunk rotated or side-bent to right or left. Patients had to determine the perspective of the picture as quickly as possible, using the computer programme Recognise® [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] linked to the HTI. In a next step, patients observed videos showing movements of increasing difficulty. The movements then had to be performed either physically or mentally as motor imagery exercise, depending on the patient’s pain intensity and ability. The first level of difficulty included small lumbar movements, such as pelvic tilting and slight side-bending. The second level involved larger unidirectional and combined lumbar movements. Movement patterns which provoked LBP were individually identified. Motor retraining exercises were instructed using mirrors, smartphone photographs and the patient’s hands, as a reminder of the experiences and to improve positive movement. The aim was to enable patients to transfer their acquired knowledge to any situation in which their LBP arose, to modulate and improve their movement behaviour and to reduce pain.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>UPT group</title><p>At the initial visit, patients were given basic patient education on adequate behaviour when having an exacerbation of LBP: a short period of protection followed, as soon as possible, by a return to normal movement, work and leisure activities. Further sessions addressed signs and symptoms. Two-thirds (i.e. 20 minutes) of each session consisted of active treatment, such as exercises for strengthening muscles, neuro-meningeal mobilisation and stretching muscles. A maximum of ten minutes of passive applications per session was allowed (such as massage, manual therapy, electrotherapy, mud packs). These activities are in accordance with the European guidelines for the management of active rehabilitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Each patient received instruction on the HTI to perform an individual home exercise programme. To observe adherence to the home programme, patients had to report their routine of performing exercises on the HTI (Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Home training Interface of the control group.</bold> For each exercise and time performed at home, these parameters had to be imputed on the HTI by the patient as shown on the picture: Number of reversals; number of sets; time required.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12891_2015_533_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Outcomes</title><p>Feasibility-related outcomes were: suitability of recruitment; patients’ ability to complete each part of the home training programme; suitability of the time frame set; treatment attendance; and adherence to home assignments.</p><p>The primary outcome was mean pain intensity over the prior 7 days (NRS 0-10). Secondary outcomes were disability, measured with the Roland and Morris Disability Questionnaire (RMDQ), and patient-specific disability, measured with the patient-specific functional scale (PSFS), an outcome measure found to be reliable and responsive in patients with NSCLBP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Fear avoidance beliefs were measured using the fear avoidance beliefs questionnaire FABQ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and catastrophizing thoughts with the pain catastrophizing scale PCS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Movement control impairment (MCI) was measured by means of six movement control tests, with established validity and reliability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], and sensory acuity of the lower back by measuring the TPD threshold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Sick leave and analgesic intake during the last seven days were recorded at both assessments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Statistics</title><p>Treatment feasibility was defined as 80% patient participation over the complete programme (i.e. 8 to 12 weeks) and completion of at least 80% of each part of the home training assignments. For MMT, we aimed at ≥ 80% correct answers to the questions related to the lessons in the book “Explain Pain”; ≥ 80% of the required quota of 10 × 60 images on recognition training using the Recognise® software; ≥ 80% completion of the required quota of 55 sets of sensory training with the SRT. Time and frequency spent on the movement control retraining exercises were recorded. For UPT, we aimed at ≥ 80% compliance with the 40 home training assignments. Satisfaction with treatment was evaluated in both groups. Patients were asked to rate whether the contents of each section were helpful using a five point Likert scale, ranging from “strongly agree” to “strongly disagree”.</p><p>Outcome analysis was by “intention to treat”. The results of patients fulfilling the before-mentioned requirements for treatment adherence were analysed in the per protocol analysis.</p><p>We compared changes within and between groups for the primary and secondary outcomes. We used a two-tailed Student’s t-test for data showing normal distribution, which was tested with the SHAPIRO-Wilks test, and a two-tailed Mann Whitney U test where data were not normally distributed. Results were analysed with SPSS 20. Confidence intervals for the median difference (e.g. for the Mann Whitney U test) were calculated with the software r, version 3.1.1 using the Hodges-Lehman test.</p></sec></sec>Additional filesAdditional file 1:
Content of sessions and home assignments of multimodal treatment.
Additional file 2:
Recruitment sources.
Additional file 3:
Online eligibility testing.
Additional file 4:
MMT Patients satisfaction with treatment.
Additional file 5:
UPT Patients satisfaction with treatment.
AbbreviationsESEffect sizeFABQFear Avoidance Beliefs QuestionnairefMRIFunctional magnetic resonance imagingGPGeneral practitionerHTIWeb-based home training interfaceKSBTKeele Start Back ToolLBPLow Back painMCIMovement control impairmentMMTMultimodal treatment (group)NRSNumeric rating scale (NRS)NSAIDNon-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugNSCLBPNon-specific chronic low back painPCSPain Catastrophizing ScalePSFSPatient-Specific Functional ScaleRCTRandomised controlled trialRMDQRoland and Morris Disability QuestionnaireSDStandard deviationSRTSensory Retraining ToolTPDTwo-point-discriminationUPTUsual physiotherapy treatment (group)[95% CI]95% confidence intervalsCompeting interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsPW, HL and JK developed the study protocol, PW coordinated the study, treated patients in the multimodal treatment group and performed the statistical analysis. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.Authors’ informationPhilipp Waelti is a physiotherapist specialized in the treatment of chronic pain, especially in the care management of cNSLBP. He has a postgraduate diploma in orthopaedic manipulative therapy and has recently completed his master’s degree in physiotherapy science. Hannu Luomajoki is a professor and lecturer in physiotherapy and an expert in physiotherapy science regarding low back pain. Jan Kool is specialized in low back pain research at the Rehabilitation Centre in Valens and teacher at the Institute of Physiotherapy, School of Health Professions, Zurich University of Applied Sciences, Winterthur, Switzerland.AcknowledgementsNo financial support was received for this trial. The authors wish to thank Tobias Buschor for initialization of the software applications needed for the web-interfaces and the database, and also the person pictured on figure one and two, as well as the person pictured on figure three who both gave written consent to publish their image.FundingZurich University of Applied Sciences (Switzerland).References1.WHO. The burden of musculoskeletal conditions at the start of the new millennium. World Health Organ Tech Rep Ser. 2003; 919, i-x, 1-218.2.Interpharma and Polynomics. Gesundheitsausgaben und Krankheitskosten. [http://www.interpharma.ch/sites/default/files/documents/polynomics-2011_gesundheitsausgaben-und-krankheitskosten_d.pdf]. Sept. 2011.3.HestbeakLLeboeuf-YdeCMannicheCLow back pain: what is the long-term course? A review of studies of general patient populationsEur Spine J20031214965127098534.AiraksinenOBroxJCedraschiCHildebrandtJKlaber-MoffettJKovacsFEuropean guidelines for the management of chronic non-specific low back pain20045.BillisEMcCarthyCOldhamJSubclassification of low back pain: a cross-country comparisonEur Spine J2007168657910.1007/s00586-007-0313-2175766046.FersumKVDankaertsWO'SullivanPBMaesJSkouenJSBjordalJMIntegration of sub-classification strategies in RCTs evaluating manual therapy treatment and exercise therapy for non-specific chronic low back pain (NSCLBP): a systematic reviewBr J Sports Med2010441410546210.1136/bjsm.2009.063289199963317.Flor H. Cortical reorganisation and chronic pain: implications for rehabilitation. J Rehabil Med. 2003;(41 Suppl):66-72.8.FlorHBraunCElbertTBirbaumerNExtensive reorganization of primary somatosensory cortex in chronic back pain patientsNeurosci Lett19972245810.1016/S0304-3940(97)13441-391326899.LotzeMMoseleyGLRole of distorted body image in painCurr Rheumatol Rep200794889610.1007/s11926-007-0079-x1817760310.MoseleyGLNicholasMKHodgesPWA randomized controlled trial of intensive neurophysiology education in chronic low back painClin J Pain2004203243010.1097/00002508-200409000-000071532243911.MoseleyGLI can't find it! Distorted body image and tactile dysfunction in patients with chronic back painPain20081402394310.1016/j.pain.2008.08.0011878676312.WandBMO'ConnellNEChronic non-specific low back pain - sub-groups or a single mechanism?BMC Musculoskelet Disord200891110.1186/1471-2474-9-111822152113.FlorHPhantom-limb pain: characteristics, causes, and treatmentLancet Neurol20021182910.1016/S1474-4422(02)00074-11284948714.MaclverKLloydDMKellySRobertsNNurmikkoTPhantom limb pain, cortical reorganization and the therapeutic effect of mental imageryBrain2008131821819110.1093/brain/awn1241856762415.MoseleyGLSymDFHenryMLSouvalisTExperimental hand pain delays recognition of the contralateral hand-Evidence that acute and chronic pain have opposite effects on information processing?Cogn Brain Res2005251889410.1016/j.cogbrainres.2005.05.00816.HodgesPWMoseleyGLPain and motor control of the lumbopelvic region: effect and possible mechanismsJ Electromyogr Kinesiol2003133617010.1016/S1050-6411(03)00042-71283216617.HodgesPWMoseleyGLGabrielssonAGandeviaSCExperimental muscle pain changes feedforward postural responses of the trunk musclesExp Brain Res20031512627110.1007/s00221-003-1457-x1278314618.LuomajokiHKoolJDe BruinEDAiraksinenOReliability of movement control tests in the lumbar spineBMC Musculoskelet Disord200789010.1186/1471-2474-8-901785066919.LuomajokiHKoolJDe BruinEDAiraksinenOMovement control tests of the low back; evaluation of the difference between patients with low back pain and healthy controlsBMC Musculoskelet Disord2008917010.1186/1471-2474-9-1701910873520.WandBMO'ConnellNEDi PietroFBulsaraMManaging chronic non-specific low back pain with a sensorimotor retraining approach: exploratory multiple-baseline study of 3 participantsPhys Ther2011915354610.2522/ptj.201001502135003421.CraigPDieppePMacintyreSMichieSNazarethIPetticrewMDeveloping and evaluating complex interventions: the new Medical Research Council guidanceBMJ2008337a165510.1136/bmj.a16551882448822.RolandMOMorrisRWA study of the natural history of back pain. Part 1: development of a reliable and sensitive measure of disability in low back painSpine19838141410.1097/00007632-198303000-00004622248623.WiesingerGFNuhrMMichaelQEbenbichlerGWölflGFialka‐MoserVCross‐cultural adaptation of the Roland‐Morris questionnaire for German‐speaking patients with low back painSpine199924111099110310.1097/00007632-199906010-000091036165924.HillJCWhitehurstDGLewisMBryanSDunnKMFosterNEComparison of stratified primary care management for low back pain with current best practice (STarT Back): a randomised controlled trialLancet201137815607110.1016/S0140-6736(11)60937-92196300225.MoseleyLGButlerDSSchmerzen Verstehen20122Heidelberg GermanySpringer Verlag26.FlorHBirbaumerNPhantom limb pain: cortical plasticity and novel therapeutic approachesCurr Opin Anaesthesiol200013561410.1097/00001503-200010000-000131701635827.LuomajokiHMoseleyGLTactile acuity and lumbopelvic motor control in patients with back pain and healthy controlsBr J Sports Med20114554374010.1136/bjsm.2009.0607311955322228.TsaoHGaleaMPHodgesPWDriving plasticity in the motor cortex in recurrent low back painEur J Pain201014832910.1016/j.ejpain.2010.01.0012018150429.Neuro Orthopaedic Institute. Recognise® software. 2011, 19 North St, Adelaide City West, South Australia 5000, Australia. [http://www.noigroup.com/Recognise/]30.HornKKJenningsSRichardsonGVlietDVHeffordCAbbottJHThe patient-specific functional scale: psychometrics, clinimetrics, and application as a clinical outcome measureJ Orthop Sports Phys Ther2012421304210.2519/jospt.2012.37272203159431.WaddellGNewtonMHendersonISomervilleDMainCJA Fear-Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire (FABQ) and the role of fear-avoidance beliefs in chronic low back pain and disabilityPain1993521576810.1016/0304-3959(93)90127-B845596332.StaerkleRMannionAFElferingAJungeASemmerNKJacobshagenNLongitudinal validation of the Fear-Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire (FABQ) in a Swiss-German sample of low back pain patientsEur Spine J2004133324010.1007/s00586-003-0663-31471424633.SullivanMJLBishopSRPivikJThe pain catastrophizing scale: development and validationPsychol Assess199575243210.1037/1040-3590.7.4.52434.MeyerKSprottHMannionAFCross-cultural adaptation, reliability, and validity of the German version of the Pain Catastrophizing ScaleJ Psychosom Res20086454697810.1016/j.jpsychores.2007.12.0041844039935.CatleyMJTaborAWandBMMoseleyGLAssessing tactile acuity in rheumatology and musculoskeletal medicine–how reliable are two-point discrimination tests at the neck, hand, back and foot?Rheumatology (Oxford)201352814546110.1093/rheumatology/ket1402361191836.BeinartNAGoodchildCEWeinmanJAAyisSGodfreyELIndividual and intervention-related factors associated with adherence to home exercise in chronic low back pain: a systematic reviewSpine J2013131219405010.1016/j.spinee.2013.08.0272416944537.RainvilleJAhernDKPhalenLAltering beliefs about pain and impairment in a functionally oriented treatment program for chronic low back painClin J Pain1993919620110.1097/00002508-199309000-00007821952038.MannionAFBalaguéFPelliséFCedraschiCPain measurement in patients with low back painNat Clin Pract Rheumatol2007311610810.1038/ncprheum06461796833139.HäggOFritzellPNordwallAThe clinical importance of changes in outcome scores after treatment for chronic low back painEur Spine J20031212201259254240.DworkinRHTurkDCMcDermottMPPeirce-SandnerSBurkeLBCowanPInterpreting the clinical importance of group differences in chronic pain clinical trials: IMMPACT recommendationsPain20091462384410.1016/j.pain.2009.08.0191983688841.LeonACDavisLLKraemerHCThe role and interpretation of pilot studies in clinical researchJ Psychiatr Res2011455626910.1016/j.jpsychires.2010.10.0082103513042.ChapmanJRNorvellDCHermsmeyerJTBransfordRJDeVineJMcGirtMJEvaluating common outcomes for measuring treatment success for chronic low back painSpine20113621SS546810.1097/BRS.0b013e31822ef74d2195219043.FaulFErdfelderELangA-GBuchnerAG*Power 3: a flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciencesBehav Res Methods2007391759110.3758/BF0319314617695343
