<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front NeurolFront NeurolFront. Neurol.Frontiers in Neurology1664-2295Frontiers Media S.A.575854410.3389/fneur.2017.00723NeuroscienceClinical TrialAction Observation Plus Sonification. A Novel Therapeutic Protocol for Parkinson’s Patient with Freezing of GaitMezzarobbaSusanna123*GrassiMichele1PellegriniLorella23CatalanMauro2KrugerBjorn4FurlanisGiovanni2ManganottiPaolo23BernardisPaolo11Department of Life Sciences, University of Trieste, Trieste, Italy2Azienda Sanitaria Universitaria Integrata di Trieste, Trieste, Italy3Department of Medical, Surgical and Health Sciences, University of Trieste, Trieste, Italy4Gokhale Method Institute, Palo Alto, CA, United StatesEdited by: Diego Minciacchi, University of Florence, ItalyReviewed by: Matthew Rodger, Queen’s University Belfast, United Kingdom; Elisa Pelosin, University of Genoa, Italy*Correspondence: Susanna Mezzarobba, mezzarob@units.itSpecialty section: This article was submitted to Neuroprosthetics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Neurology041201820178723209201713122017Copyright © 2018 Mezzarobba, Grassi, Pellegrini, Catalan, Kruger, Furlanis, Manganotti and Bernardis.2018Mezzarobba, Grassi, Pellegrini, Catalan, Kruger, Furlanis, Manganotti and BernardisThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Freezing of gait (FoG) is a disabling symptom associated with falls, with little or no responsiveness to pharmacological treatment. Current protocols used for rehabilitation are based on the use of external sensory cues. However, cued strategies might generate an important dependence on the environment. Teaching motor strategies without cues [i.e., action observation (AO) plus Sonification] could represent an alternative/innovative approach to rehabilitation that matters most on appropriate allocation of attention and lightening cognitive load. We aimed to test the effects of a novel experimental protocol to treat patients with Parkinson’s disease (PD) and FoG, using functional, and clinical scales. The experimental protocol was based on AO plus Sonification. 12 patients were treated with 8 motor gestures. They watched eight videos showing an actor performing the same eight gestures, and then tried to repeat each gesture. Each video was composed by images and sounds of the gestures. By means of the Sonification technique, the sounds of gestures were obtained by transforming kinematic data (velocity) recorded during gesture execution, into pitch variations. The same 8 motor gestures were also used in a second group of 10 patients; which were treated with a standard protocol based on a common sensory stimulation method. All patients were tested with functional and clinical scales before, after, at 1 month, and 3 months after the treatment. Data showed that the experimental protocol have positive effects on functional and clinical tests. In comparison with the baseline evaluations, significant performance improvements were seen in the NFOG questionnaire, and the UPDRS (parts II and III). Importantly, all these improvements were consistently observed at the end, 1 month, and 3 months after treatment. No improvement effects were found in the group of patients treated with the standard protocol. These data suggest that a multisensory approach based on AO plus Sonification, with the two stimuli semantically related, could help PD patients with FoG to relearn gait movements, to reduce freezing episodes, and that these effects could be prolonged over time.freezing of gaitaction observationSonificationParkinson’s diseasecueing<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2-1"><title>Design</title><p>The whole pilot RCT was carried out from April 2015 to December 2016. Post-intervention measures were collected at the end, 1 month, and 3 months after the end of the treatment. Patients were randomly assigned to two different training group (experimental and control groups). An investigator, neither involved in the treatment protocol nor in the selection and evaluation of patients, created the computerized randomization procedure (blocked randomization). The same investigator concealed treatment allocation by using small opaque envelopes. Three trained physical therapists with a solid experience in the treatment of PD were involved in the evaluation—one of them—and in the treatment of patients—the other two. Outcome measures were videotaped and also evaluated by a second independent rater blind to the whole experimental study. In case of discrepancies between the two, a third blind rater was used to resolve the evaluation.</p><p>Patients were advised to have their medical treatment continued unchanged throughout the study. This study was carried out in accordance with the recommendations of the “Comitato Etico Regionale Unico” guidelines, with written informed consent from all subjects. All subjects gave written informed consent in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. The protocol was approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee (Comitato Etico Regionale Unico—Friuli Venezia Giulia. Protocol no. 4456—05.02.2015). Patients who agreed to participate always signed a written informed consent and they were able to leave the experiment at any moment, with no additional explanations. The study has been registered at <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://Clinicaltrials.gov">http://Clinicaltrials.gov</uri>, NCT03249155.</p></sec><sec id="S2-2"><title>Participants</title><p>Thirty-seven patients with idiopathic PD (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), according UK Brain Bank (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) were assessed by a neurologist expert in movement disorders, from the outpatient Neurological Clinic, Cattinara Hospital. Eligibility criteria were occurrence of FoG (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) based on patient’s verbal account of his/her freezing experience (or recognition of their typical FoG experience when this symptom was described to him/her by a physician); stages 1–3 on the Hoehn and Yahr scale (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>); stable medication regimen for at least 8 weeks; no major depressive symptoms as defined by a Beck Depression Inventory score ≤16 [BDI (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)]; no signs of dementia as defined by a Mini-Mental Status Examination score &gt;24 [MMSE (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)]. The exclusion criteria were evidence of any adjunctive orthopedic comorbidities that make it impossible to use physical activities and an independent locomotion; others neurological and psychiatric disease; presence of any implanted stimulating or pacing device in central nervous system. Prior power analysis estimated a sample size group of 10 participants. After the first assessment, we enrolled a total of 24 patients (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Two subjects dropped out due to concurrent, unrelated medical events: thus, 22 patients completed the study (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart showing the structure of the study, enrollment and evaluation procedure, and how the patients were divided into the groups, and phases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneur-08-00723-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of patients with Parkinson’s disease at baseline.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AOS group (<italic>n</italic> = 12)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cue group (<italic>n</italic> = 10)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Patients’ characteristics</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender female/male (% female)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/7 (42%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/7 (30%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.67 ± 5.93</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 ± 5.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease duration (years)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.75 ± 3.44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4 ± 4.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mini-Mental State Exam</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.46 ± 1.81</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.58 ± 1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beck Depression Inventory</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 ± 5.98</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 ± 5.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hoehn and Yahr stage</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33 ± 0.49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 ± 0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levodopa equivalent</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">972.5 ± 253.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">983.22 ± 379.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary outcome measure</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFOGQ</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.17 ± 4.61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6 ± 7.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary outcome measures</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRS II Total</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.42 ± 5.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1 ± 6.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRS III Total</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.92 ± 8.69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2 ± 13.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPAS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.75 ± 6.27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.2 ± 9.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BBS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.75 ± 4.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8 ± 3.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6MWT (s)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280.75 ± 93.34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">296.75 ± 48.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TUG (ms)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,299.75 ± 376.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,271.3 ± 615.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 mobility</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.38 ± 22.54</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5 ± 25.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 activities of daily living</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4 ± 21.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.75 ± 17.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 emotional well-being</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.82 ± 21.84</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33 ± 20.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 stigma</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.04 ± 22.94</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.75 ± 20.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 social support</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78 ± 6.49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.83 ± 22.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 cognitions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.23 ± 15.52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.88 ± 19.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 communication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.31 ± 20.86</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.17 ± 21.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 bodily discomfort</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.67 ± 21.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5 ± 19.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 Total</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.67 ± 26.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.8 ± 29.43</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Data are mean ± SD or as otherwise indicated</italic>.</p><p><italic>n, number of patients; NFOGQ, New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire; UPDRS, Unified Parkinson’s Disease Rating Scale II and III; PDQ39, Parkinson’s disease questionnaire 39; MPAS, Modified Parkinson’s Activity Scale; BBS, Berg Balance Scale; 6MWT, 6-min walking test; TUG, Time-Up-and-Go; PDQ39, 39-item PD Questionnaire</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S2-3"><title>Experimental Procedures</title><p>All participants underwent to a 1 h of rehabilitation training during their ON condition (approximately 1 h after the antiparkinsonian medication intake), twice a week, for 8 consecutive weeks, and a total of 16 training sessions.</p><sec id="S2-3-1"><title>Experimental Group</title><p>The protocol was based on the AO method plus Sonification (AOS). During each training session, eight videos, showing an actor performing eight different motor gestures, were presented to the patient that then tried to repeat, according to the Modeling principles (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Each video, lasting 1.5 min, was composed by images (from fronto-lateral perspectives) and sounds (obtained with Sonification) of eight specific motor gestures. These gait related gestures were useful for ameliorating weight shifting, step scaling, and bilateral coordination of stepping, known as locomotion features related to FoG. In each session, all videos were presented, from simple to complex motor actions. The contents of the eight videos are reported in Appendix. Each session started with the observation of the audio–video projected on a large sized screen (2.5 m × 2 m) located in front of the patient at a distance of 2 m. During AO, to increase the accuracy of imitation, patients were asked to attend to the peculiar characteristics of the observed action, and no movements were allowed. At the beginning, after video observation, patients had to practice repetitively the observed actions for the same time (1.5 min). Then, patients performed <italic>on line</italic> the same motor gesture while they were watching the videos. With the aim to facilitate the modeling process, an expert physiotherapist in AO treatment, encouraged and corrected patient’s motor execution. Each video was repeated twice.</p></sec><sec id="S2-3-2"><title>Control Group</title><p>The same eight motor gestures were performed also in the Cue control group with the same order and amount of time, by using attentional strategies. During each training session, patients were asked to practice the motor gesture by means of visual (stripes on the floor) or auditory (metronome) cues, to facilitate the learning of temporal and spatial parameters. As for the experimental group, the expert physiotherapist encouraged and corrected each patient’s motor execution to facilitate correct motor learning process. Following physical therapist’s instructions, patients progressively learned to perform the eight motor gestures without cues.</p><p>Participants of both groups were instructed to not practice further rehabilitation/physiotherapy treatments during the duration of the study. The two therapists involved in the treatments were not dedicated to one group, but equally assigned to both of them.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S2-4"><title>Clinical Outcomes</title><p>The patients who met inclusion/exclusion criteria underwent to a clinical and motor functional evaluation before the treatment (BT), after the treatment (AT), 1 month (1MFU), and 3 months AT (3MFU). The neuropsychological evaluations were only done at the baseline and 1 month (1MFU) AT, since the minimum interval for test administration is 3 months. All clinical evaluations were performed by an experienced neurologist, and a physiotherapist blinded to participants’ allocation.</p><p>As primary outcome, FOG duration and severity were assessed by using New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire (NFOGQ). Particularly, we calculate an index of improvement obtained at AT, 1MFU, and 3MFU evaluations, respect to the BT evaluation (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S2-6">Data Analysis</xref>).</p><p><italic>A priori</italic> power analyses based on a previous experiment that compared the two treatment protocols in individuals with PD and FoG (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), suggested 10 participants per group to achieve a medium effect size (<italic>f</italic> = 0.45, alpha <italic>p</italic> = 0.05, power = 0.95, critical <italic>F</italic> = 4.41). We recruited 12 participants for each group to account for possible attenuation.</p><p>As for the secondary outcomes, disease severity was tested with the Unified Parkinson’s Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS II–III), the Hoehn and Yahr scale (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), and quality of life with the 39-item PD Questionnaire (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Motor functional performance evaluation included Modified Parkinson’s Activity Scale (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), Timed Up and Go (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), and 6-min walking test (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Berg Balance Scale (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) was used to assess static and dynamic balance capabilities. Also for the secondary outcome measures, we calculated an improvement index.</p><sec id="S2-4-1"><title>Neuropsychological Evaluation</title><p>We assessed patients’ most important cognitive functions, useful for learning new motor ability: executive functions, attention, and memory capabilities (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), to exclude that the cognitive profile of the patients of each group was changed after the end of the treatments. This was important to exclude that different levels of efficacy were due to differences in the cognitive profile of the two groups of patients. Global cognitive functioning was tested with the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>); short-term and long-term memory functions with Digit Span backward (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), Corsi Test (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), Babcock Story Recall Test (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>); attention with the Attentive Matrices (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), the Stroop Test (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), and Trail Making Test: parts A and B (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Executive functions were evaluated with the Frontal Assessment Battery (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) and Tower of London Test (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Abstract reasoning by Raven matrices (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). All neuropsychological tests scores were corrected on age, sex, and education using normative values. Moreover, patients were always tested in “ON” condition during their optimal antiparkinsonian medication.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Cognitive profile of patients with Parkinson’s disease at baseline and at 1-month follow-up (1MFU).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Cognitive domain</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Test</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AOS group at baseline</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cue group at baseline</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AOS group at 1MFU</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cue group at 1MFU</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Short-term memory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit Span Backward</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84 ± 1.27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84 ± 1.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59 ± 1.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.58 ± 1.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corsi Test</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85 ± 0.84</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.34 ± 0.84</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50 ± 0.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01 ± 1.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Long-term memory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Babcock Story Recall Test</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immediate recall</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78 ± 1.51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52 ± 2.48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27 ± 1.62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83 ± 2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delayed recall</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 1.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.41 ± 3.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16 ± 1.88</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41 ± 3.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="7" colspan="1">Attention</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attentive Matrices</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.94 ± 8.35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.46 ± 12.86</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.91 ± 11.27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.56 ± 13.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trail Making Test:</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Part A (s)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.35 ± 21.59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.51 ± 46.78</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.44 ± 45.98</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.27 ± 38.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Part B (s)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.34 ± 116.51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190.58 ± 130.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148.35 ± 199.33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.68 ± 117.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop Test</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time (s)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.78 ± 19.19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.73 ± 42.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.59 ± 26.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.72 ± 29.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Errors</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01 ± 3.55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 ± 1.76</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64 ± 2.47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36 ± 3.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Executive functions</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frontal Assessment Battery</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7 ± 1.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.19 ± 1.71</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.55 ± 1.78</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.11 ± 1.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tower of London Test</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.99 ± 1.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.56 ± 6.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.61 ± 0.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.22 ± 1.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reasoning</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raven’s progressive matrices</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.71 ± 6.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.28 ± 5.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.85 ± 6.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.70 ± 5.31</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Data are mean ± SD or as otherwise indicated</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="S2-5"><title>Audiovisual Stimuli</title><p>The short video used in the experimental group showed two healthy actors’ (one male and one female) performing the 8 motor gestures from a lateral and frontal perspective, for a total of 32 different videos (2 gender × 8 gestures × 2 perspectives). Moreover, prior rehabilitation treatment, and to be comfortable with the procedures, each participant practiced the tasks using other videos showing three movements test. The sounds of each video were obtained with the Sonification technique, by transforming kinematic data (i.e., velocity) recorded during the execution of the eight gestures, into audio pitch variations. Actors performed all tasks barefoot, walking along a 10-m walkway surrounded by a seven-camera motion-capture Qualisys System (120 Hz). During the execution of each motor gestures, kinematic data were collected recording four retroflective markers placed on the left and right anterior superior iliac spine to calculate pelvis movement velocity, and on the left and right lateral malleoli to calculate inferior limbs velocity. All data were recorded and preprocessed by a dedicated software Qualisys Track Manager, and frame by frame instantaneous speed was obtained, and transformed into pitch audio by the open source framework Pd (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) using modules developed by Henkelmann and colleagues (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The Sonification itself is done in the following steps: first, median filter with a window size of three frames is applied to the kinematic data to suppress sensor noise from the kinematic data. Second, the data stream is linearly scaled to an interval from 0 to 1. Third, the pitch sound itself is generated. Forth, the sound is mapped to the left or right audio channel. The PD module we used to generate our stimuli can be found in the supplemental materials for this publication. 32 audio track were gained (2 actors gender × 8 different gestures × 2 perspectives) for each motor gestures, and 2 audio tracks for each movement test. Videos were edited by using Final Cut Pro X software, with a dubbing procedure to merge the sounds with the video part of each gesture. The kinematic–acoustic recording was provided with a visual auditory stimulus congruence.</p></sec><sec id="S2-6"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Preliminary, applying the Kolmogorov–Smirnov (KS) test we verified the sustainability of a normal distribution for the primary and secondary clinical outcomes. Highly skewed and kurtotic variables were log transformed and then KS tested for the effectiveness of the correction. Outcomes that failed this second test where excluded from the analysis.</p><p>For each clinical outcome, the improvement (gain) from pretraining to posttraining (AT, 1MFU, and 3MFU) was computed for each participant by subtracting each person’s pretraining score from his/her posttraining score and dividing the difference for the pretraining performance. Formally:
<disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>gain</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>post-training</mml:mtext><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext>pre-training</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-training</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Systematic differences in pretraining scores between the two groups of patients were preliminary excluded with <italic>t</italic>-tests on both primary and secondary outcomes measures. As for the cognitive profile, we verified for potential differences in the pretraining (BT) and modification after 3 months (1MFU) with a 2 × 2 mixed factors ANOVA (Group and Time of evaluation). The results are reported in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Split plot ANOVA results.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean sq</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pr(&gt;F)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">η<sup>2</sup>G (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Main effect of treatment (Group)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary outcome measure</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFOGQ</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.741</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.741</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary outcome measures</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 mobility</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.630</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.633</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.91</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRSIII</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.962</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.962</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 bodily discomfort</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.962</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.962</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 Total</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.031</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.031</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.73</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRSII</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.427</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.427</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BBS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6MWT</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.470</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.470</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TUG</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.070</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.071</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPAS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 cognitions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Main effect Time (within subjects)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary outcome measure</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFOGQ</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary outcome measures</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 mobility</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRSIII</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.334</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 bodily discomfort</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.334</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 Total</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRSII</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BBS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6MWT</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.91</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TUG</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPAS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 cognitions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.546</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Interaction effect (Time × Group)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Primary outcome measure</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFOGQ</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary outcome measures</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 mobility</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.386</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.193</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRSIII</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 bodily discomfort</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 Total</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UPDRSII</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BBS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6MWT</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TUG</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPAS</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDQ39 cognitions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.451</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>ns, not significant; NFOGQ, New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire; UPDRS, Unified Parkinson’s Disease Rating Scale II and III; PDQ39: Parkinson’s disease questionnaire 39; MPAS, Modified Parkinson’s Activity Scale; BBS, Berg Balance Scale; 6MWT, 6-min walking test; TUG, Time-Up-and-Go; PDQ39, 39-item PD Questionnaire; SS, sum of squares</italic>.</p><p><italic>UPDRSIII, TUG, PDQ39 mobility, and PDQ39 bodily discomfort were log transformed for normality. Index η<sup>2</sup>G is the generalized eta-squared statistics calculated following the guidelines by Olejnik and Algina (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) and Bakeman (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). For the two main effects and interaction tested we used the formulas SSA/(SSA + SSs/A + SSPs/A), SSP/(SSP + SSs/A + SSPs/A) and SSPA/(SSPA + SSs/A + SSPs/A), where A and P refer to our variables Group and Time, respectively, and s represents the subject factor. Errors related SS are not shown in this table</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The hypothesis of differences in improvement (gain) between the experimental and control groups was tested by a mixed design ANOVA on the gain scores using <italic>Group</italic> (AOS vs. Cue) as a between subjects factor, and <italic>Time of evaluation</italic> as within-subject factor. Besides main effects, we also considered the interaction terms <italic>Group</italic> × <italic>Time</italic> to assess the stability of the effect across evaluation. <italic>Post hoc</italic> Bonferroni’s test was employed to assess gain score differences between groups at each time. The significant change threshold was set at <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05. We interpreted the meaningfulness of the significant changes using the generalized eta-squared (η<sup>2</sup>G) statistics calculated following the guidelines by Olejnik and Algina (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) and Bakeman (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>).</p><sec id="S2-6-1"><title>Linear Discriminant Analysis (LDA)</title><p>Besides these statistical criteria, to examine the clinical impact of the AOS and Cue training on outcomes scores, we used also an automated classification rates criterion. This method is commonly used as a technique for pattern classification. In our case, we used this method to compare or classify the clinical profiles of the patients in the two groups, and at the different stages of the experimental study. Automated classification problems involve continuous input variables (i.e., our clinical scales), and categorical outcomes (i.e., the rehabilitation protocol or the stage of the study). The algorithm has to learn to predict the category from the input data. We used an LDA algorithm in two differ ways, to discriminate between groups and within subjects. Finally, we choose to complement standard analysis of variance with this LDA because of recommendations on using simulative approaches to data analysis with small samples (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p><p>First, the algorithm learned between-groups’ discriminative criterion on a fraction of 70% of the data set, then for testing we applied the criterion on the remaining fraction of 30% (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S8">Supplementary Material</xref>), measuring the classification accuracy in terms of sensitivity index (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Average sensitivities were based on a complete random design, simulating all possible combination of 70–30% of the participants (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Particularly, we trained and tested the LDA four times, over each evaluation time (BT, AT, 1MFU, and 3MFU), and considering the rehabilitation protocol attended by participants as the categorical outcome to predict.</p><p>Second, to evaluate stability over time, as in the case of interaction term in the ANOVA, we considered within-subject evaluations, using the LDA algorithm on a subset composed by 70% of pre- and posttraining individual’s outcomes, and testing it on the remaining 30% of pre- and posttraining individual’s outcomes.</p><p>In both cases, we expect that the more effective is the training in transforming the participants clinical profile, the more accurate is the LDA algorithm in (learn to) classify the participants within the training actually practiced. In the first LDA implementation, we expect that the LDA classification would fail only in the comparison between the two groups at the BT time window.</p><p>All the analyses were programmed using R statistical language (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec>ResultsAt the baseline, there were no significant differences between groups with respect to demographics and clinical records, as shown in Table 1. Also for the cognitive profile, as reported in Table 2, there was no differences except for the interaction Group × Time in the Corsi test [F(1,20) = 5.975, p = 0.024, η2 = 0.225], but when we compared the two groups in the two moments with a t-test, the difference was not significant [t(20) = 1.449, p = 0.163; t(20) = −0.480, p = 0.636].Primary Outcome MeasureAction observation plus Sonification treatment had a significant positive effect in reducing the primary outcome measure, participant’s ratings of FoG severity and duration, as shown at the end of the treatment, and most important, at the second follow-up (Figure 2, NFOGQ). Noteworthy, on our sample the standard Cue protocol did not show any relevant gain effect from the baseline evaluation.Figure 2Improvement (gain) of the two groups in the primary outcome measure [New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire (NFOGQ)], at the three evaluation times. Error bars are 1 SE.Secondary Outcome MeasuresSecondary outcome measures that improved in AOS (Figure 3) were as follows: severity of motor impairment (UPDRS III); motor problems, and bodily discomfort in activity of daily life (the mobility and bodily discomfort subscales of the PDQ39 questionnaire). For this pool of outcome measures, the positive effect of AOS treatment over Cue training has a great effect size (η2G &gt; 0.30) and is stable until the last follow-up (see post hoc comparisons reported in Table 4). Even in these measures, the standard Cue protocol did not show any relevant gain effect. Figures 2 and 3 show the gain scores of the main effects.Figure 3Improvement (gain) of the two groups in five secondary outcome measures [Unified Parkinson’s Disease Rating Scale: parts II and III (UPDRS) and Parkinson’s disease questionnaire 39 (PDQ39): mobility, bodily discomfort, and the total score], at the three evaluation times. Error bars are 1 SE.Table 4Bonferroni post hoc comparisons AOS group vs. cue group.After treatment1st Follow-up2nd Follow-upPrimary outcome measureNFOGQp ≤ 0.001p ≤ 0.001p ≤ 0.001Secondary outcome measuresPDQ39 mobilityp ≤ 0.05p ≤ 0.001p ≤ 0.001UPDRSIIIp ≤ 0.001p ≤ 0.05p ≤ 0.05PDQ39 bodily discomfortp ≤ 0.001p ≤ 0.05p ≤ 0.05PDQ39 Totalnsp ≤ 0.01p ≤ 0.01UPDRSIInsp ≤ 0.05p ≤ 0.01BBSnsp ≤ 0.05ns6MWTnsnsp ≤ 0.05TUGnsnsnsMPASnsnsnsPDQ39 cognitionsnsnsnsData are p-levels of the direct comparisons at each evaluation time, between groups, after the Bonferroni correction.NFOGQ, New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire; UPDRS, Unified Parkinson’s Disease Rating Scale II and III; PDQ39, Parkinson’s disease questionnaire 39; MPAS, Modified Parkinson’s Activity Scale; BBS, Berg Balance Scale; 6MWT, 6-min walking test; TUG, Time-Up-and-Go; ns, not significant.Table 3 reports F-tests for main effects and interaction separately, for all outcomes considered, whereas Table 4 reports direct comparisons at each evaluation time, between groups.At first glance, for nearly all secondary outcomes, the group factor (the main effect of rehabilitation protocol) had the greater effect size (η2G). These effects are stable over time since interaction terms are not significant and/or with negligible amounts of variance explained.The problems in activity of daily living (PDQ39 total score, UPDRS II) were significantly reduced by AOS training, with stable results also after 3 months. Moreover, AOS training determined also a small improvement on average gain scores of motor balance (BBS, see Tables 3 and 4).Linear Discriminant AnalysisWe trained an LDA algorithm to learn to discriminate between rehabilitation protocols attended by participants, using as input variables significant outcomes identified by ANOVA. Particularly, inclusion criteria were the following: (a) significant main effect on group factor and great effect size (&gt;0.30), (b) stable result over evaluation time (no interaction in Table 1 and significant post hoc comparisons in Table 3). Input variables were the raw data, not transformed into gain scores. Figure 4A shows average discrimination accuracy, expressed in terms of sensitivity—i.e., SDs from chance (51). At the baseline, the algorithm could not learn a reliable criterion to recognize “AOS” or “Cue” participants since their clinical profiles are homogeneous (Table 2) and hence its performance stops to a chance level. Immediately AT, at 1 month, and after 3 months, experimental protocol differentiates participant’s outcomes from the baseline levels and the algorithm can learn a criterion that move the performance (nearly) 1 SD from the chance. Importantly, the effect is far more evident considering the mobility outcome (NFOGQ and UPDRS III), over the improvement in ability of daily activities (PDQ39 mobility and bodily discomfort).Figure 4Average discrimination accuracy expressed in terms of sensitivity (d′) of the linear discriminant analysis (LDA) algorithm. (A) Results of testing between-groups’ discrimination. Dark gray bars represent LDA results from the New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire (NFOGQ) and UPDRS III scales. Light gray bars represent LDA results from the PDQ39 mobility and bodily discomfort scales. (B) Results of testing within-subject discrimination. Dark and light red bars represent LDA results from the NFOGQ and UPDRS III scales for the Action Observation plus Sonification experimental group. Dark and light blue bars represent LDA results from the PDQ39 mobility and bodily discomfort scales, for the Cue control group.Furthermore, using the same input variables, we trained an LDA algorithm to discriminate each participant’s pre- and posttraining conditions, within each group; Figure 4B shows average sensitivity index, separately for the AOS and Cue conditions. Participants trained with experimental AOS protocol were discriminable with respect to their baseline condition to an extent of 2 SD from chance, using clinical motor profile, and this result is quite stable over time. The ability of the algorithm to learn systematically a criterion over the chance was not proven, within participant’s undergoing rehabilitation with Cue.Ethics StatementThis study was carried out in accordance with the recommendations of the “Comitato Etico Regionale Unico” guidelines, with written informed consent from all subjects. All subjects gave written informed consent in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. The protocol was approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee (Comitato Etico Regionale Unico—Friuli Venezia Giulia. Protocol no. 4456—05.02.2015). Patients who agreed to participate always signed a written informed consent and they were able to leave the experiment at any moment, with no additional explanations. The study has been registered at http://Clinicaltrials.gov, NCT03249155.Author ContributionsConception, and design of the research project: SM and PB. Organization of the research project: SM, PB, and PM. Execution of the research project: SM, LP, MC, BK, GF, and PB. Treatment of the patients: SM and LP. Statistical analysis and interpretation of data; writing of the manuscript first draft: SM, MG, and PB. Manuscript review and critique: SM, MG, LP, MC, BK, PM, and PB.Conflict of Interest StatementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.The authors wish to thank the patients of the Neurology Clinic—Cattinara Hospital (Trieste) for being so generous with their time and efforts.Funding. This work was not supported by any third party funding or research grant.References1KwakYMüllerMLBohnenNIDayaluPSeidlerRD. l-DOPA changes ventral striatum recruitment during motor sequence learning in Parkinson’s disease. Behav Brain Res (2012) 230:116–24.10.1016/j.bbr.2012.02.006223430692RuitenbergMFLDuthooWSantensPSeidlerRDNotebaertWAbrahamseEL. Sequence learning in Parkinson’s disease: focusing on action dynamics and the role of dopaminergic medication. Neuropsychologia (2016) 93(Pt A):30–9.10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2016.09.027277025973CoolsRBarkerRASahakianBJRobbinsTW. Enhanced or impaired cognitive function in Parkinson’s disease as a function of dopaminergic medication and task demands. Cereb Cortex (2001) 11(12):1136–43.10.1093/cercor/11.12.1136117094844DuthooWBraemSHoutmanFSchouppeNSantensPNotebaertW. Dopaminergic medication counteracts conflict adaptation in patients with Parkinson’s disease. Neuropsychology (2013) 27(5):556–61.10.1037/a0033377238150935RedgravePRodriguezMSmithYRodriguez-OrozMCLehericySBergmanH
Goal-directed and habitual control in the basal ganglia: implications for Parkinson’s disease. Nat Rev Neurosci (2010) 11(11):760–72.10.1038/nrn2915209446626VandenbosscheJDeroostNSoetensECoomansDSpildoorenJVercruysseS
Impaired implicit sequence learning in Parkinson’s disease patients with freezing of gait. Neuropsychology (2013) 27(1):28–36.10.1037/a0031278233565947GinisPNackaertsENieuwboerAHeremansE. Cueing for people with Parkinson’s disease with freezing of gait: a narrative review of the state-of-the-art and novel perspectives. Ann Phys Rehabil Med (2017).10.1016/j.rehab.2017.08.002288903418PatlaAEVickersJN. Where and when do we look as we approach and step over an obstacle in the travel path?
Neuroreport (1997) 8(17):3661–5.10.1097/00001756-199712010-0000294273479YoungWRShreveLQuinnEJCraigCBronte-StewartH
Auditory cueing in Parkinson’s patients with freezing of gait. What matters most_action-relevance or cue-continuity?
Neuropsychologia (2016) 87:54–62.10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2016.04.0342716339710StefanKCohenLGDuqueJMazzocchioRCelnikPSawakiL
Formation of a motor memory by action observation. J Neurosci (2005) 25(41):9339–46.10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2282-05.20051622184211GattiRTettamantiAGoughPMRiboldiEMarinoniLBuccinoG. Action observation versus motor imagery in learning a complex motor task: a short review of literature and a kinematics study. Neurosci Lett (2013) 540:37–42.10.1016/j.neulet.2012.11.0392320674812AbbruzzeseGAvanzinoLMarcheseRPelosinE. Action observation and motor imagery: innovative cognitive tools in the rehabilitation of Parkinson’s disease. Parkinsons Dis (2015) 2015:124214.10.1155/2015/1242142649515013ShamsLSeitzAR. Benefits of multisensory learning. Trends Cogn Sci (2008) 12(11):411–7.10.1016/j.tics.2008.07.0061880503914DavidsdottirSCronin-GolombALeeA. Visual and spatial symptoms in Parkinson’s disease. Vision Res (2005) 45(10):1285–96.10.1016/j.visres.2004.11.0061573396115LehmannSMurrayMM. The role of multisensory memories in unisensory object discrimination. Brain Res Cogn Brain Res (2005) 24(2):326–34.10.1016/j.cogbrainres.2005.02.0051599377016Von KriegsteinKGiraudAL. Implicit multisensory associations influence voice recognition. PLoS Biol (2006) 4(10):e326.10.1371/journal.pbio.00403261700251917SchmitzGMohammadiBHammerAHeldmannMSamiiAMünteTF
Observation of sonified movements engages a basal ganglia frontocortical network. BMC Neurosci (2013) 14(1):32.10.1186/1471-2202-14-322349682718KimRSSeitzARShamsL. Benefits of stimulus congruency for multisensory facilitation of visual learning. PLoS One (2008) 3(1):e1532.10.1371/journal.pone.00015321823161219SilvaAEBarakatBKJimenezLOShamsL
Multisensory congruency enhances explicit awareness in a sequence learning task. Multisensor Res (2017) 30(7–8):681–9.10.1163/22134808-0000258720SigristRRauterGRienerRWolfP. Augmented visual, auditory, haptic, and multimodal feedback in motor learning: a review. Psychon Bull Rev (2013) 20(1):21–53.10.3758/s13423-012-0333-82313260521RodgerMWMYoungWRCraigCM. Synthesis of walking sounds for alleviating gait disturbances in Parkinson’s disease. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng (2014) 22(3):543–8.10.1109/TNSRE.2013.22854102423527522EffenbergAO
Movement sonification: effects on perception and action. IEEE Multimedia (2005) 12(2):53–9.10.1109/MMUL.2005.3123HughesAJDanielSEKilfordLLeesAJ. Accuracy of clinical diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson’s disease: a clinico-pathological study of 100 cases. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry (1992) 55(3):181–4.10.1136/jnnp.55.3.181156447624NieuwboerARochesterLHermanTVandenbergheWEmilGEThomaesT
Reliability of the new freezing of gait questionnaire: agreement between patients with Parkinson’s disease and their carers. Gait Posture (2009) 30(4):459–63.10.1016/j.gaitpost.2009.07.1081966094925GoetzCGPoeweWRascolOSampaioCStebbinsGTCounsellC
Movement Disorder Society Task Force report on the Hoehn and Yahr staging scale: status and recommendations. Mov Disord (2004) 19:1020–8.10.1002/mds.202131537259126BeckATSteerRABrownGK
Beck Depression Inventory: Manual BDI-II. New York: Psychological Corporation (1996).27Arevalo-RodriguezISmailagicNRoquéIFigulsMCiapponiASanchez-PerezE
Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) for the detection of Alzheimer’s disease and other dementias in people with mild cognitive impairment (MCI). Cochrane Database Syst Rev (2015) 25(3):CD01078310.1002/14651858.CD010783.pub228BanduraA
Social Learning Theory. Toronto, Canada: Prentice-Hall (1977).29PelosinEAvanzinoLBoveMStramesiPNieuwboerAAbbruzzeseG
Action observation improves freezing of gait in patients with Parkinson’s disease. Neurorehabil Neural Repair (2010) 24(8):746–52.10.1177/15459683103686852045315530PetoVJenkinsonCFitzpatrickR
PDQ-39: a review of the development, validation and application of a Parkinson’s disease quality of life questionnaire and its associated measures. J Neurol (1998) 245(1):S10–4.10.1007/PL00007730961771631KeusSHJNieuwboerABloemBRBormGFMunnekeM. Clinimetric analyses of the Modified Parkinson Activity Scale. Parkinsonism Relat Disord (2009) 15(4):263–9.10.1016/j.parkreldis.2008.06.0031869192932PodsiadloDRichardsonS
The timed “Up &amp; Go”: a test of basic functional mobility for frail elderly persons. J Am Geriatr Soc (1991) 39(2):142–8.10.1111/j.1532-5415.1991.tb01616.x199194633FalvoMJEarhartGM. Six-minute walk distance in persons with Parkinson disease: a hierarchical regression model. Arch Phys Med Rehabil (2009) 90(6):1004–8.10.1016/j.apmr.2008.12.0181948087734BergKOWood-DauphineeSLWilliamsJIMakiB. Measuring balance in the elderly: validation of an instrument. Can J Public Health (1992) 83:S7–11.146805535NasreddineZSPhillipsNABédirianVCharbonneauSWhiteheadVCollinI
The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment. J Am Geriatr Soc (2005) 53(4):695–9.10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x1581701936OrsiniAGrossiDCapitaniELaiaconaMPapagnoCVallarG. Verbal and spatial immediate memory span: normative data from 1355 adults and 1112 children. Ital J Neurol Sci (1987) 8(6):537–48.10.1007/BF02333660342921337De RenziENichelliP. Verbal and non-verbal short-term memory impairment following hemispheric damage. Cortex (1975) 11(4):341–54.10.1016/S0010-9452(75)80026-8122257838CarlesimoGABuccioneIFaddaL
Normative data of two memory tasks: short-story recall and Rey’s figure. Nuova Rivista Di Neurologia (2002) 12(1):1–13.39Della SalaSLaiaconaMSpinnlerHUbezioC. A cancellation test: its reliability in assessing attentional deficits in Alzheimer’s disease. Psychol Med (1992) 22(4):885–901.10.1017/S0033291700038460148848640BarbarottoRLaiaconaMFrosioRVecchioMFarinatoACapitaniE. A normative study on visual reaction times and two Stroop colour-word tests. Ital J Neurol Sci (1998) 19(3):161–70.10.1007/BF008315661093347141GiovagnoliARDel PesceMMascheroniSSimoncelliMLaiaconaMCapitaniE. Trail making test: normative values from 287 normal adult controls. Ital J Neurol Sci (1996) 17(4):305–9.10.1007/BF01997792891576442IavaroneARongaBPellegrinoLLoréEVitalianoSGaleoneF
The Frontal Assessment Battery (FAB): normative data from an Italian sample and performances of patients with Alzheimer’s disease and frontotemporal dementia. Funct Neurol (2004) 19(3):191–5.1559571443KrikorianRBartokJGayN. Tower of London procedure: a standard method and developmental data. J Clin Exp Neuropsychol (1994) 16(6):840–50.10.1080/01688639408402697789081944BelacchiCScalisiTGCannoniECornoldiC
CPM-Coloured Progressive Matrices. Standardizzazione Italiana. Firenze: Giunti – Organizzazioni Speciali (2008).45PucketteM
Pd Documentation. (2017). Available from: http://msp.ucsd.edu/Pd_documentation/46HenkelmannC
Improving the Aesthetic Quality of Realtime Motion Data Sonification (No. CG-2007-4). Bonn, Germany: Universität Bonn (2007).47HenkelmannCZinkeAWeberA
Towards aesthetic realtime sonification of motion data. Presented at the 4. Workshop Virtuelle Realität und Augmented Reality der GI-Fachgruppe VR/AR 2007. Bonn, Germany: Weimar (2007).48OlejnikSAlginaJ. Generalized eta and omega squared statistics: measures of effect size for some common research designs. Psychol Methods (2003) 8(4):434–47.10.1037/1082-989X.8.4.4341466468149BakemanR. Recommended effect size statistics for repeated measures designs. Behav Res Methods (2005) 37(3):379–84.10.3758/BF031927071640513350MoreauDKirkIJWaldieKE. Seven pervasive statistical flaws in cognitive training interventions. Front Hum Neurosci (2016) 10:153.10.3389/fnhum.2016.001532714801051MacmillanNACreelmanCD
Detection Theory: A User’s Guide. Mahwah, New Jersey: Laurence Erlbaum Associates (2005).52R Development Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing (2017). Available from: http://www.R-project.org53AgostaFGattiRSarassoEVolontéMACanuEMeaniA
Brain plasticity in Parkinson’s disease with freezing of gait induced by action observation training. J Neurol (2017) 264(1):88–101.10.1007/s00415-016-8309-72777816154NieuwboerARochesterLMüncksLSwinnenSP
Motor learning in Parkinson’s disease: limitations and potential for rehabilitation. Parkinsonism Relat Disord (2009) 15(Suppl 3):S53–8.10.1016/S1353-8020(09)70781-355LuCAmundsen HuffmasterSLTuitePJVachonJMMacKinnonCD. Effect of cue timing and modality on gait initiation in Parkinson disease with freezing of gait. Arch Phys Med Rehabil (2017) 98(7):1291–9.e1.10.1016/j.apmr.2017.01.0092816709356SeidlerRDBernardJABurutoluTBFlingBWGordonMTGwinJT
Motor control and aging: links to age-related brain structural, functional, and biochemical effects. Neurosci Biobehav Rev (2010) 34(5):721–33.10.1016/j.neubiorev.2009.10.0051985007757Bunting-PerryLSpindlerMRobinsonKMNoorigianJCianciHJDudaJE. Laser light visual cueing for freezing of gait in Parkinson disease: a pilot study with male participants. J Rehabil Res Dev (2013) 50(2):223–30.10.1682/JRRD.2011.12.02552376100358SpenceC
Audiovisual multisensory integration. Acoust Sci Technol (2007) 28(2):61–70.10.1250/ast.28.6159VatakisASpenceC
Crossmodal binding: evaluating the “unity assumption” using audiovisual speech stimuli. Percept Psychophys (2007) 69(5):744–56.10.3758/BF031937761792969760WolpertDMDiedrichsenJFlanaganJR
Principles of sensorimotor learning. Nat Rev Neurosci (2011) 12:739–51.10.1038/nrn31122203353761BrunettiRIndraccoloAMastroberardinoSSpenceCSantangeloV. The impact of cross-modal correspondences on working memory performance. J Exp Psychol Hum Percept Perform (2017) 43(4):819–31.10.1037/xhp00003482834594862HallJMShineJMWaltonCCGilatMKamsmaYPTNaismithSL
Early phenotypic differences between Parkinson’s disease patients with and without freezing of gait. Parkinsonism Relat Disord (2014) 20(6):604–7.10.1016/j.parkreldis.2014.02.0282467990163PetzingerGMFisherBEMcEwenSBeelerJAWalshJPJakowecMW. Exercise-enhanced neuroplasticity targeting motor and cognitive circuitry in Parkinson’s disease. Lancet Neurol (2013) 12(7):716–26.10.1016/S1474-4422(13)70123-62376959864ForresterLWHanleyDFMackoRF. Effects of treadmill exercise on transcranial magnetic stimulation-induced excitability to quadriceps after stroke. Arch Phys Med Rehabil (2006) 87(2):229–34.10.1016/j.apmr.2005.10.01616442977AppendixExercise 1Shifting the body weight in the frontal plane and taking a step—Actor stands straight up, with both feet on the floor, shifting the body weight to the right (or to the left), to the left (or to the right), and then raise and move forward the right (or the left) leg and the body to take the first step.Exercise 2Shifting the body weight in the sagittal plane and taking a step—Actor stands straight up with both feet on the floor. One foot placed in front of the other, with the heel ahead of the other foot’s toes. The actor shifts weight from one foot to the other, always keeping the feet on the floor; afterwards he takes a step forward.Exercise 3Gait initiation—Actor starts to walk with the preferred leg.Exercise 4Turning around—Actor walks two steps with a straight trajectory, and then made a 180° turn in a narrow quarter (U-turn).Exercise 5Stepping over an obstacle—Actor walks three steps with a straight trajectory, and then steps over the obstacle (obstacle’s height: 10% of patient’s height).Exercise 6Sit-to-walk—Actor is seated on a backless and armless stool (knee angle 100°), and then raises and walks three steps forward.Exercise 7Walking straight with long steps—Actor walks about 10 long steps with a straight trajectory trying to maintain a steady pace and to take long steps.Exercise 8Walking through a doorway—Actor walks three steps with a straight trajectory, moves through a real doorway without stopping and then continue to walk two more steps.
