<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-0640</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5574875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2017.00157</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Pilot Study of the Effects of Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction on Post-traumatic Stress Disorder Symptoms and Brain Response to Traumatic Reminders of Combat in Operation Enduring Freedom/Operation Iraqi Freedom Combat Veterans with Post-traumatic Stress Disorder</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>James Douglas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/310487"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>Sanskriti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/382796"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campanella</surname><given-names>Carolina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Majid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/384057"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kasher</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/466970"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fani</surname><given-names>Negar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Amit Jasvant</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/172529"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reiff</surname><given-names>Collin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Lori L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>Viola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Emory University</institution>, <addr-line>Atlanta, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Radiology, Emory University</institution>, <addr-line>Atlanta, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Atlanta VA Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Decatur, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Psychiatry, University of Alabama</institution>, <addr-line>Birmingham, AL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>The Tuskegee VA Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Tuskegee, AL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Department of Epidemiology, Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University</institution>, <addr-line>Atlanta, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup><institution>Department of Medicine, Division of Cardiology, Emory University School of Medicine, Emory University</institution>, <addr-line>Atlanta, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><sup>8</sup><institution>Department of Medicine, Division of Preventive and Behavioral Medicine, University of Massachusetts Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Worcester, MA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Brian Edward Engdahl, University of Minnesota, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Annegret Krause-Utz, Central Institute of Mental Health, Germany; Stefania Tognin, King&#x02019;s College London, United Kingdom</p></fn><corresp content-type="corresp" id="cor1">*Correspondence: James Douglas Bremner, <email>doug.bremner@emory.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>Specialty section: This article was submitted to Neuroimaging and Stimulation, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychiatry</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>157</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017 Bremner, Mishra, Campanella, Shah, Kasher, Evans, Fani, Shah, Reiff, Davis, Vaccarino and Carmody.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bremner, Mishra, Campanella, Shah, Kasher, Evans, Fani, Shah, Reiff, Davis, Vaccarino and Carmody</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><sec id="ST1"><title>Objective</title><p>Brain imaging studies in patients with post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) have implicated a circuitry of brain regions including the medial prefrontal cortex, amygdala, hippocampus, parietal cortex, and insula. Pharmacological treatment studies have shown a reversal of medial prefrontal deficits in response to traumatic reminders. Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) is a promising non-pharmacologic approach to the treatment of anxiety and pain disorders. The purpose of this study was to assess the effects of MBSR on PTSD symptoms and brain response to traumatic reminders measured with positron-emission tomography (PET) in Operation Enduring Freedom/Operation Iraqi Freedom (OEF/OIF) combat veterans with PTSD. We hypothesized that MBSR would show increased prefrontal response to stress and improved PTSD symptoms in veterans with PTSD.</p></sec><sec id="ST2"><title>Method</title><p>Twenty-six OEF/OIF combat veterans with PTSD who had recently returned from a combat zone were block randomized to receive eight sessions of MBSR or present-centered group therapy (PCGT). PTSD patients underwent assessment of PTSD symptoms with the Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS), mindfulness with the Five Factor Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ) and brain imaging using PET in conjunction with exposure to neutral and Iraq combat-related slides and sound before and after treatment. Nine patients in the MBSR group and 8 in the PCGT group completed all study procedures.</p></sec><sec id="ST3"><title>Results</title><p>Post-traumatic stress disorder patients treated with MBSR (but not PCGT) had an improvement in PTSD symptoms measured with the CAPS that persisted for 6&#x02009;months after treatment. MBSR also resulted in an increase in mindfulness measured with the FFMQ. MBSR-treated patients had increased anterior cingulate and inferior parietal lobule and decreased insula and precuneus function in response to traumatic reminders compared to the PCGT group.</p></sec><sec id="ST4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study shows that MBSR is a safe and effective treatment for PTSD. Furthermore, MBSR treatment is associated with changes in brain regions that have been implicated in PTSD and are involved in extinction of fear responses to traumatic memories as well as regulation of the stress response.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>stress disorders</kwd><kwd>post-traumatic</kwd><kwd>brain imaging</kwd><kwd>positron-emission tomography</kwd><kwd>mindfulness training</kwd><kwd>mindfulness-based stress reduction</kwd><kwd>anterior cingulate cortex</kwd><kwd>insula</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn01">National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000050</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn01">R01 HL088726, K24 HL077506</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn02">National Institute of Mental Health<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000025</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn02">K24 MH076955, T32 MH067547, R01 MH56120</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn03">National Center for Research Resources<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000097</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn03">S10 RR016917</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn04">U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100000738</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn04">VET HEAL/Samueli</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="8"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="155"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="12573"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is an important clinical problem in populations exposed to traumatic experiences such as war, sexual assault, and natural disasters. Prevalence rates vary but large epidemiological studies show a lifetime prevalence of PTSD in the United States of about 8% (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Increasing awareness and an increase in research in the field have furthered our understanding of this disorder, which is reflected in the revisions of the diagnostic criteria for PTSD and its reclassification from a form of anxiety disorder to its current place in trauma- and stressor-related disorders in the DSM-V criteria (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>Operation Enduring Freedom/Operation Iraqi Freedom (OEF/OIF) entailed multiple deployments of American military personnel to Afghanistan and Iraq. Thirteen percent of soldiers deployed to Iraq were reported to have PTSD, and many of these soldiers did not seek mental health care (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). For those who do seek treatment, the available treatments are not always effective. Pharmacological treatment results in improvement in only a portion of PTSD patients and in others there is only a partial response to treatment (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Psychological treatments involve either trauma-based and non-trauma-based interventions (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Prolonged exposure therapy and cognitive processing therapy, two of the most well-studied forms of therapy, have been shown to be efficacious in many veterans with PTSD; however, about 30&#x02013;60% of patients failed to show clinically significant improvement (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Among the reasons cited for the same included high dropout rates of 30&#x02013;40% due difficulties in tolerating the therapy, or failure to initiate therapy in the first place related to avoidance of traumatic reminders (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). These limitations have led to the search for alternative treatments for PTSD, such as mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) and other mindfulness-based training approaches (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>Mindfulness may be defined as intentionally paying attention to present-moment experience (physical sensations, affective states, thoughts, and imagery) in a non-judgmental way and thereby cultivating a stable and non-reactive awareness (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Mindfulness is one of eight qualities cultivated in Buddhism to reduce psychic angst. It is the commonly used English translation of the word &#x0201c;sati&#x0201d; in the Pali cannon, where its meaning is akin to remembering awareness. In that system, relief comes through recognition of distress being created moment by moment through conditioned mental processes and behavior. It also teaches that everyday experience is composed of three phenomenological components; cognitions, sensations, and their pleasant/unpleasant feeling tones, which are interwoven in conditioned cycles of association. A thought gives rise to a feeling, that gives rise to a sensation, which reminds again of the thought, and on it goes.</p><p>Mindfulness training exercises are designed to cultivate recognition of these processes in real time. Attention is used to notice whichever thoughts, sensations, and feelings are appearing in awareness, while at the same time retaining the capacity to maintain the focus on these contents, or to redirect attention elsewhere. Recognition of this process, normally disguised beneath life&#x02019;s everyday demands, results in a change in relationship with one&#x02019;s thoughts, feelings, and sensations; rather than attention becoming preoccupied with their content, and trying to change or avoid them, they are recognized as events occurring in the field of awareness and will, by their nature, change. By providing a sense of control in stressful situations and encounters, this less-reactive response reduces the likelihood of being overwhelmed by thoughts and feelings and leaves mental space for more creative and less habitual responses.</p><p>Mindfulness training found its way into Western clinical settings largely through the work of Kabat-Zinn, who developed the manualized MBSR program (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The program classes also provide education in applying those recognitions to habitual and reactive patterns in everyday situations as they are occurring (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The program has been found to promote attention processes (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) and feelings of well-being, as well as reducing stress and worry (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). In the context of the present study, mindfulness training appears to target reactivity and experiential avoidance, key factors in the development and maintenance of PTSD (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Because it is not based on processing the content of traumatic experience, it potentially circumvents problems related to treatment compliance related to symptoms of avoidance.</p><p>Mindfulness-based stress reduction has been shown to be effective for a variety of conditions, including chronic pain (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), hot flashes (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), asthma (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), depression (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) fibromyalgia (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), psoriasis (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), and anxiety (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). MBSR is also helpful as an adjunctive intervention in patients with complex medical conditions, including promoting cancer recovery (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), reducing psychological distress and depression, and promoting well-being and health-related quality of life (QOL), and sense of well-being (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) with positive effects persisting well beyond the initial treatment period (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p><p>Specific to PTSD, MBSR could potentially increase participants&#x02019; overall sense of control (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) through a positive accepting mode of control (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), which is associated with greater QOL and emotional well-being (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). This less reactive mode of coping with difficulties may provide a way for PTSD patients to experience a greater sense of control in relation to their trauma-related thought and memories and to be less emotionally reactive to their presence (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). This process may also prevent the rehearsing and replay of traumatic memories, which may modify the way they are stored and make them indelible, or resistant to further modification. A number of studies demonstrated the utility of MBSR for the promotion of well-being and mental health (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).</p><p>Studies have assessed the effect of mindfulness-based programs on symptoms of PTSD (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). An uncontrolled study in veterans with PTSD showed an improvement in PTSD with MBSR in comparison to baseline (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>), A controlled study in veterans with PTSD of primary care brief mindfulness training showed a reduction in PTSD symptoms in comparison to treatment as usual (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). A controlled study of standard MBSR in veterans with PTSD, however, did not show clear improvements in PTSD symptoms compared to treatment as usual, although mental health QOL was improved, and there was a pattern of PTSD symptom response in treatment completers (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Increases in mindfulness with MBSR, especially mindful awareness and non-reactivity, were associated with a decrease in PTSD symptoms when data from this study were combined with other data from the same group in a re-analysis (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Another controlled study in veterans with PTSD showed reductions in self-reported PTSD symptoms with MBSR compared to present-centered group therapy (PCGT), but not clinician ratings as measured with the Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS). Women with a history of interpersonal violence, of whom 38% met a checklist cutoff for PTSD, who underwent a trauma-informed MBSR treatment showed a reduction in symptoms compared to a wait-list control group (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Patients with a history of childhood abuse, of whom 55% met a checklist cutoff for PTSD, who underwent an uncontrolled MBSR course of treatment showed a reduction in self-reported PTSD symptoms with treatment (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). In summary, no studies using active comparison groups have shown a reduction in PTSD symptoms with MBSR based on clinician ratings.</p><p>Previous studies have outlined a network of brain regions involved in symptoms of PTSD (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>) that show functional responses to successful treatment (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Brain imaging studies have identified a network of brain regions involved in the symptoms of PTSD that includes the amygdala, prefrontal cortex, hippocampus, parietal cortex, and insula (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>), brain regions that play an important role in both memory, fear learning, and the physiological response to threat (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). The amygdala signals other parts of the brain to initiate the fight or flight response and in conjunction with hippocampus to convert this experience into a long-term memory. The suppression of the amygdala during extinction of fearful memories is mediated by the prefrontal cortex. The parietal cortex is involved in evaluating the self and other in space and time, which is an important facet of the stress response (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), and the insula serves as a gateway to peripheral responses to stress as well as regulating sense of time (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Positron-emission tomography (PET), single-photon emission computed tomography, and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies have shown traumatic reminders to result in decreased cerebral blood flow, and failure of activation in the medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC)/anterior cingulate in PTSD patients (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Other brain areas implicated in PTSD include the parietal cortex (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>), precuneus (<xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>, <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>), and insula (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>). These brain areas are involved memory, spatial attention, and coordination of peripheral physiological responses to stress.</p><p>A hypoactive frontal lobe leads to impairment in the differentiation of benign stresses from true stresses, consequently leading to reduction in the suppression of the amygdala manifesting as a hypervigilant state that is seen in PTSD (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Fear learning paradigms have shown an increase in amygdala function in PTSD, and studies have shown both smaller hippocampal volume (<xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>) and decreased function with memory tasks in PTSD patients. Smaller hippocampal volume and decreased medial prefrontal cortical function has been shown to reverse with both pharmacotherapy (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>) and psychotherapies including eye movement desensitization reprocessing (<xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>, <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>) and cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) (<xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). Psychotherapy for PTSD also led to changes in parietal cortex function (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). Imaging studies suggest that MBSR may affect brain areas and physiological systems involved in the fear response in a beneficial way (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>). A recent study showed an increased connectivity between default mode network brain regions and frontal brain regions involved in executive control in PTSD patients treated with a novel therapy called mindfulness-based exposure therapy (<xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>).</p><p>Studies have used functional brain imaging to study neural correlates of MBSR. MBSR has also been associated with changes in brain function and structure in normal individuals (<xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>, <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>). In social anxiety disorder patients, MBSR increased recruitment of posterior (parietal and occipital) cortical attention-related brain regions (<xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>). No studies to date have assessed the effects of standard MBSR on PTSD. Furthermore, no studies have looked specifically at PTSD related to OIF/OEF. This is significant since studies in animals show that early intervention before memories become indelible may have a positive effect on the long-term course of PTSD (<xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>). Understanding neural correlates of successful treatment response could improve understanding of the mechanisms by which successful treatments effects symptom improvement in the brain. This could be useful in guiding the development of new treatments. Brain imaging of neural correlates of response also provides an objective, quantifiable measure of treatment response that may be related to changes in the core pathophysiology.</p><p>The purpose of this study was to assess the efficacy of MBSR in the treatment of PTSD and the effects of MBSR on brain function in returning veterans with PTSD from deployment to combat in Iraq and Afghanistan. PTSD patients were randomized to 8&#x02009;weeks of MBSR training or a control group that received 8&#x02009;weeks of PCGT. PCGT involves weekly group sessions with a therapist that emphasize problem solving, being in the here and now, and health education. It was selected to control for the non-specific effects of attending weekly group sessions with other veterans with PTSD and participating in a treatment program. Subjects were assessed before and after treatment with brain imaging during exposure to neutral and combat-trauma-related slides and sounds. Brain imaging was performed with high-resolution positron-emission tomography (HR-PET) which is minimally invasive (requires insertion of an intravenous catheter) but offers superior anatomical resolution, a closer approximation to actual brain blood flow, and improved ease of presentation of visual and auditory materials compared to other imaging techniques such as fMRI. We hypothesized that MBSR (but not PCGT) would result in increased medial prefrontal and parietal cortex function and decreased insula and precuneus function with exposure to trauma-related stimuli.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2-1"><title>Participants</title><p>Participants were male veterans aged 18&#x02013;65&#x02009;years returning from a combat deployment in Iraq or Afghanistan as part of OEF and OIF-OEF/OIF. All veterans had returned from deployment in the past year, had not been treated with psychotropic medications in the previous 4&#x02009;weeks, and had the diagnosis of combat-related PTSD. All participants were recruited through fliers and public bulletins distributed within the community and the Mental Health Assessment Team at the Atlanta VA Medical Center. This study was approved by the Investigational Review Board of Emory University, and all enrolled subjects provided written informed consent. All participants spoke fluent English and had at least an eighth grade reading ability. Participants were considered ineligible if they had experienced significant head trauma or loss of consciousness for at least 2&#x02009;min, or if they reported significant medical histories, current alcohol or substance abuse, or psychotic illness as identified by DSM-IV criteria in the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV (SCID), or the diagnosis of PTSD preceding military service (<xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>).</p><p>A total of 26 PTSD patients were found to be eligible and were randomly assigned in blocks to MBSR therapy (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) and the control treatment, PCGT (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). Nine subjects completed the MBSR group and eight the PCGT group as well as the other study procedures. Before attending the first class, three MBSR subjects dropped out because of lack of interest, and five because of lack of transportation and work-related issues. One member of the PCGT moved out of town before attending the first PCGT group. There were no differences in age, race, or years of education between the two groups (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic factors in patients with post-traumatic stress disorder related to Operation Enduring Freedom/Operation Iraqi Freedom combat randomized to mindfulness based stress reduction (MBSR) and present-centered group therapy (PCGT).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBSR (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9)</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCGT (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (7 SD)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (10 SD)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 White, 4 African-American</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 White, 3 African-American</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years of education</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (2)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S2-2"><title>Treatment</title><p>All enrolled participants were randomized (by an outside researcher) by block to 8&#x02009;weeks of treatment with MBSR or PCGT. The 8-week, 9-session MBSR intervention provides systematic and intensive training in mindfulness through formal meditation and mindful hatha yoga exercises, as well as application of their principles to everyday life and the range of challenges arising from real-life stressors and chronic diseases. In this way, participants were supported in becoming more aware of their internal resources and in acquiring skills that could be flexibly applied to cope more effectively with stress and PTSD symptoms. This range of self-regulatory skills were aimed at increasing relaxation and proprioceptive awareness, as well as awareness of the mind/body experiences related to their PTSD-related emotions and thoughts, overall sense of self, and self-in-relationship. Groups met for eight weekly, 2 1/2&#x02009;h sessions and an all-day (6&#x02009;h) session during week 6. The MBSR expert on the study team (JC) tailored the MBSR teaching materials to veterans, using metaphors that they could relate to, such as using analogies of attending to one&#x02019;s breathing to training in sniper fire.</p><p>Formal mindfulness training was through: (a) body scan meditation, a gradual moving of attention through the body from feet to head accompanied by awareness of breathing and other bodily sensations while lying in a supine position, (b) sitting meditation, focusing on the awareness of breathing, bodily sensations, thoughts, and emotions, practiced sitting upright on a chair or cushion, and (c) mindful hatha yoga, stretching, and strengthening exercises practiced with awareness of breathing and intended to develop awareness (mindfulness) during movement. Participants were given two guided meditation CDs to be practiced at home for 30&#x02009;min, 6&#x02009;days/week. Subjects were assessed to determine the degree to which they followed homework assignments. In-class didactic material emphasized the systematic development of mindfulness awareness and its application in everyday life. Additional discussion focused on the psychology and physiology of stress reactivity and suggestions for the application of mindfulness as a method for responding positively to stress.</p><p>Mindfulness-based stress reduction instructors were trained by the Center for Mindfulness at the University of Massachusetts. All instructors and therapists did not participate in the research assessments. MBSR instructors were supervised by a research psychologist with expertise in MBSR (JC). Recordings were made of sessions which were reviewed by the supervisor to ensure adherence to treatment integrity.</p><p>In this study, PCGT was used as a control for the non-specific effects of a group-based intervention. PCGT was initially developed for use as a control group in a VA multisite study that tested the effects of trauma-focused group therapy in veterans with combat-related PTSD (no difference between the two groups was found for the treatment of PTSD) (<xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>). The primary elements of PCGT include expectations of symptom reduction, normalization of PTSD symptoms though education, decreasing isolation, the opportunity to both give and receive support, and have positive experiences with others who also suffer from similar symptoms. PCGT also offers an atmosphere of safety and support where subjects can have an increased awareness of how PT SD affects their daily lives and those of other group members, and can gain more perspective and objectivity about the effects of PTSD on their lives. PCGT emphasized a &#x0201c;here-and-now&#x0201d; focus that avoided discussion of the trauma, as done in exposure therapy and cognitive restructuring. PCGT groups were conducted for the same number of hours as the MBSR groups. The initial phase of PCGT treatment was psycho-educational. After this phase, the primary content of PCGT was discussion of everyday problems of group members and coming to a better understanding of how PTSD creates or intensifies these problems. At the end of the program, there was a barbecue to balance the mindful retreat of the active group.</p></sec><sec id="S2-3"><title>Measures</title><p>The CAPS was used to assess PTSD symptoms at baseline and in response to treatment. The CAPS is a psychometrically sound measure that assesses presence and severity of PTSD (both lifetime and current PTSD) and can be used to assess changes in PTSD symptoms with treatment (<xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>). The CAPS includes indices measuring reexperiencing, avoidance and numbing, and hyperarousal symptoms. The CAPS has a coefficient alpha of 0.94, test&#x02013;retest reliability of 0.9&#x02013;0.98, a sensitivity of 0.91, and specificity of 0.86 for diagnosis of PTSD, and good convergent and divergent validity (<xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>, <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>).</p><p>Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV (with PTSD module) was used to establish psychiatric diagnosis. The PTSD module of the SCID has been shown to have a kappa of 0.93 for test&#x02013;retest reliability, and excellent sensitivity (0.81) and specificity (0.98) against a composite PTSD diagnosis (<xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>).</p><p>Mindfulness was assessed with the Five Factor Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ), a validated measure of the capacity for mindfulness (<xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>). This instrument was derived from a factor analysis of questionnaires measuring a trait-like general tendency to be mindful in daily life. It consists of 39 items assessing five facets of mindfulness: observing, describing, acting with awareness, non-judging of inner experience, and non-reactivity to inner experience. Items are rated on a Likert scale ranging from 1 (never or very rarely true) to 5 (very often or always true). The FFMQ has been shown to have good internal consistency and significant relationships in the predicted directions with a variety of constructs related to mindfulness (<xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>, <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>).</p><p>Mindful spirituality was assessed with the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Spiritual Well-Being Scale (FACIT-Sp), a valid and reliable 12-item scale designed to measure spiritual well-being independent of religious beliefs (<xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>). It has been adapted for use with non-medical populations and comprises two subscales: Meaning and Peace (8 items) and Faith (4 items) (<xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>). The FACIT-Sp (<xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>) is part of the FACIT battery (<xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>) to assess QOL associated with chronic illness.</p></sec><sec id="S2-4"><title>PET Procedures</title><p>High-resolution positron-emission tomography scanning was conducted using methods previously described (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>). HR-PET imaging of the brain was performed with the high-resolution research tomograph (CTI, Knoxville, TN, USA) (&#x0003c;2&#x02009;mm resolution) (<xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>, <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>). Subjects were scanned during exposure to traumatic (Iraqi combat) slides, and sounds, and neutral slides and sounds using methods previously described (<xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>). Subjects underwent four scans in conjunction with injection of radiolabeled water: two successive scans while watching neutral slides and sounds, followed by two scans while viewing combat-related slides and sounds. Content of the slides was matched between combat and neutral for sound and content, e.g., scenes involving persons and buildings in Iraq with loud noises were matched with a city scene with buildings and persons and city traffic noises. Radiolabeled water (H<sub>2</sub>[<sup>15</sup>O]) was prepared on-site in a cyclotron. During the hours of the test, subjects reclined in bed except to use the bathroom. An intravenous infusion of normal saline was started by a technologist to permit the bolus injection of radiolabeled water. Subjects were scanned with eyes open in a dimly lit room. Subjects were placed in the scanner with the head held in a head holder, and the head was positioned with the canthomeatal line parallel to the external laser light. Following positioning within the camera gantry, a transmission scan of the head was obtained. Subjects received a 20&#x02009;mCi intravenous bolus of radiolabeled water for each of the scans. Subjects were scanned twice during exposure to neutral slides and sounds (city scenes with people, buildings, city sounds, people talking, birds tweeting), and twice during exposure to Iraq combat scenes and sounds. Each scan lasted 60&#x02009;s, with the PET scan acquisition beginning at the initiation of the condition.</p></sec><sec id="S2-5"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Post-traumatic stress disorder symptoms as measured with the CAPS were compared before and after intervention with MBSR or PCGT using one-tailed <italic>t</italic>-tests with significance defined as <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. HR-PET images were reconstructed and analyzed using Statistical Parametric Mapping software (SPM8) (<xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>, <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>). Regions of interest were identified within hypothesized brain regions (mPFC, parietal cortex, insula, precuneus) using standard stereotactic coordinates (<xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>). Images were realigned to the first scan of the study session. The mean concentration of radioactivity in each scan was obtained as an area-weighted sum of the concentration of each slice, and was adjusted to a nominal value of 50&#x02009;ml/min per 100&#x02009;g. The data underwent transformation into a common anatomical space and were smoothed with a three-dimensional Gaussian filter to 8-mm FWHM. Regional blood flow was compared for traumatic minus neutral slides, and sounds conditions. Statistical analyses yielded image data sets in which the values assigned to individual voxels correspond to the <italic>t</italic> statistic. Statistical images were displayed with values of <italic>z</italic> score units. Location of areas of activation was identified as the distance from the anterior commissure in millimeters, with <italic>x, y</italic>, and <italic>z</italic> coordinates; a standard stereotaxic (Talairach) atlas was used (<xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>). A threshold <italic>z</italic> score of 2.67 (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005, uncorrected) and a minimal cluster of 11 voxels was used to examine areas of activation within hypothesized areas (medial prefrontal and parietal cortex, precuneus, insula) (<xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>, <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>, <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>). This level of significance has been shown to optimize the reduction of risk of both Type 1 and Type 2 errors (<xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>, <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>). Activations in non-hypothesized regions meeting this statistical threshold were also presented for the purpose of hypothesis generation for future studies.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><p>There were no differences in demographic variables between PTSD patients randomized to either MBSR or PCGT (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Eight weeks of MBSR therapy (but not PCGT) resulted in significant reductions in PTSD symptoms (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). These effects persisted 6&#x02009;months after the ends of treatment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The greatest reductions in symptoms were seen in the CAPS hyperarousal symptom cluster in the MBSR group [31 (14 SD) baseline versus 16 (11 SD)] (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.006) although significant changes were seen in the avoidance (but not intrusion) cluster as well. MBSR also resulted in an increase in mindfulness as measured by the FFMQ (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) as well as a non-statistically significant increase of 23% in spiritual mindfulness as measured by the FACIT-Sp (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.06; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Increases were equally seen in the Faith and Meaning/Purpose Subscales.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effects of 8&#x02009;weeks of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR), or present-centered group therapy (PCGT) on symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) as measured with the Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS). There was a significant reduction in PTSD symptoms immediately posttreatment in the MBSR group (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), but not in the PCGT group. These effects persisted at the 6-month follow-up period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-08-00157-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of MBSR and PCGT on symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder and measures of mindfulness and spirituality.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measure</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-MBSR</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-MBSR</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-PCGT</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-PCGT</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-Value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn1">*</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS-I</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS-Av</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (9 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (7 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (6 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS-Ar</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (14 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (11 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (6 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (8 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS-TOTAL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (29 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (20 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (14 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (15 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFMQ</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (11 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (22 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (19 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (23 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FACIT-Sp</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (18 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (21 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (16 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (18 SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>CAPS-I, CAPS-Intrusions Subscale; CAPS-Av, CAPS-Avoidance Subscale; CAPS-Ar, CAPS-Arousal Subscale; CAPS-TOTAL, CAPS total score; FFMQ, Five Factor Mindfulness Scale; FACIT-Sp, Functional Assessment of Cancer Illness Therapy-Spirituality Subscale; PCGT, present-centered group therapy; MBSR, mindfulness-based stress reduction</italic>.</p><fn id="tfn1"><p><italic>*p-Value for difference between outcome before and after MBSR therapy</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Exposure to combat-related slides, and sounds resulted in increased activation in multiple frontal, and temporal cortical brain regions in both the MBSR and PCGT-treated groups (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). Both groups showed additionally decreased activation in subcortical areas, insula, and cerebellum. PTSD patients treated with MBSR also showed a differential brain response to combat-trauma-related slides, and sounds when compared to the PCGT group, with an increased activation in the right anterior cingulate, and right inferior parietal lobule (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">7</xref>), and decreased activation in the right insula and precuneus (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">8</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Areas of increased activation for traumatic slides and sounds after present-centered group therapy treatment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Talairach coordinates<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> Score</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voxel number</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain region</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann&#x02019;s area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.68</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. orbital gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilateral cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. caudate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. putamen</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;53</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;72</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>z&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.68, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Areas of decreased activations for traumatic slide and sounds after present-centered group therapy treatment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Talairach coordinates<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> Score</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voxel number</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain region</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann&#x02019;s area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.93</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. postcentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. postcentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. putamen</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. putamen</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. caudate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. claustrum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. claustrum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. thalamus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. thalamus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. insula</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilateral precuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;90</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;60</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;68</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;73</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;65</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;53</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>z&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.68, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Areas of increased activation for traumatic slides and sounds after mindfulness-based stress reduction treatment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Talairach coordinates<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> Score</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voxel number</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain region</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann&#x02019;s area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilateral superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.84</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. inferior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.91</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. postcentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. postcentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. orbital gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. posterior cingulate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;41</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. anterior cingulate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. thalamus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. thalamus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. lateral globus pallidus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. claustrum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. uncus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;23</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;53</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;71</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. uncus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;53</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. superior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;66</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;60</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;70</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;64</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;40</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;23</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>z&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.68, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Areas of decreased activation for traumatic slides and sounds after mindfulness-based stress reduction treatment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Talairach coordinates<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> Score</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voxel number</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain region</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann&#x02019;s area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. transverse temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. postcentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. transverse temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. insula</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. insula</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. insula</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. claustrum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. insula</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. claustrum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. claustrum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. caudate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;97</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. lingual gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;73</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;30</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. medulla</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>z&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.68, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Areas of increased activation when viewing traumatic pictures, and sounds vs. neutral pictures and sounds, Mindfulness-based stress reduction&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;traditional supportive therapy. Increased activations in anterior cingulate, and subcallosal gyrus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-08-00157-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="T7" position="float"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Areas of increased activation for traumatic slides and sounds in mindfulness-based stress reduction greater than present-centered group therapy.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Talairach coordinates<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> Score</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voxel number</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain region</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann&#x02019;s area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cingulate gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. lateral globus pallidus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. claustrum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. subthalamic nucleus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;53</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;68</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.68</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;57</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;68</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cerebellum</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. pons</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>z&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.68, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T8" position="float"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Areas of decreased activation for traumatic slides and sounds in mindfulness-based stress reduction greater than present-centered group therapy.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Talairach coordinates<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> Score</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voxel number</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>x</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>y</italic></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain region</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann&#x02019;s area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1669</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1252</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. transverse temporal gyrus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8132</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. insula</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1287</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R. cuneus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>z&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;2.68, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Patients with PTSD related to Iraq combat treated with MBSR in this study had a decrease in PTSD symptoms as measured with the CAPS not seen in PTSD patients treated with the control condition, PCGT. PTSD patients treated with MBSR also showed a differential brain response to combat-trauma-related slides, and sounds when compared to the PCGT group, with an increased activation in the right anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) and right inferior parietal lobule, and decreased activation in the right insula, and precuneus. MBSR resulted in an increase in mindfulness as measured with the FFMQ. Results from a measure of spirituality showed a 23% improvement that was not statistically significant.</p><p>Mindfulness-based stress reduction was well tolerated in this sample of veterans with PTSD. Although there are several reports of the use of treatments similar to MBSR now in the literature, at the time of this study there was little experience with MBSR in traumatized populations. MBSR in this sample of PTSD patients did not lead to flooding of traumatic memories, dissociation, or other negative consequences. Additionally, MBSR treatment had a robust effect on PTSD symptoms, leading to reductions that maintained for 6&#x02009;months after the end of the classes. This is consistent with sustained (12&#x02009;months) improvements in distress found in an RCT comparing MBSR to an educational control program (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). It was also superior to PCGT, which has been shown to have some efficacy in and of itself, showing equal efficacy to Cognitive-Behavioral Group Therapy (CBGT) in a prior multisite trial in veterans (<xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>).</p><p>This study suggests that treatment with MBSR results in increased function in the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) region within the mPFC. Prior studies from our group, and others have implicated this area in the pathophysiology of PTSD (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Additionally, we previously found that successful treatment with the selective serotonin reuptake, paroxetine, in PTSD patients resulted in an increase in function in this area in response to trauma-related scripts of the patients&#x02019; personal individual traumas (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>). Activation was also seen in this area with placebo, although to a lesser degree than with paroxetine (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>). In contrast, there were no activations in this area with the PCGT control treatment in the current study.</p><p>The ACC plays an important role in emotion, and regulation of the fear response (<xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>, <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>). It has connections to limbic areas that mediate threat response and extinction of conditioned fear responses that are characteristic of PTSD (<xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>) as well as with the insula in the regulation of peripheral autonomic and neurohormonal responses to stress (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>, <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>, <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>). Exposure to traumatic reminders has been shown in a number of studies of PTSD patients to result in a blunted ACC activation (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>, <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>). Training with MBSR may enhance the ability of the ACC to inhibit fear responses that occur in response to traumatic reminders. Indeed, uncontrolled fear responses to traumatic reminders are a paradigmatic facet of the disorder of PTSD (<xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>).</p><p>Mindfulness-based stress reduction also resulted in an increase in function in the inferior parietal lobule. This brain area plays an important role in the perception of the self in time and space, perception of contextual cues, and visuospatial memory (<xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>), in addition to modulation of peripheral cardiovascular responses to stress (<xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>). Prior studies also implicated this region in PTSD (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). Increased function in this area with MBSR training may be indicative of an enhancement of the ability to successfully respond to threat.</p><p>Mindfulness-based stress reduction also resulted in a decrease in function in the insula and precuneus. The precuneus has important connections with the parietal cortex and is involved in memory, which is an important part of the stress response (<xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>, <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>). Prior studies in PTSD have implicated dysfunction of a network that includes precuneus, anterior cingulate, and insula (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>).</p><p>The insula is an important portal to peripheral responses to stress, including cardiovascular responses such as heart rate and blood pressure, respiratory function like increased respirations, and other functions important to survival under stress (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>). It also has important connections to brain areas involved in the stress response (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>), and altered function and structure in this region has been linked to PTSD (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>, <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>).</p><p>Decreased function with MBSR may represent a decrease in peripheral stress response to traumatic reminders.</p><p>Changes in brain function with MBSR appeared to be localized to the right side of the brain. The right side of the brain is more involved in emotion, while the left side in logical thought (<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>, <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>, <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>). Although suggestive that MBSR facilitates emotion-related brain areas, this finding needs to be replicated.</p><p>There are several limitations of this study that should be noted. Our findings are in patients with OIF/OEF combat-related PTSD and cannot necessarily be generalized to other PTSD patient populations. The sample size is small, which limited the statistical analyses, and therefore this should be considered a pilot study. Due to the small sample size, we were not able to adjust for potentially confounding factors such as differences in PTSD symptom severity. These pilot findings need to be replicated in larger, controlled studies. This is the first study, however, to use brain imaging in the assessment of the effects of MBSR in PTSD, and should generate useful hypotheses for future studies with larger sample sizes.</p><p>In summary, we found that MBSR results in an improvement in PTSD symptoms, an increase in mindfulness that could be associated with an improvement in spiritual well-being, and a pattern of brain activation to traumatic reminders that included increased function in anterior cingulate, and inferior parietal lobe, and decreased function in insula and precuneus. These brain areas are involved in stress, and the fear response. The findings suggest that MBSR leads to a change in brain function that is associated with a decrease in activation of fear, and stress responses in PTSD patients.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>This study was approved by the Investigational Review Board of Emory University, and all enrolled subjects provided written informed consent.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors designed the study, obtained funding, supervised and trained teachers, monitored treatment fidelity, and contributed to the editing of the paper.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was supported by a grant from the VA Merit Review MIND/HEAL Program and NIH research grants to JB R01 HL088726, K24 MH076955, T32 MH067547-01, R01 MH56120, S10 RR016917, and NIH grants to LVV K24 HL077506, R01 AG026255, R01 HL068630, and R21 HL093665 and the clinical interactions network (CIN) of the Atlanta Clinical and Translational Sciences Institute (ACTSI). We wish to acknowledge Delicia Votaw, C.N.M.T., and Margie Jones, C.N.M.T., for their assistance with imaging and analysis procedures, Lai Reed, M.B.A., for program management, Sandi DiVitale, B.A., for research assistance, and Kay Coker, M.S.W., and Amanda Lorenz, Ph.D., for teaching of MBSR and PCGT classes.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnega</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bromet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder in the National Comorbidity Survey</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>52</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1048</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1995.03950240066012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7492257?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7492257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>. <source>The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5)</source>. <edition>5th ed</edition>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>McGurk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotting</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Koffman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Combat duty in Iraq and Afghanistan, mental health problems, and barriers to care</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>351</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa040603</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15229303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15229303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Auchterlonie</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Milliken</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mental health problems, use of mental health services, and attrition from military service after returning from deployment to Iraq or Afghanistan</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Assoc</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>295</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.295.9.1023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Terhakopian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Messer</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of posttraumatic stress disorder with somatic symptoms, health care visits, and absenteeism among Iraq war veterans</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>164</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.164.1.150</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17202557?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17202557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Riviere</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>McGurk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of mental health problems and functional impairment among active component and National Guard soldiers 3 and 12 months following combat in Iraq</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>614</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.54</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20530011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20530011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoge</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stigma, barriers to care, and use of mental health services among active duty and National Guard soldiers after combat</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>61</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.61.6.582</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20513681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20513681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pharmacotherapy for PTSD: Effects on PTSD symptoms and the brain</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder: From Neurobiology to Treatment</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name> (<year>2016</year>). p. <fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlin</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruzek</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Chard</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eftekhari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Monson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hembree</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Dissemination of evidence-based psychological treatments for posttraumatic stress disorder in the Veterans Health Administration</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Stress</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.20588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21171126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnurr</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Foa</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cognitive behavioral therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder in women</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Assoc</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>297</volume>:<fpage>820</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.297.24.2695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Varker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A multisite randomized controlled effectiveness trial of cognitive processing therapy for military-related posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>J Anxiety Disord</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>442</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2012.01.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22366446?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuerk</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grubaugh</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Myrick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Acierno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prolonged exposure therapy for combat-related posttraumatic stress disorder: an examination of treatment effectiveness for veterans of the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq</article-title>. <source>J Anxiety Disord</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2010.11.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21131170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21131170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eftekhari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruzek</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlin</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of national implementation of prolonged exposure therapy in Veterans Affairs care</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>70</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2013.36</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23863892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23863892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An outpatient program in behavioral medicine for chronic pain patients based on the practice of mindfulness meditation: theoretical considerations and preliminary results</article-title>. <source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source> (<year>1982</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0163-8343(82)90026-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7042457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7042457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipworth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Burney</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Four-year follow-up of a meditation-based program for the self-regulation of chronic pain: treatment outcomes and compliance</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source> (<year>1987</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002508-198602030-00004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxe</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarzobski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Can diet, in conjunction with stress reduction, affect the rate of increase in prostate specific antigen after biochemical recurrence of prostate cancer?</article-title>
<source>J Urol</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>166</volume>:<fpage>2202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005392-200112000-00041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11696736?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11696736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Three-year follow-up and clinical implications of a mindfulness-based stress reduction intervention in the treatment of anxiety disorders</article-title>. <source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>192</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0163-8343(95)00025-M</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7649463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Niemann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Walach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction and health benefits: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Psychosom Res</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(03)00573-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15256293?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15256293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miake-Lye</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beroes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<source>Evidence Map of Mindfulness</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>West Los Angeles VA Medical Center</publisher-name> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teasdale</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Metacognition, mindfulness and the modification of mood disorders</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol Psychother</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1099-0879(199905)6:2&#x0003c;146::AID-CPP195&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-E</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teasdale</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>ZV</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JMG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridgeway</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soulsby</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevention of relapse/recurrence in major depression by mindfulness-based cognitive therapy</article-title>. <source>J Consult Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-006X.68.4.615</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10965637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10965637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nature and autonomy: an organizational view of social and neurobiological aspects of self-regulation in behavior and development</article-title>. <source>Dev Psychopathol</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0954579497001405</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9449002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9449002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>PLG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Meditation and attention: a comparison of the effects of concentrative and mindfulness meditation on sustained attention</article-title>. <source>Ment Health Relig Cult</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13674679908406332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heatherton</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tice</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Losing Control: How and Why People Fail at Self-regulation</source>. <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>1994</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness training as a clinical intervention: a conceptual and empirical review</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol Sci Pract</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roemer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Orsillo</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Expanding our conceptualization of and treatment for generalized anxiety disorder: integrating mindfulness/acceptance-based approaches with existing cognitive-behavioral models</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol (New York)</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linehan</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Cognitive-Behavioral Treatment of Borderline Personality Disorder</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name> (<year>1993</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness: a proposed operational definition</article-title>. <source>Clin Psychol (New York)</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trauma-informed mindfulness-based stress reduction for female survivors of interpersonal violence: results from a stage I RCT</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>72</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.22273</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27002222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27002222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipworth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Burney</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The clinical use of mindfulness meditation for the self-regulation of chronic pain</article-title>. <source>J Behav Med</source> (<year>1985</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00845519</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3897551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3897551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braden</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipe</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaspy</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Deatherage</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Brain and behavior changes associated with an abbreviated 4-week mindfulness-based stress reduction course in back pain patients</article-title>. <source>Brain Behav</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e00443</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/brb3.443</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26925304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26925304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmoirago-Blotcher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Olendzki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness training for coping with hot flashes: results of a randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Menopause</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/gme.0b013e318204a05c</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pbert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Madison</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Druker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Olendzki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Magner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of mindfulness training on asthma quality of life and lung function: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>67</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2011-200253</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22544892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Angen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A randomized, wait-list controlled clinical trial: the effect of a mindfulness-based stress reduction program on mood and symptoms of stress in cancer outpatients</article-title>. <source>Psychosom Med</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006842-200009000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11020090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massion</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Teas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wertheimer</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meditation, melatonin and breast/prostate cancer: Hypothesis and preliminary data</article-title>. <source>Med Hypotheses</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0306-9877(95)90299-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7776900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7776900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reibel</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Greeson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction and health-related quality of life in a heterogeneous patient population</article-title>. <source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0163-8343(01)00149-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11543844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11543844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristeller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mindfulness, spirituality, and health-related symptoms</article-title>. <source>J Psychosom Res</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>64</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2007.06.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18374738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relationships between mindfulness practice and levels of mindfulness, medical and psychological symptoms and well-being in a mindfulness-based stress reduction program</article-title>. <source>J Behav Med</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10865-007-9130-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17899351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17899351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weissbecker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Studts</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dedert</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sephton</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction and sense of coherence among women with fibromyalgia</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol Med Settings</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1020786917988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Light</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Skillings</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cropley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Influence of a mindfulness-based stress reduction intervention on rates of skin clearing in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis undergoing phototherapy (UVB) and photo chemotherapy (PUVA)</article-title>. <source>Psychosom Med</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006842-199809000-00020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9773769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabat-Zinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Massion</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristeller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pbert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effectiveness of a meditation-based stress reduction program in the treatment of anxiety disorders</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>149</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>936</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.149.7.936</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1609875?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1609875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koszycki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavounza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Daoust</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Taljaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradwejn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preliminary investigation of a mindfulness-based intervention for social anxiety disorder that integrates compassion meditation and mindful exposure</article-title>. <source>J Altern Complement Med</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/acm.2015.0108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27070853?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27070853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polusny</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbes</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thuras</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamberty</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction for posttraumatic stress disorder among veterans: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>314</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.8361</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26241597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26241597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lykins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Olendzki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An empirical study of the mechanisms of mindfulness in a mindfulness-based stress reduction program</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.20579</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19267330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19267330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvin-Nadeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of a meditation-based stress reduction program on fibromyalgia</article-title>. <source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0163-8343(93)90020-O</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8307341?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8307341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reibel</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Greeson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hojat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction lowers psychological distress in medical students</article-title>. <source>Teach Learn Med</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15328015TLM1502_03</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12708065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12708065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolar</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reger</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of a wellness-based mindfulness stress reduction intervention: a controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Health Promot</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4278/0890-1171-15.6.422</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11523499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11523499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ursuliak</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Angen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Speca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of a mindfulness meditation-based stress reduction program on mood and symptoms of stress in cancer outpatients: 6-month follow-up</article-title>. <source>Support Care Cancer</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s005200000206</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11305069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11305069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Astin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stress reduction through mindfulness meditation: effects on psychological symptomatology, sense of control, and spiritual experiences</article-title>. <source>Psychother Psychosom</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000289116</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9097338?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9097338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bootzin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueredo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Braden</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Quality of life and breast cancer: Relationship to psychosocial variables</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.1026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11255204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11255204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Boggs</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigue</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Urry</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Algina</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Stage II breast cancer: differences between four coping patterns in side effects during adjuvant chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>J Psychosom Res</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(97)80001-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9278904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9278904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teasdale</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JMG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>How does cognitive therapy prevent depressive relapse and why should attentional control (mindfulness) training help?</article-title>
<source>Behav Res Ther</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0005-7967(94)E0011-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7872934?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7872934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodeur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A controlled study of a stress-reduction, cognitive-behavioral treatment program in fibromyalgia</article-title>. <source>J Musculoskelet Pain</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1300/J094v02n02_05</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tacon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>McComb</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldera</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mindfulness meditation, anxiety reduction, and heart disease: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Fam Community Health</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003727-200301000-00004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12802125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12802125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fjorback</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Arendt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d8;rnb&#x000f8;l</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Walach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction and mindfulness-based cognitive therapy &#x02013; a systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>124</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0447.2011.01704.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21534932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evolving conceptions of mindfulness in clinical settings</article-title>. <source>J Cognit Psychother</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>270</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1891/0889-8391.23.3.270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Changes in mindfulness and posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms among veterans enrolled in mindfulness-based stress reduction</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.22323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27152480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Malte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of participation in a mindfulness program for veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder: a randomized controlled pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>69</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.21911</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22930491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Malte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of participation in a mindfulness program with measures of PTSD, depression and quality of life in a veteran sample</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.20853</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22125187?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22125187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimbrough</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Magyari</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chesney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness intervention for child abuse survivors</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>66</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.20624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19998425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Possemato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergen-Cico</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Treatman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pigeon</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A randomized clinical trial of primary care brief mindfulness training for veterans with PTSD</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>72</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.22241</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26613203?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26613203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giardino</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Favorite</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A pilot study of group mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) for combat veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD)</article-title>. <source>Depress Anxiety</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>638</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.22104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23596092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campanella</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neuroimaging of PTSD</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder: From Neurobiology to Treatment</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name> (<year>2016</year>). p. <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Amygdala, medial prefrontal cortex, and hippocampal function in PTSD</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>1071</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1196/annals.1364.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16891563?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16891563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Correll</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment options for individuals with PTSD and concurrent TBI: a literature review and case presentation</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychiatry Rep</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-016-0699-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27222137?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27222137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Campanella</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of psychotherapy for psychological trauma on PTSD symptoms and the brain</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder: From Neurobiology to Treatment</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name> (<year>2016</year>). p. <fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thayer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Claude Bernard and the heart-brain connection: further elaboration of a model of neurovisceral integration</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2008.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18771686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selemon</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman-Rakic</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Common cortical and subcortical targets of the dorsolateral prefrontal and posterior parietal cortices in the rhesus monkey: evidence for a distributed neural network subserving spatially guided behavior</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> (<year>1988</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>4049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 2846794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2846794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoshide</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kario</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The insular cortex and cardiovascular system: a new insight into the brain-heart axis</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Hypertens</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jash.2010.05.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20655502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20655502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Insular cortex and neuropsychiatric disorders: a review of recent literature</article-title>. <source>Eur Psychiatry</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eurpsy.2007.02.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17416488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Innis</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Staib</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>PET measurement of cerebral metabolic correlates of yohimbine administration in posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1997.01830150070011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9075465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberzon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Martis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neuroimaging studies of emotional responses in PTSD</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>1071</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1196/annals.1364.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16891565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16891565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindauer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Booij</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Habraken</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Uylings</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Olff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cerebral blood flow changes during script-driven imagery in police officers with posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>56</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.08.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15576062?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15576062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Staib</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>McGlashan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neural correlates of memories of childhood sexual abuse in women with and without posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>156</volume>:<fpage>1787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 10553744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10553744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanius</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boksman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Recall of emotional states in posttraumatic stress disorder: an fMRI investigation</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(02)01466-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12559652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fig</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberzon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Corticolimbic blood flow in posttraumatic stress disorder during script-driven imagery</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>57</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>832</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.12.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15820703?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15820703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosslyn</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Regional cerebral blood flow during script-driven imagery in childhood sexual abuse-related PTSD: A PET investigation</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>156</volume>:<fpage>575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 10200737?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10200737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Macklin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasko</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Regional cerebral blood flow in the amygdala and medial prefrontal cortex during traumatic imagery in male and female Vietnam veterans with PTSD</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>61</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.61.2.168</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14757593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Rooij</surname><given-names>SJH</given-names></name><name><surname>Geuze</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rademaker</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neural correlates of inhibition and contextual cue processing related to treatment response in PTSD</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2014.220</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25154707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25154707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moores</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Puce</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Abnormal recruitment of working memory updating networks during maintenance of trauma-neutral information in post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>163</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pscychresns.2007.08.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18455372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18455372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geuze</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermetten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>de Kloet</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Westenberg</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Precuneal activity during encoding in veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Prog Brain Res</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>167</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0079-6123(07)67026-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18037028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18037028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Paige</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasko</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>PTSD arousal and depression symptoms associated with increased right-sided parietal EEG asymmetry</article-title>. <source>J Abnorm Psychol</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>113</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-843X.113.2.324</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15122952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15122952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Staib</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaloupek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soufer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neural correlates of exposure to traumatic pictures and sound in Vietnam combat veterans with and without posttraumatic stress disorder: a positron emission tomography study</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>806</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(98)00297-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10202567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10202567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teicher</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Polcari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Childhood maltreatment: altered network centrality of cingulate, precuneus, temporal pole and insula</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>76</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2013.09.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24209775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24209775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapru</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frewen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>RWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000e9;berge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Unique insula subregion resting-state functional connectivity with amygdala complexes in posttraumatic stress disorder and its dissociative subtype</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>250</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pscychresns.2016.02.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27042977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27042977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanius</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frewen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tursich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetly</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinnon</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Restoring large-scale brain networks in PTSD and related disorders: a proposal for neuroscientifically-informed treatment interventions</article-title>. <source>Eur J Psychotraumatol</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>27313</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ejpt.v6.27313</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25854674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25854674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheline</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Altered emotional interference processing in the amygdala and insula in women with post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage Clin</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2012.11.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Frewen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Kolk</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanius</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neural correlates of reexperiencing, avoidance, and dissociation in PTSD: Symptom dimensions and emotion dysregulation in responses to script-driven trauma imagery</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Stress</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.20284</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17955540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17955540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osuch</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Geraci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Podell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Herscovitch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Regional cerebral blood flow correlated with flashback intensity in patients with posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(01)01107-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11522258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11522258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whalley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroes</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugg</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An fMRI investigation of posttraumatic flashbacks</article-title>. <source>Brain Cogn</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>81</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bandc.2012.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23207576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Seibyl</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MRI-based measurement of hippocampal volume in patients with combat-related posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>152</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>973</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.152.7.973</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7793467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7793467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermetten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Staib</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bronen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazure</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MRI-based measurement of hippocampal volume in posttraumatic stress disorder related to childhood physical and sexual abuse: a preliminary report</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(96)00162-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8988792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neuroanatomical substrates of late-life mental disorders</article-title>. <source>J Geriatr Psychiatry Neurol</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/089198879901200303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10593698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jawed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitayama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Increased neural response to trauma scripts in posttraumatic stress disorder following paroxetine treatment: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>491</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2011.01.037</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21256927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21256927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vermetten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vythilingam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term treatment with paroxetine increases verbal declarative memory and hippocampal volume in posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>54</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(03)00634-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14512209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mletzko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Welter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brummer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of phenytoin on memory, cognition and brain structure in posttraumatic stress disorder: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269881105048996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bossini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavanti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calossi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Polizzotto</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Changes in hippocampal volume in patients with post-traumatic stress disorder after sertraline treatment</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.jcp.0000264979.09862.a8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17414261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><label>98</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pissiota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frans</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>von Knorring</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredrikson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Brain function in a patient with torture related post-traumatic stress disorder before and after fluoxetine treatment: a positron emission tomography provocation study</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>297</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(00)01674-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11121880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><label>99</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seedat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Heerden</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zungu-Dirwayi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Kradenburg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Single photon emission computed tomography in posttraumatic stress disorder before and after treatment with a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>80</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0327(03)00047-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15094257?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15094257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><label>100</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmaso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of EMDR psychotherapy on 99mTc-HMPAO distribution in occupation-related post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Nucl Med Commun</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>28</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MNM.0b013e3282742035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17728604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><label>101</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lansing</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Amen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High-resolution brain SPECT imaging and eye movement desensitization and reprocessing in police officers with PTSD</article-title>. <source>J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/jnp.17.4.526</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16387993?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><label>102</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>JFP</given-names></name><name><surname>Newberg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercante</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Simao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cerebral blood flow changes during retrieval of traumatic memories before and after psychotherapy: a SPECT study</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>37</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S003329170700997X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17288648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17288648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><label>103</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peduto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Changes in anterior cingulate and amygdala after cognitive behavior therapy of posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Psychol Sci</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01860.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17425531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><label>104</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitford</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peduto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Rostral anterior cingulate volume predicts treatment response to cognitive-behavioural therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatry Neurosci</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 18330460?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18330460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B105"><label>105</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peduto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Amygdala and ventral anterior cingulate activation predicts treatment response to cognitive behaviour therapy for post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0033291707002231</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18005496?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18005496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B106"><label>106</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000f6;lzel</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunsch</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction, fear conditioning, and the uncinate fasciculus: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Front Behav Neurosci</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnbeh.2016.00124</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27378875?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27378875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B107"><label>107</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gotink</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijboom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernooij</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunink</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>8-week mindfulness based stress reduction induces brain changes similar to traditional long-term meditation practice &#x02013; a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Brain Cogn</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bandc.2016.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27429096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B108"><label>108</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyklicek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mommersteeg</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Beugen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Boxtel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mindfulness-based stress reduction and physiological activity during acute stress: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0032200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23527521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23527521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B109"><label>109</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sripada</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Giardino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Favorite</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Altered default mode network (DMN) resting state functional connectivity following a mindfulness-based exposure therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in combat veterans of Afghanistan and Iraq</article-title>. <source>Depress Anxiety</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.22481</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27038410?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27038410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B110"><label>110</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotzel</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mindfulness practice leads to increased regional gray matter density</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>30</volume>(<issue>191</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B111"><label>111</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jazaieri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>MBSR vs aerobic exercise in social anxiety: fMRI of emotion regulation of negative self-beliefs</article-title>. <source>Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nss054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22586252?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22586252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B112"><label>112</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanselow</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modality-specific retrograde amnesia of fear</article-title>. <source>Science</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>256</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1585183</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1585183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1585183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B113"><label>113</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>First</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JBW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Press</publisher-name> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B114"><label>114</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnurr</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Foy</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavori</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Randomized trial of trauma-focused group therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.60.5.481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12742869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B115"><label>115</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Weathers</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaloupek</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gusman</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The development of a clinician-administered PTSD scale</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Stress</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.2490080106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7712061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7712061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B116"><label>116</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weathers</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruscio</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Psychometric properties of nine scoring rules for the clinician-administered PTSD Scale</article-title>. <source>Psychol Assess</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1040-3590.11.2.124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B117"><label>117</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>First</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JBW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Structured Clinical Interview for DSMIV-Patient Edition (SCID-P)</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Press</publisher-name> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B118"><label>118</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Krietemeyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Toney</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Using self-report assessment methods to explore facets of mindfulness</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073191105283504</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16443717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B119"><label>119</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lykins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Button</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Krietemeyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Construct validity of the five facet mindfulness questionnaire in meditating and nonmeditating samples</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073191107313003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18310597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B120"><label>120</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristeller</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reliability and validity of the FACT-G spiritual well-being scale in a community cancer population</article-title>. <conf-name>Society of Behavioral Medicine&#x02019;s 21st Annual Meeting [29]</conf-name>
<conf-loc>Nashville, TN</conf-loc> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B121"><label>121</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterman</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitchett</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Measuring spiritual well-being in people with cancer: the functional assessment of chronic illness therapy &#x02013; Spiritual Well-being Scale (FACIT-Sp)</article-title>. <source>Ann Behav Med</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15324796ABM2401_06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12008794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B122"><label>122</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cella</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Manual &#x02013; Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy (FACT) Scales</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Division of Psychosocial Oncology, Rush Cancer Center</publisher-name> (<year>1994</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B123"><label>123</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinhard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Performance evaluation of a new LSO high resolution research tomograph-HRRT</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Med Imaging</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B124"><label>124</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinhard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The ECAT HRRT: performance and first clinical application of the new high resolution research tomograph</article-title>. <conf-name>IEEE Trans Med Imaging (Nuclear Science Symposium Conference Record)</conf-name> (Vol. <volume>3</volume>); <conf-loc>Lyon</conf-loc>: <conf-sponsor>IEEE</conf-sponsor> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B125"><label>125</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Staib</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaloupek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soufer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Positron emission tomographic (PET)-based measurement of cerebral blood flow correlates of traumatic reminders in Vietnam combat veterans with and without posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD)</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>806</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(98)00297-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10202567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B126"><label>126</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Statistical parametric mapping</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Thatcher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeffiro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Functional Neuroimaging: Technical Foundations</source>. <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>1994</year>). p. <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B127"><label>127</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Introduction to Experimental Design and Statistical Parametric Mapping</source> (<year>2004</year>). Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/doc/intro/intro.pdf">http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/doc/intro/intro.pdf</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B128"><label>128</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talairach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tournoux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Co-planar Stereotaxic Atlas of the Human Brain: 3-Dimensional Proportional System, An Approach to Cerebral Imaging</source>. <publisher-loc>Stuttgart, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Georg Thieme</publisher-name> (<year>1988</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B129"><label>129</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Frackowiak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparing functional (PET) images: the assessment of significant change</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>690</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jcbfm.1991.122</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2050758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2050758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B130"><label>130</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Worsley</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frackowiak</surname><given-names>RSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazziotta</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing the significance of focal activations using their spatial extent</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.460010306</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24578041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24578041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B131"><label>131</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neuroanatomical correlates of happiness, sadness, and disgust</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>154</volume>:<fpage>926</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.154.7.926</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9210742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9210742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B132"><label>132</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Neuroanatomical correlates of externally and internally generated human emotion</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>154</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>918</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.154.7.918</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9210741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9210741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B133"><label>133</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional heterogeneity in cingulate cortex: the anterior executive and posterior evaluative regions</article-title>. <source>Cereb Cortex</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/2.6.435</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1477524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1477524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B134"><label>134</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devinsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Contributions of anterior cingulate to behavior</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/118.1.279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7895011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B135"><label>135</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirk</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neurons in medial prefrontal cortex signal memory for fear extinction</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>420</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12422216?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12422216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B136"><label>136</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Napadow</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhond</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Makris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbieri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Brain correlates of autonomic modulation: combining heart rate variability with fMRI</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>42</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.04.238</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18524629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18524629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B137"><label>137</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Kolk</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisler</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A symptom provocation study of posttraumatic stress disorder using positron emission tomography and script-driven imagery</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>380</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1996.01830050014003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8624181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B138"><label>138</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanius</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boksman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Neural correlates of traumatic memories in posttraumatic stress disorder: a functional MRI investigation</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>158</volume>:<fpage>1920</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.158.11.1920</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11691703?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11691703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B139"><label>139</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elzinga</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Are the neural substrates of memory the final common pathway in PTSD?</article-title>
<source>J Affect Disord</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0327(01)00351-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12113915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B140"><label>140</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintun</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raichle</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Positron emission tomographic studies of the cortical anatomy of single word processing</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>1988</year>) <volume>331</volume>:<fpage>585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/331585a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3277066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B141"><label>141</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Raichle</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Localization of a human system for sustained attention by positron emission tomography</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>349</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/349061a0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1985266?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1985266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B142"><label>142</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonides</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Koeppe</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Awh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Minoshima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintun</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial working memory in humans as revealed by PET</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>363</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/363623a0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8510752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8510752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B143"><label>143</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zandbelt</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloemendaal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neggers</surname><given-names>SFW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Expectations and violations: delineating the neural network of proactive inhibitory control</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>2015</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.22047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22359406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22359406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B144"><label>144</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Krystal</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional neuroanatomical correlates of the effects of stress on memory</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Stress</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.2490080403</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8564272?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8564272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B145"><label>145</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Morree</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutten</surname><given-names>G-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kop</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Central nervous system involvement in the autonomic responses to psychological distress</article-title>. <source>Neth Heart J</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12471-012-0351-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23184602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23184602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B146"><label>146</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional neuroanatomical correlates of traumatic stress revisited 7 years later, this time with data</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacol Bull</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 14566211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14566211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B147"><label>147</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Grasby</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schallice</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Frackowiak</surname><given-names>RSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Brain systems of encoding and retrieval of auditory&#x02013;verbal memory. An in vivo study in humans</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/118.2.401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7735882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B148"><label>148</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreasen</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Leary</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cizadlo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurtig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Short-term and long-term memory: a positron emission tomography study</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>5111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.92.11.5111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7761457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B149"><label>149</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Javanmard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shlik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Houle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradwejn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neuroanatomic correlates of CCK-4-induced panic attacks in healthy humans: a comparison of two time points</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(98)00348-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10202575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10202575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B150"><label>150</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased amygdala and insula activation during emotion processing in anxiety-prone subjects</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>164</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.2007.164.2.318</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17267796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17267796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B151"><label>151</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Strigo</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Initial evidence of a failure to activate right anterior insula during affective set shifting in posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Psychosom Med</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>71</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181a56ed8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19398499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19398499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B152"><label>152</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Insular cortex involvement in declarative memory deficits in patients with post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-244x-9-39</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19538748?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19538748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B153"><label>153</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Gray matter density reduction in the insula in fire survivors with posttraumatic stress disorder: a voxel-based morphometric study</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>146</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pscychresns.2005.09.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16371250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16371250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B154"><label>154</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schiffer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Teicher</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Papanicolaou</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evoked potential evidence for right brain activity during the recall of traumatic memories</article-title>. <source>J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/jnp.7.2.169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7626959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B155"><label>155</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abercrombie</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Metabolic rate in the right amygdala predicts negative affect in depressed patients</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>3301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001756-199810050-00028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9831467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9831467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>