<?xml version="1.0"?>
PLoS OnePLoS ONEplosplosonePLoS ONE1932-6203Public Library of ScienceSan Francisco, USA379651324155873PONE-D-12-2606910.1371/journal.pone.0075859Research ArticlePET-Scan Shows Peripherally Increased Neurokinin 1 Receptor Availability in Chronic Tennis Elbow: Visualizing Neurogenic Inflammation?PET-Scan of NK1 Receptors in Chronic Tennis ElbowPetersonMagnus
1

*
SvärdsuddKurt
1
AppelLieuwe
2
EnglerHenry
2

3
AarnioMikko
4
GordhTorsten
4
LångströmBengt
2

5

6
SörensenJens
2

1
Department of Public Health and Caring Sciences, Family Medicine and Clinical Epidemiology, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden

2
Uppsala PET Centre, Department of Radiology, Oncology and Radiation Sciences, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden

3
Uruguayan Centre of Molecular Imaging (CUDIM), Faculty of Medicine and Faculty of Sciences, University of the Republic, Montevideo, Uruguay

4
Department of Surgical Sciences, Pain Research, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden

5
Department of Biochemistry and Organic Chemistry, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden

6
Neuropsychopharmacology Section, Faculty of Medicine, Imperial College, London, United Kingdom
PaulFriedemannEditor
Charité University Medicine Berlin, Germany
* E-mail: magnus.peterson@pubcare.uu.seCompeting Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: MP KS LA HE BL TG JS. Performed the experiments: MP LA HE BL JS. Analyzed the data: MP KS MA JS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MP KS MA JS. Wrote the manuscript: MP KS TG JS. 201314102013810e7585924820122282013© 2013 Peterson et al2013Peterson et alThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.In response to pain, neurokinin 1 (NK1) receptor availability is altered in the central nervous system. The NK1 receptor and its primary agonist, substance P, also play a crucial role in peripheral tissue in response to pain, as part of neurogenic inflammation. However, little is known about alterations in NK1 receptor availability in peripheral tissue in chronic pain conditions and very few studies have been performed on human beings. Ten subjects with chronic tennis elbow were therefore examined by positron emission tomography (PET) with the NK1 specific radioligand [11C]GR205171 before and after treatment with graded exercise. The radioligand signal intensity was higher in the affected arm as compared with the unaffected arm, measured as differences between the arms in volume of voxels and signal intensity of this volume above a reference threshold set as 2.5 SD above mean signal intensity of the unaffected arm before treatment. In the eight subjects examined after treatment, pain ratings decreased in all subjects but signal intensity decreased in five and increased in three. In conclusion, NK1 receptors may be activated, or up-regulated in the peripheral, painful tissue of a chronic pain condition. This up-regulation does, however, have moderate correlation to pain ratings. The increased NK1 receptor availability is interpreted as part of ongoing neurogenic inflammation and may have correlation to the pathogenesis of chronic tennis elbow.The study was supported by grants from the Swedish Research Council (grant no. K2005-27X-15293-01A), The Amersham Fund at Uppsala University, The Research Fund at Uppsala County Council, The Family Medicine Foundation, and Uppsala University. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2.1"><title>Study population</title><p>The study was performed in the city of Uppsala, Sweden, and was nested in a larger randomized controlled trial of graded exercise as treatment for chronic TE (lateral epicondylosis). All 150 general practitioners and 90 physiotherapists at primary health care centres within a radius of 70 kilometers of the city of Uppsala were asked for information on subjects with long-lasting TE problems. In addition, subjects with TE symptoms were invited to participate in the trial through advertisements in the main local newspaper in order to recruit a sufficiently large number of subjects.</p><p>The inclusion criteria were: age 20-75 years, symptoms of TE for more than three months, and a verified diagnosis. Exclusion criteria were any of concomitant supinator syndrome, compartment syndrome of musculus anconeus, rhizopathy, inflammatory joint disease, fibromyalgia, previous elbow surgery, treatment by injection of steroids within the previous three months, and inability to understand Swedish. At a first appointment the diagnosis was checked by pain on palpation, stretching (Mill´s test), loading and Maudsley´s middle finger test by the same physician, a general practitioner and pain specialist (MP). One hundred and seventy-three patients were evaluated, of which 53 were excluded for reasons of incorrect diagnosis, other concomitant pain diagnoses, or interfering treatment, leaving 120 subjects as the final RCT study population.</p><p>Subjects in the RCT were consecutively invited to participate in the PET study until ten had accepted. Exclusion criteria for the PET study were any of: current medication interfering with the nervous or inflammatory system, substance abuse, pregnancy, recent or planned participation in another PET study, X-ray or other significant exposure to radiation, bilateral symptoms or other pain diagnosis of the upper extremities. All subjects gave written informed consent before entering the study. The Regional Ethical Review Board in Uppsala, Sweden and the Radiation Safety Committee in Uppsala, Sweden approved the study. The trial is registered as NCT00888225 at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/"><underline>http://clinicaltrials.gov/</underline></ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title>PET examination and exercise treatment procedure</title><p>The PET examinations were performed twice in each participant, before and after the treatment protocol of the RCT. The treatment consisted of a three-month daily exercise regime performed at home, with gradually increasing load on the extensor muscles of the affected forearm. The protocol has been previously described in detail [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Pain was rated on a 100 mm visual analogue scale (VAS), during maximum voluntary contraction of the forearm extensor muscles.</p><p>Prior to scanning, all participants refrained from analgesics for one day and anti-inflammatory drugs for three days. They also abstained from tobacco, alcohol and caffeine for twelve hours before, and from food for three hours before PET investigations.</p><p>Examinations were performed with the NK1 specific radioligand [<sup>11</sup>C]GR205171, synthesized according to standard manufacturing procedures and previously published methods [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] at the chemistry section of the Uppsala PET Center. The scanning procedure was executed with a Siemens ECAT EXACT HR+ whole body tomograph (CTI, Knoxville, TN, USA). The scanner enables acquisition of 63 contiguous planes of data with 2.46 mm plane spacing resulting in a total axial field of view of 155 mm.</p><p>Subjects were placed in prone position in the scanner with their arms stretched above the head and gently fixated, so that the elbow joints of both arms were in the field of view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0075859-g001">Figure 1</xref>). A venous catheter was inserted in the foot and a bolus of the radioligand was injected intravenously approximately 50 minutes prior to the elbow investigation. The amount of injected radioactivity was approximately 5.6 MBq/kg bodyweight, average dose 405 (SD 17.4) MBq. A dynamic examination of other tissues was performed during the first 45 minutes. Then the imaging data was collected during a ten-minute time frame. Finally, a ten-minute transmission scan was performed using three retractable <sup>68</sup>GE rotating line sources.</p><fig id="pone-0075859-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075859.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Position in the PET-scanner.</title><p>The subject of the photograph has given written informed consent, as outlined in the PLOS consent form, to publication of the photograph.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0075859.g001"/></fig><p>Emission scans were reconstructed using an ordered subset expectation maximization (OSEM) method with six iterations and eight subsets using an eight mm Hanning filter, zoom two point five. The PET data were reconstructed to a 128x128 matrix with filtered back projection and corrected for photon attenuation, decay, scattered radiation and random coincidences according to standard procedures [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title>Data analysis</title><p>The image data were analyzed according to a non-observer dependent statistical approach. A full description including tutorial, source code and imaging data test files is available as supporting information supplement, File S3-S7. The original three-dimensional matrices representing radioactivity concentration (signal intensity) and the density maps used to correct for attenuation were loaded into ImageJ, (a public domain Java image processing program developed at the National Institutes of Health) [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. An algorithm was constructed with which the left and right arms were semi-automatically located and segmented from the density maps. Based on this segmentation, the total number of voxels, their mean signal intensity, and the standard deviation (SD) of this signal intensity were calculated for each arm. The mean signal intensity of all voxels in the unaffected arm was used as reference.</p><p>Then two new image matrices were created, in which the voxel data represented the signal intensity, measured in SD units (Z score). From each Z score image, the signal intensity of voxels located &gt;2.5 SD above reference in each arm was computed. In order to obtain a composite measure of voxel volume and signal intensity, a “Volume intensity score” was calculated by multiplying the volume of voxels with signal intensity &gt; 2.5 SD above reference in each arm, by the summed Z score signal intensity of this volume. Two subjects discontinued exercise intervention and declined participation in the PET examination after treatment due to “lack of time”.</p><p>The derived data were analyzed using SAS software, version 9.2. Differences between the arms were computed with Student’s t-test and with unbalanced analysis of variation, both methods giving almost identical results. All statistical tests were two-tailed. P-values less than 0.05 were regarded as statistically significant. The correlation between pain rating and the Volume intensity score was calculated according to Spearman.</p></sec></sec>Dr. Stephen Butler of Pain Centre, Uppsala University Hospital, the pain research group of Uppsala Berzelii Centre as well as Mimmi Lidholm and the staff of Uppsala PET Centre, are acknowledged for their knowledge and assistance. Raw data of all subjects will be made available to researchers on request. Test-files with imaging data is provided as supporting information supplement, File S4-S7.References1
YelinE (2003) Cost of musculoskeletal diseases: impact of work disability and functional decline. J Rheumatol Suppl
68: 8-11. PubMed: 14712615.147126152
AllanderE (1974) Prevalence, incidence, and remission rates of some common rheumatic diseases or syndromes. Scand J Rheumatol
3: 145-153. doi:10.3109/03009747409097141. PubMed: 4428194.44281943
AssendelftW, GreenS, BuchbinderR, StruijsP, SmidtN (2002) Tennis elbow (lateral epicondylitis). Clin Evid: 1290-1300. PubMed: 12603940.126039404
PaavolaM, KannusP, JärvinenTA, JärvinenTL, JózsaL
et al. (2002) Treatment of tendon disorders. Is there a role for corticosteroid injection?
Foot Ankle Clin
7: 501-513. doi:10.1016/S1083-7515(02)00056-6. PubMed: 12512406.125124065
LeadbetterWB (1992) Cell-matrix response in tendon injury. Clin Sports Med
11: 533-578. PubMed: 1638640.16386406
KjaerM, LangbergH, SkovgaardD, OlesenJ, BülowJ
et al. (2000) In vivo studies of peritendinous tissue in exercise. Scand J Med Sci Sports
10: 326-331. doi:10.1034/j.1600-0838.2000.010006326.x. PubMed: 11085559.110855597
LangbergH, SkovgaardD, KaramouzisM, BülowJ, KjaerM (1999) Metabolism and inflammatory mediators in the peritendinous space measured by microdialysis during intermittent isometric exercise in humans. J Physiol
515 ( 3): 919-927. doi:10.1111/j.1469-7793.1999.919ab.x. PubMed: 10066916.100669168
MarchandF, PerrettiM, McMahonSB (2005) Role of the immune system in chronic pain. Nat Rev Neurosci
6: 521-532. doi:10.1038/nrn1700. PubMed: 15995723.159957239
PaavolaM, KannusP, JärvinenTA, KhanK, JózsaL
et al. (2002) Achilles tendinopathy. J Bone Joint Surg Am
84-A: 2062-2076. PubMed: 12429771.1242977110
ReganW, WoldLE, CoonradR, MorreyBF (1992) Microscopic histopathology of chronic refractory lateral epicondylitis. Am J Sports Med
20: 746-749. doi:10.1177/036354659202000618. PubMed: 1280910.128091011
GoldieI (1964) Epicondylitis Lateralis Humeri (Epicondylalgia or Tennis Elbow). a Pathogenetical Study. Acta Chir Scand Supp: 57
suppl 339:331
+
12
LjungBO, AlfredsonH, ForsgrenS (2004) Neurokinin 1-receptors and sensory neuropeptides in tendon insertions at the medial and lateral epicondyles of the humerus. Studies on tennis elbow and medial epicondylalgia. J Orthop Res
22: 321-327. doi:10.1016/S0736-0266(03)00183-9. PubMed: 15013091.1501309113
AnderssonG, DanielsonP, AlfredsonH, ForsgrenS (2008) Presence of substance P and the neurokinin-1 receptor in tenocytes of the human Achilles tendon. Regul Pept
150: 81-87. doi:10.1016/j.regpep.2008.02.005. PubMed: 18394729.1839472914
Hoe-HansenC (2001) Subacromial inflammation; Clinical and experimental studies [Medicine]. Linkoping: University of Linkoping.15
LjungBO, ForsgrenS, FridénJ (1999) Substance P and calcitonin gene-related peptide expression at the extensor carpi radialis brevis muscle origin: implications for the etiology of tennis elbow. J Orthop Res
17: 554-559. doi:10.1002/jor.1100170414. PubMed: 10459762.1045976216
O'ConnorTM, O'ConnellJ, O'BrienDI, GoodeT, BredinCP
et al. (2004) The role of substance P in inflammatory disease. J Cell Physiol
201: 167-180. doi:10.1002/jcp.20061. PubMed: 15334652.1533465217
QuartaraL, MaggiCA (1998) The tachykinin NK1 receptor. Part II: Distribution and pathophysiological roles. Neuropeptides
32: 1-49. doi:10.1016/S0143-4179(98)90015-4. PubMed: 9571643.957164318
Pedersen-BjergaardU, NielsenLB, JensenK, EdvinssonL, JansenI
et al. (1991) Calcitonin gene-related peptide, neurokinin A and substance P: effects on nociception and neurogenic inflammation in human skin and temporal muscle. Peptides
12: 333-337. doi:10.1016/0196-9781(91)90022-H. PubMed: 1712469.171246919
TraubRJ (1996) The spinal contribution of substance P to the generation and maintenance of inflammatory hyperalgesia in the rat. Pain
67: 151-161. doi:10.1016/0304-3959(96)03076-X. PubMed: 8895243.889524320
MurrayCW, CowanA, LarsonAA (1991) Neurokinin and NMDA antagonists (but not a kainic acid antagonist) are antinociceptive in the mouse formalin model. Pain
44: 179-185. doi:10.1016/0304-3959(91)90135-K. PubMed: 1711193.171119321
SeguinL, Le Marouille-GirardonS, MillanMJ (1995) Antinociceptive profiles of non-peptidergic neurokinin1 and neurokinin2 receptor antagonists: a comparison to other classes of antinociceptive agent. Pain
61: 325-343. doi:10.1016/0304-3959(94)00194-J. PubMed: 7659444.765944422
SakuradaT, KatsumataK, YogoH, Tan-NoK, SakuradaS
et al. (1995) The neurokinin-1 receptor antagonist, sendide, exhibits antinociceptive activity in the formalin test. Pain
60: 175-180. doi:10.1016/0304-3959(94)00107-P. PubMed: 7540280.754028023
BoyceS, HillR (2000) Discrepant results from precinical and clinical studies on the potential of substance P-receptor antagonist compounds as analgesics. In: MeaD
Proceedings of the 9th World Congress on Pain: Seattle. IASP Press pp. 313-324.24
HillR (2000) NK1 (substance P) receptor antagonists--why are they not analgesic in humans?
Trends Pharmacol Sci
21: 244-246. doi:10.1016/S0165-6147(00)01502-9. PubMed: 10871891.1087189125
LinnmanC, AppelL, FurmarkT, SöderlundA, GordhT
et al. (2010) Ventromedial prefrontal neurokinin 1 receptor availability is reduced in chronic pain. Pain
149: 64-70. doi:10.1016/j.pain.2010.01.008. PubMed: 20137858.2013785826
BuchbinderR, GreenSE, StruijsP (2008) Tennis elbow. Clin Evid (Online): 1117 PubMed: 19450309.27
WoodleyBL, Newsham-WestRJ, BaxterGD (2007) Chronic tendinopathy: effectiveness of eccentric exercise. Br J Sports Med
41: 188-198; commentary 199 doi:10.1136/bjsm.2006.029769. PubMed: 17062655.1706265528
KjaerM (2004) Role of extracellular matrix in adaptation of tendon and skeletal muscle to mechanical loading. Physiol Rev
84: 649-698. doi:10.1152/physrev.00031.2003. PubMed: 15044685.1504468529
PetersonM, ButlerS, ErikssonM, SvärdsuddK (2011) A randomized controlled trial of exercise versus wait-list in chronic tennis elbow (lateral epicondylosis). Ups J Med Sci
116: 269-279. doi:10.3109/03009734.2011.600476. PubMed: 22066975.2206697530
BergströmM, FasthKJ, KilpatrickG, WardP, CableKM
et al. (2000) Brain uptake and receptor binding of two [11C]labelled selective high affinity NK1-antagonists, GR203040 and GR205171--PET studies in rhesus monkey. Neuropharmacology
39: 664-670. doi:10.1016/S0028-3908(99)00182-3. PubMed: 10728887.1072888731
SiemensECAT
Software version 7.1.1, Operating Instructions, Appendix B.32
ImageJ Image processing and analysis in Java. Available: 
http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/
. Accessed (2013, Sep 5)
33
AbràmoffMD, RamSJ (2004) Image processing with ImageJ. Biophotonics Int: 36-43.34
MichelgårdA, AppelL, PissiotaA, FransO, LångströmB
et al. (2007) Symptom provocation in specific phobia affects the substance P neurokinin-1 receptor system. Biol Psychiatry
61: 1002-1006. doi:10.1016/j.biopsych.2006.07.003. PubMed: 16950220.1695022035
FarrarJT, YoungJPJr., LaMoreauxL, WerthJL, PooleRM (2001) Clinical importance of changes in chronic pain intensity measured on an 11-point numerical pain rating scale. Pain
94: 149-158. doi:10.1016/S0304-3959(01)00349-9. PubMed: 11690728.1169072836
FarrarJT, PortenoyRK, BerlinJA, KinmanJL, StromBL (2000) Defining the clinically important difference in pain outcome measures. Pain
88: 287-294. doi:10.1016/S0304-3959(00)00339-0. PubMed: 11068116.1106811637
McMahonSB, CaffertyWB, MarchandF (2005) Immune and glial cell factors as pain mediators and modulators. Exp Neurol
192: 444-462. doi:10.1016/j.expneurol.2004.11.001. PubMed: 15755561.1575556138
HarmarA, KeenP (1982) Synthesis, and central and peripheral axonal transport of substance P in a dorsal root ganglion-nerve preparation in vitro. Brain Res
231: 379-385. doi:10.1016/0006-8993(82)90374-2. PubMed: 6173094.617309439
HarrisonS, GeppettiP (2001) Substance p. Int J Biochem Cell Biol
33: 555-576. doi:10.1016/S1357-2725(01)00031-0. PubMed: 11378438.1137843840
PatelHJ, RamkissoonSH, PatelPS, RameshwarP (2005) Transformation of breast cells by truncated neurokinin-1 receptor is secondary to activation by preprotachykinin-A peptides. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
102: 17436-17441. doi:10.1073/pnas.0506351102. PubMed: 16291810.1629181041
PageNM, BellNJ, GardinerSM, ManyondaIT, BrayleyKJ
et al. (2003) Characterization of the endokinins: human tachykinins with cardiovascular activity. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
100: 6245-6250. doi:10.1073/pnas.0931458100. PubMed: 12716968.1271696842
McCarsonKE (1999) Central and peripheral expression of neurokinin-1 and neurokinin-3 receptor and substance P-encoding messenger RNAs: peripheral regulation during formalin-induced inflammation and lack of neurokinin receptor expression in primary afferent sensory neurons. Neuroscience
93: 361-370. doi:10.1016/S0306-4522(99)00102-5. PubMed: 10430499.1043049943
PotterHG, HannafinJA, MorwesselRM, DiCarloEF, O'BrienSJ
et al. (1995) Lateral epicondylitis: correlation of MR imaging, surgical, and histopathologic findings. Radiology
196: 43-46. PubMed: 7784585.778458544
BackmanLJ, FongG, AnderssonG, ScottA, DanielsonP (2011) Substance P is a mechanoresponsive, autocrine regulator of human tenocyte proliferation. PLOS ONE
6: e27209. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0027209. PubMed: 22069500.2206950045
MantyhPW, AllenCJ, GhilardiJR, RogersSD, MantyhCR
et al. (1995) Rapid endocytosis of a G protein-coupled receptor: substance P evoked internalization of its receptor in the rat striatum in vivo. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
92: 2622-2626. doi:10.1073/pnas.92.7.2622. PubMed: 7535928.753592846
BowdenJJ, GarlandAM, BalukP, LefevreP, GradyEF
et al. (1994) Direct observation of substance P-induced internalization of neurokinin 1 (NK1) receptors at sites of inflammation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
91: 8964-8968. doi:10.1073/pnas.91.19.8964. PubMed: 7522326.752232647
PatelL, LindleyC (2003) Aprepitant--a novel NK1-receptor antagonist. Expert Opin Pharmacother
4: 2279-2296. doi:10.1517/14656566.4.12.2279. PubMed: 14640927.1464092748
KingT, GardellLR, WangR, VardanyanA, OssipovMH
et al. (2005) Role of NK-1 neurotransmission in opioid-induced hyperalgesia. Pain
116: 276-288. doi:10.1016/j.pain.2005.04.014. PubMed: 15964684.1596468449
KreamRM, KatoT, ShimonakaH, MarchandJE, WurmWH (1993) Substance P markedly potentiates the antinociceptive effects of morphine sulfate administered at the spinal level. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A
90: 3564-3568. doi:10.1073/pnas.90.8.3564. PubMed: 7682711.768271150
LinnmanC, AppelL, FredriksonM, GordhT, SöderlundA
et al. (2011) Elevated [11C]-D-deprenyl uptake in chronic Whiplash Associated Disorder suggests persistent musculoskeletal inflammation. PLOS ONE
6: e19182. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0019182. PubMed: 21541010.21541010
