<?xml version="1.0"?>
Exp NeurobiolExp NeurobiolENExperimental Neurobiology1226-25602093-8144The Korean Society for Brain and Neural Science468833110.5607/en.2015.24.4.312Review Article: Autism Spectrum DisordersIs Oxytocin Application for Autism Spectrum Disorder Evidence-Based?LeeSeung Yup1LeeAh Rah2HwangboRam3HanJuhee3HongMinha4BahnGeon Ho51Graduate School of Medicine, Kyung Hee University, Seoul 02543, Korea.2Kyung Hee University School of Medicine, Seoul 02543, Korea.3Department of Psychiatry, Kyung Hee University Hospital, Seoul 02447, Korea.4Department of Psychiatry, Seonam University, College of Medicine, Myongji Hospital, Goyang 10475, Korea.5Department of Psychiatry, Kyung Hee University School of Medicine, Seoul 02447, Korea.To whom correspondence should be addressed. TEL: 82-2-958-8556, FAX: 82-2-957-1997, mompeian@khu.ac.kr12201516122015244312324281020152511201525112015Copyright © Experimental Neurobiology 2015.2015This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is characterized by persistent deficits within two core symptom domains: social communication and restricted, repetitive behaviors. Although numerous studies have reported psychopharmacological treatment outcomes for the core symptom domains of ASD, there are not enough studies on fundamental treatments based on the etiological pathology of ASD. Studies on candidate medications related to the pathogenesis of ASD, such as naltrexone and secretin, were conducted, but the results were inconclusive. Oxytocin has been identified as having an important role in maternal behavior and attachment, and it has been recognized as a key factor in the social developmental deficit seen in ASD. Genetic studies have also identified associations between ASD and the oxytocin pathway. As ASD has its onset in infancy, parents are willing to try even experimental or unapproved treatments in an effort to avoid missing the critical period for diagnosis and treatment, which can place their child in an irreversible state. While therapeutic application of oxytocin for ASD is in its early stages, we have concluded that oxytocin would be a promising therapeutic substance via a thorough literature review focusing on the following: the relationship between oxytocin and sociality; single nucleotide polymorphisms as a biological marker of ASD; and validity verification of oxytocin treatment in humans. We also reviewed materials related to the mechanism of oxytocin action that may support its potential application in treating ASD.Autism spectrum disorderOxytocinSocialityGeneBehaviorIntranasalMinistry of Health and Welfarehttp://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100008903A120029NEUROSCIENTIFIC BACKGROUND OF SOCIALITY IN ANIMALS AND HUMANSPrairie voles develop long-term monogamous relationships with their mates and both sexes provide parental care [29]. These characteristics make the prairie vole a useful model for studying affiliative behavior, especially pair bonding. On the other hand, montane voles exhibit polygamy, and are appropriate for comparison studies with prairie voles. In a study comparing prairie voles and montane voles, there was no significant difference in the expression of oxytocin between the species. However, there was a difference in the distribution of regional oxytocin receptors, which has been suggested to mediate pair bond formation [29]. In prairie voles, oxytocin receptors are highly expressed in the nucleus accumbens, prelimbic cortex, lateral amygdala, and midline thalamic nuclei. In contrast, oxytocin receptors in montane voles are expressed in the lateral septum and cortical nucleus of amygdala. Although gaps in knowledge remain, it is assumed that oxytocin is released in prairie voles during mating and it acts on the limbic sites, producing selective reinforcement of the mate. Furthermore, infusion of oxytocin into the cerebral ventricles facilitates partner preference in female prairie voles [30]. Though partner preference may differ from the complicated process of pair bonding, formation of a preference may be one of the earliest behavioral events in selective, enduring attachment. The formation of partner preference is blocked in the mating female prairie vole by infusion of oxytocin receptor antagonist into the prelimbic cortex and nucleus accumbens [3031]. This result suggests that these brain regions may be important for pair bond formation, although as yet, no common physiological mechanisms for pair bond formation have been identified between animals and humans. Pair bond formation is also a necessary component of human sexuality. In a healthy human population, nipple stimulation facilitates oxytocin release [32] and plasma oxytocin levels are increased during orgasm in both women and men [3334]. If oxytocin induces social attachment, sexual activity may reinforce sexual bonding [35]. In an experiment with healthy male students who had demonstrated insecure attachment patterns, administration of intranasal oxytocin produced an increase in secure attachment experience [36].Evidence indicates that oxytocin is not only associated with pair bond formation, but also with social cognition. Since rats are born functionally blind and deaf, nipple attachment by olfactory learning and response to maternal odor is important for survival [37]. Endogenous oxytocin promotes associative learning of maternal odor in young rats. On the other hand, if the rats are pretreated with oxytocin antagonists, the odor-mother conditioning is blocked. This suggests that oxytocin is an important neuropeptide for young rats to form associations, especially with their mothers. In adult rats, onset of maternal behavior was facilitated with intracerebroventricular administration of oxytocin [38]. Onset of maternal behavior in rats includes overcoming natural avoidance of neonates, which can be induced by neonatal odors. It appears, therefore, that in rats, oxytocin induces maternal care by blunting olfactory processing in associated brain areas [39]. Oxytocin released during birth seems to reduce the firing rate of the mitral and granule cells in the olfactory bulb, and thus may facilitate approach behavior [40]. Oxytocin knockout mice suffer deficits in social recognition memory, despite normal olfactory bulb function and spatial learning abilities [41]. Social recognition was restored following intraventricular oxytocin administration to the medial nucleus of the amygdala [42]. This suggests that oxytocin receptor activation in the medial amygdala is necessary for social recognition in mouse. Adult oxytocin receptor knockout mice demonstrate deficits in social discrimination and exhibit more aggressive behavior than wild type mice [43]. Oxytocin receptor gene null mutant mice have two additional characteristics: 'resistance to change in a learned pattern of behavior,' corresponding to ASD's 'restricted interests and repetitive behavior'; 'increased susceptibility to seizures', which is frequently comorbid with ASD. However, administering intracerebroventricular oxytocin restores social exploration and social recognition, along with aggressive behavior [43]. There is an increasing body of literature on humans suggesting that oxytocin reinforces social memory by playing an important role selectively in facial processing and social communication. Through primarily employing intranasal administration, the following effects were reported: improvements in mental status inference ability [44]; increase in eye gaze number and duration for neutral human faces [45]; improvements in recognition memory for faces [46]. While a few authors reported enhancements in recognition of prosocial facial expression [4748], other studies reported enhancement of neutral, angry, and fearful face recognitions [495051].In studies employing peripheral oxytocin injection in rats, prosocial behaviors such as increased adjacent lying (side-by-side contact) and decreased anogenital sniffing were observed [52]. Two specific mouse strains (BALB/cByJ, C58/J) with deficits in sociability showed an increase in social approach activities after intraperitoneal administration of oxytocin, based on performance in the three-chambered choice test [53]. The amygdala has been highlighted as one of the core areas thought to mediate the prosocial effects of exogenous oxytocin. In a double blind study with 15 men, each performed visual matching tasks for different fear-inducing visual stimuli after intranasal administration of oxytocin (27 IU) or placebo. Comparing the activity of the amygdala before and after the task with functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), the authors observed reduced activity of the amygdala during viewing of aversive, fear-inducing visual stimuli along with decreased functional coupling of the amygdala regions mediating autonomic and behavioral aspects of fear and the brain stem [54]. These findings suggest that the prosocial effect of oxytocin is the result of an anxiolytic effect, which may include an adjustment in amygdala responsivity. Additionally, some groups have reported attenuation of aversive conditioning of fear-conditioned face stimuli following intranasal oxytocin (32 IU) administration [55]. These results were interpreted as resulting from decreased activity in the right amygdala and right fusiform face area during aversive conditioning. In a recent high-resolution fMRI study, subjects who received intranasal oxytocin (24 IU) frequently gazed at the eye region despite instructions to gaze at the mouth region [56]. Such fixation changes are correlated with increased right posterior amygdala activity and are coupled with increased activity of the superior colliculi. Intranasal oxytocin administration attenuated activity in the lateral and dorsal regions of the anterior amygdala in response to fearful faces, and increased activity in response to happy faces.GENETIC BACKGROUND IN ANIMALS AND HUMANSBased on the fact that children with autism have lower average levels of blood oxytocin [57] and higher oxytocin precursor levels [58] in comparison with typically developing age-matched children, early genetic studies were designed to attempt to find genetic evidence for such differences. However, correlation between peripheral oxytocin levels and ASD psychopathology is uncertain [59]. Although single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) correlation studies on behavioral problems and oxytocin are in progress, results vary across research groups. Yrigollen et al. reported a correlation between rs2740204 of the oxytocin genes and stereotyped behaviors [60], and Ebstein et al. reported a correlation between rs6133010 and ASD [61]. However, Hovey et al. could not replicate such correlations [62].In addition to blood oxytocin concentration, there is also increasing evidence that oxytocin receptor genotype is strongly associated with ASD, more with social cognition than with ASD diagnosis itself [63] (Table 1). Since the physiological effect of oxytocin is mediated by the oxytocin receptor, many studies have identified the oxytocin receptor as the modifier of social cognition and behavior. Several studies indicated an association between genetic variations in the oxytocin receptor gene and ASD or related phenotypes in the Caucasian population [646566]: a nominal association between SNP rs237880 in the oxytocin receptor gene and autistic traits [67]; a significant association between SNP rs2268493 in the oxytocin receptor gene and Asperger syndrome [64]; an association between rs2268493 and affiliative behavior in ASD [60]. Campbell et al. [68] identified three SNPs (rs2268493, rs1042778, rs7632287) nominally associated with autism. Several studies have indicated linkages in Asian populations: two SNPs (rs2254298, rs53576) in the Chinese Han populations [66] and in the Japanese populations [69]. In a recent meta-analysis, 4 SNPs, rs7632287, rs237887, rs2268491, rs2254298, were correlated with ASD, and there was a significant correlation between the oxytocin receptor gene and ASD in gene-based tests for association [63].Methylation of the oxytocin receptor gene, which decreases its expression, has been proposed as one of the etiologies of autism [70]. Postmortem analysis of a separate subgroup of brains of individuals with autism revealed that the oxytocin receptor gene was significantly methylated and oxytocin mRNA was reduced in some samples when compared with that in the control brain samples in the temporal cortex [70]. These findings suggest that the decrease of the oxytocin receptor gene expression is related to some subgroups of ASD. The methylation of the oxytocin receptor gene was reported to increase the activity in the temporal parietal junction, which is known to participate in social perception [71]. In other words, methylation of the oxytocin receptor gene affects brain activity, and thus, may affect the social perception of an individual.CD38 is a transmembrane antigen that has been studied as a negative prognostic marker for chronic lymphocytic leukemia [72]. CD38 participates in the oxytocin secretion in the brain and affects maternal nurturing and social behavior [73]. Plasma levels of oxytocin are strongly reduced in CD38 knockout mice (CD38-/-mice) and subcutaneous oxytocin injection or lentiviralvector-mediated delivery of human CD38 into the hypothalamus rescued social memory and maternal care in these mice [73]. In an association study on humans in the U.S., rs6449197 and rs3796863, which are SNPs of CD38, were correlated with high functioning autism (Table 1) [74]. ASD probands, with a mutant allele (W140) of rs1800561 SNP (R140W), had significantly lower plasma oxytocin levels than those without the mutant allele [74]. CD38 expression in lymphoblastoid cells derived from patients with ASD was reduced [75]. Transition of rs6449182 SNP was correlated with CD38 mRNA expression levels, which were in turn significantly correlated with social skill, and communication subscores on the Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales in patients with ASD [75]. According to the attention capacity to emotional information conveyed by the eyes, the attention of human babies to angry and happy eyes varies as a function of exclusive breastfeeding experience and genetic variation in CD38 [76]. Extended duration of breastfeeding resulted in enhanced looking preference to happy eyes and decreased looking preference to angry eyes. While looking preferences of infants with CA/AA genotype were not influenced by breastfeeding exposure, infants who were homozygous for the C allele of rs3796863 were affected by feeding experience [76].PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGIC BACKGROUND OF SIGNIFICANT AND NEGATIVE HUMAN STUDIESApplication route of oxytocinIn clinical trials with oxytocin administration targeting a diversity of psychiatric disorders (including ASD), the routes of oxytocin administration are oral, intravenous, and intranasal [77] (Table 2). Oral administration is not suitable due to the extensive metabolism of oxytocin by the liver and gastrointestinal tract. Through intravenous administration, only a small amount is able to pass the blood-brain barrier, and there is a latent possibility of uterus contraction side effects in females [77]. Moreover, since it is an invasive method, applications for community treatment are limited. The intranasal route has several advantages, such as bypassing the bloodstream and directly accessing the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) within 30 min, achieving effective concentrations of neuropeptides in the brain without systemic side effects [78], no requirement for specific skill, and ease of application at home [79].Studies using oxytocin with clinical significanceAs studies of animal behavior imply that oxytocin is related to one of autism's core features, 'repetitive behavior' [80]. Similar results were replicated in humans. In the first human study on oxytocin infusion effects on autism core behavior, 15 patients with autism and Asperger's syndrome were administered intravenous oxytocin and showed significantly decreased repetitive behavior (Table 2) [80]. In another study by the same authors, intravenous injection of oxytocin for 4 h promoted social learning in patients with ASD [81]. In the first study on adolescent subjects with ASD, 16 participants showed significant improvement in the 'Reading the Mind in the Eyes' task after administration of intranasal oxytocin (24 IU) [82]. Later results from the same research group indicated that, although there was no significant difference between groups, oxytocin nasal spray may improve emotion recognition, in which impairment is one of the core features of ASD [83]. In a study on children with autism and Asperger's syndrome, the subjects were administered intranasal oxytocin twice a day (0.4 IU/kg/dose) for 12 weeks. The results showed improvement in not only repetitive behavior, but also facial recognition and social cognition [84]. In a study on 20 men with ASD, a single-dose of intranasal oxytocin (24 IU) improved the 'deficit in inferring others' social emotion' and restored decreases in right anterior insula activity [27]. In a study on 40 high-functioning men with ASD, a single-dose intranasal administration of oxytocin (24 IU) improved the frequency and response time of nonverbal information-based judgments and also restored activity levels of the medial prefrontal cortex, [26]. To investigate the long-term effect of oxytocin administration, Watanabe et al. [85] performed a randomized controlled trial (RCT), including 6 weeks of intranasal administration of oxytocin (48 IU/day), to 20 high-functioning adult men with ASD. The trial showed improved social reciprocity and enhanced task-independent resting-state functional connectivity between the anterior cingulate cortex and the dorso-medial prefrontal cortex [85]. Unlike previous short-term studies, Tachibana et al. administrated intranasal oxytocin for 7 months to 8 adolescent boys with outcomes presenting improvement in communication and social interaction [86]. Considering that poor social interaction and repetitive behaviors are core symptom domains of autism, the study results imply that oxytocin may be a potential treatment option for ASD.Studies using oxytocin with negative findingsSometimes studies fail to reproduce treatment effects of oxytocin reported in previous work. In a study on 19 adult patients with ASD, intranasal oxytocin (24 IU) was administered for 6 weeks, and although social cognition and low order repetitive behaviors (stereotype, self-injury) improved, there was no effect on higher order repetitive behaviors (ritualistic, sameness) [87]. This study is of significant importance as it is the first study on the daily administration of oxytocin. However, its implications may be limited by the small number of subjects and the short duration of administration [87]. In a study on 38 male youth patients, nasal administration (24 or 12 IU) was done for 5 days but results showed no difference from the placebo group in terms of emotion recognition and social interaction skills, among others [88]. The authors suggested that there might be patient subgroups that may not benefit from exogenous oxytocin and that further research is needed. In a RCT of 50 adolescent men with autistic or Asperger's syndrome receiving oxytocin nasal spray (18 or 24 IU) twice-daily for 8 weeks, the oxytocin group did not show improvements in social cognition following treatment as rated by caregivers and clinicians [83]. While the results did not suggest any benefits of oxytocin for autistic symptoms, further research is needed to explore earlier age interventions and package program involving a combination of pharmacological treatment and social-learning exercises.Safety of oxytocin treatmentThere is some evidence that very young animals may show long-lasting negative consequences in social behavior following direct intraperitoneal injection of large doses of oxytocin [89]. Chronic or repeated intranasal oxytocin treatment in humans might also result in undesired counter-regulatory consequences [90]. A 55-year old patient with obsessive compulsive disorder showed clear improvement in symptoms following intranasal oxytocin treatment for 4 weeks, but concurrently developed severe memory impairments [91]. This case lends support for the amnestic properties of the peptide. When administrating intravenous oxytocin for labor induction or abortion, adverse effects such as reflex tachycardia, seizures, headache, memory impairment, hyponatremia, a syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion, and anaphylaxis have been reported [92]. Large cohort studies have suggested a very small but significant risk for the future development of autism later in life following augmented childbirth with oxytocin [93]. Although side effects such as irritability, nasal congestion, fatigue, and headache were reported in human studies following intranasal oxytocin administration, there were no statistically significant differences from the placebo group [94]. In a recent report on children with ASD administered long-term nasal oxytocin for more than 6 months, six of eight participants reported positive effects on the quality of reciprocal communication and showed excellent compliance with no side effects [86]. According to the review of previous human data, there are no serious adverse effects with short-term application of oxytocin with 18~40 IU [94], but human data on the outcomes following extended treatment, especially in young children with ASD, are required.OXYTOCIN-RELATED CANDIDATE AGENTS FOR FUTURE ASD RESEARCHSince the atypical antipsychotics, risperidone and aripiprazole, are the only FDA-approved medications for ASD, research for new therapeutics based on specific mechanisms and pathways involving etiological factors is urgently necessary [95]. Apart from intranasal oxytocin, molecules or pathways related to oxytocin release can be candidates for such novel research. In animal studies, vasopressin increased prosocial behavior [52], and decreased social interaction was observed in arginine vasopressin receptor 1A (V1aR) knockout mice [96]. In a human study [97], blood measures of arginine vasopressin (AVP) concentrations represented CSF AVP activity in human and were used as a predictor of social functioning in children with ASD. Although AVP has received less attention than oxytocin for a possible role in ASD, AVP levels can be used as a biomarker of ASD, and AVP physiology maybe a promising therapeutic target to improve social cognition in individuals with ASD [97].Several peptides have been identified that affect endogenous oxytocin levels. Each peptide affects oxytocin release through a different mechanism. Orexin is a peptide produced in the lateral hypothalamus [98]. Adrenaline, noradrenaline, serotonin, and dopamine are known to increase oxytocin levels. After preincubation of rat neurohypophyseal cell cultures with orexin, adrenaline-, histamine- and serotonin-induced increases in oxytocin levels were attenuated. These results indicate that changes in oxytocin secretion induced by the monoaminergic system can be directly influenced by the orexin system [98]. The serotonin system is also involved in oxytocin release [99]. Serotonergic fibers and receptors are located in the oxytocinergic supraoptic nucleus and paraventricular nuclei of the hypothalamus. Serotonergic receptor agonists, including 8-hydroxy-2-(dipropylamino) tetralin (8-OH-DPAT), 1-(2,5-dimethoxy 4-iodophenyl)-2-amino propane hydrochloride (DOI), and buspirone, cause increased release of oxytocin [99]. In addition to increasing levels of oxytocin, buspirone can promote prosocial behaviors. Galanin is a neuropeptide involved in feeding behavior, memory, cognition, gut secretion, and motility [100]. Galanin works on the hypothalamo-neurohypophyseal system and has a modulatory role in oxytocin release.CD38 transcription is highly sensitive to cytokines and vitamins, including all-trans retinoic acid (ATRA), a known inducer of CD38 [75]. In a study on lymphoblastoid cell lines in patients with ASD and their parents, ATRA exhibited an upmodulatory potential on CD38 mRNA [75]. Although there have been almost no followup studies on ATRA and ASD treatment, there is a possibility that substances affecting CD38 expression, such as ATRA, may be potential therapeutic candidates.Stimulation of melanocortin 4 receptors (MC4R) on supraoptic neurons activates oxytocinergic neurons and induces central, but not peripheral release of oxytocin in mice [99]. A selective MC4R agonist, Ro27-3225, administered to Cntnap2 knockout mouse restores social behavior [101]. Administration of MC4R agonist, melanotan II (MTII), promotes partner preference development and activates hypothalamic oxytocin neurons [102]. These studies suggest that MC4R agonists may be a possible treatment option to improve social function in individuals with ASD.ACKNOWLEDGEMENTSThis work was supported by a grant from the Korean Health Technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, Republic of Korea (No. A120029).1KannerLAutistic disturbances of affective contactNerv Child194322172502American Psychiatric AssociationTask Force on Nomenclature and StatisticsAmerican Psychiatric AssociationCommittee on Nomenclature and StatisticsDiagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders3rd edWashington DCAmerican Psychiatric Association19803American Psychiatric AssociationAmerican Psychiatric AssociationDSM-5 Task ForceDiagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM-55th edWashington DCAmerican Psychiatric Association20134HuVWFrontiers in autism research: new horizons for diagnosis and treatmentHackensack, NJWorld Scientific Publishing Company20145PretiAMelisMSiddiSVellanteMDonedduGFaddaROxytocin and autism: a systematic review of randomized controlled trialsJ Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol2014245468246791736GhanizadehASahraeizadehABerkMA head-to-head comparison of aripiprazole and risperidone for safety and treating autistic disorders, a randomized double blind clinical trialChild Psychiatry Hum Dev201445185192238012567GiovagnoliGPostorinoVFattaLMSangesVDe PeppoLVassenaLRosePDVicariSMazzoneLBehavioral and emotional profile and parental stress in preschool children with autism spectrum disorderRes Dev Disabil201545-46411421263185058SahleyTLPankseppJBrain opioids and autism: an updated analysis of possible linkagesJ Autism Dev Disord19871720121630388369CampbellMAndersonLTSmallAMAdamsPGonzalezNMErnstMNaltrexone in autistic children: behavioral symptoms and attentional learningJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry19933212831291828267610ElchaarGMMaischNMAugustoLMWehringHJEfficacy and safety of naltrexone use in pediatric patients with autistic disorderAnn Pharmacother200640108610951673564811Willemsen-SwinkelsSHBuitelaarJKNijhofGJvan EnglandHFailure of naltrexone hydrochloride to reduce self-injurious and autistic behavior in mentally retarded adults. Double-blind placebo-controlled studiesArch Gen Psychiatry199552766773765412812FeldmanHMKolmenBKGonzagaAMNaltrexone and communication skills in young children with autismJ Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry1999385875931023019113SymonsFJThompsonARodriguezMCSelf-injurious behavior and the efficacy of naltrexone treatment: a quantitative synthesisMent Retard Dev Disabil Res Rev2004101932001561198214RoyARoyMDebSUnwinGRoyAAre opioid antagonists effective in attenuating the core symptoms of autism spectrum conditions in children: a systematic reviewJ Intellect Disabil Res2015592933062458934615HorvathKStefanatosGSokolskiKNWachtelRNaborsLTildonJTImproved social and language skills after secretin administration in patients with autistic spectrum disordersJ Assoc Acad Minor Phys19989915958567016TodaYMoriKHashimotoTMiyazakiMNozakiSWatanabeYKurodaYKagamiSAdministration of secretin for autism alters dopamine metabolism in the central nervous systemBrain Dev200628991031616859617WilliamsKWrayJAWheelerDMIntravenous secretin for autism spectrum disorders (ASD)Cochrane Database Syst Rev20124CD0034952251391318PedersenCAPrangeAJJrInduction of maternal behavior in virgin rats after intracerebroventricular administration of oxytocinProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1979766661666529375219InselTROxytocin--a neuropeptide for affiliation: evidence from behavioral, receptor autoradiographic, and comparative studiesPsychoneuroendocrinology199217335131907120InselTRYoungLWangZCentral oxytocin and reproductive behavioursRev Reprod199722837941446321WaterhouseLFeinDModahlCNeurofunctional mechanisms in autismPsychol Rev1996103457489875904422CarterCSNeuroendocrine perspectives on social attachment and lovePsychoneuroendocrinology199823779818992473823InselTRO'BrienDJLeckmanJFOxytocin, vasopressin, and autism: is there a connection?Biol Psychiatry199945145157995156124InselTRYoungLJThe neurobiology of attachmentNat Rev Neurosci200121291361125299225ShaoYWolpertCMRaifordKLMenoldMMDonnellySLRavanSABassMPMcClainCvon WendtLVanceJMAbramsonRHWrightHHAshley-KochAGilbertJRDeLongRGCuccaroMLPericak-VanceMAGenomic screen and follow-up analysis for autistic disorderAm J Med Genet2002114991051184051326WatanabeTAbeOKuwabaraHYahataNTakanoYIwashiroNNatsuboriTAokiYTakaoHKawakuboYKamioYKatoNMiyashitaYKasaiKYamasueHMitigation of sociocommunicational deficits of autism through oxytocin-induced recovery of medial prefrontal activity: a randomized trialJAMA Psychiatry2014711661752435237727AokiYYahataNWatanabeTTakanoYKawakuboYKuwabaraHIwashiroNNatsuboriTInoueHSugaMTakaoHSasakiHGonoiWKunimatsuAKasaiKYamasueHOxytocin improves behavioural and neural deficits in inferring others' social emotions in autismBrain2014137307330862514941228YoungLJBarrettCENeuroscience. Can oxytocin treat autism?Science20153478258262570050129InselTRShapiroLEOxytocin receptor distribution reflects social organization in monogamous and polygamous volesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A19928959815985132143030WilliamsJRInselTRHarbaughCRCarterCSOxytocin administered centrally facilitates formation of a partner preference in female prairie voles (Microtus ochrogaster)J Neuroendocrinol19946247250792059031YoungLJLimMMGingrichBInselTRCellular mechanisms of social attachmentHorm Behav2001401331381153497332ChristenssonKNilssonBAStockSMatthiesenASUvnäs-MobergKEffect of nipple stimulation on uterine activity and on plasma levels of oxytocin in full term, healthy, pregnant womenActa Obstet Gynecol Scand198968205210261860233CarmichaelMSHumbertRDixenJPalmisanoGGreenleafWDavidsonJMPlasma oxytocin increases in the human sexual responseJ Clin Endocrinol Metab1987642731378243434McCarthyMMAltemusMCentral nervous system actions of oxytocin and modulation of behavior in humansMol Med Today19973269275921141835YoungLJWangZThe neurobiology of pair bondingNat Neurosci20047104810541545257636BuchheimAHeinrichsMGeorgeCPokornyDKoopsEHenningsenPO'ConnorMFGündelHOxytocin enhances the experience of attachment securityPsychoneuroendocrinology200934141714221945761837NelsonEPankseppJOxytocin mediates acquisition of maternally associated odor preferences in preweanling rat pupsBehav Neurosci1996110583592888900338PedersenCAAscherJAMonroeYLPrangeAJJrOxytocin induces maternal behavior in virgin female ratsScience1982216648650707160539FlemingASRosenblattJSOlfactory regulation of maternal behavior in rats. II. Effects of peripherally induced anosmia and lesions of the lateral olfactory tract in pup-induced virginsJ Comp Physiol Psychol197486233246459049240YuGZKabaHOkutaniFTakahashiSHiguchiTSetoKThe action of oxytocin originating in the hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus on mitral and granule cells in the rat main olfactory bulbNeuroscience19967210731082873523041FergusonJNYoungLJHearnEFMatzukMMInselTRWinslowJTSocial amnesia in mice lacking the oxytocin geneNat Genet2000252842881088887442FergusonJNAldagJMInselTRYoungLJOxytocin in the medial amygdala is essential for social recognition in the mouseJ Neurosci200121827882851158819943SalaMBraidaDLentiniDBusnelliMBulgheroniECapurroVFinardiADonzelliAPattiniLRubinoTParolaroDNishimoriKParentiMChiniBPharmacologic rescue of impaired cognitive flexibility, social deficits, increased aggression, and seizure susceptibility in oxytocin receptor null mice: a neurobehavioral model of autismBiol Psychiatry2011698758822130670444DomesGHeinrichsMMichelABergerCHerpertzSCOxytocin improves "mind-reading" in humansBiol Psychiatry2007617317331713756145GuastellaAJMitchellPBDaddsMROxytocin increases gaze to the eye region of human facesBiol Psychiatry200863351788841046RimmeleUHedigerKHeinrichsMKlaverPOxytocin makes a face in memory familiarJ Neurosci20092938421912938247GuastellaAJMitchellPBMathewsFOxytocin enhances the encoding of positive social memories in humansBiol Psychiatry2008642562581834335348MarshAAYuHHPineDSBlairRJOxytocin improves specific recognition of positive facial expressionsPsychopharmacology (Berl)20102092252322018639749Di SimplicioMMassey-ChaseRCowenPJHarmerCJOxytocin enhances processing of positive versus negative emotional information in healthy male volunteersJ Psychopharmacol2009232412481880182950Fischer-ShoftyMShamay-TsoorySGHarariHLevkovitzYThe effect of intranasal administration of oxytocin on fear recognitionNeuropsychologia2010481791841974793051SavaskanEEhrhardtRSchulzAWalterMSchächingerHPost-learning intranasal oxytocin modulates human memory for facial identityPsychoneuroendocrinology2008333683741822183852RamosLHicksCKevinRCaminerANarlawarRKassiouMMcGregorISAcute prosocial effects of oxytocin and vasopressin when given alone or in combination with 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine in rats: involvement of the V1A receptorNeuropsychopharmacology201338224922592367679153TengBLNonnemanRJAgsterKLNikolovaVDDavisTTRiddickNVBakerLKPedersenCAJarstferMBMoySSProsocial effects of oxytocin in two mouse models of autism spectrum disordersNeuropharmacology2013721871962364374854KirschPEsslingerCChenQMierDLisSSiddhantiSGruppeHMattayVSGallhoferBMeyer-LindenbergAOxytocin modulates neural circuitry for social cognition and fear in humansJ Neurosci20052511489114931633904255PetrovicPKalischRSingerTDolanRJOxytocin attenuates affective evaluations of conditioned faces and amygdala activityJ Neurosci200828660766151857973356GamerMZurowskiBBüchelCDifferent amygdala subregions mediate valence-related and attentional effects of oxytocin in humansProc Natl Acad Sci USA2010107940094052042146957ModahlCGreenLFeinDMorrisMWaterhouseLFeinsteinCLevinHPlasma oxytocin levels in autistic childrenBiol Psychiatry199843270277951373658GreenLFeinDModahlCFeinsteinCWaterhouseLMorrisMOxytocin and autistic disorder: alterations in peptide formsBiol Psychiatry2001506096131169059659HeinrichsMDomesGNeuropeptides and social behaviour: effects of oxytocin and vasopressin in humansProg Brain Res20081703373501865589460YrigollenCMHanSSKochetkovaABabitzTChangJTVolkmarFRLeckmanJFGrigorenkoELGenes controlling affiliative behavior as candidate genes for autismBiol Psychiatry2008639119161820713461EbsteinRPIsraelSLererEUzefovskyFShalevIGritsenkoIRieboldMSalomonSYirmiyaNArginine vasopressin and oxytocin modulate human social behaviorAnn N Y Acad Sci20091167871021958055662HoveyDZettergrenAJonssonLMelkeJAnckarsäterHLichtensteinPWestbergLAssociations between oxytocin-related genes and autistic-like traitsSoc Neurosci201493783862463566063LoParoDWaldmanIDThe oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) is associated with autism spectrum disorder: a meta-analysisMol Psychiatry2015206406462509224564Di NapoliAWarrierVBaron-CohenSChakrabartiBGenetic variation in the oxytocin receptor (OXTR) gene is associated with Asperger SyndromeMol Autism20145482526447965JacobSBruneCWCarterCSLeventhalBLLordCCookEHJrAssociation of the oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) in Caucasian children and adolescents with autismNeurosci Lett2007417691738381966WuSJiaMRuanYLiuJGuoYShuangMGongXZhangYYangXZhangDPositive association of the oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) with autism in the Chinese Han populationBiol Psychiatry20055874771599252667ChakrabartiBDudbridgeFKentLWheelwrightSHill-CawthorneGAllisonCBanerjee-BasuSBaron-CohenSGenes related to sex steroids, neural growth, and social-emotional behavior are associated with autistic traits, empathy, and Asperger syndromeAutism Res200921571771959823568CampbellDBDattaDJonesSTBatey LeeESutcliffeJSHammockEALevittPAssociation of oxytocin receptor (OXTR) gene variants with multiple phenotype domains of autism spectrum disorderJ Neurodev Disord201131011122148420269LiuXKawamuraYShimadaTOtowaTKoishiSSugiyamaTNishidaHHashimotoONakagamiRTochigiMUmekageTKanoYMiyagawaTKatoNTokunagaKSasakiTAssociation of the oxytocin receptor (OXTR) gene polymorphisms with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) in the Japanese populationJ Hum Genet2010551371412009406470GregorySGConnellyJJTowersAJJohnsonJBiscochoDMarkunasCALintasCAbramsonRKWrightHHEllisPLangfordCFWorleyGDelongGRMurphySKCuccaroMLPersicoAPericak-VanceMAGenomic and epigenetic evidence for oxytocin receptor deficiency in autismBMC Med20097621984597271JackAConnellyJJMorrisJPDNA methylation of the oxytocin receptor gene predicts neural response to ambiguous social stimuliFront Hum Neurosci201262802308763472DeaglioSAydinSVaisittiTBerguiLMalavasiFCD38 at the junction between prognostic marker and therapeutic targetTrends Mol Med2008142102181840326573JinDLiuHXHiraiHTorashimaTNagaiTLopatinaOShnayderNAYamadaKNodaMSeikeTFujitaKTakasawaSYokoyamaSKoizumiKShiraishiYTanakaSHashiiMYoshiharaTHigashidaKIslamMSYamadaNHayashiKNoguchiNKatoIOkamotoHMatsushimaASalminaAMunesueTShimizuNMochidaSAsanoMHigashidaHCD38 is critical for social behaviour by regulating oxytocin secretionNature200744641451728772974MunesueTYokoyamaSNakamuraKAnithaAYamadaKHayashiKAsakaTLiuHXJinDKoizumiKIslamMSHuangJJMaWJKimUHKimSJParkKKimDKikuchiMOnoYNakataniHSudaSMiyachiTHiraiHSalminaAPichuginaYASoumarokovAATakeiNMoriNTsujiiMSugiyamaTYagiKYamagishiMSasakiTYamasueHKatoNHashimotoRTaniikeMHayashiYHamadaJSuzukiSOoiANodaMKamiyamaYKidoMALopatinaOHashiiMAminaSMalavasiFHuangEJZhangJShimizuNYoshikawaTMatsushimaAMinabeYHigashidaHTwo genetic variants of CD38 in subjects with autism spectrum disorder and controlsNeurosci Res2010671811912043536675RieboldMMankutaDLererEIsraelSZhongSNemanovLMonakhovMVLeviSYirmiyaNYaariMMalavasiFEbsteinRPAll-trans retinoic acid upregulates reduced CD38 transcription in lymphoblastoid cell lines from Autism spectrum disorderMol Med2011177998062152815576KrolKMMonakhovMLaiPSEbsteinRPGrossmannTGenetic variation in CD38 and breastfeeding experience interact to impact infants' attention to social eye cuesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A2015112E5434E54422637131377YamasueHPromising evidence and remaining issues regarding the clinical application of oxytocin in autism spectrum disordersPsychiatry Clin Neurosci2015(in press)78BornJLangeTKernWMcGregorGPBickelUFehmHLSniffing neuropeptides: a transnasal approach to the human brainNat Neurosci200255145161199211479GuastellaAJHickieIBMcGuinnessMMOtisMWoodsEADisingerHMChanHKChenTFBanatiRBRecommendations for the standardisation of oxytocin nasal administration and guidelines for its reporting in human researchPsychoneuroendocrinology2013386126252326531180HollanderENovotnySHanrattyMYaffeRDeCariaCMAronowitzBRMosovichSOxytocin infusion reduces repetitive behaviors in adults with autistic and Asperger's disordersNeuropsychopharmacology2003281931981249695681HollanderEBartzJChaplinWPhillipsASumnerJSooryaLAnagnostouEWassermanSOxytocin increases retention of social cognition in autismBiol Psychiatry2007614985031690465282GuastellaAJEinfeldSLGrayKMRinehartNJTongeBJLambertTJHickieIBIntranasal oxytocin improves emotion recognition for youth with autism spectrum disordersBiol Psychiatry2010676926941989717783GuastellaAJGrayKMRinehartNJAlvaresGATongeBJHickieIBKeatingCMCacciotti-SaijaCEinfeldSLThe effects of a course of intranasal oxytocin on social behaviors in youth diagnosed with autism spectrum disorders: a randomized controlled trialJ Child Psychol Psychiatry2015564444522508790884AnagnostouESooryaLBrianJDupuisAMankadDSmileSJacobSIntranasal oxytocin in the treatment of autism spectrum disorders: a review of literature and early safety and efficacy data in youthBrain Res201415801881982450857885WatanabeTKurodaMKuwabaraHAokiYIwashiroNTatsunobuNTakaoHNippashiYKawakuboYKunimatsuAKasaiKYamasueHClinical and neural effects of six-week administration of oxytocin on core symptoms of autismBrain2015138340034122633690986TachibanaMKagitani-ShimonoKMohriIYamamotoTSanefujiWNakamuraAOishiMKimuraTOnakaTOzonoKTaniikeMLong-term administration of intranasal oxytocin is a safe and promising therapy for early adolescent boys with autism spectrum disordersJ Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol2013231231272348032187AnagnostouESooryaLChaplinWBartzJHalpernDWassermanSWangATPepaLTanelNKushkiAHollanderEIntranasal oxytocin versus placebo in the treatment of adults with autism spectrum disorders: a randomized controlled trialMol Autism20123162321671688DaddsMRMacDonaldECauchiAWilliamsKLevyFBrennanJNasal oxytocin for social deficits in childhood autism: a randomized controlled trialJ Autism Dev Disord2014445215312388835989BalesKLPlotskyPMYoungLJLimMMGrotteNFerrerECarterCSNeonatal oxytocin manipulations have long-lasting, sexually dimorphic effects on vasopressin receptorsNeuroscience200714438451705517690NeumannIDSlatteryDAOxytocin in General Anxiety and Social Fear: A Translational ApproachBiol Psychiatry2015(in press)91AnsseauMLegrosJJMormontCCerfontaineJLPapartPGeenenVAdamFFranckGIntranasal oxytocin in obsessive-compulsive disorderPsychoneuroendocrinology198712231236361575292CabestreroDPérez-ParedesCFernández-CidRArribasMABronchospasm and laryngeal stridor as an adverse effect of oxytocin treatmentCrit Care200373921297497293GregorySGAnthopolosROsgoodCEGrotegutCAMirandaMLAssociation of autism with induced or augmented childbirth in North Carolina Birth Record (1990-1998) and Education Research (1997-2007) databasesJAMA Pediatr20131679599662393861094MacDonaldEDaddsMRBrennanJLWilliamsKLevyFCauchiAJA review of safety, side-effects and subjective reactions to intranasal oxytocin in human researchPsychoneuroendocrinology201136111411262142967195KimJWSeungHKwonKJKoMJLeeEJOhHAChoiCSKimKCGonzalesELYouJSChoiDHLeeJHanSHYangSMCheongJHShinCYBahnGHSubchronic treatment of donepezil rescues impaired social, hyperactive, and stereotypic behavior in valproic acid-induced animal model of autismPLoS One20149e1049272513371396EgashiraNTanoueAMatsudaTKoushiEHaradaSTakanoYTsujimotoGMishimaKIwasakiKFujiwaraMImpaired social interaction and reduced anxiety-related behavior in vasopressin V1a receptor knockout miceBehav Brain Res20071781231271722768497CarsonDSGarnerJPHydeSALiboveRABerquistSWHornbeakKBJacksonLPSumiyoshiRDHowertonCLHannahSLPartapSPhillipsJMHardanAYParkerKJArginine vasopressin is a blood-based biomarker of social functioning in children with autismPLoS One201510e01322242620085298OcskóTGálfiMRadácsMMolnárZKisGKRákosiKMolnárAHLászlóFLászlóFAVargaCEffects of orexin-monoaminergic interactions on oxytocin secretion in rat neurohypophyseal cell culturesRegul Pept201217543482228080199ModiMEYoungLJThe oxytocin system in drug discovery for autism: animal models and novel therapeutic strategiesHorm Behav20126134035022206823100IzdebskaKCiosekJGalanin influences on vasopressin and oxytocin release: in vitro studiesNeuropeptides20104434134820466422101PeñagarikanoOLázaroMTLuXHGordonADongHLamHAPelesEMaidmentNTMurphyNPYangXWGolshaniPGeschwindDHExogenous and evoked oxytocin restores social behavior in the Cntnap2 mouse model of autismSci Transl Med20157271ra8102ModiMEInoueKBarrettCEKittelbergerKASmithDGLandgrafRYoungLJMelanocortin receptor agonists facilitate oxytocin-dependent partner preference formation in the prairie voleNeuropsychopharmacology2015401856186525652247Table 1Promising genes for investigating the mechanism of autism spectrum disorderASD: autism spectrum disorder; HFA: high functioning autism; SNP: single nucleotide polymorphism.Table 2Results of randomized placebo controlled trials with oxytocin in autism spectrum disorder grouped by administration routeAS: Asperger's syndrome; ASD: autism spectrum disorder; HFA: high functioning autism.
