<?xml version="1.0"?>
Neuroimage ClinNeuroimage ClinNeuroImage : Clinical2213-1582Elsevier3777795S2213-1582(13)00032-610.1016/j.nicl.2013.03.011ArticleNeural mechanisms of symptom improvements in generalized anxiety disorder following mindfulness training☆☆☆HölzelBritta K.britta@nmr.mgh.harvard.eduab⁎1HogeElizabeth A.ehoge@partners.orga1GreveDouglas N.greve@nmr.mgh.harvard.edua1GardTimtgard@nmr.mgh.harvard.eduab1CreswellJ. Davidcreswell@cmu.educBrownKirk Warrenkwbrown@vcu.edudBarrettLisa Feldmanl.barrett@neu.eduae1SchwartzCarlcarl_Schwartz@hms.harvard.edua1VaitlDietervaitl@bion.debLazarSara W.lazar@nmr.mgh.harvard.edua1aMassachusetts General Hospital, 120 2nd Ave., Charlestown, MA, 02129, USAbBender Institute of Neuroimaging, Justus-Liebig University, Otto-Behaghel-Str. 10H, 35394 Giessen, GermanycDepartment of Psychology, Carnegie Melon University, 5000 Forbes Ave., Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USAdDepartment of Psychology, Virginia Commonwealth University, 806 West Franklin Street, Richmond, VA, 23284, USAeDepartment of Psychology, Northeastern University, Boston, MA, 02115, USA⁎Corresponding author at: Bender Institute of Neuroimaging, Otto-Behaghel-Str. 10H, 35394 Giessen, Germany. Tel.: + 1 617 724 2256; fax: + 1 617 643 7340. britta@nmr.mgh.harvard.edu1Tel.: + 1 617 724 2256; fax: + 1 617 643 7340.25320132532013201324484582711201213320131732013© 2013 The Authors2013This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.Mindfulness training aims to impact emotion regulation. Generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) symptoms can be successfully addressed through mindfulness-based interventions. This preliminary study is the first to investigate neural mechanisms of symptom improvements in GAD following mindfulness training. Furthermore, we compared brain activation between GAD patients and healthy participants at baseline. 26 patients with a current DSM-IV GAD diagnosis were randomized to an 8-week Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction (MBSR, N = 15) or a stress management education (SME, N = 11) active control program. 26 healthy participants were included for baseline comparisons. BOLD response was assessed with fMRI during affect labeling of angry and neutral facial expressions. At baseline, GAD patients showed higher amygdala activation than healthy participants in response to neutral, but not angry faces, suggesting that ambiguous stimuli reveal stronger reactivity in GAD patients. In patients, amygdala activation in response to neutral faces decreased following both interventions. BOLD response in ventrolateral prefrontal regions (VLPFC) showed greater increase in MBSR than SME participants. Functional connectivity between amygdala and PFC regions increased significantly pre- to post-intervention within the MBSR, but not SME group. Both, change in VLPFC activation and amygdala–prefrontal connectivity were correlated with change in Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) scores, suggesting clinical relevance of these changes. Amygdala–prefrontal connectivity turned from negative coupling (typically seen in down-regulation of emotions), to positive coupling; potentially suggesting a unique mechanism of mindfulness. Findings suggest that in GAD, mindfulness training leads to changes in fronto-limbic areas crucial for the regulation of emotion; these changes correspond with reported symptom improvements.Highlights•GAD patients show higher amygdala activation to neutral faces than healthy subjects.•In GAD patients, amygdala activation decreased after stress reduction interventions.•Ventrolateral PFC activation during affect labeling increases following mindfulness.•Amygdala–PFC functional connectivity increases following mindfulness.•These changes following mindfulness correlate with improvements in anxiety symptoms.KeywordsGeneralized anxiety disorderEmotion regulationMindfulnessInterventionLongitudinalAmygdalaPrefrontal cortexConnectivityVentrolateral prefrontal cortexBeck Anxiety InventoryStress1IntroductionGeneralized anxiety disorder (GAD) is characterized by pervasive and intrusive worry (American Psychiatric Association, 2000), and is associated with impairment in daily functioning. Individuals with GAD show deficits in emotion regulation (Tull et al., 2009), such as a greater negative reactivity to, and poorer understanding of emotions (Mennin et al., 2005). Psychological treatments therefore aim to help clients to become more comfortable with arousing emotional experiences and foster better emotion regulation (Mennin et al., 2002). Mindfulness-based interventions, which focus on the cultivation of attention to present moment experiences with an attitude of openness and non-judgmental (Bishop et al., 2004; Kabat-Zinn, 1990), directly address such deficits. They have been shown to effectively ameliorate anxiety symptoms (Hofmann et al., 2010), and have been successfully applied in the treatment of GAD (Hoge et al., in press; Roemer et al., 2008). While mindfulness-based interventions are increasingly applied in the therapeutic context (Baer, 2003; Grossman et al., 2004), the investigation of the neurobiology underlying the beneficial effects is still in its infancy (Davidson et al., 2003; Farb et al., 2010; Gard et al., 2012; Goldin and Gross, 2010; Goldin et al., 2012; Hölzel et al., 2010). To date, the neural mechanisms underlying the effects of mindfulness-based interventions on GAD have not been studied.Models of various anxiety disorders hypothesize amygdala hyperresponsivity to threat-related stimuli (Etkin and Wager, 2007; Rauch et al., 2003). However, it has not been unambiguously established how brain activation in response to evocative stimuli differentiates GAD patients from healthy participants (Etkin, 2011). A few GAD studies have found that consciously presented threatening stimuli (posed facial expressions) do not evoke amygdala hyperactivation (Blair et al., 2008; Monk et al., 2006; Palm et al., 2011; Whalen et al., 2008). In one study, viewing posed angry faces was even associated with amygdala hypoactivation in these patients (Blair et al., 2008). However, adolescents with GAD showed exaggerated amygdala activation in response to nonconsciously presented angry faces (Monk et al., 2008), and adult GAD patients show greater amygdala activation during anticipation of seeing aversive or neutral pictures (Nitschke et al., 2009) suggesting that GAD patients may be more sensitive to ambiguous stimuli than to overtly threatening stimuli.2Anxiety symptoms have also been associated with abnormalities in prefrontal activation and altered relationships between activity of prefrontal regions and amygdala (Kim et al., 2011a, 2011b). For example, stronger activation of the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex (VLPFC) in response to angry faces has been reported in GAD patients as compared to healthy controls, and greater VLPFC activation has been associated with less severe anxiety in these patients (Monk et al., 2006). There is speculation that enhanced VLPFC activation in GAD patients serves a compensatory response designed to regulate abnormal function (Monk et al., 2006). Interestingly, treatment of GAD with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) or cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) has been shown to increase VLPFC activation (Maslowsky et al., 2010). These findings suggest that increased VLPFC activation in GAD is part of a compensatory mechanism that can be enhanced by treatment. The VLPFC is involved in inhibitory control (Cohen et al., 2013) and its activation typically increases when healthy subjects voluntarily downregulate unpleasant emotions (Ochsner et al., 2004; Phan et al., 2005; Wager et al., 2008). It modulates amygdala responses during strategic emotion regulation processes (Hariri et al., 2003; Ochsner and Gross, 2005), and it has been speculated that breakdowns in amygdala–VLPFC interactions might influence anxiety (Hariri et al., 2003). GAD patients show weaker coupling between the VLPFC and amygdala than healthy controls (Etkin et al., 2009; Monk et al., 2008), suggesting modified connectivity between these two regions. Other prefrontal regions, too, have shown abnormal – decreased and increased – connectivity with the amygdala in GAD (Etkin et al., 2009) and in heightened state anxiety (Kim et al., 2011b).Labeling the affect of encountered stimuli, such as facial expressions, has been suggested to be an incidental emotion regulation process that helps attenuate distress (Lieberman et al., 2011) and to diminish anxiety in a clinical context (Kircanski et al., 2012; Tabibnia et al., 2008). Several fMRI studies have reported that explicitly labeling an evocative stimulus can lead to reduced amygdala response (Foland et al., 2008; Hariri et al., 2000; Lieberman et al., 2007) and increase activation in the VLPFC (Lieberman et al., 2007). Interestingly, in a study on the neural correlates of trait mindfulness, Creswell et al. found that higher trait mindfulness was related to greater activation of prefrontal areas, including ventrolateral and medial regions, lower amygdala activation, and greater amygdala–prefrontal connectivity during affect labeling (Creswell et al., 2007), suggesting a potential neural mechanism of mindfulness training. Given the implication of these same neural regions in GAD, we investigated whether prefrontal and amygdala activation and amygdala–prefrontal connectivity would be modified during affect labeling in GAD patients following mindfulness training. Since mindfulness works through enhanced recognition of emotional states, the affect labeling task was chosen in order to expose the beneficial effects of this training.The present randomized trial is an initial investigation of neural mechanisms underlying GAD symptom improvements following an eight-week mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR (Kabat-Zinn, 1990)) program relative to a structurally equivalent, active control intervention. We measured brain activity with fMRI during the explicit labeling of posed emotional expressions (neutral and angry) both before and after intervention in both GAD groups and in comparison to a reference group of healthy controls. We explored whether 1) GAD patients would show altered amygdala responses to angry and neutral faces compared with healthy participants, 2) GAD patients receiving the MBSR intervention would show greater attenuation in amygdala response compared to the control intervention, 3) GAD patients receiving MBSR would show a greater increase of prefrontal activation, as well as stronger increases in amygdala–prefrontal functional connectivity, compared to the control intervention, and 4) changes in brain activation and functional connectivity would be related to reduced anxiety symptoms.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Participants</title><p>29 GAD patients were recruited to participate in the MRI study. Participants were assigned to either the MBSR program or the active control intervention, the stress management education (SME) program, based on the time of enrolment into the study (block randomization); 15 were allocated to the MBSR group, and 14 to the SME group. Three subjects in the SME group dropped out (one moved out of town, one had a panic attack in the scanner, and one did not complete the class). Complete data sets were thus available from 26 GAD patients. Furthermore, 26 healthy demographically matched individuals were included for baseline comparisons.</p><p>GAD patients were recruited from among participants of a larger RCT (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Hoge et al., in press</xref>). Healthy participants were recruited through local newspapers and email lists advertising a stress-reduction intervention. All participants were right-handed, had no significant previous meditation experience (≤ 10 sessions) and complied with scanner safety requirements. The groups did not significantly differ in age, gender, and education level (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). All participants were assessed with the Structured Clinical Instrument for DSM-IV (SCID (<xref rid="bb0480" ref-type="bibr">First et al., 2002</xref>)) by a trained clinician. Healthy participants were included if they did not meet any DSM-IV Axis I disorder, and did not take medications that alter cerebral blood flow or metabolism. Patients were included if they met a current DSM-IV GAD diagnosis. Four participants additionally met a diagnosis for comorbid major depressive disorder (MBSR group: 3), one for panic disorder (in the control group), and six for social anxiety disorder (SAD; MBSR group: 5).<xref rid="fn0015" ref-type="fn">3</xref> Four patients were medicated (MBSR group: 3), three on daily SSRIs, and one taking trazodone twice a week for insomnia. Medicated subjects were included if they had been on a stable dose for at least two months prior to enrollment and agreed to remain on a stable dose over the participation period. Participants provided written informed consent. The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Massachusetts General Hospital.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Interventions</title><p>Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction (MBSR) is an eight-week, manualized program that was designed specifically to increase mindfulness (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Kabat-Zinn, 1990</xref>). The program was developed to inculcate emotion regulatory skills to prevent stress and associated mental health problems. It consists of once-weekly, teacher-led group meetings (with duration of two hours in the current study) plus one “day of mindfulness” in the sixth week of the course. During these group sessions, mindfulness is trained via sitting and walking meditation, yoga exercises, and the “body scan”, in which attention is sequentially directed through the whole body. Participants also receive stress education. In addition to the group sessions, participants are instructed to practice mindfulness exercises at home (with the help of an audio recording). They are taught to practice mindfulness also in their daily activities, such as eating, washing the dishes, taking a shower, etc., as a way to facilitate the transfer of mindfulness into daily life.</p><p>The stress management education (SME) program was designed as an active control stress reduction intervention for MBSR to disentangle the effects of the mindfulness practice from other, potentially effective elements of the group program, such as a supportive social environment, instructor attention, participants' expectations, and physical exercise. The course has the same in-class and home exercise time as the MBSR program, including a ‘day of stress reduction’ in the 6th week, and is composed of several elements that match the MBSR components. Gentle physical exercises match the yoga component and nutrition and healthy lifestyle education components match the stress education component of MBSR. The SME program is described in detail elsewhere (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Hoge et al., in press</xref>).</p><p>The MBSR group showed greater average compliance with home practice assignments (average = 1116 min, SD = 499 min) than the SME group (average = 868 min, SD = 413 min), but this difference was not significant (<italic>t</italic>(24) = − 1.34, p = .19). There was also no group difference in the number of classes attended (MBSR average = 7.27, SD = .59; SME average = 7.00, SD = .76; <italic>t</italic>(24) = − 1.00, p = .33). Finally, there was no group difference in the number of participants who missed the retreat day (MBSR: 4 out of 15; SME: 1 out of 11; Fisher's exact test, p = .274).</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Experimental paradigm</title><p>Healthy and GAD participants underwent MRI scanning at a baseline timepoint (‘pre’ intervention), and GAD patients completed the same MRI procedures following the interventions (‘post’). While undergoing fMRI scanning, participants labeled the affect of photographs of angry, happy, and neutral facial expressions from a standardized set (<xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Tottenham et al., 2009</xref>). The BOLD response to viewing angry, neutral, and happy faces was compared to a fixation cross control condition. Within each of five blocks, nine pictures of each emotional category were presented in random order and were displayed for four seconds each with varying inter-stimulus intervals. Each face was displayed only once to avoid repetition and familiarity effects. Additional fixation cross resting blocks of 20 s were included after each block. Participants indicated facial affect (affect labeling) by choosing from a pair of labels (e.g., the words ‘angry’ and ‘neutral’) shown below the target face with a button press response. Of note, participants were not instructed to be mindful during the task. The experiment also included a condition wherein subjects labeled the gender of the face. This condition was used only to assess comparability of our baseline findings of healthy participants (comparison affect vs. gender labeling) with previous findings from the field of affect labeling research. For all other analyses, gender labeling conditions were not included, rather contrasts were calculated with the fixation cross condition. This approach was chosen because a) the longitudinal approach already provides a control contrast, where each individual's post data is compared to their own baseline measure, b) responses to gender labeling might also change with the interventions, thereby introducing unnecessary confounds, and c) some subjects reported mentally noting both gender and affect during the gender labeling condition, potentially introducing bleed-over confounds. The scans took place within three weeks before and after the intervention period. The groups did not significantly differ in amount of time between scanning sessions (MBSR mean = 60.3 days, SD = 4.4 days; SME mean = 63.5 days, SD = 6.8 days; independent samples <italic>t</italic>-test: <italic>t</italic>(24) = 1.46, p = .16).</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Self-report data</title><p>The Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI (<xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">Beck and Steer, 1993</xref>)) is a widely used 21-item multiple choice questionnaire assessing anxiety severity. GAD patients completed the BAI before and after the intervention. Results regarding symptom improvements measured with the BAI have been reported elsewhere (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Hoge et al., in press</xref>). Here, we report these scores as they relate to the imaging findings.</p><p>The 10-item version of the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) is a validated measure assessing the level of subjective life stresses (<xref rid="bb0245 bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Cohen and Williamson, 1988; Cohen et al., 1983</xref>). Complete data sets were obtained from 25 healthy and 26 GAD participants. Questionnaire data were analyzed with SPSS (<xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">SPSS, 2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.5</label><title>fMRI data acquisition and analysis</title><p>Data were acquired with a Siemens Magnetom Avanto 1.5 Tesla MRI scanner (Siemens Medical Systems, Erlangen, Germany). Structural images of the whole brain were collected using a T1 weighted MPRAGE-sequence, consisting of 128 sagittal slices (1.0 × 1.0 × 1.3 mm, TI = 1000 ms; TE = 3.39 ms; TR = 2730 ms). Functional data were acquired across the whole brain using a T2*-weighted gradient echo planar pulse sequence (25 axial slices, 5 mm thickness with no gap, voxel size: 3.1 × 3.1 × 5 mm, TR = 2000 ms, TE = 40 ms, flip angle = 90°, interleaved).</p><p>To enable surface-based analysis of fMRI data, anatomical data were processed using FreeSurfer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu" id="ir0035">https://surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu</ext-link>) to construct models of the cortical surfaces for each subject (<xref rid="bb0255 bb0260" ref-type="bibr">Dale et al., 1999; Fischl et al., 1999a</xref>). These were then registered to a surface-based group template (<xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Fischl et al., 1999b</xref>), and aligned with the MNI305 brain (<xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">Collins et al., 1995</xref>). fMRI data was analyzed with FS-FAST (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu/fswiki/FsFast" id="ir0040">https://surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu/fswiki/FsFast</ext-link>). Preprocessing involved motion correction using the AFNI (afni.nimh.nih.gov/afni) 3dvolreg program (<xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">Cox and Jesmanowicz, 1999</xref>), and slice-timing using the FSL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl" id="ir0045">www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl</ext-link>) slicetimer program. Non-brain voxels were masked out using the FSL Brain Extraction Tool (<xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 2002</xref>). The middle timepoint was registered to the subject's anatomical image using the FreeSurfer bbregister program (<xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr">Greve and Fischl, 2009</xref>). Using this registration, the raw fMRI time series was mapped to the three group analysis spaces: (1) left and (2) right hemisphere group surface space, and (3) MNI305 space within a subcortical mask of gray matter structures. Data was spatially smoothed on the surface by 5 mm full-width/half-max (FWHM) using an iterative technique (<xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">Hagler et al., 2006</xref>), and in the volume using a 3D smoothing kernel of 5 mm FWHM.</p><p>First-level time series analysis was performed using a General Linear Model (<xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr">Worsley et al., 2002</xref>) as implemented in FS-FAST. The hemodynamic response to each experimental condition (neutral, angry, and happy faces, instruction) was modeled using a difference of gamma functions (<xref rid="bb0300" ref-type="bibr">Glover, 1999</xref>). Low frequency drift was accounted for using a 2nd order polynomial and temporal whitening (<xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr">Burock and Dale, 2000</xref>). First-level contrasts were then carried up to the group level random effect analysis. Two masks were created to restrict multiple comparison corrections to: (1) bilateral amygdalae in volume space (<xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">Fischl et al., 2002</xref>), and (2) frontal cortex in the surface space (excluding the precentral gyrus and paracentral lobule) plus insula, based on the regions defined by <xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr">Desikan et al. (2006)</xref>. Exploratory analyses across the whole brain were also performed. For each analysis space (i.e., left and right hemispheres and subcortical areas), we applied a cluster-based correction for multiple comparisons using a simulation-based technique (<xref rid="bb0290 bb0320" ref-type="bibr">Hagler et al., 2006; Hayasaka and Nichols, 2003</xref>), using a cluster-forming threshold of p &lt; 0.05.</p><p>Furthermore, a standard connectivity analysis examined interactions between the chosen seed and the prefrontal cortex. The seed was selected based on voxels in the amygdala that showed decreased activation from pre- to post-intervention (see <xref rid="s0040" ref-type="sec">Results</xref>) in both groups. These voxels were mapped back into each individual and used to average the functional time series. This waveform was then correlated with all other voxels in the bilateral prefrontal cortex (global signal, white matter signal, ventricle-CSF signal and motion parameters were included as nuisance variables). The map of regression coefficients was then used for higher-level group analysis. For post-hoc analyses and the analysis of correlations with PSS and BAI scores, values for clusters that were extracted were reported below and Spearman's ρ was calculated in SPSS (<xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">SPSS, 2004</xref>). P-values for all correlations are reported uncorrected.</p></sec></sec>ReferencesAmerican Psychiatric AssociationDiagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders4th ed., text revision2000American Psychiatric AssociationWashington, DCBaerR.A.Mindfulness training as a clinical intervention: a conceptual and empirical reviewClinical Psychology Science and Practice102003125143BanksS.J.EddyK.T.AngstadtM.NathanP.J.PhanK.L.Amygdala–frontal connectivity during emotion-regulationSocial Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience2200730331218985136BeckA.T.SteerR.A.Beck Anxiety Inventory Manual1993Psychological CorporationSan Antonio, TXBeharE.DiMarcoI.D.HeklerE.B.MohlmanJ.StaplesA.M.Current theoretical models of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD): conceptual review and treatment implicationsJournal of Anxiety Disorders2320091011102319700258BishopS.R.LauM.ShapiroS.CarlsonL.E.AndersonN.D.CarmodyJ.Mindfulness: a proposed operational definitionClinical Psychology Science and Practice112004230241BlackfordJ.U.AveryS.N.CowanR.L.SheltonR.C.ZaldD.H.Sustained amygdala response to both novel and newly familiar faces characterizes inhibited temperamentSocial Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience6201062162920660534BlairK.ShaywitzJ.SmithB.W.RhodesR.GeraciM.JonesM.Response to emotional expressions in generalized social phobia and generalized anxiety disorder: evidence for separate disordersThe American Journal of Psychiatry16520081193120218483136BorkovecT.D.The nature, functions, and origins of worryGCDFTWorrying: Perspectives on Theory, Assessment, and Treatment Sussex1994Wiley &amp; SonsEngland533BorkovecT.D.AlcaineO.M.BeharE.Avoidance theory of worry and generalized anxiety disorderHeimbergR.TurkC.MenninD.Generalized Anxiety Disorder: Advances in Research and Practice2004Guilford PressNew York, NY, US77108BradleyM.M.SabatinelliD.LangP.J.FitzsimmonsJ.R.KingW.DesaiP.Activation of the visual cortex in motivated attentionBehavioral Neuroscience117200336938012708533BreiterH.C.RauchS.L.Functional MRI and the study of OCD: from symptom provocation to cognitive-behavioral probes of cortico-striatal systems and the amygdalaNeuroImage41996S127S1389345537BucknerR.L.Andrews-HannaJ.R.SchacterD.L.The brain's default network: anatomy, function, and relevance to diseaseAnnals of the New York Academy of Sciences1124200813818400922BurockM.A.DaleA.M.Estimation and detection of event-related fMRI signals with temporally correlated noise: a statistically efficient and unbiased approachHuman Brain Mapping11200024926011144754CohenS.WilliamsonG.M.Perceived stress in a probability sample of the United StatesSpacapanS.OskampS.The Social Psychology of Health1988SageNewbury Park, CA3167CohenS.KamarckT.MermelsteinR.A global measure of perceived stressJournal of Health and Social Behavior2419833853966668417CohenJ.R.BerkmanE.T.LiebermanM.D.Intentional and incidental self-control in ventrolateral PFCStussD.T.KnightR.T.Principles of Frontal Lobe Function2nd ed2013Oxford University PressNew York417440CollinsD.DaiW.PetersT.EvansA.Automatic 3D model-based neuroanatomical segmentationHuman Brain Mapping31995190208CoxR.W.JesmanowiczA.Real-time 3D image registration for functional MRIMagnetic Resonance in Medicine4219991014101810571921CreswellJ.D.WayB.M.EisenbergerN.I.LiebermanM.D.Neural correlates of dispositional mindfulness during affect labelingPsychosomatic Medicine69200756056517634566CritchleyH.D.Neural mechanisms of autonomic, affective, and cognitive integrationThe Journal of Comparative Neurology493200515416616254997DaleA.M.FischlB.SerenoM.I.Cortical surface-based analysis. I. Segmentation and surface reconstructionNeuroImage919991791949931268DavidsonR.J.Kabat-ZinnJ.SchumacherJ.RosenkranzM.MullerD.SantorelliS.F.Alterations in brain and immune function produced by mindfulness meditationPsychosomatic Medicine65200356457012883106DesbordesG.NegiL.T.PaceT.W.W.WallaceB.A.RaisonC.L.SchwartzE.L.Effects of mindful-attention and compassion meditation training on amygdala response to emotional stimuli in an ordinary, non-meditative stateFrontiers in Human Neuroscience6201229223125828DesikanR.S.SegonneF.FischlB.QuinnB.T.DickersonB.C.BlackerD.An automated labeling system for subdividing the human cerebral cortex on MRI scans into gyral based regions of interestNeuroImage31200696898016530430DugasM.J.GagnonF.LadouceurR.FreestonM.H.Generalized anxiety disorder: a preliminary test of a conceptual modelBehaviour Research and Therapy3619982152269613027EtkinA.Functional neuroanatomy of anxiety: a neural circuit perspectiveCurrent Topics in Behavioral Neurosciences2201125127721309113EtkinA.WagerT.D.Functional neuroimaging of anxiety: a meta-analysis of emotional processing in PTSD, social anxiety disorder, and specific phobiaThe American Journal of Psychiatry16420071476148817898336EtkinA.EgnerT.PerazaD.M.KandelE.R.HirschJ.Resolving emotional conflict: a role for the rostral anterior cingulate cortex in modulating activity in the amygdalaNeuron51200687188216982430EtkinA.PraterK.E.SchatzbergA.F.MenonV.GreiciusM.D.Disrupted amygdalar subregion functional connectivity and evidence of a compensatory network in generalized anxiety disorderArchives of General Psychiatry6620091361137219996041EvansK.C.WrightC.I.WedigM.M.GoldA.L.PollackM.H.RauchS.L.A functional MRI study of amygdala responses to angry schematic faces in social anxiety disorderDepression and Anxiety25200849650517595018EysenckM.W.MoggK.MayJ.RichardsA.MathewsA.Bias in interpretation of ambiguous sentences related to threat in anxietyJournal of Abnormal Psychology10019911441502040764FarbN.A.AndersonA.K.MaybergH.BeanJ.McKeonD.SegalZ.V.Minding one's emotions: mindfulness training alters the neural expression of sadnessEmotion102010253320141299FirstM.B.SpitzerR.L.GibbonM.WilliamsJ.B.W.Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV-TR Axis I Disorders, Research Version, Patient Edition (SCID-I/P)2002Biometrics Research, New York State Psychiatric InstituteNew YorkFischlB.SerenoM.I.DaleA.M.Cortical surface-based analysis. II: inflation, flattening, and a surface-based coordinate systemNeuroImage919991952079931269FischlB.SerenoM.I.TootellR.B.DaleA.M.High-resolution intersubject averaging and a coordinate system for the cortical surfaceHuman Brain Mapping8199927228410619420FischlB.SalatD.H.BusaE.AlbertM.DieterichM.HaselgroveC.Whole brain segmentation: automated labeling of neuroanatomical structures in the human brainNeuron33200234135511832223FolandL.C.AltshulerL.L.BookheimerS.Y.EisenbergerN.TownsendJ.ThompsonP.M.Evidence for deficient modulation of amygdala response by prefrontal cortex in bipolar maniaPsychiatry Research1622008273718063349FrescoD.M.MooreM.T.van DulmenM.H.SegalZ.V.MaS.H.TeasdaleJ.D.Initial psychometric properties of the experiences questionnaire: validation of a self-report measure of decenteringBehavior Therapy38200723424617697849GardT.HölzelB.K.SackA.T.HempelH.LazarS.W.VaitlD.Pain attenuation through mindfulness is associated with decreased cognitive control and increased sensory processing in the brainCerebral Cortex221120122692270222172578GloverG.H.Deconvolution of impulse response in event-related BOLD fMRINeuroImage9199941642910191170GoldinP.R.GrossJ.J.Effects of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) on emotion regulation in social anxiety disorderEmotion102010839120141305GoldinP.ZivM.JazaieriH.HahnK.GrossJ.J.MBSR vs. aerobic exercise in social anxiety: fMRI of emotion regulation of negative self-beliefsSocial Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience812013657222586252GreveD.N.FischlB.Accurate and robust brain image alignment using boundary-based registrationNeuroImage482009637219573611Grill-SpectorK.KnoufN.KanwisherN.The fusiform face area subserves face perception, not generic within-category identificationNature Neuroscience72004555562Grill-SpectorK.KourtziZ.KanwisherN.The lateral occipital complex and its role in object recognitionVision Research4120111409142211322983GrossmanP.NiemannL.SchmidtS.WalachH.Mindfulness-based stress reduction and health benefits. A meta-analysisJournal of Psychosomatic Research572004354315256293HaglerD.J.Jr.SayginA.P.SerenoM.I.Smoothing and cluster thresholding for cortical surface-based group analysis of fMRI dataNeuroImage3320061093110317011792HaririA.R.BookheimerS.Y.MazziottaJ.C.Modulating emotional responses: effects of a neocortical network on the limbic systemNeuroReport112000434810683827HaririA.R.MattayV.S.TessitoreA.FeraF.WeinbergerD.R.Neocortical modulation of the amygdala response to fearful stimuliBiological Psychiatry53200349450112644354HayasakaS.NicholsT.E.Validating cluster size inference: random field and permutation methodsNeuroImage2020032343235614683734HofmannS.G.SawyerA.T.WittA.A.OhD.The effect of mindfulness-based therapy on anxiety and depression: a meta-analytic reviewJournal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology78201016918320350028Hoge, E.A., Bui, E., Marques, L., Metcalf, C.A., Morris, L.K., Robinaugh, D.J., Worthington, J.J., Pollack, M.H., Simon, N.M., in press. Randomized Controlled Trial of Mindfulness Meditation for Generalized Anxiety Disorder: Effects on Anxiety and Stress Reactivity. Journal of Clinical Psychiatry.HölzelB.K.CarmodyJ.EvansK.C.HogeE.A.DusekJ.A.MorganL.Stress reduction correlates with structural changes in the amygdalaSocial Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience52010111719776221Kabat-ZinnJ.Full Catastrophe Living1990Delta PublishingNew YorkKimJ.J.AndreasenN.C.O'LearyD.S.WiserA.K.PontoL.L.B.WatkinsG.L.HichwaR.D.Direct comparison of the neural substrates of recognition memory for words and facesBrain12219991069108310356060KimM.J.LoucksR.A.PalmerA.L.BrownA.C.SolomonK.M.MarchanteA.N.The structural and functional connectivity of the amygdala: from normal emotion to pathological anxietyBehavioural Brain Research223201140341021536077KimM.J.GeeD.G.LoucksR.A.DavisF.C.WhalenP.J.Anxiety dissociates dorsal and ventral medial prefrontal cortex functional connectivity with the amygdala at restCerebral Cortex2120111667167321127016KircanskiK.LiebermanM.D.CraskeM.G.Feelings into words: contributions of language to exposure therapyPsychological Science231020121086109122902568LeeH.HellerA.S.van ReekumC.M.NelsonB.DavidsonR.J.Amygdala–prefrontal coupling underlies individual differences in emotion regulationNeuroImage6220121575158122634856LiebermanM.D.EisenbergerN.I.CrockettM.J.TomS.M.PfeiferJ.H.WayB.M.Putting feelings into words: affect labeling disrupts amygdala activity in response to affective stimuliPsychological Science18200742142817576282LiebermanM.D.InagakiT.K.TabibniaG.CrockettM.J.Subjective responses to emotional stimuli during labeling, reappraisal, and distractionEmotion11201146848021534661MacCoonD.SullivanJ.LutzA.StoneyC.M.JohnsonL.L.ChristmasP.Health-enhancement program (HEP) guidelines2008MaslowskyJ.MoggK.BradleyB.P.McClure-ToneE.ErnstM.PineD.S.A preliminary investigation of neural correlates of treatment in adolescents with generalized anxiety disorderJournal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology20201010511120415605MathewsA.RichardsA.EysenckM.Interpretation of homophones related to threat in anxiety statesJournal of Abnormal Psychology98198931342708637MenninD.S.HeimbergR.G.TurkC.L.FrescoD.M.Applying an emotion regulation framework to integrative approaches to generalized anxiety disorderClinical Psychology Science and Practice92002MenninD.S.HeimbergR.G.TurkC.L.FrescoD.M.Preliminary evidence for an emotion dysregulation model of generalized anxiety disorderBehaviour Research and Therapy4320051281131016086981MonkC.S.NelsonE.E.McClureE.B.MoggK.BradleyB.P.LeibenluftE.Ventrolateral prefrontal cortex activation and attentional bias in response to angry faces in adolescents with generalized anxiety disorderThe American Journal of Psychiatry16320061091109716741211MonkC.S.TelzerE.H.MoggK.BradleyB.P.MaiX.LouroH.M.Amygdala and ventrolateral prefrontal cortex activation to masked angry faces in children and adolescents with generalized anxiety disorderArchives of General Psychiatry65200856857618458208NitschkeJ.B.SarinopoulosI.OathesD.J.JohnstoneT.WhalenP.J.DavidsonR.J.Anticipatory activation in the amygdala and anterior cingulate in generalized anxiety disorder and prediction of treatment responseThe American Journal of Psychiatry166200930231019122007OchsnerK.N.GrossJ.J.The cognitive control of emotionTrends in Cognitive Sciences9200524224915866151OchsnerK.N.RayR.D.CooperJ.C.RobertsonE.R.ChopraS.GabrieliJ.D.For better or for worse: neural systems supporting the cognitive down- and up-regulation of negative emotionNeuroImage23200448349915488398PalmM.E.ElliottR.McKieS.DeakinJ.F.AndersonI.M.Attenuated responses to emotional expressions in women with generalized anxiety disorderPsychological Medicine4120111009101820716396PhanK.L.FitzgeraldD.A.NathanP.J.MooreG.J.UhdeT.W.TancerM.E.Neural substrates for voluntary suppression of negative affect: a functional magnetic resonance imaging studyBiological Psychiatry57200521021915691521RauchS.L.ShinL.M.WrightC.I.Neuroimaging studies of amygdala function in anxiety disordersAnnals of the New York Academy of Sciences985200338941012724173RayR.D.ZaldD.H.Anatomical insights into the interaction of emotion and cognition in the prefrontal cortexNeuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews36201247950121889953RoemerL.OrsilloS.M.Salters-PedneaultK.Efficacy of an acceptance-based behavior therapy for generalized anxiety disorder: evaluation in a randomized controlled trialJournal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology7620081083108919045976SchwartzC.E.WrightC.I.ShinL.M.KaganJ.RauchS.L.Inhibited and uninhibited infants “grown up”: adult amygdalar response to noveltyScience30020031952195312817151SchwartzC.E.WrightC.I.ShinL.M.KaganJ.WhalenP.J.McMullinK.G.Differential amygdalar response to novel versus newly familiar neutral faces: a functional MRI probe developed for studying inhibited temperamentBiological Psychiatry53200385486212742672ShinL.M.WrightC.I.CannistraroP.A.WedigM.M.McMullinK.MartisB.A functional magnetic resonance imaging study of amygdala and medial prefrontal cortex responses to overtly presented fearful faces in posttraumatic stress disorderArchives of General Psychiatry62200527328115753240SmithS.M.Fast robust automated brain extractionHuman Brain Mapping17200214315512391568SomervilleL.H.KimH.JohnstoneT.AlexanderA.L.WhalenP.J.Human amygdala responses during presentation of happy and neutral faces: correlations with state anxietyBiological Psychiatry55200489790315110733SPSSStatistical Package for Social Sciences, Release 12.0.22004SPSS IncChicagoStrawnJ.R.WehryA.M.DelbelloM.P.RynnM.A.StrakowskiS.Establishing the neurobiologic basis of treatment in children and adolescents with generalized anxiety disorderDepression and Anxiety29201232833922511364TabibniaG.LiebermanM.D.CraskeM.G.The lasting effect of words on feelings: words may facilitate exposure effects to threatening imagesEmotion83200830731718540747TangY.Y.MaY.FanY.FengH.WangJ.FengS.Central and autonomic nervous system interaction is altered by short-term meditationProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America10620098865887019451642TottenhamN.TanakaJ.W.LeonA.C.McCarryT.NurseM.HareT.A.The NimStim set of facial expressions: judgments from untrained research participantsPsychiatry Research168200924224919564050TullM.T.StipelmanB.A.Salters-PedneaultK.GratzK.L.An examination of recent non-clinical panic attacks, panic disorder, anxiety sensitivity, and emotion regulation difficulties in the prediction of generalized anxiety disorder in an analogue sampleJournal of Anxiety Disorders23200927528218804947WagerT.D.DavidsonM.L.HughesB.L.LindquistM.A.OchsnerK.N.Prefrontal–subcortical pathways mediating successful emotion regulationNeuron5920081037105018817740WhalenP.J.Fear, vigilance, and ambiguity: Initial neuroimaging studies of the human amygdalaCurrent Directions in Psychological Science71998177188WhalenP.J.JohnstoneT.SomervilleL.H.NitschkeJ.B.PolisS.AlexanderA.L.A functional magnetic resonance imaging predictor of treatment response to venlafaxine in generalized anxiety disorderBiological Psychiatry63200885886317964548WorsleyK.J.LiaoC.H.AstonJ.PetreV.DuncanG.H.MoralesF.A general statistical analysis for fMRI dataNeuroImage15200211511771969AcknowledgmentThis research was funded by a Marie Curie International Outgoing Fellowship within the 7th European Community Framework Programme to B.K.H., grant 5K23AT004432 from the National Institutes of Health to E.A.H., a Varela research grant by the Mind and Life Institute to B.K.H., and grant R21-AT003425 from the National Institutes of Health-NCCAM to S.W.L. This research was carried out at the Athinoula A. Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging at the Massachusetts General Hospital, using resources provided by the Center for Functional Neuroimaging Technologies, P41RR14075, a P41 Regional Resource supported by the Biomedical Technology Program of the National Center for Research Resources (NCRR), National Institutes of Health. This work also involved the use of instrumentation supported by the NCRR Shared Instrumentation Grant Program; specifically, grant numbers 1S10RR023401, S10RR019307, and 1S10RR023043. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. The authors declare no conflicts of interest. B.K.H. takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. We thank Zayda Vallejo for conducting the MBSR courses, Jennifer Johnston for conducting the SME courses, Narayan Brach and Christina Metcalf for support in data collection, and Andrea Hermann, Markus Graf, and Rudolf Stark for helpful comments on this manuscript. This study was registered with ClinicalTrials.gov (Identifier NCT01128309, Title: “Stress Reduction and Anxiety: Effects on the Function and Structure of the Brain”, http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=NCT01128309).☆This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.☆☆ClinicalTrials.gov registration NCT01128309, Title: “Stress Reduction and Anxiety: Effects on the Function and Structure of the Brain”, http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?term=NCT01128309.2For a review of findings with pediatric GAD, see 27 Strawn et al. (2012): Establishing the neurobiologic basis of treatment in children and adolescents with generalized anxiety disorder. Depress Anxiety. 29:328–339.3Additional post-hoc analyses were performed excluding patients with comorbid SAD, excluding patients with comorbid major depressive disorder and excluding medicated subjects. Full results are reported in the Supplementary materials. The major conclusions of the data analyses remained the same when excluding these subgroups. We have opted to report results based on the full sample here, since comorbid conditions in GAD are the norm.4The dorsolateral PFC receives minimal direct projections from the amygdala and has only weak projections to it, so projections might be relayed through other prefrontal areas, such as the dorsal ACC 77. Ray and Zald (2012): Anatomical insights into the interaction of emotion and cognition in the prefrontal cortex. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 36:479–501.Fig. 1When labeling the affect, compared to the gender of facial expressions, healthy participants (N = 26) show decreased activation in the left amygdala (A; p = 0.0121, multiple comparison corrections within area of bilateral amygdalae), the right rostral ACC (C; p = 0.0314; multiple comparison corrections within mask of the frontal cortex/insula), and left inferior parietal cortex (B; p = 0.0321, multiple comparison corrections for entire brain for this and all following clusters) and increased activation in the left lateral occipital (B; p = 0.0087), left fusiform (B; p = 0.0099), and right lingual cortex (C; p = 0.0105).Fig. 2GAD patients (N = 26) show greater activation in a cluster in the right amygdala when viewing neutral facial expressions when compared to healthy participants (N = 26; p = 0.0001; size = 440 mm3; multiple comparison corrections within area of bilateral amygdalae; cluster overlaid over a FreeSurfer subcortical parcellation image).Fig. 3MBSR participants (N = 15) show stronger increases in brain activation in clusters in the right pars opercularis (A; p = 0.0156; multiple comparison corrections within mask of the frontal cortex/insula) and left pars triangularis (B; p = 0.0015), i.e., ventrolateral prefrontal regions when viewing neutral emotional expressions than SME participants (N = 11). Extracted averaged values from the clusters in the right pars opercularis (C), and the left pars triangularis (D) for the MBSR (black) and SME (blue) groups when viewing neutral facial expressions at pre- and post-interventions (error bars indicate standard errors). Signal in the cluster in the left pars triangularis is correlated with scores on the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) at post-intervention (E; ρ = − .645, p &lt; .001, uncorrected) and the pre–post intervention change in this cluster is correlated with the change in BAI (F; ρ = − .617, p = .001, uncorrected).Fig. 4MBSR participants (N = 15) show stronger pre–post increases than SME participants (N = 11) in two clusters in the right VLPFC when viewing angry facial expressions (A; pars opercularis: p = 0.0003; rostral middle frontal gyrus: p = 0.0018; multiple comparison corrections within mask of the frontal cortex/insula). Extracted averaged signal for the MBSR (black) and SME (blue) groups at pre- and post-interventions in the right rostral middle frontal gyrus, reaching into the pars opercularis (B) and right pars opercularis, reaching into the pars triangularis and insula (C; error bars indicate standard errors).Fig. 5Functional connectivity between the seed region in the right amygdala and several regions in the frontal cortex increased from pre- to post-intervention in GAD patients who underwent the MBSR program (N = 15), but not in those who underwent the SME class (N = 11). Anatomical location displayed on an inflated surface with FreeSurfer cortex parcellations (top row), regression coefficients extracted from the clusters from the MBSR (black) and SME (blue) participants at pre- and post-interventions (middle row) and scatter plots of regression coefficients (y-axis) and Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI, x-axis) for MBSR and SME participants at post (bottom row) for the left rostral anterior cingulate cortex (ACC, column A, pre- to post increase in connectivity: p = 0.0002, multiple comparison corrections within mask of the frontal cortex/insula; correlation with BAI scores: ρ = − .229, ns, uncorrected), right superior frontal cortex (column B, pre–post increase: p = 0.04; correlation: ρ = − .470, p = .015), right rostral middle frontal cortex (column C, pre–post increase: p = 0.03; correlation: ρ = − .572, p = .002), and left rostral middle frontal cortex (column D, pre–post increase: p = 0.01; correlation: ρ = − .646, p &lt; .001).Table 1Age, gender, and education of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) patients and healthy participants, as well as separately for the two GAD subgroups (MBSR and SME participants).GADHealthyTestGAD MBSRGAD SMETestAge mean years (SD)37.9 (12.2)35.7 (9.3)Independent sample t-test t(50) = .76, p = .4538.5 (13.3)35.6 (10.8)Independent sample t-test t(26) = − .58, p = .57Gender14 females, 12 males16 females, 10 malesχ2(Fisher's exact test) p = .789 females, 6 males5 females, 6 malesχ2 = .54, asymp significance = .46Education mean years (SD)17.5 (2.5)16.9 (1.9)Independent sample t-test t(46.28) = 1.05, p = .3017.1 (2.8)18.2 (2.1)Independent sample t-test t(24) = 1.11, p = .28Table 2Brain activation in healthy participants during affect labeling (compared to gender labeling) of emotional facial expressions (angry, happy, and neutral faces combined).Brain region of maximumCluster-wise pSize (mm2/mm3)Max (Z)MNI-xMNI-yMNI-zAmygdala region of interestLeft amygdala0.0121248− 2.64− 26− 3− 27  Prefrontal/insular region of interestRight rostral ACC0.0314251− 2.98531− 2  Exploratory whole brain analysisLeft inferior parietal0.0321480− 4.34− 40− 7533Left lateral occipital0.00875823.47− 17− 99− 9Left fusiform0.00995643.40− 38− 68− 17Right lingual0.01054634.0014− 93− 9Table 3Brain regions within the prefrontal/insula regions of interest where MBSR participants showed stronger pre–post intervention increases than SME participants when viewing neutral and when viewing angry facial expressions.Brain region of maximumCluster-wise pSize (mm2)Max (Z)MNI-xMNI-yMNI-zNeutral facial expressionsRight pars opercularis0.01563393.0946209Left pars triangularis0.00154702.91− 34269  Angry facial expressionsRight pars opercularis0.00035833.5234.621.711.7Right rostral middle frontal0.00184732.9345.028.523.9Table 4Areas of significant change in BOLD signal in response to angry and neutral facial expressions in the MBSR and the SME groups in exploratory whole brain analyses.Brain region of maximumCluster-wise pSize (mm2)Max (Z)MNI-xMNI-yMNI-zMBSR groupNeutral facial expressionsRight fusiform gyrus0.01671537− 3.2634− 45− 19Angry facial expressionsRight precuneus0.030584983.199− 4945Left lateral occipital0.02440496− 3.96− 43− 75− 10SME groupNeutral facial expressionsRight superior temporal0.02115431− 3.8355− 312Left banks superior temporal sulcus0.000301010− 3.71− 57− 46− 2Left pars opercularis0.00060657− 3.20− 361024Left pars opercularis0.00927462− 3.76− 501912Angry facial expressionsNo significant clustersTable 5Areas of increased connectivity with the cluster in the right amygdala in the GAD group that underwent the MBSR program.Brain region of maximumCluster-wise pSize (mm2)Max (Z)MNI-xMNI-yMNI-zRH rostral middle frontal0.034302743.13245119RH superior frontal0.043712643.12102836LH rostral anterior cingulate0.000206923.46− 11445LH rostral middle frontal0.011373193.23− 334518
