<?xml version="1.0"?>
J Neuroeng RehabilJ Neuroeng RehabilJournal of NeuroEngineering and Rehabilitation1743-0003BioMed Central40177051743-0003-11-792488541210.1186/1743-0003-11-79ResearchNon-invasive neuromodulation to improve gait in chronic multiple sclerosis: a randomized double blind controlled pilot trialTylerMitchell E12metyler1@wisc.eduKaczmarekKurt A2kakaczma@wisc.eduRustKathy L2rustkathleen@gmail.comSubbotinAlla M2amsubbotin@wisc.eduSkinnerKimberly L1kzskinner@wisc.eduDanilovYuri P2ydanilov@wisc.edu1Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI 53706, USA2Department of Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI 53706, USA201415201411797925620132442014Copyright © 2014 Tyler et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.2014Tyler et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited.BackgroundThis study sought to examine the effect of targeted physical therapy with and without cranial nerve non-invasive neuromodulation (CN-NINM), on the walking ability of people with MS who exhibited a dysfunctional gait. We hypothesized that subjects who received electrical stimulation would have greater improvement than those who had a control device after a 14-week intervention. Gait disturbance is a common problem for people with multiple sclerosis (MS). Current management may include exercise, pharmacology, functional electrical stimulation, compensatory strategies, use of assistive devices, and implanted electrical devices. We have developed an effective rehabilitative strategy using neuromodulation of the cranial nerves via electrical stimulation of the tongue to enhance the plasticity of the brain.MethodsThe study is a within-subject blinded randomized control design. Twenty chronic MS subjects with an identified gait disturbance were assigned to either an active or control group. Both groups completed a 14-week intervention program using a standardized combination of exercise and a device that provided electrical stimulation to the tongue. Those in the active group received electrical stimulation on the tongue that they could perceive. Those in the control group used a device that did not provide a physiologically significant stimulus and was not perceivable. Subjects were assessed with the Dynamic Gait Index (DGI).ResultsThe DGI scores improved for both groups. There were significant between-group differences, with the active group showing statistically greater improvement than the control group mean.ConclusionPeople with MS demonstrated improved gait with CN-NINM training in a pilot randomized controlled trial. This study suggests that tongue-based neurostimulation may amplify the benefits of exercise for improving gait in people with chronic MS.Multiple sclerosisNeuromodulationBalanceGaitTongueNeurostimulationNon-invasiveElectrical stimulationBackgroundIndividuals with moderate multiple sclerosis (MS) present with an array of symptoms, with walking impairment being among the most common. Gait speed, cadence, stride length and time spent on double-limb support are frequently affected, and correlate with reduced independence and productivity, impacting overall quality of life [1]. It is a major factor in estimates of disease progression [2-4], and approximately 40% of MS patients will need some form of walking assistance within 15 years of disease onset [5]. Consequently, interventions targeting gait disturbance in patients with MS are in demand. Currently these include rehabilitation therapy and pharmacological management.While therapeutic exercise has long been believed to increase symptoms, more recent evidence has demonstrated that exercise and increased physical activity are beneficial for people with MS, and are becoming more commonly included as part of treatment interventions [6-10]. The optimal type or mode of exercise, intensity, frequency, duration and maintenance of exercise training to manage the progression of balance and gait dysfunction in MS has, however, yet to be established through randomized trials [3].Rehabilitation therapy includes occupational, physical and speech therapies as part of the comprehensive management of symptoms [11,12]. Compensatory strategies such as energy conservation, use of adaptive equipment, and environmental adaptations are often utilized in these interventions [13-20]. Medical devices and physical modalities may also be used in multidisciplinary interventions [21]. A recent Cochrane review of multidisciplinary rehabilitation for adults with MS did not find strong evidence of interventions that resulted long-term improvements [12].Pharmacological management may slow disease progress or reduce motor symptoms. For example, Ampyra (Acorda Therapeutics) was approved after it was shown to be effective in improving walking speed by 20% when compared to a placebo group that improved 8% [2]. This outcome, however, was observed in only 35% of those tested, and many participants reported significant side effects. Additionally, there is little evidence that these drugs will prevent the mobility disability of persons with 2nd stage MS (Kurtzke Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) score of 4.0 or greater) [1,3,22,23].The medical devices and physical modalities utilized in treatment for people with MS vary. Functional electrical stimulation, as delivered through electrodes attached to the skin, has been shown to be effective in improving gait, as long as the electrodes are attached and the stimulation unit is on [24-29]. Other contemporary forms of neurostimulation (aimed at induced neuromodulation) are invasive, expensive and have the potential for adverse effects. For example, deep brain stimulation and vagus nerve stimulation, which use implanted pacemaker-like electrical devices, are indicated for decreasing tremors in MS, but carry surgical risks [30-33]. These therapies have not been widely attempted in MS rehabilitation. Neurostimulation that directly stimulates the peripheral or central nervous systems to improve motor impairments is still being investigated. Non-invasive neurostimulation that has been tried in people with MS are typically large clinic-based devices that employ powerful electromagnetic stimulation of the brain’s cortex (transcranial magnetic stimulation) [34,35], or electrodes that pass electric current through the skull (transcranial direct current brain stimulation) [36,37]. Intermittent theta burst stimulation of the motor cortex has been demonstrated to reduce spasticity in people with MS [38], and when combined with exercise therapy, to decrease fatigue [35]. Success with these interventions has, however, been limited. Consequently, there continues to be a need for alternative approaches that have the potential to help improve mobility in people with MS.Previous studies have shown that the tongue can be used as an effective interface for sending electrical signals to the central nervous system [39-45], for example sensory substitution in balance-impaired or blind individuals [43,46-50]. Individuals with primary vestibular disorders who trained using electrical stimulation through the tongue coupled to head-position information demonstrated balance improvements that were sustained for weeks beyond the final stimulation session [46,51].Using a different methodology that delivers tongue stimulation which, like the present study, is devoid of information linked to head position or any other exogenous variable, our recent functional MRI results indicated that the improvements that occurred with the neuromodulation training (using electrical stimulation on the tongue) are likely related to modulation of neural activity within structures of the brain that control balance and movement [44,45,52].ObjectiveThis study sought to examine the effect of targeted physical therapy, with and without cranial nerve non-invasive neuromodulation (CN-NINM), on the walking ability of people with MS who exhibited a dysfunctional gait. We hypothesized that subjects who received electrical stimulation on the tongue would have greater improvement than those who had a control device after a 14-week intervention.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study design</title><p>The study was a randomized, double blind controlled trial. Twenty subjects (males and females) with identified gait deficits due to the effects of MS were distributed into 2 treatment groups: 10 used an “Active” CN-NINM device, or Portable Neuromodulation Stimulator (PoNS™), and 10 used a “Control” (very low stimulation) device. The study consisted of two phases: 2 weeks of twice-daily gait training in the laboratory while using the PoNS, followed by 12 weeks of the same daily routine at home. All subjects performed the same gait training over the period of the study. All subjects were tested at the beginning and end of the first phase, and every 4 weeks during the second phase. The structure of the study is depicted in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Detailed flow chart of the study intervention.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-0003-11-79-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>Twenty-six subjects with stable symptoms from MS were recruited by physician and subject referrals. Because gait impairment can be manifested in persons with any type of MS, we thought it was important to include people with any type of MS who were affected by a walking impairment. Inclusion criteria were: relapsing remitting (RRMS), primary progressive (PPMS), or secondary progressive (SPMS) without relapse within 6 months of enrollment in the study; EDSS scores of 3.5 to 6.0; no changes in medication within 3 months of enrollment; and ability to walk 20 minutes on a treadmill (with handrail support as needed) without rest. The EDSS is a rating system used for classifying the condition of people with MS, and emphasizes walking ability. Scores in the range of 3.5 to 6.0 on the EDSS represent people who are ambulatory and have a few functional systems affected to those more significantly affected, requiring intermittent or constant unilateral assistance (e.g., a cane, crutch, or brace) to walk 100 meters with or without resting.</p><p>Exclusion criteria were: major co-morbidities, especially other neurological disorders, uncontrolled pain, hypertension, diabetes, or oral health problems. A summary of the subjects’ general characteristics is presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Three subjects (2 Control, 1 Active) were on neurostimulating medication (e.g. fampridine) that might alter motor function. Five subjects were on anti-inflammatory medications, six on antispasmodics, and six had non-narcotic prescriptions to manage chronic pain. Four candidates were not enrolled because they did not meet the inclusion criteria, and two did not participate because they could not meet the time commitments of the study.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Subject characteristics at baseline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Active</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Control</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Subjects</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>10</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>10</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Men/Women</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>4/6</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>2/8</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left"> </th><th align="center"><bold>Mean</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>SD</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Mean</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>SD</bold></th><th align="center"><bold><italic>p</italic>
</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Age<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">55.40<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.73<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">51.90<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9.31<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.40<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Years with MS<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">24.10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">11.03<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">13.10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6.72<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.01*<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">EDSS<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">5.25<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.98<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4.60<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1.05<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.17<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">DGI</td><td align="center">8.90</td><td align="center">2.85</td><td align="center">11.95</td><td align="center">4.04</td><td align="center">0.07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Indicates significant difference.</p><p><italic>EDSS</italic>, Expanded Disability Status Scale, DGI = Dynamic Gait Index.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The University of Wisconsin-Madison Health Sciences Institutional Review Board approved this study and all subjects gave written consent before participation.</p></sec><sec><title>Randomization and blinding</title><p>Subjects were randomly assigned to either the control or active group by the primary investigator (PI) as they enrolled in the study. Ten subjects were assigned to each group, with no regard given to age, gender, individual EDSS score, disease state, functional status, or chronicity of MS. The PI provided each subject with the proper neuromodulation device and instructed the subject in its use. The subjects in the active group used a device that provided electrical stimulation on the tongue that they could perceive. Those in the control group used a device that provided a stimulus that was not perceivable. Subjects were instructed that this was controlled study investigating the effects of stimulus level so they may or may not feel the stimulation. To avoid deception, all subjects in both groups were assured that they were in fact receiving stimulation, whether or not they could feel the stimulus. The subjects and the therapists providing the intervention and testing were not informed which group a subject was assigned. In order to maintaining blinding, both subjects and therapists were instructed to not discuss any details of the stimulus sensation with each other. Additionally, all subjects were instructed to not adjust the stimulus intensity in the presence of the therapist. All questions about device use or the stimulation were to be addressed only to the PI. A summary of subject distribution in the two cohorts is presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Multiple sclerosis subgroups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"> </th><th align="center"><bold>Active (10)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Control (10)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Relapsing Remitting<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"> Male/Female<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1/4<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2/6<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Secondary Progressive<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"> Male/Female<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3/2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0/1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Primary Progressive<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Male/Female</td><td align="center">0/0</td><td align="center">0/1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Experimental procedures</title><sec><title>Intervention</title><p>The goal of the training was to develop a more normal gait pattern. The twice-daily intervention was identical for each subject, and progressed in two phases: a 2-week twice daily in-lab phase, followed by a 12-week at-home phase where subjects performed the same training as instructed in the laboratory. The structure and progression of both the in-lab and at-home interventions, as well as the assessments, are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. Subjects were telephoned weekly during the at-home phase to ensure compliance with the protocol. In order to maximize any potential benefit from participation, the degree of challenge in each subject’s training program was increased according to the progress they made at each 4-week follow-up visit for testing and retraining.</p></sec><sec><title>Device</title><p>Electrical stimulation to the tongue was delivered via the Portable Neuromodulation Stimulator (PoNS™) device shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. The PoNS™ device was held in place lightly by the lips and teeth around a rectangular tab that goes into the mouth and rests on the anterior, superior part of the tongue. The tab has 144 exposed gold-plated circular electrodes (1.5 mm diam., on 2.3-mm centers) on a 3 cm × 3 cm square matrix on a rigid printed circuit board that is coated with a biocompatible epoxy (Epotech 302-3 M, Epoxy Technology, Billerica, MA). The 12x12 array is divided into nine 4x4 sectors. Only one electrode in each sector is pulsed at any given time; the remaining electrodes serve as the return current path. The stimulation on each electrode is a triplet of 50 μs-wide positive pulses delivered at 200 pulses/s every 20 ms. Capacitive coupling ensures zero net direct current to minimize the possibility of tissue irritation. Electrode and waveform parameters were derived from earlier research aimed at developing electrotactile stimulation that is maximally comfortable and controllable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>], and implemented using circuitry similar to that in the earlier Tongue Display Unit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Portable Neuromodulation Stimulator (PoNS™) device, top and bottom view.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-0003-11-79-2"/></fig><p>Device function is user-controlled by buttons for ‘On’ and ‘Off,’ and subjects could adjust the stimulus level (pulse amplitude) from 0 to 17 volts by manipulating a knob on the device (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The “Control” version of the device was physically identical to the Active device, but delivered a stimulus at approximately 1/1,000 the minimum perceivable level. Here, adjustment of the intensity knob did not change this level.</p><p>To avoid bias or deception, subjects in both groups were provided with identical instructions to adjust the intensity level by turning the knob. They were told that they may or may not feel the stimulation. If they could feel the stimulus, they were to adjust the intensity until it was strong but not uncomfortable. We allowed individual adjustment rather than setting a fixed amplitude across all subjects, because of known inter-subject differences in tongue sensitivity, with the rationale that it is more important to hold invariant the result of the stimulation rather than its physical level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]. From our previous research, we have observed that with experience, subjects set the intensity level at between 50 and 80% of the maximum dynamic range of sensation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. If subjects could not feel it, they were reassured that they were still receiving stimulation but it was below their individual threshold of perception.</p></sec><sec><title>CN-NINM training</title><p>Instruction and implementation of the 14-week intervention was identical for both groups. Subjects trained in the lab for 5 consecutive days (Monday through Friday) for 2 consecutive weeks working one-on-one with a therapist researcher for all in-laboratory training sessions. Subjects then continued the same training independently at home for the next 12 weeks. Subjects returned to the lab every 4 weeks for assessment, training review, and exercise program progression. Compliance was monitored daily in the lab, and weekly via self-reports by phone when the subjects trained at home.</p><p>The in-lab training consisted of two appointments per day. Within each appointment, subjects performed movement isolation exercises without the device, 20 minutes of gait training with the device, 20 minutes of balance training with the device, and 20 minutes of relaxation training with the device. The training was targeted to the specific ability of each individual, and they were provided with rest periods as needed. Subjects who were unable to complete the training components in the lab due to fatigue were allowed to delay that component until later in the day after they had had an opportunity to rest. Subjects were also expected to incorporate an additional relaxation session with the device at home each evening one hour before bed.</p><p>Subjects were instructed in movement isolation exercises (without device) at the beginning of each training session. These were geared to the ability of that individual. These exercises were designed to change abnormal movement patterns and re-train movements for improved neuromuscular control and mobility. Sample exercises were chin circles, shoulder circles, and hip circles. The emphasis was placed on quality of movements, not speed, and mirrors were used to provide visual feedback as needed. As the individual demonstrated competency with an exercise, new exercises were introduced.</p><p>During gait training subjects walked on a treadmill at progressive speeds and challenges designed to re-establish appropriate dynamic balance and gait patterns. Particular attention was given to symmetry of the gait pattern, including dynamic weight transfer, stride length, kinematics of the hip, knee, and ankle flexions/extensions, and bilateral symmetry of the stance and swing phases. In-lab gait training was performed on the treadmill for the first week, and both over ground and on the treadmill during the second week. Subjects were required to use a treadmill for at least 50% of the at-home training phase to control and monitor their training progress.</p><p>Gait training sessions were 20 minutes in overall duration. The first 5 minutes were performed at a comfortable pace. In the next two 5-minute periods the challenge was increased by changing a gait variable. The last 5-minute period was performed at a comfortable intensity but greater than that for the first 5-minute period. The variables were:</p><p>• Speed: from very slow to fast walking, focusing on maintaining gait kinematics without deterioration of performance;</p><p>• Grade: an incline increases effort and affects the relative involvement of the ankle, knee and hip joints;</p><p>• Support: use of handrails provides greater stability, but prevents arm swing and full weight transfer during the gait cycle. Challenge was created by decreasing hand contact time and force on the rails, with the goal of achieving arm swing commensurate with normal gait.</p><p>The therapist worked with the subject to determine an appropriate starting point relative to the subject’s baseline. The objective of each session of gait training was to start at a higher level than the previous session. The therapist used verbal and tactile cues as needed to correct posture and abnormal movement patterns during gait.</p><p>Balance training (with device) was performed by having the subjects stand on the floor or on foam with eyes closed, depending on their ability. As in gait training, balance training was targeted to each subject, advancing their challenge as they improved. To increase the balance challenge, subjects could change their stance width, foot position, or stand barefoot. Subjects stood close to a table for support if needed, and were guarded against falls by the therapist providing stand-by assist if needed.</p><p>Relaxation training (with device) was performed in an unsupported sitting position while wearing headphones and listening to theta-wave based sound tracks. Subjects were instructed in diaphragmatic breathing and maintaining relaxed attention.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Assessments</title><p>Subjects completed the Dynamic Gait Index (DGI), a clinician-scored index of 8 gait tasks: normal walking, changing speed while walking, head turns and up/down tilts while walking, turning and stopping, walking around and stepping over objects, and traversing stairs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. This test was performed at baseline, after the 2-week in-lab intervention, and after 4, 8 and 12 weeks of at-home training (a total of 14 weeks intervention) for a total of 5 assessment points. Subjects were also instructed to provide daily (in-lab) and weekly (at-home) written documentation of their at-home training program in order to monitor compliance with the protocol.</p><p>The EDSS is a clinical tool for assessing and comparing patients’ global neurological disability and was not used to assess any changes in gait. It was used only for entrance criteria for the study. The final score reflects the status of many functional systems and may not be impacted by changes in gait. It has been shown to lack responsiveness to change and is therefore not recommended for research as an assessment tool for measuring change.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>Statistical analyses were completed with Systat version 8.0 (SPSS, Inc.). The demographic data presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> were examined by descriptive statistics and the differences between active and control groups were compared using unpaired, two-tailed t-tests. DGI data summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> were also examined with descriptive statistics. DGI differences from baseline (week 0) were calculated for the 2, 6, 10, and 14-week test points and subjected to analysis of variance, separately for active and control groups; multiple comparisons for these analyses were performed with a Tukey HSD test and are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. Finally, the DGI differences from baseline were compared for the active and control groups using unpaired, two-tailed t-tests, separately for the 2, 6, 10, and 14 week data points. Although the DGI scale is technically categorical, it has been shown to have good psychometric properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. As a precaution we repeated the latter analyses using the non-parametric Wilcoxon Rank Sum Test.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>DGI Mean Scores</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Active</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Control</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center"><bold>Week</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>N</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Diff</bold><sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup></th><th align="center"><bold>
<italic>p</italic>
</bold><sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup></th><th align="center"><bold>N</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Diff</bold><sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup></th><th align="center"><bold>p</bold><sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.90 (2.85)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">11.95 (4.04)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">13.30 (3.92)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4.40<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.056<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">14.95 (4.29)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3.00<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.610<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">6<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15.05 (3.53)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6.15<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.003<sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15.63 (4.73)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3.68<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.471<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">16.60 (3.95)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">7.70<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">16.75 (5.20)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4.80<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.166<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">16.85 (3.40)</td><td align="center">7.95<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">15.40 (5.03)</td><td align="center">3.45</td><td align="center">0.745</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Difference from baseline (week 0).</p><p><sup>b</sup>Statistically significant difference (<italic>p &lt; .05).</italic></p><p><sup>c</sup>Clinically significant difference (&gt; = 4).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec>Abbreviations(ANOVA): Analysis of variance; (CN-NINM): Cranial nerve non-invasive neuromodulation; (DGI): Dynamic gait index; (DGIB): Dynamic gait index baseline; (EDSS): Expanded disability status scale; (fMRI): Functional magnetic resonance imaging; (MA): Massachusetts; (MS): Multiple sclerosis; (RRMS): Relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis; (PoNS™): Portable neuromodulation stimulator; (PPMS): Primary progressive multiple sclerosis; (SPMS): Secondary progressive.Competing interestsDanilov, Kaczmarek, and Tyler have a financial interest in Advanced NeuroRehabilitation, LLC and in NeuroHabilitation Corp., which both have intellectual property rights in the field of use reported in this article.Authors’ contributionsMT, YD, KK, KR, AS, KS. 1 Study design. 2 Draft manuscript. 3 Statistical analysis. 4 Implementation of the intervention/study protocol. 5 Critical revision of manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.Authors’ informationAll authors are affiliated with the University of Wisconsin, Madison.MT teaches in the Department of Biomedical Engineering at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. He is a co-inventor of the PoNS device and is a contributor to the development of the CN-NINM training method. YD is a co-inventor of the PoNS device and is a major contributor to the development of the CN-NINM training method. KK is an expert in electrotactile stimulation and a co-inventor of the PoNS device. KR is an Occupational Therapist with an interest in human subjects rehabilitation research. AS is a psychiatrist who specializes in cognitive function and emotional processing. KS is a Physical Therapist with an interest in the application of neuromodulation for rehabilitation and is a contributor to the development of the CN-NINM training method.AcknowledgementsWe gratefully acknowledge Chris Luzzio, MD, for advice on both the clinical and experimental assessments, and for referring human subjects; and Scott Hetzel, MS (Dept. of Biostatistics and Medical Informatics, University of Wisconsin, Madison) for assistance with, and independent verification of the statistical analyses. Funding for this study was provided by the University of Wisconsin Foundation.PanitchHApplebeeATreatment of walking impairment in multiple sclerosis: an unmet need for a disease-specific disabilityExpert Opin Pharmacother2011121511152110.1517/14656566.2011.58633821635193GoodmanADBrownTRKruppLBSchapiroRTSchwidSRCohenRMarinucciLNBlightARFampridineMSFISustained-release oral fampridine in multiple sclerosis: a randomised, double-blind, controlled trialLancet200937373273810.1016/S0140-6736(09)60442-619249634MotlRWPhysical activity and irreversible disability in multiple sclerosisExerc Sport Sci Rev20103818619110.1097/JES.0b013e3181f44fab20871235SnookEMMotlRWEffect of exercise training on walking mobility in multiple sclerosis: a meta-analysisNeurorehabil Neural Repair20092310811618948413MyhrKRiiseTVedelerCNortvedtMWGronningMMidgardRNylandHIDisability and prognosis in multiple sclerosis: demographic and clinical variables important for the ability to walk and awarding of disability pensionMult Scler20017596510.1177/13524585010070011011321195PiluttiLALelliDAPaulsethJECromeMJiangSRathboneMPHicksALEffects of 12 weeks of supported treadmill training on functional ability and quality of life in progressive multiple sclerosis: a pilot studyArch Phys Med Rehabil201192313610.1016/j.apmr.2010.08.02721187202RietbergMBBrooksDUitdehaagBMJKwakkelGExercise therapy for multiple sclerosisCochrane Database Syst Rev20043135WilesCMPhysiotherapy and related activities in multiple sclerosisMult Scler20081486387110.1177/135245850708815518535020GarrettMCooteSMultiple sclerosis and exercise in people with minimal gait impairment-a reviewPhys Ther Rev20091416918010.1179/174328809X435295HoganNCooteSTherapeutic interventions in the treatment of people with multiple sclerosis with mobility problems: a literature reviewPhys Ther Rev20091416016810.1179/174328809X435286RasovaKFeysPHenzeTvan TongerenHCattaneoDJonsdottirJHerbenovaAEmerging evidence-based physical rehabilitation for Multiple Sclerosis - Towards an inventory of current content across EuropeHealth Qual Life Outcomes20108768210.1186/1477-7525-8-7620667079KhanFPallantJBrandCKilpatrickTEffectiveness of rehabilitation intervention in persons with multiple sclerosis: a randomized controlled trialJ Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry200879111230123510.1136/jnnp.2007.13377718535027Shumway-CookAWoollacottMMotor Control: Translating Research into Clinical Practice20073Lippincott, Williams, and Wilkins: PhiladelphiaThompsonAJThe effectiveness of neurological rehabilitation in multiple sclerosisJ Rehabil Res Dev20003745546111028701PattiFCiancioMRReggioELopesRPalermoFCacopardoMReggioAThe impact of outpatient rehabilitation on quality of life in multiple sclerosisJ Neurol20022491027103310.1007/s00415-002-0778-112195449FreemanJALangdonDWHobartJCThompsonAJThe impact of inpatient rehabilitation on progressive multiple sclerosisAnn Neurol19974223624410.1002/ana.4104202169266735KhanFPallantJFZhangNTurner-StokesLClinical practice improvement approach in multiple sclerosis rehabilitation: a pilot studyInt J Rehabil Res20103323824710.1097/MRR.0b013e328338b05f20410826PaltamaaJSarasojaTLeskinenEWikstromJMalkiaEMeasures of physical functioning predict self-reported performance in self-care, mobility, and domestic life in ambulatory persons with multiple sclerosisArch Phys Med Rehabil2007881649165710.1016/j.apmr.2007.07.03218047881GrassoMGTroisiERizziFMorelliDPaolucciSPrognostic factors in multidisciplinary rehabilitation treatment in multiple sclerosis: an outcome studyMult Scler20051171972410.1191/1352458505ms1226oa16320734KhanFGrayODisability management and rehabilitation for persons with multiple sclerosisNeural Regeneration Res20105301309FregniFImamuraMChienHFLewHLBoggioPKaptchukTJRibertoMHsingWTBattistellaLRFurlanAChallenges and recommendations for placebo controls in randomized trials in physical and rehabilitation medicine A report of the international Placebo symposium working groupAm J Phys Med Rehabil20108916017210.1097/PHM.0b013e3181bc0bbd20090428CompstonAColesAMultiple sclerosisLancet20083721502151710.1016/S0140-6736(08)61620-718970977KatrychOSimoneTMAzadSMousaSADisease-modifying agents in the treatment of multiple sclerosis: a review of long-term outcomesCns Neuro Disord Drug Targets2009851251910.2174/187152709789824598KelleherKJSpenceWSolomonidisSApatsidisDAmbulatory rehabilitation in multiple sclerosisDisabil Rehabil2009311625163210.1080/0963828090275193119479529TaylorNFDoddKJPrasadDDenisenkoSProgressive resistance exercise for people with multiple sclerosisDisabil Rehabil2006281119112610.1080/0963828050053183416966232PaulLRaffertyDYoungSMillerLMattisonPMcFadyenAThe effect of functional electrical stimulation on the physiological cost of gait in people with multiple sclerosisMult Scler20081495496110.1177/135245850809066718573839EsnoufJETaylorPNMannGEBarrettCLImpact on activities of daily living using a functional electrical stimulation device to improve dropped foot in people with multiple sclerosis, measured by the Canadian Occupational Performance MeasureMult Scler2010161141114710.1177/135245851036601320601398BarrettCLMannGETaylorPNStrikePA randomized trial to investigate the effects of functional electrical stimulation and therapeutic exercise on walking performance for people with multiple sclerosisMult Scler20091549350410.1177/135245850810132019282417CourtneyAMCastro-BorreroWDavisSLFrohmanTCFrohmanEMFunctional treatments in multiple sclerosisCurr Opin Neurol20112425025410.1097/WCO.0b013e328346055a21455067FahyBGIntraoperative and perioperative complications with a vagus nerve stimulation deviceJ Clin Anesth20102221322210.1016/j.jclinane.2009.10.00220400010SpuckSTronnierVOroszISchonweilerRSepehrniaANowakGSpernerJOperative and technical complications of vagus nerve stimulator implantationNeurosurgery20106748949421099577HuXJiangXZhouXLiangJWangLCaoYJinAYangPAvoidance and management of surgical and hardware-related complications of deep brain stimulationStereotact Funct Neurosurg20108829630310.1159/00031676220588081ChangEFChengJSRichardsonRMLeeCStarrPALarsonPSIncidence and management of venous air embolisims during awake deep brain stimulation surgery in a large clinical seriesStereotact Funct Neurosurg201189768210.1159/00032333521293166ZellerDDangSYStefanKBillerABartschASaurDBendszusMRieckmannPToykaKVClassenJFunctional role of ipsilateral motor areas in multiple sclerosisJ Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry20118257858310.1136/jnnp.2010.21996420980484MoriFLjokaCMagniECodecaCKusayanagiHMonteleoneFSancesarioABernardiGKochGFotiCCentonzeDTranscranial magnetic stimulation primes the effects of exercise therapy in multiple sclerosisJ Neurol20112581281128710.1007/s00415-011-5924-121286740MoriFCodecaCKusayanagiHMonteleoneFButtariFFioreSBernardiGKochGCentonzeDEffects of anodal transcranial direct current stimulation on chronic neuropathic pain in patients with multiple sclerosisJ Pain20101143644210.1016/j.jpain.2009.08.01120018567CogiamanianFFerrucciRde RizMVergariMTadiniLCioccaMDilenaRMarcegliaSMameliFFumagalliMMrakic-SpostaAScarpiniEBarbieriSPrioriATranscranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) for fatigue in multiple sclerosisNeurology200972A82A8210.1212/WNL.0b013e3181a669ffMoriFCodecaCKusayanagiHMonteleoneFBoffaLRimanoABernardiGKochGCentonzeDEffects of intermittent theta burst stimulation on spasticity in patients with multiple sclerosisEur J Neurol20101729530010.1111/j.1468-1331.2009.02806.x19863647Bach-y-RitaPKaczmarekKAMeierKThe tongue as a man–machine interface: A wireless communication systemProc Int Symp Info Theory &amp; Apps (ISITA ’98); Oct. 14–161998Mexico City: IEEE7981Bach-y-RitaPKercelSWSensory substitution and the human-machine interfaceTrends Cogn Sci2003754154610.1016/j.tics.2003.10.01314643370ChebatDRRainvilleCKupersRPtitoMTactile ‘visual’ acuity of the tongue in early blind individualsNeuroreport2007181901190410.1097/WNR.0b013e3282f2a6318007183SampaioEMarisSBachy-y-RitaPBrain plasticity: ‘visual’ acuity of blind persons via the tongueBrain Res200190820420710.1016/S0006-8993(01)02667-111454331TylerMDanilovYBach-y-RitaPClosing an open-loop control system: Vestibular substitution through the tongueJ Integr Neurosci2003215916410.1142/S021963520300026315011268WildenbergJCTylerMEDanilovYPKaczmarekKAMeyerandMESustained cortical and subcortical neuromodulation induced by electrical tongue stimulationBrain Imaging Behav2010419921110.1007/s11682-010-9099-720614202WildenbergJTylerMDanilovYKaczmarekKKuoJMeyerandMEHigh-Resolution FMRI detects activity and neuromodulation of individual brainstem nucleiJ Neurosurg2011115A438A439DanilovYPTylerMESkinnerKLHogleRABach-y-RitaPEfficacy of electrotactile vestibular substitution in patients with peripheral and central vestibular lossJ Vestib Res20071711913018413905VuillermeNCuisinierRSensory supplementation through tongue electrotactile stimulation to preserve head stabilization in space in the absence of visionInvest Ophthalmol Vis Sci20095047648118708618VuillermeNPinsaultNFleuryAChenuODemongeotJPayanYPavanPEffectiveness of an electro-tactile vestibular substitution system in improving upright postural control in unilateral vestibular-defective patientsGait Posture20082871171510.1016/j.gaitpost.2008.05.01718632272KaczmarekKABronzino JDSensory augmentation and substitutionCRC Handbook of Biomedical Engineering2000Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press1431-143.10BadkeMBShermanJBoynePPageSDunningKTongue-based biofeedback for balance in stroke: results of an 8-week pilot studyArch Phys Med Rehabil2011921364137010.1016/j.apmr.2011.03.03021878206KaczmarekKAThe tongue display unit for electrotactile spatiotemporal pattern presentationScientia Iranica D2011181476148510.1016/j.scient.2011.08.020WildenbergJCTylerMEDanilovYPKaczmarekKAMeyerandMEElectrical tongue stimulation normalizes activity within the motion-sensitive brain network in balance-impaired subjects as revealed by group independent component analysisBrain Connectivity2011125526510.1089/brain.2011.002922433053KaczmarekKAWebsterJGRadwinRGMaximal dynamic range electrotactile stimulation waveformsIEEE Trans Biomed Eng19923970171510.1109/10.1426451516937TylerMEBraunJGDanilovYPSpatial mapping of electrotactile sensation threshold and intensity range on the human tongue: Initial resultsProc IEEE Eng Med Biol Soc2009Minneapolis, MN559562Bach-y-RitaPKaczmarekKATylerMEGarcia-LaraMForm perception with a 49-point electrotactile stimulus array on the tongue: A technical noteJ Rehab Res Dev199835427430KaczmarekKATylerMEEffect of electrode geometry and intensity control method on comfort of electrotactile stimulation on the tongueProc ASME Dyn Sys Contr Div2000Orlando, Florida: ASME12391243McConveyJBennettSEReliability of the dynamic gait index in individuals with multiple sclerosisArch Phys Med Rehabil20058613013310.1016/j.apmr.2003.11.03315641003CattaneoDJonsdottirJRepettiSReliability of four scales on balance disorders in persons with multiple sclerosisDisabil Rehabil2007291920192510.1080/0963828070119185917852286CattaneoDRegolaAMeottiMValidity of six balance disorders scales in persons with multiple sclerosisDisabil Rehabil20062878979510.1080/0963828050040428916754576ErratumComparing exercise in Parkinson’s disease-The Berlin LSVT(R)BIG studyMov Disord2010252478KandelERSchwartzJHJessellTMKandel ER, Schwartz JH, Jessel TMPrinciples of Neural Science1991ThirdNew York, NY: McGraw-Hill2232AbrahamWCBearMFMetaplasticity: the plasticity of synaptic plasticityTrends Neurosci19961912613010.1016/S0166-2236(96)80018-X8658594BlissTVGardner-MedwinARLong-lasting potentiation of synaptic transmission in the dentate area of the unanaestetized rabbit following stimulation of the perforant pathJ Physiol19732323573744727085BlissTVLomoTLong-lasting potentiation of synaptic transmission in the dentate area of the anaesthetized rabbit following stimulation of the perforant pathJ Physiol19732323313564727084BuchsPAMullerDInduction of long-term potentiation is associated with major ultrastructural changes of activated synapsesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A1996938040804510.1073/pnas.93.15.80408755599NudoRJPlautzEJFrostSBRole of adaptive plasticity in recovery of function after damage to motor cortexMuscle Nerve2001241000101910.1002/mus.110411439375ZuckerRSCalcium- and activity-dependent synaptic plasticityCurr Opin Neurobiol1999930531310.1016/S0959-4388(99)80045-210395573ZuckerRSRegehrWGShort-term synaptic plasticityAnnu Rev Physiol20026435540510.1146/annurev.physiol.64.092501.11454711826273WilesCMNewcombeRGFullerKJShawSFurnival-DoranJPickersgillTPMorganAControlled randomised crossover trial of the effects of physiotherapy on mobility in chronic multiple sclerosisJ Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry20017017417910.1136/jnnp.70.2.17411160464DiFabioRPSJChoiTHansenCRSchapiroRTExtended outpatient rehabilitation: Its influence on symptom frequency, fatigue, and functional status for persons with progressive multiple sclerosisArch Phys Med Rehabil19987914114610.1016/S0003-9993(98)90290-89473994SchapiroRTSoderbergJHooleyMTerryGRuhsamSLinrothRHatgidakisJHallSThe Multiple Sclerosis Achievement Center: a maintenance rehabilitation approach toward a chronic progressive form of the diseaseJ Neuro Rehabil198822123
