<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?npg-journal-abbreviation?><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPGSJ//DTD full length article DTD version 7.0 XML//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ajarticle_v7_x.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 7.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName naturesa2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1359-4184</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-5578</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5401767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">mp201716</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2017.16</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28289283</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The dopamine hypothesis of bipolar affective disorder: the state of the art and implications for treatment</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running">Dopamine hypothesis of bipolar affective disorder</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashok</surname><given-names>A H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>T R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jauhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nour</surname><given-names>M M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>G M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>A H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>O D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Psychiatric Imaging Group, MRC London Institute of Medical Sciences, Hammersmith Hospital, Imperial College London</institution>, London, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Psychiatric Imaging Group, Institute of Clinical Sciences (ICS), Faculty of Medicine, Imperial College London</institution>, London, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Psychosis Studies, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience, Kings College London</institution>, London, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>South London and Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust</institution>, Camberwell, London, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, University of Oxford and Oxford Health NHS Trust, Warneford Hospital</institution>, Oxford, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Psychological Medicine, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience, King's College London</institution>, London, <country>UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label><institution>Psychiatric Imaging Group, MRC London Institute of Medical Sciences, Hammersmith Hospital, Imperial College London</institution>, Du Cane Road, London W12 0NN, <country>UK</country>. E-mail: <email>oliver.howes@lms.mrc.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>05</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>03</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>07</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>01</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Bipolar affective disorder is a common neuropsychiatric disorder. Although its neurobiological underpinnings are incompletely understood, the dopamine hypothesis has been a key theory of the pathophysiology of both manic and depressive phases of the illness for over four decades. The increased use of antidopaminergics in the treatment of this disorder and new <italic>in vivo</italic> neuroimaging and post-mortem studies makes it timely to review this theory. To do this, we conducted a systematic search for post-mortem, pharmacological, functional magnetic resonance and molecular imaging studies of dopamine function in bipolar disorder. Converging findings from pharmacological and imaging studies support the hypothesis that a state of hyperdopaminergia, specifically elevations in D2/3 receptor availability and a hyperactive reward processing network, underlies mania. In bipolar depression imaging studies show increased dopamine transporter levels, but changes in other aspects of dopaminergic function are inconsistent. Puzzlingly, pharmacological evidence shows that both dopamine agonists and antidopaminergics can improve bipolar depressive symptoms and perhaps actions at other receptors may reconcile these findings. Tentatively, this evidence suggests a model where an elevation in striatal D2/3 receptor availability would lead to increased dopaminergic neurotransmission and mania, whilst increased striatal dopamine transporter (DAT) levels would lead to reduced dopaminergic function and depression. Thus, it can be speculated that a failure of dopamine receptor and transporter homoeostasis might underlie the pathophysiology of this disorder. The limitations of this model include its reliance on pharmacological evidence, as these studies could potentially affect other monoamines, and the scarcity of imaging evidence on dopaminergic function. This model, if confirmed, has implications for developing new treatment strategies such as reducing the dopamine synthesis and/or release in mania and DAT blockade in bipolar depression.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Bipolar disorder (BD) is a severe mental illness characterised by recurrent episodes of mania, depression or mixed states.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup> The lifetime prevalence of the full spectrum of bipolar disorder is estimated to be 2&#x02013;4&#x00025; in the general population and it is the sixth leading cause of disability worldwide.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup> The costs due to BD are immense, with annual direct healthcare costs in the USA of about $30 billion and indirect costs of &#x0003e;$120 billion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup></p><p>Lithium has been the mainstay of maintenance treatment for BD for decades, together with valproate, an option that has emerged more recently. However their modes of action have not been well established. By contrast antidopaminergic drugs do have well-understood class action at D2/3 receptors and have long been used to treat acute manic episodes. However, as will be explained below, newer drugs (particularly olanzapine and quetiapine) have been shown to have antimanic and antidepressant actions in bipolar disorder together with long-term benefit in preventing relapse to either pole of the illness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> Although the newer drugs were introduced for the treatment of schizophrenia, they have arguably represented a bigger advance for the management of bipolar disorder.</p><p>Despite these advances in treatment, many patients continue to experience high levels of disability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref></sup> Furthermore drugs may be associated with significant side-effect burden and the risk of toxicity and/or teratogenicity in some instances.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref></sup> Hence better understanding of pathophysiology and drug action appears necessary to improve the use of current treatments and develop better alternatives.</p><p>The dopamine hypothesis of BD dates back at least to the 1970s.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup> Early incarnations focused on mania, and the parallels between the behavioural consequences of amphetamine ingestion and the antimanic actions of antidopaminergic drugs. If hyperdopaminergia underlies the development of manic symptoms, then hypodopaminergia might underlie the depressive phase of the illness. Thus, opposite changes in dopaminergic function were hypothesised to underlie the opposing affective poles of the disorder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup> This theory did not explain how hyper- or hypodopaminergia would arise and subsequent versions proposed an additional component to the hypothesis, where an intrinsic dysregulation in the homoeostatic regulation of dopaminergic function leads to cyclical changes in dopaminergic neurotransmission,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> which would further distinguish the dopamine hypothesis of bipolar from theories of schizophrenia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup> Thus, faulty homoeostatic mechanisms responding to hyperdopaminergia in the manic phase of the illness are proposed to result in an excessive reduction in dopaminergic function, rapidly leading to a hypodopaminergic state and depression. In turn a faulty regulatory response to hypodopaminergia leads, to a switch back to mania.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> Implicit in this model is that a normalisation of dopaminergic function leads to remission and euthymia. Clearly, some kind of dysregulation must be required to account for the onset of episodes, but BD is also characterised by inter-episode mood instability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> Any satisfactory theory must account for the randomness of much bipolar experience as well as the cyclicity. As current antimanic antipsychotics are all dopamine D2 receptor blockers, their use for mania has long supported the involvement of dopamine in mania, but the increasing use of some antidopaminergic drugs to treat bipolar depression and as maintenance drugs makes it timely to review the dopamine hypothesis of BD. Furthermore, a number of new lines of evidence relevant to the role of dopamine, in particular from molecular and functional neuroimaging, have developed in recent years. Thus, we synthesize evidence from pharmacological, <italic>in vivo</italic> neuroimaging and post-mortem studies addressing the role of the dopamine system in BD and then consider the treatment and drug development implications.</p></sec><sec><title>Animal models and their implications for understanding the role of dopamine in bipolar disorder</title><p>Initial animal models of mania were based on amphetamine-induced hyperlocomotion, and it was shown that lithium reverses this behaviour.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup> Following this, a dopamine transporter (DAT) knockout rodent model was developed, and dopamine transporter blockers other than amphetamine (such as GBR12909) have been used. Both these approaches have been shown to induce manic-like behaviour, such as hyperlocomotion and increased exploration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> Subsequently, dopamine receptor stimulation using quinipirole (a dopamine agonist) was shown to induce manic-like behaviour.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> Interestingly, mood stabilisers such as valproate and carbamazepine reversed these effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> Recently, Sidor and colleagues demonstrated the impact of alterations in the regulation of circardian rhythm on dopaminergic activity and behaviour.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref></sup> In this study, mice with a mutation in a circadian clock gene displayed a manic-like phenotype as measured by hyperlocomotion in the daytime. Moreover, hyperlocomotion was linked to an elevated daytime spike in ventral tegmental area (VTA) dopaminergic activity, as well as increased dopamine synthesis and tyrosine hydroxylase activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref></sup> This was further validated using sustained optogenetic stimulation of the VTA, which also induced hyperlocomotion behaviour.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref></sup> Taken together this evidence suggests that hyperdopaminergia, induced either by increased dopamine release, dopamine transporter blockade or dopamine receptor stimulation, results in a mania-like phenotype in rodents. In contrast, lesions in dopaminergic areas (such as the VTA and substantia nigra) induce depressive behaviour, such as learned helplessness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref></sup> Moreover, optogenetic stimulation of VTA dopaminergic neurons reverses depressive behaviour (as assessed using the forced swim test in chronically stressed animals).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> These models thus provide evidence that hypodopaminergia may induce depressive-like behaviours and hyperdopaminergia may induce manic-like behaviour. Further research is needed to determine the key components of the dopaminergic circuit underlying this, particularly in relation to depressive behaviour.</p></sec><sec><title>Post-mortem studies on dopamine gene expression in bipolar disorder</title><p><xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the post-mortem studies addressing dopaminergic gene expression in BD. Overall the most consistent findings come from studies on the D2 receptor expression, with two studies suggesting that the D2 receptor is upregulated in BD in the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> However, to date only four studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref></sup> have been conducted, and only two focus on the same region (dorsolateral prefrontal cortex). Thus, this finding still requires replication in other brain regions to determine if there is regional specificity. The literature on other dopaminergic receptors is more limited, with only two studies on the D1 receptor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref></sup> and one study on the D5 receptor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup> Another issue for the post-mortem studies is that they are affected by several confounding factors such as medication status, post-mortem interval, substance abuse and cause of death. Antidopaminergic treatment has been shown to increase D2/3 receptor levels in animals,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup> and there is evidence this may also occur in schizophrenia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup> This suggests that prior treatment could also have affected the D2/3 receptor findings in BD. Finally, data on phase-specific changes are difficult to characterise as clinical status at the time of death remains unknown. Despite these limitations, post-mortem data supports the notion that an abnormality within the dopaminergic pathways, in particular involving D2/3 receptors, might play a role in the pathogenesis of BD.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vivo</italic> imaging of dopamine</title><sec><title>Dopamine in mania</title><p>We have summarised the <italic>in vivo</italic> imaging studies of mania in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Interestingly, patients with psychotic mania showed an elevated density of D2/3 receptors as measured by N-[<sup>11</sup>C]-methylspiperone, when compared with healthy controls (HC) and non-psychotic mania patients,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref></sup> although, as this tracer has significant affinity for 5HT2 receptors as well,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref></sup> this finding requires replication with more selective tracers. Moreover, no significant difference in the striatal D2/3 density was noted in non-psychotic mania patients compared to HC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref></sup> These studies also explored the relationship between manic symptoms (as assessed using Young's Mania Rating Scale Score) and dopamine synthesis capacity and D2/3 density, finding no significant correlations between these variables in patients with mania.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> However, in one of these studies D2/3 density was directly correlated with psychosis scores on the present state examination.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref></sup> Taken together, these data suggest that psychotic symptoms in mania may be associated with dopaminergic abnormalities, although the same cannot be inferred in non-psychotic mania patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Dopamine in euthymic BD</title><p>Two studies have assessed dopamine transporters in the euthymic state and are conflicting. Chang <italic>et al</italic> reported an upregulation of the dopamine transporter in drug naive euthymic bipolar patients, while Anand <italic>et al.</italic> observed a downregulation in a group consisting of both euthymic bipolar and bipolar depression patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup> Additionally, one study has assessed the vesicular monoamine transporter protein (VMAT-2), located in presynaptic neurons and involved in the storage of dopamine. There was an increase in VMAT-2 in the thalamus and dorsal brainstem, but no significant alteration in striatum, in currently euthymic patients with a history of psychotic mania compared with HC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup> A positron emission tomography (PET) study using [<sup>11</sup>C]-SCH23390 found decreased D1 density in the frontal cortex but not in the striatum of bipolar patients compared to HC, suggesting a regional difference in D1 receptor distribution (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">49</xref></sup></p><p>So far, only one PET study has assessed dopamine release in BD. This study used [<sup>123</sup>I]-IBZM to measure dopamine receptor density and release after amphetamine challenge in patients in their euthymic phase of illness, and found no significant differences between patients and HC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Dopamine in bipolar depression</title><p>There is a paucity of literature on dopamine release and post-synaptic dopamine receptor density. Findings on dopamine transporter density remains controversial, with one study showing an increase in bipolar depressive patients when compared with HC, whilst the others, which recruited both euthymic and depressed patients, noted a reduction (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec><title>Dopamine, reward processing and bipolar disorder: functional magnetic resonance imaging studies</title><p>Dopaminergic projections from the VTA to the ventral striatum (VS) (including nucleus accumbens) and prefrontal cortex have an important role in reward processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref></sup> and have also been implicated in the processing of other behaviourally salient stimuli.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">54</xref></sup> The word 'reward' implies three related functional elements: a positive reinforcer for learning, movement towards a desired object and subjective/emotional choices. The brain processes underlying reinforcement and movement can be quantitatively assessed using specific behavioural tasks and single cell or optogenetic recording in animals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref></sup> Tasks that inform emotion <italic>per se</italic> are increasingly being performed in man but necessarily with less direct measures of neuronal activity.</p><p>Investigations in animals have shown that individual neurons signal reward-related information in the midbrain (substantia nigra and VTA), striatum, orbitofrontal cortex, amygdala and associated structures. Most dopamine neurons in the substantia nigra and VTA show brief, phasic responses that reflect the difference in value between received reward and predicted reward. The precise relationship between cell firing and function is still debated, but it would be misleading to think of dopamine neurotransmission simply in terms of a pleasure signal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">56</xref></sup> Changes in BOLD signal occur in the human nucleus accumbens, striatum and frontal cortex over a time course of seconds in response to anticipated reward.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref></sup> Consistent with the animal literature, event-related functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) reward paradigms have demonstrated robust activation of the ventral striatum in relation to both the anticipation and receipt of reward,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">61</xref></sup> presumably related to dopaminergic neurotransmission.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">69</xref></sup></p><p>In BD several fMRI studies employing reward tasks support the existence of abnormal reward-related neural activity in the VS and frontal cortex (task paradigms and results for VS summarised in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, respectively).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">79</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">82</xref></sup> This provides another indirect line of evidence for a dopaminergic abnormality in this disorder. We discuss the evidence in relation to specific mood polarities below.</p><sec><title>Bipolar mania</title><p>During cued reward anticipation Abler <italic>et al.</italic> reported that medicated manic patients had reduced activity to high- vs no-anticipated reward in the VTA,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref></sup> owing to increased neural activity for no-reward-predicting cues in BD patients. Three studies using monetary reward tasks found no difference in VS activation to cued reward anticipation between patients and controls.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">80</xref></sup> Two of these studies did, however, find elevated frontal cortex activity during reward anticipation in manic patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">80</xref></sup> During reward feedback Abler <italic>et al.</italic> reported reduced activity in response to receipt of probabilistic rewards in the VS in BD compared with HC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref></sup> This finding has not been replicated in more recent studies in patients with current manic symptoms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref></sup> or a recent manic episode.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">80</xref></sup></p><p>Together, these studies suggest hyperactive neuronal activity in putatively dopaminergic circuits of the reward system in currently manic patients, particularly during cue-induced reward anticipation. The precise nature of this abnormality, however, remains uncertain.</p></sec><sec><title>Euthymic bipolar</title><p>Euthymic patients are of particular interest because they are at risk of mania. In these patients abnormalities in dopaminergic function would then indicate how vulnerability might be mediated. In medicated euthymic bipolar I patients, VS and prefrontal cortex activity to cued reward anticipation has been variously reported as increased,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref></sup> and no different<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref></sup> compared with controls. During reward feedback VS activity in euthymic bipolar I patients has been reported as increased,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">76</xref></sup> no different<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref></sup> and decreased (in euthymic and mildly depressed patients),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> compared with controls. Reward feedback related activation in the frontal cortex has also variously been reported as elevated,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">76</xref></sup> decreased (in euthymic and mildly depressed patients)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> or no different<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref></sup> in bipolar I patients compared with controls. In euthymic bipolar II patients Caseras <italic>et al.</italic> reported elevated VS and prefrontal cortex activity for cued reward anticipation compared with controls.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">72</xref></sup> This finding, however, was not replicated in a more recent study of medication-naive bipolar II patients, which instead reported reduced anticipation-related activity in the right dorsal striatum in patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">82</xref></sup> Both studies reported no difference in VS activity during reward feedback in patients vs controls. Increased responses in the anticipatory phase of the monetary incentive delay task have been described in euthymic unipolar patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">83</xref></sup> Careful comparison of unipolar with bipolar cases will be necessary to distinguish network dysfunction associated with (hypo)mania from that with depression. All such studies need to be adequately powered and preferably address pre-specified hypotheses, not always a standard observed in imaging studies.</p><p>In summary, the precise nature of the abnormality of reward-related activity in euthymic bipolar patients remains unclear. However, abnormalities of reward processing are probably not confined to the manic phase of the illness. Important differences in task structure and the <italic>post hoc</italic> choice of analysis contrasts between these studies may account for the inconsistencies and non-replication. Further studies are required to explore the suggested differences between euthymic bipolar I, bipolar II and unipolar disorder.</p></sec><sec><title>Bipolar depression</title><p>Three studies have compared monetary reward processing in medicated depressed bipolar I patients and HC. Only one study analysed activity during cued reward anticipation; it reported no difference in anticipation-related activity between patients and HC in VS or prefrontal cortex, although there was blunting in the anterior cingulate cortex in depressed patients (bipolar and unipolar). Neural activity related to outcome anticipation <italic>per se</italic> was increased in left ventrolateral prefrontal cortex in patients with bipolar-1 disorder, compared with healthy controls or patients with unipolar depressive disorder; it may represent a more generalised &#x02018;arousal' response in the bipolar depressed group.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">73</xref></sup> Ventral striatal and prefrontal activation during reward feedback in bipolar depressive patients has been reported both as similar to controls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">79</xref></sup> and decreased.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref></sup></p><p>Recent fMRI studies and meta-analyses have demonstrated blunted activation of the reward network in the ventral striatum and frontal cortex in schizophrenia,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">84</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">86</xref></sup> as well as major depressive disorder and alcohol addiction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">84</xref></sup> In contrast, the fMRI findings in bipolar disorder summarised above do not provide consistent evidence for blunting. It may be important to consider only studies in the manic state, because depressed or even euthymic (often dysthymic) bipolar patients may well show blunting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">82</xref></sup> In mania there was increased frontal activation to reward anticipation in two out of three studies. If this finding is confirmed in further studies, including direct comparisons with patients with schizophrenia, it could point to a key difference in the reward network between mania and schizophrenia. To date a small number of studies have compared reward processing in bipolar disorder with schizophrenia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref></sup> or major depressive disorder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref></sup> Of these, one study reported blunted VS activation in depressed patients diagnosed with bipolar disorder compared with major depressive disorder, at reward feedback.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref></sup> Only one study compared reward processing in schizophrenia and manic patients with controls.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref></sup> Patients with schizophrenia and healthy controls showed an activation in the VTA on expectation of monetary rewards and nucleus accumbens activation during receipt vs omission of rewards. Manic patients, however, showed reduced differential activation in the nucleus accumbens on receipt vs omission of rewards compared to the healthy control subjects. Taken together with the findings in the frontal cortex discussed above, this small study does suggest that in mania there is a deficit in prediction error processing not seen in schizophrenia. It may further imply bipolar disorder specific changes in dopaminergic function, although how much of the fMRI response is driven by disrupted dopaminergic function remains to be determined. Further studies investigating differences in reward processing between bipolar disorder and other psychotic and affective disorders, and across illness phases, will shed light on the reward processing abnormalities specific to bipolar disorder.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Pharmacological evidence</title><sec><title>Dopaminergic manipulations and the induction of mania</title><p>The role of dopaminergic abnormalities in BD has been extensively investigated using a variety of pharmacological approaches (<xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Firstly, studies have shown that psychostimulants, particularly amphetamine, cause mania-like symptoms in healthy volunteers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">87</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">89</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90">90</xref></sup> Further, there are several case series of manic and hypomanic episodes in Parkinson's disease patients treated with Levodopa.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">91</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">92</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib93">93</xref></sup> Bromocriptine, another dopamine agonist, has also been shown to induce manic symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94">94</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">95</xref></sup> Similarly, an increased risk of hypomania/mania was observed in bipolar patients who received stimulant (methylphenidate, amphetamine or modafinil) augmentation for bipolar depression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib96">96</xref></sup> Secondly, pharmacological strategies to deplete tyrosine, a dopamine precursor, are known to reduce manic symptoms, although it remains to be established if this is specifically due to reducing dopamine levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">97</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98">98</xref></sup> Alpha-methyl-p-tyrosine, which induces dopamine depletion by inhibition of tyrosine hydroxylase, also attenuates mania-like symptom in bipolar patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99">99</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib100">100</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Dopaminergic manipulations and the induction of bipolar depression</title><p>Reserpine and tetrabenazine depletes synaptic dopamine by irreversibly inhibiting vesicular uptake of monoamines and has long been known to induce depression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib101">101</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102">102</xref></sup> In addition, a high prevalence of depression is seen in patients with Parkinson's disease and this has been linked to loss of striatal dopaminergic innervation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib104">104</xref></sup> Finally, depletion of tyrosine has been shown to precipitate depressive symptoms in remitted patients with a history of major depressive disorder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105">105</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib106">106</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec><title>Modulation of the dopamine system and treatment of bipolar disorder</title><sec><title>Antidopaminergic drugs in the treatment of mania</title><p>Dopamine antagonists and partial agonists are increasingly used in the treatment of acute mania, bipolar depression and also as maintenance treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib107">107</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib108">108</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib109">109</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib110">110</xref></sup> Olanzapine, risperidone, quetiapine, aripiprazole, asenapine, ziprasidone and cariprazine have been approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) as monotherapy for the treatment of acute mania.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib111">111</xref></sup> Pertinently, a network meta-analysis of 68 randomised controlled trials (RCT), involving 16 073 participants, addressed the efficacy of different drugs in the treatment of acute mania. This showed that dopamine antagonists have larger effect sizes (Haloperidol (standardised mean difference (SMD) relative to placebo: &#x02212;0.56 (95&#x00025; CI &#x02212;0.69 to &#x02212;0.43)), risperidone (&#x02212;0.50 (&#x02212;0.63 to &#x02212;0.38)), olanzapine (&#x02212;0.43 (&#x02212;0.54 to &#x02212;0.32)) than mood stabilisers for the treatment of acute mania (lithium) (&#x02212;0.37 (&#x02212;0.63 to &#x02212;0.11)), carbamazepine (&#x02013;0.36 (&#x02013;0.60 to &#x02212;0.11)), valproate (&#x02013;0.20 (&#x02013;0.37 to &#x02212;0.04)).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup></p><p>As the blockade of the dopamine D2/3 receptors is their common mechanism of action,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup> it is likely that reduced dopamine neurotransmission at least contributes to the clinical efficacy of these drugs. This assumption is supported by the greater efficacy of the cis- but not the trans-isomer of clopenthixol in the treatment of manic symptoms,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib112">112</xref></sup> as the cis-isomer is a high affinity D2/3 receptor blocker while the trans-isomer has much lower affinity for D2/3 receptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib112">112</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Use of antidopaminergic in the maintenance phase</title><p>The FDA have approved olanzapine as monotherapy, quetiapine and ziprasidone as adjunctive therapy, and aripiprazole and risperidone long acting injections as both adjunctive and monotherapy for the maintenance treatment of BD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib111">111</xref></sup> Although lithium and valproate should be preferred, recent guidelines highlight that dopaminergic drugs have a place in maintenance treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib113">113</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Action of non-D2/3 blocker mood stabilisers on dopamine pathways</title><p>Interestingly, it is possible that sodium valproate might exhibit antimanic effect through an action on the dopaminergic system.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> In a study consisting of 13 manic patients, 2 weeks of sodium valproate was shown to decrease presynaptic dopamine synthesis capacity,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> although this was not correlated with clinical improvement. Interestingly D2/3 density remained essentially unchanged after valproate treatment,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref></sup> despite the reduction in dopamine synthesis capacity with valproate, which is anticipated to alter D2/3 availability. Taken together these two could either suggest valproate blocks the capacity of the D2 receptor to respond to reduced dopamine synthesis, or that the capacity of D2 receptors to respond is intrinsically impaired in bipolar disorder. Although both possibilities are speculative at this stage, the latter is particularly interesting as it suggests that a failure of D2 adaptation could contribute to the pathophysiology of bipolar disorder, making the dopamine system more vulnerable to dopamine transporter driven changes in presynaptic function.</p><p>Although the exact mechanism by which lithium acts remains unclear, it is known to modulate signalling pathways downstream of dopamine receptors. Preclinical studies have shown that lithium reverses dopamine dependent behaviour by acting through the protein kinase B (AKT)/glycogen synthase kinase 3 signalling cascade.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib114">114</xref></sup> Furthermore, lithium acts on the adenyl cyclase and phospho-inositide, as well as protein kinase C pathways, which are part of the intracellular signalling pathway downstream of dopamine receptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib115">115</xref></sup> In addition, micro-dialysis studies show a reduction in extracellular dopamine levels in lithium treated animals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib116">116</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib117">117</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib118">118</xref></sup> In summary, there is evidence to suggest that some non-D2/3 blocking mood stabilisers also act to reduce dopamine transmission, either through reducing presynaptic dopamine synthesis capacity in the case of sodium valproate, or post-synaptic dopaminergic signal transduction in the case of lithium. The degree to which these effects explain the therapeutic efficacy of these compounds remains to be determined.</p></sec><sec><title>Use of dopaminergic treatments for bipolar depression</title><p>Three double-blind placebo-controlled studies have shown that short-term use of pramipexole, a D2/D3 receptor agonist, is efficacious as an augmentation strategy for the treatment of bipolar depression and positive results have also been seen in other open-label studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib119">119</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib120">120</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib121">121</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib122">122</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib123">123</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib124">124</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib125">125</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib126">126</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib127">127</xref></sup> Although there have not been any RCTs investigating the efficacy of methylphenidate or amphetamines in bipolar depression, the available open-label and naturalistic studies point towards a benefit of stimulants in a selected group of patients with drowsiness and fatigue.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib128">128</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib129">129</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib130">130</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib131">131</xref></sup> Randomised controlled studies and open-label reports with other stimulant like agents such as modafinil and its R-enantiomer, armodafinil also indicate efficacy in bipolar depression although the development programme for armodafinil failed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib132">132</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib133">133</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib134">134</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib135">135</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib136">136</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib137">137</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib138">138</xref></sup> There is evidence to support the potential use of monoamine oxidase inhibitors such as tranylcypromine in bipolar depression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib139">139</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib140">140</xref></sup> It is speculated that tranylcypromine acts as dopamine releaser with about 1/10th the potency of amphetamine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib139">139</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib140">140</xref></sup> There are thus several lines of evidence suggesting that dopaminergic augmentation is beneficial in bipolar depression.</p><p>However, there is also evidence that dopamine antagonists are effective in the treatment of bipolar depression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> The FDA has approved the combination of olanzapine and fluoxetine, as well as monotherapy with quetiapine or lurasidone, for the treatment of acute bipolar depression. A recent meta-analysis of 24 placebo-controlled trails (<italic>n</italic>=7307) revealed the following order of efficacy of drugs for the treatment of bipolar depression: olanzapine&#x0002b;fluoxetine&#x02a7e;valproate&#x0003e;quetiapine&#x0003e;lurasidone&#x0003e;olanzapine, aripiprazole and carbamazepine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib141">141</xref></sup> The analysis is interesting in showing that antidopaminergics on their own have efficacy in bipolar depression.</p><p>The evidence thus suggests that both dopaminergic agonists and dopaminergic blockers, are effective in treating bipolar depression. This presents a paradox for understanding the role of dopamine in bipolar depression. However, actions at receptors other than dopamine ones may underlie the efficacy of the dopamine blockers. For example, as well as all being D2/3 receptor blockers, olanzapine and quetiapine are both relatively high affinity 5HT<sub>2A</sub> antagonists,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib142">142</xref></sup> whilst both lurasidone and aripiprazole have high affinity for 5HT<sub>1A</sub> receptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib142">142</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib143">143</xref></sup> Potentially supporting this explanation, there are no clinical trials reporting efficacy of pure D2/3 blockers in bipolar depression. Nevertheless, the doses used in the clinical trials correspond to the dose ranges associated with substantial dopamine D2/3 receptor occupancy,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup> so dopamine receptor blockade is certainly compatible with antidepressant efficacy. The final consideration is that there has been a relatively small number of good quality RCTs for antidopaminergic treatment in bipolar depression, certainly in comparison to studies in mania. Studies that can directly test the mechanism underlying the mode of action of these drugs and pramipexole would be of great interest.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our main findings for bipolar mania are that (i) there is consistent pharmacological evidence, especially from treatment studies, to support the hypothesis that a state of hyperdopaminergia can lead to mania; (ii) imaging studies support this hypothesis, with several studies reporting elevations in D2/3 receptor availability in psychotic mania and fMRI imaging evidence that identifies hyperactivity of the reward circuit in mania. Dopamine synthesis and receptor density appear to remain unchanged, at least in non-psychotic mania patients compared with HC.</p><p>For bipolar depression (i) pharmacological evidence shows that dopamine agonists are potentially beneficial for bipolar depression, but the same seems true for dopamine blocking drugs; (ii) the imaging studies show replicated increases in dopamine transporter levels, but there is inconsistency and it is not clear if there are other alterations as well. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> summarises our main imaging findings for mania and depression.</p><p>Finally, post-mortem evidence suggests an upregulation of the D2/3 receptors in bipolar patients, but interpretation is limited by lack of information on phase of illness and medication status at the time of death.</p><sec><title>Implications for the dopamine hypothesis of bipolar disorder</title><p>More than four decades on from the early conceptualisations of the dopamine hypothesis of BD, it has stood the test of time, and the evidence for elements have strengthened. This is particularly the case for mania where the strength of the clinical trial evidence for the benefit of dopamine antagonists and partial agonists, supported by meta-analysis, would require an improbably large number of negative studies for reversal. Added to this there is now molecular and fMRI imaging evidence in bipolar disorder. Further, preclinical studies using optogenetic methods and knockout mice have shown that dopaminergic neuron activation leads to manic-like behaviour and it is linked to circadian gene expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib144">144</xref></sup> Tentatively, these studies suggest elevated D2/3 receptor availability and a hyper-responsive reward system in ventral striatum in mania, and an increase in striatal dopamine transporter availability in bipolar depression. Dopamine neurotransmission in the striatum is primarily terminated by reuptake of dopamine into the presynaptic dopamine nerve terminal by dopamine transporters. Thus, an elevation in striatal D2/3 receptor availability in mania would lead to increased dopaminergic neurotransmission whilst increased striatal dopamine transporter levels in depression would lead to reduced dopaminergic function. This suggests a model in which elevated D2/3 receptor levels lead to altered reward processing and the development of mania, which is followed by a compensatory increase in dopamine transporter levels to reduce dopaminergic neurotransmission. However, if, over time, D2/3 receptor levels reduce but dopamine transporter levels do not normalise, this would then lead to reduced dopaminergic transmission, leading to depression and, in turn, a compensatory upregulation of D2/3 receptor levels, precipitating a further phase switch. One can see how a failure of homoeostatic regulation of the dopaminergic system could lead to cyclical periods of elevated and blunted dopaminergic neurotransmission. This model might apply most precisely to rapid cycling bipolar disorder. However it could be a component of all manic episodes, with other systems acting to disrupt the regular cyclicity that is so obvious in a substantial number of patients.</p><p>We recognise that this model is conjectural at this stage. Nevertheless, it makes predictions that can be tested empirically. In particular it predicts longitudinal changes in dopamine transporter and receptor levels linked to phase switches. Moreover it predicts that these changes and alterations in reward processing will pre-date symptom changes. However, many aspects of dopamine function in bipolar disorder are incompletely characterised. In particular baseline dopamine levels have not been measured in mania or depression. In addition, psychotic symptoms may also be present in manic patients, and psychosis <italic>per se</italic> may drive dopaminergic changes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib145">145</xref></sup> It is worth noting that, none of the studies have investigated dopamine function in mixed states. As approximately two thirds of depressed patients have concomitant manic symptoms,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib146">146</xref></sup> any theory needs to explain mixed states as well as mania and depression. It would be hard to account for mixed states by dysfunction in dopaminergic function alone. Interestingly, asenapine seems to be more effective than olanzapine for mixed episodes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib147">147</xref></sup> As asenapine has higher affinity for 5HT2A than D2/3 receptors, which could suggest a role of serotonergic system in mixed episode states. Finally elevations in D<sub>2/3</sub> receptor availability would be predicted to increase dopaminergic neurotransmission via the indirect pathway, and reduce response to cues,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib148">148</xref></sup> while the fMRI findings in mania do not seem to fit with this. However, the majority of the patients in these studies were treated with dopamine antagonists and mood stabilisers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>), which confounds simple interpretation of effects based on dopamine neurotransmission.</p></sec><sec><title>Implications for treatment</title><p>If dopamine transmission is increased in mania, the use of D2/3 receptor blockers is logical, but alternative approaches, such as reducing dopamine synthesis and/or release, are alternative approaches that may be more effective and/or better tolerated if they could be sufficiently selective. Similarly, selective DAT blockade could be beneficial for BD depression, at the risk of precipitating mania. Finally mood stabilisation should improve homoeostatic regulation of dopaminergic neurotransmission, and this requires further evaluation and understanding.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations and future directions</title><p>The key limitation of the dopamine hypothesis remains that its strongest supporting evidence comes from pharmacological studies, which offer an indirect and sometimes imprecise approach to studying dopaminergic function. Reserpine, alpha-methyl-para-tyrosine, amphetamine and <sc>l</sc>-DOPA, for example, can affect neurotransmission of other monoamines, in particular norepinephrine, which could contribute to the clinical effects observed. By the same token, the efficacy of antidopaminergic drugs in mania may be due to actions at other neurotransmitter systems, although relatively selective dopamine blockers do appear to be effective. There is a relative paucity of evidence from more direct measures, such as molecular imaging studies, and thus conclusions remain tentative at this stage. Earlier molecular imaging studies on D2/3 density in mania were conducted using non-selective ligand [<sup>11</sup>C]N-methylspiperone, which has affinity to both D2/3 and 5HT2A receptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib149">149</xref></sup> Interpretation is further complicated by some studies not being restricted to one illness phase. Moreover, none of the studies addressed dopamine transporter availability in mania, dopamine release in mania or dopamine release in bipolar depression (summarised in Figure 1).</p><p>Although our model suggests euthymia is a state of normalised dopamine, based on a study demonstrating no significant alteration in the dopamine release paradigm in euthymic patients compared to controls,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref></sup> this is not consistent with the finding of elevated DAT in a euthymic state.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup> It also remains unclear whether the dopamine hypothesis can completely explain bipolar depression and how dopaminergic dysregulation will be linked to the involvement of other neurotransmitter systems.</p><p>A critical limitation is the lack of longitudinal studies that investigate changes across phases of illness, including mixed states. Ideally future studies should focus on elucidating phase-related dopamine dysfunction by studying patients longitudinally in euthymic, manic and depressive episodes to determine the direction of causality. Clearly this will be difficult, although a focus on rapid cycling patients might make it feasible. Cross-sectional studies are more feasible and could test key elements of the dopamine hypothesis if well designed. Another key issue is why some antidopaminergics are effective for bipolar depression. Molecular imaging studies are needed to determine whether dopaminergic, serotonergic or other systems are involved in their mode of action. Finally, although studies have found an effect of valproate and lithium on dopaminergic function,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib115">115</xref></sup> it is not established if this is their mechanism of action. Determining whether dopaminergic mechanisms are common across classes of medication would be an important advance in understanding. Finally, it remains unclear if hyperdopaminergic activity is specific to mania or psychosis because many of the manic patients in the studies had psychotic symptoms as well. It is interesting to note that in schizophrenia molecular imaging studies indicate there is an elevation in dopamine synthesis and release capacity, but unaltered dopamine transporter and D2/3 receptor availability in striatum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup> PET studies have also demonstrated elevated striatal dopamine turnover, but blunted cortical and midbrain dopamine release in schizophrenia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib150">150</xref></sup> In addition, blunting of the fMRI signal during reward tasks is observed in schizophrenia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">85</xref></sup> In contrast, studies in bipolar disorder suggest dopamine synthesis capacity is unaltered, at least in non-psychotic mania, but there is elevated D2/3 receptor availability in psychotic mania. However, direct comparisons of dopaminergic function in psychotic mania and schizophrenia as well as longitudinal studies of dopaminergic activity across various phases of illness are needed to determine if there are differences between mania and schizophrenia, and between mania and bipolar depression (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box1">Box 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The dopamine hypothesis of bipolar disorder proposes that faulty homoeostasis between dopamine transporter and receptors underlies depressive and manic phases of the illness. The available evidence suggests elevated D2/3 receptor availability and a hyper-responsive reward system in mania, and possibly increased dopamine transporter availability in bipolar depression. Future longitudinal studies are needed to elucidate the precise phase-related changes in dopaminergic function and the specificity of alterations to mania over psychosis.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>AHA, TRM and MMN conduct research funded by the Medical Research Council (UK). TRM received honoraria as a speaker for Lundbeck. SJ conducts research funded by Medical Research Council (UK) and Wellcome trust. Professor Howes conducts research funded by the Medical Research Council (UK), the National Institute of Health Research (UK) and the Maudsley Charity. Professor Goodwin holds a grant from Wellcome Trust, holds shares in P1vital and has served as consultant, advisor or CME speaker for AstraZeneca, Merck, Cephalon/Teva, Eli Lilly, Lundbeck, Medscape, Otsuka, P1Vital, Pfizer, Servier, Sunovion, Takeda. He is a NIHR Senior Investigator. Professor Young has been a consultant to or has received honoraria or grants from AstraZeneca, Lunbeck, Eli Lilly, Janssen, Servier, Sunovion, Cyberonics and Wyeth. ODH has received investigator-initiated research funding from and/or participated in advisory/speaker meetings organised by AstraZeneca, BMS, Eli Lilly, Jansenn, Lundbeck, Lyden-Delta, Servier, and Roche. The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Information</xref> accompanies the paper on the Molecular Psychiatry website (http://www.nature.com/mp)</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Judd LL, Akiskal HS, Schettler PJ, Endicott J, Leon AC, Solomon DA et al. <article-title>Psychosocial disability in the course of bipolar I and II disorders: a prospective, comparative, longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1322</fpage>&#x02013;1330.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16330720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Judd LL, Schettler PJ, Solomon DA, Maser JD, Coryell W, Endicott J et al. <article-title>Psychosocial disability and work role function compared across the long-term course of bipolar I, bipolar II and unipolar major depressive disorders</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;58.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18006071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vos T, Flaxman AD, Naghavi M, Lozano R, Michaud C, Ezzati M et al. <article-title>Years lived with disability (YLDs) for 1160 sequelae of 289 diseases and injuries 1990-2010: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>380</volume>: <fpage>2163</fpage>&#x02013;2196.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23245607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Merikangas KR, Cui L, Kattan G, Carlson GA, Youngstrom EA, Angst J. <article-title>Mania with and without depression in a community sample of US adolescents</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>943</fpage>&#x02013;951.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22566563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Merikangas KR, Jin R, He JP, Kessler RC, Lee S, Sampson NA et al. <article-title>Prevalence and correlates of bipolar spectrum disorder in the world mental health survey initiative</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;251.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21383262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Grande I, Berk M, Birmaher B, Vieta E. <article-title>Bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>387</volume>: <fpage>1561</fpage>&#x02013;1572.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26388529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dilsaver SC. <article-title>An estimate of the minimum economic burden of bipolar I and II disorders in the United States: 2009</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;83.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20888048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jann MW. <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of bipolar disorders in adults: a review of the evidence on pharmacologic treatments</article-title>. <source>Am Health Drug Benefits</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;499.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25610528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alda M. <article-title>Lithium in the treatment of bipolar disorder: pharmacology and pharmacogenetics</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>&#x02013;670.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25687772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Geddes JR, Burgess S, Hawton K, Jamison K, Goodwin GM. <article-title>Long-term lithium therapy for bipolar disorder: systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;222.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14754766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gitlin M. <article-title>Treatment-resistant bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;240.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16432528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ketter TA, Miller S, Dell'Osso B, Wang PW. <article-title>Treatment of bipolar disorder: review of evidence regarding quetiapine and lithium</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>&#x02013;273.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26688495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Severus E, Taylor MJ, Sauer C, Pfennig A, Ritter P, Bauer M et al. <article-title>Lithium for prevention of mood episodes in bipolar disorders: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25530932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cipriani A, Barbui C, Salanti G, Rendell J, Brown R, Stockton S et al. <article-title>Comparative efficacy and acceptability of antimanic drugs in acute mania: a multiple-treatments meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>378</volume>: <fpage>1306</fpage>&#x02013;1315.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21851976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Young AH, McElroy SL, Olausson B, Paulsson B. <article-title>A randomised, placebo-controlled 52-week trial of continued quetiapine treatment in recently depressed patients with bipolar I and bipolar II disorder</article-title>. <source>World J Biol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>&#x02013;112.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22404704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Giles JJ, Bannigan JG. <article-title>Teratogenic and developmental effects of lithium</article-title>. <source>Curr Pharm Des</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1531</fpage>&#x02013;1541.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16611133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gentile S. <article-title>Lithium in pregnancy: the need to treat, the duty to ensure safety</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Drug Saf</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;437.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22400907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McKnight RF, Adida M, Budge K, Stockton S, Goodwin GM, Geddes JR. <article-title>Lithium toxicity profile: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>379</volume>: <fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;728.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tissot R. <article-title>The common pathophysiology of monaminergic psychoses: a new hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychobiology</source>
<year>1975</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;260.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">775359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wittenborn JR. <article-title>Deductive approaches to the catecholamine hypothesis of affective disorders</article-title>. <source>J Nerv Ment Dis</source>
<year>1974</year>; <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>&#x02013;324.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4823932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Singh MM. <article-title>A unifying hypothesis on the biochemical basis of affective disorder</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Q</source>
<year>1970</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>706</fpage>&#x02013;724.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4251300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berk M, Dodd S, Kauer-Sant'anna M, Malhi GS, Bourin M, Kapczinski F et al. <article-title>Dopamine dysregulation syndrome: implications for a dopamine hypothesis of bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand Suppl</source>
<year>2007</year>; (<fpage>434</fpage>): <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;49.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cousins DA, Butts K, Young AH. <article-title>The role of dopamine in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;806.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19922550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Howes OD, Egerton A, Allan V, McGuire P, Stokes P, Kapur S. <article-title>Mechanisms underlying psychosis and antipsychotic treatment response in schizophrenia: insights from PET and SPECT imaging</article-title>. <source>Curr Pharm Des</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2550</fpage>&#x02013;2559.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19689327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Harrison PJ, Cipriani A, Harmer CJ, Nobre AC, Saunders K, Goodwin GM et al. <article-title>Innovative approaches to bipolar disorder and its treatment</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>1366</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;89.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27111134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berggren U, Tallstedt L, Ahlenius S, Engel J. <article-title>The effect of lithium on amphetamine-induced locomotor stimulation</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology</source>
<year>1978</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;45.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">100811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gould TJ, Keith RA, Bhat RV. <article-title>Differential sensitivity to lithium's reversal of amphetamine-induced open-field activity in two inbred strains of mice</article-title>. <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;105.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perry W, Minassian A, Paulus MP, Young JW, Kincaid MJ, Ferguson EJ et al. <article-title>A reverse-translational study of dysfunctional exploration in psychiatric disorders: from mice to men</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1072</fpage>&#x02013;1080.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Young JW, Goey AK, Minassian A, Perry W, Paulus MP, Geyer MA. <article-title>The mania-like exploratory profile in genetic dopamine transporter mouse models is diminished in a familiar environment and reinstated by subthreshold psychostimulant administration</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;15.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20363246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shaldubina A, Einat H, Szechtman H, Shimon H, Belmaker RH. <article-title>Preliminary evaluation of oral anticonvulsant treatment in the quinpirole model of bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>J Neural Transm</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;440.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11956963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sidor MM, Spencer SM, Dzirasa K, Parekh PK, Tye KM, Warden MR et al. <article-title>Daytime spikes in dopaminergic activity drive rapid mood-cycling in mice</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1406</fpage>&#x02013;1419.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25560763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Winter C, von Rumohr A, Mundt A, Petrus D, Klein J, Lee T et al. <article-title>Lesions of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra pars compacta and in the ventral tegmental area enhance depressive-like behavior in rats</article-title>. <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;141.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17698212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tye KM, Mirzabekov JJ, Warden MR, Ferenczi EA, Tsai HC, Finkelstein J et al. <article-title>Dopamine neurons modulate neural encoding and expression of depression-related behaviour</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>493</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>&#x02013;541.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23235822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kaalund SS, Newburn EN, Ye T, Tao R, Li C, Deep-Soboslay A et al. <article-title>Contrasting changes in DRD1 and DRD2 splice variant expression in schizophrenia and affective disorders, and associations with SNPs in postmortem brain</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1258</fpage>&#x02013;1266.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24322206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhan L, Kerr JR, Lafuente MJ, Maclean A, Chibalina MV, Liu B et al. <article-title>Altered expression and coregulation of dopamine signalling genes in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuropathol Appl Neurobiol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>&#x02013;219.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20874815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Glantz LA, Gilmore JH, Overstreet DH, Salimi K, Lieberman JA, Jarskog LF. <article-title>Pro-apoptotic Par-4 and dopamine D2 receptor in temporal cortex in schizophrenia, bipolar disorder and major depression</article-title>. <source>Schizophr Res</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>&#x02013;299.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20067857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pantazopoulos H, Stone D, Walsh J, Benes FM. <article-title>Differences in the cellular distribution of D1 receptor mRNA in the hippocampus of bipolars and schizophrenics</article-title>. <source>Synapse</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;155.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Knable MB, Barci BM, Webster MJ, Meador-Woodruff J, Torrey EF. <article-title>Molecular abnormalities of the hippocampus in severe psychiatric illness: postmortem findings from the Stanley Neuropathology Consortium</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ginovart N, Wilson AA, Hussey D, Houle S, Kapur S. <article-title>D2-receptor upregulation is dependent upon temporal course of D2-occupancy: a longitudinal [11C]-raclopride PET study in cats</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;671.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18688210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Howes OD, Kambeitz J, Kim E, Stahl D, Slifstein M, Abi-Dargham A et al. <article-title>The nature of dopamine dysfunction in schizophrenia and what this means for treatment</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;786.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22474070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pearlson GD, Wong DF, Tune LE, Ross CA, Chase GA, Links JM et al. <article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> D2 dopamine receptor density in psychotic and nonpsychotic patients with bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;477.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7771917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wong DF, Pearlson GD, Tune LE, Young LT, Meltzer CC, Dannals RF et al. <article-title>Quantification of neuroreceptors in the living human brain: IV. Effect of aging and elevations of D2-like receptors in schizophrenia and bipolar illness</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;342.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9119906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Swart JA, van der Werf JF, Wiegman T, Paans AM, Vaalburg W, Korf J. <article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> binding of spiperone and N-methylspiperone to dopaminergic and serotonergic sites in the rat brain: multiple modeling and implications for PET scanning</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source>
<year>1990</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;306.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1970341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yatham LN, Liddle PF, Lam RW, Shiah IS, Lane C, Stoessl AJ et al. <article-title>PET study of the effects of valproate on dopamine D(2) receptors in neuroleptic- and mood-stabilizer-naive patients with nonpsychotic mania</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>1718</fpage>&#x02013;1723.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12359678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yatham LN, Liddle PF, Shiah IS, Lam RW, Ngan E, Scarrow G et al. <article-title>PET study of [(18)F]6-fluoro-L-dopa uptake in neuroleptic- and mood-stabilizer-naive first-episode nonpsychotic mania: effects of treatment with divalproex sodium</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>768</fpage>&#x02013;774.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11986130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anand A, Barkay G, Dzemidzic M, Albrecht D, Karne H, Zheng QH et al. <article-title>Striatal dopamine transporter availability in unmedicated bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>406</fpage>&#x02013;413.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21843280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chang TT, Yeh TL, Chiu NT, Chen PS, Huang HY, Yang YK et al. <article-title>Higher striatal dopamine transporters in euthymic patients with bipolar disorder: a SPECT study with [Tc] TRODAT-1</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;106.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zubieta JK, Huguelet P, Ohl LE, Koeppe RA, Kilbourn MR, Carr JM et al. <article-title>High vesicular monoamine transporter binding in asymptomatic bipolar I disorder: sex differences and cognitive correlates</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>1619</fpage>&#x02013;1628.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11007716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Suhara T, Nakayama K, Inoue O, Fukuda H, Shimizu M, Mori A et al. <article-title>D1 dopamine receptor binding in mood disorders measured by positron emission tomography</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology</source>
<year>1992</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;18.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1531387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anand A, Verhoeff P, Seneca N, Zoghbi SS, Seibyl JP, Charney DS et al. <article-title>Brain SPECT imaging of amphetamine-induced dopamine release in euthymic bipolar disorder patients</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>1108</fpage>&#x02013;1114.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10873919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berridge KC. <article-title>From prediction error to incentive salience: Mesolimbic computation of reward motivation</article-title>. <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1124</fpage>&#x02013;1143.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22487042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schultz W. <article-title>Dopamine signals for reward value and risk: basic and recent data</article-title>. <source>Behav Brain Funct</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20047681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Winton-Brown TT, Fusar-Poli P, Ungless MA, Howes OD. <article-title>Dopaminergic basis of salience dysregulation in psychosis</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;94.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24388426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Howes OD, Nour MM. <article-title>Dopamine and the aberrant salience hypothesis of schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>World Psychiatry</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26833595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tsai HC, Zhang F, Adamantidis A, Stuber GD, Bonci A, de Lecea L et al. <article-title>Phasic firing in dopaminergic neurons is sufficient for behavioral conditioning</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>324</volume>: <fpage>1080</fpage>&#x02013;1084.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19389999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schultz W. <article-title>Updating dopamine reward signals</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;238.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23267662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schott BH, Minuzzi L, Krebs RM, Elmenhorst D, Lang M, Winz OH et al. <article-title>Mesolimbic functional magnetic resonance imaging activations during reward anticipation correlate with reward-related ventral striatal dopamine release</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>14311</fpage>&#x02013;14319.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19109512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bartra O, McGuire JT, Kable JW. <article-title>The valuation system: a coordinate-based meta-analysis of BOLD fMRI experiments examining neural correlates of subjectivevalue</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>&#x02013;427.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23507394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Diekhof EK, Kaps L, Falkai P, Gruber O. <article-title>The role of the human ventral striatum and the medial orbitofrontal cortex in the representation of reward magnitude - an activation likelihood estimation meta-analysis of neuroimaging studies of passive reward expectancy and outcome processing</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1252</fpage>&#x02013;1266.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu X, Hairston J, Schrier M, Fan J. <article-title>Common and distinct networks underlying reward valence and processing stages: a meta-analysis of functional neuroimaging studies</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1219</fpage>&#x02013;1236.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21185861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nusslock R, Young CB, Damme KSF. <article-title>Elevated reward-related neural activation as a unique biological marker of bipolar disorder: assessment and treatment implications</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Therapy</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;87.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Aarts E, Roelofs A, Franke B, Rijpkema M, Fernandez G, Helmich RC et al. <article-title>Striatal dopamine mediates the interface between motivational and cognitive control in humans: evidence from genetic imaging</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1943</fpage>&#x02013;1951.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20463658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dreher JC, Kohn P, Kolachana B, Weinberger DR, Berman KF. <article-title>Variation in dopamine genes influences responsivity of the human reward system</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;622.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19104049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Forbes EE, Brown SM, Kimak M, Ferrell RE, Manuck SB, Hariri AR. <article-title>Genetic variation in components of dopamine neurotransmission impacts ventral striatal reactivity associated with impulsivity</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17893706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jonasson LS, Axelsson J, Riklund K, Braver TS, Ogren M, Backman L et al. <article-title>Dopamine release in nucleus accumbens during rewarded task switching measured by [(1)(1)C]raclopride</article-title>. <source>NeuroImage</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;364.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24862078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schultz W. <article-title>Multiple dopamine functions at different time courses</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;288.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17600522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van der Schaaf ME, van Schouwenburg MR, Geurts DE, Schellekens AF, Buitelaar JK, Verkes RJ et al. <article-title>Establishing the dopamine dependency of human striatal signals during reward and punishment reversal learning</article-title>. <source>Cereb Cortex</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>&#x02013;642.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23183711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Knutson B, Gibbs SEB. <article-title>Linking nucleus accumbens dopamine and blood oxygenation</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>813</fpage>&#x02013;822.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17279377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pessiglione M, Seymour B, Flandin G, Dolan RJ, Frith CD. <article-title>Dopamine-dependent prediction errors underpin reward-seeking behaviour in humans</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>442</volume>: <fpage>1042</fpage>&#x02013;1045.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16929307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Abler B, Greenhouse I, Ongur D, Walter H, Heckers S. <article-title>Abnormal reward system activation in mania</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>2217</fpage>&#x02013;2227.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17987058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bermpohl F, Kahnt T, Dalanay U, H&#x000e4;gele C, Sajonz B, Wegner T et al. <article-title>Altered representation of expected value in the orbitofrontal cortex in Mania</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>958</fpage>&#x02013;969.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19950195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Caseras X, Lawrence NS, Murphy K, Wise RG, Phillips ML. <article-title>Ventral striatum activity in response to reward: differences between bipolar i and II disorders</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>170</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;541.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23558337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chase HW, Nusslock R, Almeida JR, Forbes EE, Labarbara EJ, Phillips ML. <article-title>Dissociable patterns of abnormal frontal cortical activation during anticipation of an uncertain reward or loss in bipolar versus major depression</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;854.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24148027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dutra S, Cunningham W, Kober H, Gruber J. <article-title>Elevated striatal reactivity across monetary and social rewards in bipolar I disorder</article-title>. <source>J Abnorm Psychol</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>890</fpage>&#x02013;904.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26390194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Linke J, King AV, Rietschel M, Strohmaier J, Hennerici M, Gass A et al. <article-title>Increased medial orbitofrontal and amygdala activation: evidence for a systems-level endophenotype of bipolar I disorder</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>&#x02013;325.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22267184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mason L, O'Sullivan N, Montaldi D, Bentall RP, El-Deredy W. <article-title>Decision-making and trait impulsivity in bipolar disorder are associated with reduced prefrontal regulation of striatal reward valuation</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>2346</fpage>&#x02013;2355.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nusslock R, Almeida J, Forbes E, Versace A, Frank E, LeBarbara E et al. <article-title>Waiting to win: elevated striatal and orbitofrontal cortical activity during reward anticipation in euthymic bipolar disorder adults</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;260.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22548898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Redlich R, Dohm K, Grotegerd D, Opel N, Zwitserlood P, Heindel W et al. <article-title>Reward processing in unipolar and bipolar depression: a functional MRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;28.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25482168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Satterthwaite TD, Kable JW, Vandekar L, Katchmar N, Bassett DS, Baldassano CF et al. <article-title>Common and dissociable dysfunction of the reward system in bipolar and unipolar depression reward dysfunction in depression</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25482168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Singh MK, Chang KD, Kelley RG, Cui X, Sherdell L, Howe ME et al. <article-title>Reward processing in adolescents with bipolar I disorder</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;83.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23265635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Trost S, Diekhof EK, Zvonik K, Lewandowski M, Usher J, Keil M et al. <article-title>Disturbed anterior prefrontal control of the mesolimbic reward system and increased impulsivity in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1914</fpage>&#x02013;1923.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24535101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yip SW, Worhunsky PD, Rogers RD, Goodwin GM. <article-title>Hypoactivation of the ventral and dorsal striatum during reward and loss anticipation in antipsychotic and mood stabilizer-naive bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>658</fpage>&#x02013;666.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25139065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dichter GS, Kozink RV, McClernon FJ, Smoski MJ. <article-title>Remitted major depression is characterized by reward network hyperactivation during reward anticipation and hypoactivation during reward outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>1126</fpage>&#x02013;1134.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22036801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hagele C, Schlagenhauf F, Rapp M, Sterzer P, Beck A, Bermpohl F et al. <article-title>Dimensional psychiatry: reward dysfunction and depressive mood across psychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>232</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;341.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24973896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Radua J, Schmidt A, Borgwardt S, Heinz A, Schlagenhauf F, McGuire P et al. <article-title>Ventral striatal activation during reward processing in psychosis: a neurofunctional meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1243</fpage>&#x02013;1251.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26558708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yan C, Yang T, Yu QJ, Jin Z, Cheung EF, Liu X et al. <article-title>Rostral medial prefrontal dysfunctions and consummatory pleasure in schizophrenia: a meta-analysis of functional imaging studies</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>231</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;196.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25637357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Asghar SJ, Tanay VA, Baker GB, Greenshaw A, Silverstone PH. <article-title>Relationship of plasma amphetamine levels to physiological, subjective, cognitive and biochemical measures in healthy volunteers</article-title>. <source>Hum Psychopharm</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;299.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Silverstone T. <article-title>Dopamine in manic depressive illness. A pharmacological synthesis</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>1985</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;231.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2862169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jacobs D, Silverstone T. <article-title>Dextroamphetamine-induced arousal in human subjects as a model for mania</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>
<year>1986</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;329.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3726006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nurnberger JI Jr., Gershon ES, Simmons S, Ebert M, Kessler LR, Dibble ED et al. <article-title>Behavioral, biochemical and neuroendocrine responses to amphetamine in normal twins and 'well-state' bipolar patients</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>
<year>1982</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;176.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6891082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ko GN, Leckman JF, Heninger GR. <article-title>Induction of rapid mood cycling during L-dopa treatment in a bipolar patient</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>1981</year>; <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>1624</fpage>&#x02013;1625.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7304798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Harsch HH, Miller M, Young LD. <article-title>Induction of mania by L-dopa in a nonbipolar patient</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source>
<year>1985</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>338</fpage>&#x02013;339.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4066999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Murphy DL. <article-title>L-dopa, behavioral activation and psychopathology</article-title>. <source>Res Publ Assoc Res Nerv Ment Dis</source>
<year>1972</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>&#x02013;493.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4627219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fisher G, Pelonero AL, Ferguson C. <article-title>Mania precipitated by prednisone and bromocriptine</article-title>. <source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source>
<year>1991</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;346.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1743505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kemperman CJ, Zwanikken GJ. <article-title>Psychiatric side effects of bromocriptine therapy for postpartum galactorrhoea</article-title>. <source>J R Soc Med</source>
<year>1987</year>; <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;388.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3625697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wingo AP, Ghaemi SN. <article-title>Frequency of stimulant treatment and of stimulant-associated mania/hypomania in bipolar disorder patients</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacol Bull</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McTavish SF, McPherson MH, Harmer CJ, Clark L, Sharp T, Goodwin GM et al. <article-title>Antidopaminergic effects of dietary tyrosine depletion in healthy subjects and patients with manic illness</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;360.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11581118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Scarna A, Gijsman HJ, McTavish SF, Harmer CJ, Cowen PJ, Goodwin GM. <article-title>Effects of a branched-chain amino acid drink in mania</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>182</volume>: <fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;213.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12611783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anand A, Darnell A, Miller HL, Berman RM, Cappiello A, Oren DA et al. <article-title>Effect of catecholamine depletion on lithium-induced long-term remission of bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>972</fpage>&#x02013;978.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10386179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">van Enkhuizen J, Geyer MA, Halberstadt AL, Zhuang X, Young JW. <article-title>Dopamine depletion attenuates some behavioral abnormalities in a hyperdopaminergic mouse model of bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;254.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24287168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schildkraut JJ. <article-title>The catecholamine hypothesis of affective disorders: a review of supporting evidence</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>1965</year>; <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;522.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5319766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kenney C, Hunter C, Mejia N, Jankovic J. <article-title>Is history of depression a contraindication to treatment with tetrabenazine</article-title>? <source>Clin Neuropharmacol</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;264.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16960470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martinez-Martin P, Damian J. <article-title>Parkinson disease: depression and anxiety in Parkinson disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;245.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20445560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Remy P, Doder M, Lees A, Turjanski N, Brooks D. <article-title>Depression in Parkinson's disease: loss of dopamine and noradrenaline innervation in the limbic system</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>1314</fpage>&#x02013;1322.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15716302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Parker G, Brotchie H. <article-title>Mood effects of the amino acids tryptophan and tyrosine: 'Food for Thought' III</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;426.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21488845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ruhe HG, Mason NS, Schene AH. <article-title>Mood is indirectly related to serotonin, norepinephrine and dopamine levels in humans: a meta-analysis of monoamine depletion studies</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;359.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17389902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Greil W, Haberle A, Haueis P, Grohmann R, Russmann S. <article-title>Pharmacotherapeutic trends in 2231 psychiatric inpatients with bipolar depression from the International AMSP Project between 1994 and 2009</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>534</fpage>&#x02013;542.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22134044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hayes J, Prah P, Nazareth I, King M, Walters K, Petersen I et al. <article-title>Prescribing trends in bipolar disorder: cohort study in the United Kingdom THIN primary care database 1995-2009</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28725</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22163329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hooshmand F, Miller S, Dore J, Wang PW, Hill SJ, Portillo N et al. <article-title>Trends in pharmacotherapy in patients referred to a bipolar specialty clinic, 2000-2011</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;287.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24314912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib110"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Walpoth-Niederwanger M, Kemmler G, Grunze H, Weiss U, Hortnagl C, Strauss R et al. <article-title>Treatment patterns in inpatients with bipolar disorder at a psychiatric university hospital over a 9-year period: focus on mood stabilizers</article-title>. <source>Int Clin Psychopharmacol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>&#x02013;266.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22842799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib111"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ketter TA, Miller S, Dell'Osso B, Calabrese JR, Frye MA, Citrome L. <article-title>Balancing benefits and harms of treatments for acute bipolar depression</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>S24</fpage>&#x02013;S33.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25533911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib112"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nolen WA. <article-title>Dopamine and mania. The effects of trans- and cis-clopenthixol in a double-blind pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>1983</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;96.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6222099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib113"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Goodwin GM, Haddad PM, Ferrier IN, Aronson JK, Barnes T, Cipriani A et al. <article-title>Evidence-based guidelines for treating bipolar disorder: Revised third edition recommendations from the British Association for Psychopharmacology</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;553.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26979387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib114"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Beaulieu JM, Sotnikova TD, Yao WD, Kockeritz L, Woodgett JR, Gainetdinov RR et al. <article-title>Lithium antagonizes dopamine-dependent behaviors mediated by an AKT/glycogen synthase kinase 3 signaling cascade</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>5099</fpage>&#x02013;5104.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15044694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib115"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Malhi GS, Tanious M, Das P, Coulston CM, Berk M. <article-title>Potential mechanisms of action of lithium in bipolar disorder. Current understanding</article-title>. <source>CNS Drugs</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;153.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23371914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib116"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gambarana C, Ghiglieri O, Masi F, Scheggi S, Tagliamonte A, De Montis MG. <article-title>The effects of long-term administration of rubidium or lithium on reactivity to stress and on dopamine output in the nucleus accumbens in rats</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>826</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;209.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10224297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib117"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ichikawa J, Dai J, Meltzer HY. <article-title>Lithium differs from anticonvulsant mood stabilizers in prefrontal cortical and accumbal dopamine release: role of 5-HT(1&#x02009;A) receptor agonism</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>1049</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>&#x02013;190.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15936730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib118"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ferrie LJ, Gartside SE, Martin KM, Young AH, McQuade R. <article-title>Effect of chronic lithium treatment on D2/3 autoreceptor regulation of dopaminergic function in the rat</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;225.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18031799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib119"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Burdick KE, Braga RJ, Nnadi CU, Shaya Y, Stearns WH, Malhotra AK. <article-title>Placebo-controlled adjunctive trial of pramipexole in patients with bipolar disorder: targeting cognitive dysfunction</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;112.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22152405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib120"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cassano P, Lattanzi L, Soldani F, Navari S, Battistini G, Gemignani A et al. <article-title>Pramipexole in treatment-resistant depression: an extended follow-up</article-title>. <source>Depress Anxiety</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;138.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15549689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib121"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dell'osso B, Timtim S, Hooshmand F, Miller S, Wang PW, Hill SJ et al. <article-title>Superior chronic tolerability of adjunctive modafinil compared to pramipexole in treatment-resistant bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;135.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23261131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib122"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">El-Mallakh RS, Penagaluri P, Kantamneni A, Gao Y, Roberts RJ. <article-title>Long-term use of pramipexole in bipolar depression: a naturalistic retrospective chart review</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Q</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;213.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20425143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib123"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Goldberg JF, Burdick KE, Endick CJ. <article-title>Preliminary randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of pramipexole added to mood stabilizers for treatment-resistant bipolar depression</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>564</fpage>&#x02013;566.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14992985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib124"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lattanzi L, Dell'Osso L, Cassano P, Pini S, Rucci P, Houck PR et al. <article-title>Pramipexole in treatment-resistant depression: a 16-week naturalistic study</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>&#x02013;314.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12479663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib125"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perugi G, Toni C, Ruffolo G, Frare F, Akiskal H. <article-title>Adjunctive dopamine agonists in treatment-resistant bipolar II depression: an open case series</article-title>. <source>Pharmacopsychiatry</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;141.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11518474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib126"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sporn J, Ghaemi SN, Sambur MR, Rankin MA, Recht J, Sachs GS et al. <article-title>Pramipexole augmentation in the treatment of unipolar and bipolar depression: a retrospective chart review</article-title>. <source>Ann Clin Psychiatry</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;140.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10984002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib127"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zarate CA Jr., Payne JL, Singh J, Quiroz JA, Luckenbaugh DA, Denicoff KD et al. <article-title>Pramipexole for bipolar II depression: a placebo-controlled proof of conceptstudy</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15219473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib128"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carlson PJ, Merlock MC, Suppes T. <article-title>Adjunctive stimulant use in patients with bipolar disorder: treatment of residual depression and sedation</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>416</fpage>&#x02013;420.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15383134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib129"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">El-Mallakh RS. <article-title>An open study of methylphenidate in bipolar depression</article-title>. <source>Bipolar Disord</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>&#x02013;59.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib130"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lydon E, El-Mallakh RS. <article-title>Naturalistic long-term use of methylphenidate in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>516</fpage>&#x02013;518.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16974196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib131"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Parker G, Brotchie H. <article-title>Do the old psychostimulant drugs have a role in managing treatment-resistant depression</article-title>? <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;314.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19594481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib132"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Goss AJ, Kaser M, Costafreda SG, Sahakian BJ, Fu CH. <article-title>Modafinil augmentation therapy in unipolar and bipolar depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1101</fpage>&#x02013;1107.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24330897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib133"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dell'Osso B, Ketter TA, Cremaschi L, Spagnolin G, Altamura AC. <article-title>Assessing the roles of stimulants/stimulant-like drugs and dopamine-agonists in the treatment of bipolar depression</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychiatry Rep</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23881710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib134"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rao JS, Kellom M, Reese EA, Rapoport SI, Kim HW. <article-title>Dysregulated glutamate and dopamine transporters in postmortem frontal cortex from bipolar and schizophrenic patients</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;71.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21925739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib135"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lee FJ, Pei L, Liu F. <article-title>Disruption of the dopamine transporter-dopamine D2 receptor interaction in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Synapse (New York, NY)</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>710</fpage>&#x02013;712.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib136"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Amsterdam JD, Newberg AB. <article-title>A preliminary study of dopamine transporter binding in bipolar and unipolar depressed patients and healthy controls</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychobiology</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;170.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17657170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib137"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nasr S. <article-title>Modafinil as adjunctive therapy in depressed outpatients</article-title>. <source>Ann Clin Psychiatry</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;138.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15517845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib138"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nasr S, Wendt B, Steiner K. <article-title>Absence of mood switch with and tolerance to modafinil: a replication study from a large private practice</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;114.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16737742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib139"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Heijnen WT, De Fruyt J, Wierdsma AI, Sienaert P, Birkenhager TK. <article-title>Efficacy of tranylcypromine in bipolar depression: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>700</fpage>&#x02013;705.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26479223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib140"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shulman KI, Herrmann N, Walker SE. <article-title>Current place of monoamine oxidase inhibitors in the treatment of depression</article-title>. <source>CNS Drugs</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>789</fpage>&#x02013;797.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23934742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib141"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Selle V, Schalkwijk S, Vazquez GH, Baldessarini RJ. <article-title>Treatments for acute bipolar depression: meta-analyses of placebo-controlled, monotherapy trials of anticonvulsants, lithium and antipsychotics</article-title>. <source>Pharmacopsychiatry</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;52.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24549862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib142"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Farah A. <article-title>Atypicality of atypical antipsychotics</article-title>. <source>Prim Care Companion J Clin Psychiatry</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>&#x02013;274.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16498489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib143"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Meyer JM, Loebel AD, Schweizer E. <article-title>Lurasidone: a new drug in development for schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Investig Drugs</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1715</fpage>&#x02013;1726.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib144"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chung S, Lee EJ, Yun S, Choe HK, Park SB, Son HJ et al. <article-title>Impact of circadian nuclear receptor REV-ERBalpha on midbrain dopamine production and mood regulation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>858</fpage>&#x02013;868.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24813609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib145"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fusar-Poli P, Howes OD, Allen P, Broome M, Valli I, Asselin MC et al. <article-title>Abnormal prefrontal activation directly related to pre-synaptic striatal dopamine dysfunction in people at clinical high risk for psychosis</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19949389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib146"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Goldberg JF, Perlis RH, Bowden CL, Thase ME, Miklowitz DJ, Marangell LB et al. <article-title>Manic symptoms during depressive episodes in 1,380 patients with bipolar disorder: findings from the STEP-BD</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;181.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19122008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib147"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berk M, Tiller JW, Zhao J, Yatham LN, Malhi GS, Weiller E. <article-title>Effects of asenapine in bipolar I patients meeting proxy criteria for moderate-to-severe mixed major depressive episodes: a post hoc analysis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>728</fpage>&#x02013;734.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25612216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib148"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hazy TE, Frank MJ, O'Reilly RC. <article-title>Neural mechanisms of acquired phasic dopamine responses in learning</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>&#x02013;720.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19944716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib149"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hall H, Wedel I, Halldin C, Kopp J, Farde L. <article-title>Comparison of the <italic>in vitro</italic> receptor binding properties of N-[3H]methylspiperone and [3H]raclopride to rat and human brain membranes</article-title>. <source>J Neurochem</source>
<year>1990</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>2048</fpage>&#x02013;2057.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1977888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib150"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Slifstein M, van de Giessen E, Van Snellenberg J, Thompson JL, Narendran R, Gil R et al. <article-title>Deficits in prefrontal cortical and extrastriatal dopamine release in schizophrenia: a positron emission tomographic functional magnetic resonance imaging study</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>&#x02013;324.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25651194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sup1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp201716x1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Summary of dopamine molecular imaging findings in bipolar disorder.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mp201716f1"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Post-mortem studies assessing the role of dopamine in bipolar disorder</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Measure of</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Author</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Bipolar patients/controls (</italic>n<italic>)</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Bipolar patients/ controls age mean (s.d.) in years</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Method</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Area</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Cause of death patients/ controls</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Patients' medication</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Post-mortem interval (h): patients/ controls</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Results (BD relative to controls)</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine transporter</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Rao <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib134">134</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">10/10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">55 (s.e.m.: 6.6)/49 (s.e.m.: 4.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Western blot analysis, RNA isolation, RT-PCR</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Prefrontal Cortex</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lithium: 4&#x0000a;Valproate: 5&#x0000a;Rispiridone: 1&#x0000a;Carbamazepine: 1</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">21/20</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02193; DAT protein and mRNA levels</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lee <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib135">135</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">15/15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">42.3 (9.3)/48 (10.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Coimmunoprecipitation and Western blot analyses</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Striatum</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Suicide-9/0&#x0000a;Non suicidal-6/15</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine antagonist: 7</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">33/24</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; DAT protein levels</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine D1 receptor</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pantazopoulos <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">15/15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">58.3/61.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>In situ</italic> hybridisation</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hippocampus</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Suicide-3/0&#x0000a;Non suicidal- 12/15</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine antagonist: 8</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">21/20</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191;D1 mRNA&#x0000a;expression in hippocampal sector CA2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Kaalund <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DLPFC 61/ 244&#x0000a;Hippocampus 31/192&#x0000a;Caudate nucleus 44/78</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">45/40&#x0000a;46/40&#x0000a;43/41</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">RNA extraction and Quantitative real-time PCR</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DLPFC, hippocampus and caudate</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine antagonist: 17</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191;DRD1 in DLPFC and hippocampus.&#x0000a;&#x02194; caudate nucleus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine D2 receptor</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Zhan <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">32/34</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">45 (10)/43 (7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Quantitative real-time PCR</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Prefrontal cortex</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sucide-15/0&#x0000a;Non suicidal causes-17/34</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mean lifetime antidopaminergic exposure:&#x0000a;10&#x02009;071&#x02009;mg fluphenazine equivalent</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">37/29</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191; D2 mRNA level in prefrontal cortex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Glantz <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">14/14</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">42.3 (11.7)/48.1 (10.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Western blot analysis and immunohistochemistry</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Temporal Cortex</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Suicide-9/0&#x0000a;Non suicidal-6/15</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lithium: 4&#x0000a;Dopamine antagonist: 8&#x0000a;Antidepressant: 8</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">33/24</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Kaalund <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DLPFC 61/ 244&#x0000a;Hippocampus 31/192&#x0000a;Caudate nucleus 44/78</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">45/40&#x0000a;46/40&#x0000a;43/41</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">RNA extraction and Quantitative real-time PCR</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">DLPFC, hippocampus and caudate</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine antagonist: 17</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191;D2L in DLPFC and hippocampus&#x0000a;&#x02194; Caudate nucleus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Lee <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib135">135</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">15/15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">42.3 (9.3)/48 (10.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Coimmunoprecipitation and Western blot analyses</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Striatum</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Suicide-9/0&#x0000a;Non suicidal-6/15</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine antagonist: 7</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">33/24</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; D2 protein levels</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D5 receptor</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Knable <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">48 data sets</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>In situ</italic> hybridisation</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hippocampus</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not mentioned</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191; Dopamine D5 receptor RNA in dentate gyrus, CA1 and subiculum</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: DAT, dopamine transporter; DLPFC, dorsolateral prefrontal cortex; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; RT-PCR, reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>
<italic>In vivo</italic> imaging studies assessing dopamine in mania</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Dopamine system studied</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Author</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Patients/controls (</italic>n<italic>)</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Phase of illness-number of participants in the given phase</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Medication</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Tracer&#x0002a;</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Primary outcome</italic>&#x0000a;<italic>In patients compared with controls</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Secondary outcome</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine synthesis</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Yatham <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">13/14</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mania (Non-psychotic)-13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sodium valproate</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>18</sup>F]DOPA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; FDOPA uptake rate constants in the striatum.&#x0000a;After 2&#x02013;6 weeks treatment with sodium valporate, FDOPA rate constants - &#x02193;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No correlations were found between YMRS and pre/post Ki values</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D2/3 receptor availability</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Yatham <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">13/14</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mania (Non-psychotic)-13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sodium valproate</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>11</sup>C]raclopride</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; Striatal D2 density.&#x0000a;After 2&#x02013;6 weeks of treatment with sodium valproate no change in striatal D2 density (10 patients had second scan).</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No correlation was found between D2 density and score of young mania rating scale.&#x0000a;Similarly changes in the D2 density did not correlate with score in the YMRS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pearlson <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">14/12</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mania-11&#x0000a;(6 psychotic mania)&#x0000a;Depression-3</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">All received two scans. Second scan was preceded by haloperidol lactate</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>11</sup>C]N-methylspiperone</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191; D2 density in caudate and putamen</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D2 availability directly correlated with psychotic symptom severity score, but no correlation with mania symptom rating</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Wong <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">14/24</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mania-11 (7 psychotic)&#x0000a;Depression-3</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Drug naive</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">N-[<sup>11</sup>C] methylspiperone&#x0000a;([<sup>11</sup>C]NMSP)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191; D2 dopamine receptor density in caudate were seen in psychotic patients compared with non-psychotic patients and healthy controls</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: YMRS, Young's Mania Rating Scale; &#x02194;, no significant difference.</p></fn><fn id="t2-fn2"><p>&#x0002a;Further details of scan and patient characteristics are given in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>
<italic>In vivo</italic> imaging studies assessing dopamine in the depressive and euthymic phase of bipolar disease</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Dopamine system studied</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Author</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Patients/controls (</italic>n<italic>)</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Phase of illness-number of participants in the given phase</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Medication</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Tracer</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Primary outcome</italic>&#x0000a;<italic>In patients compared with controls</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Secondary outcome</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Vesicular monoamine&#x0000a;transporter protein (VMAT-2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Zubieta <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">16/16</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Euthymic-16 (history of psychotic mania)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Valproic acid; lithium; carbamazepine; lamotrigine</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[11C]dihydrotetrabenazine&#x0000a;(DTBZ)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; Caudate&#x0000a;&#x02191; Brainstem and thalamus</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">VMAT concentration in brainstem and thalamus positively correlated with the measure of frontal executive function</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine release</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Anand <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref></sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13/13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Euthymic-13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">7 Drug naive and 6 were on mood stabiliser: lithium (4) valproate (2). After first scan patients were administered amphetamine</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>123</sup>I]IBZM</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; In amphetamine-induced decrease in striatal&#x0000a;[123I]IBZM binding.</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">In patients, amphetamine-induced decrease in [123I] IBZM binding did not correlate with post amphetamine YMRS score.&#x0000a;In healthy controls, there was trend level correlation.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine transporter</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Anand <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref></sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11/13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Depressed-6&#x0000a;Euthymic-5</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Drug naive</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>11</sup>C]CFT</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02193; DAT availability in caudate nucleus in patients</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No correlations were found between YMRS/HDRS and D2 binding</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Amsterdam and Newberg<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib136">136</xref></sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">5/46</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Depression-5</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Drug naive for at least a week</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>99</sup>mTc]&#x0000a;TRODAT-1</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191; Binding potential in the posterior putamen and in the left caudate region</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Chang <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17/17</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Euthymic-17</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Drug naive</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>99</sup>mTc] TRODAT-1</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191; Striatal DAT availability</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No significant difference in DAT availability between bipolar I and II.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D2/3 density</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Anand <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref></sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">13/13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Euthymic-13</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">7 Drug naive and 6 were on mood stabiliser: lithium (4) valproate (2). After first scan patients were administered amphetamine</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>123</sup>I]IBZM</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; In striatal D2 receptor binding at baseline.&#x0000a;&#x02194; In amphetamine-induced decrease in striatal&#x0000a;[123I] IBZM binding.</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">In patients, amphetamine-induced decrease in [123I] IBZM binding did not correlate with post amphetamine YMRS score.&#x0000a;In healthy controls, there was trend level correlation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D1 density</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Suhara <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">49</xref></sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10/21</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Depressed-3&#x0000a;Manic-1&#x0000a;Euthymic-6</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">All except one were drug naive for at least one week before scan</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">[<sup>11</sup>C]-SCH23390</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02193; D1, in the frontal cortex&#x02194;striatum</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t3-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: DAT, dopamine transporter; DVR, distribution volume ratio; HDRS, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale; YMRS, Young's Mania Rating Scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Functional magnetic resonance imaging studies investigating bipolar patients vs healthy controls during monetary reward tasks</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Phase of illness</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Author</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>BD</italic> n <italic>(&#x00025;M)/ HC</italic> n <italic>(&#x00025;M)</italic><xref ref-type="fn" rid="t4-fn3">a</xref></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>fMRI task</italic></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>VS &#x02018;reward' activity in BD vs HC</italic><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Association with symptoms/dopamine antagonist medication</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Anticipation</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Feedback</italic><xref ref-type="fn" rid="t4-fn3">a</xref></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Manic</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Abler <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">12 BD I (58.3)/12 HC (58.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Monetary incentive task</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02193; Left VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Bermpohl <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">15 BD I (53.3)/26 HC (57.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MID</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No association with antidopaminergic medication. Remitted BD (<italic>n</italic>=7, YMRS&#x0003c;8) OFC activation was similar to HC.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Euthymic</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Yip <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">82</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">20 BD II /NOS (60)/20 HC (50)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MID</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; VS (&#x02193; r.DS)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194; VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No correlation between subsyndromal depressive symptoms (HDRS) and reward-related BOLD signal.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Caseras <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">72</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">17 BD I (36)/15 BD II (40)/20 HC (35)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Card guessing task</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BD I: &#x02194;VS&#x0000a;BD II: &#x02191;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BD I:&#x02191; left VS (trend)&#x0000a;BD II:&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">During reward anticipation BD I had &#x02193;VS activation vs BD II. At reward feedback BD I had &#x02191; activity in right VS vs BD II (not significant when excluding patients taking antidopaminergic medication or co-varying for medication load). VS activity not correlated with YMRS or HDRS.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mason <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">76</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">20 BD (18=BD I, 2=BD II) (50)/20 HC (45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Roulette task</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191;left VS (trend)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Preferential activity for high probability rewards negatively correlated with impulsivity (DLPFC) and risk taking (DLPDC and VS)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Trost <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">16 BD I (37.5)/16 HC (43.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Desire-reason dilemma</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02193;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Task-appropriate bilateral VS suppression in BD correlated with antidopaminergic dose</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Nusslock <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">21 BD I (42.9)/20 HC (40)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Card guessing task</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191;Right VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No association with antidopaminergic medication</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dutra <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">24 BD I (37.5)/25 HC (40)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MID (no &#x02018;loss' condition)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02191;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No association with antidopaminergic medication or symptom scores</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Linke <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">75</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">19 BD I (42.1)/19 HC (42.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Reversal learning</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Negative correlation between medication load and mean activation of the right amygdala in response to reward in BD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Bipolar depression</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Chase <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">73</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">23 BD I (17.4)/37 HC (32.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Card guessing task</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AP associated with&#x02193;&#x02018;prediction error' VS signal. Illness duration associated with &#x02193;ACC reward anticipation activation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Satterthwaite <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">79</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">23 BD (21 BD I, 2 BD II) (37)/32 HC (51)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Monetary reward task</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BDI correlated with diminished reward-related (win&#x0003e;loss) activation of bilateral VS, anterior and posterior cingulate, and anterior insula&#x0000a;No effect of antidopaminergic dose on reward-related BOLD signal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Redlich <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">33 BD I (51.5)/34 HC (52.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Card guessing task</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Not analysed</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02193;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">No association with medication load or symptom scores</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Heterogeneous</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Singh <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">80</xref></sup></td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">24 adolescent BD1 (54)/24 HC (37)</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MID</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02194;VS</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">YMRS score associated with &#x02193;VS activation during reward anticipation, when MID was preceded by &#x02018;positive mood induction'</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t4-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: ACC, anterior cingulate cortex; BD(I/II), bipolar disorder (I/II); BDI, beck depression inventory; DLPFC, dorsolateral prefrontal cortex; DS, dorsal striatum; fMRI, functional magnetic resonance imaging; HC, healthy controls; HDRS, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale; MDD, major depressive disorder; MID, monetary incentive delay task; NOS, not otherwise specified; YMRS, Young Mania Rating Scale.</p></fn><fn id="t4-fn2"><p>Results presented are restricted to ventral striatum (VS), which has been most consistently implicated in event-related fMRI reward tasks. Values given as mean (s.d.) unless stated otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="t4-fn3"><label>a</label><p>Subject characteristics and reward feedback analysis contrasts are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Summary of pharmacological evidence on dopamine dysfunction in the bipolar disorder</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Phase of illness</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Drug</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Mechanism of action</italic></th><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Effect</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mania</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Levodopa</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine precursor</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Induced mania and hypomania in parkinsonian patients</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Bromocriptine</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine agonist</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Induced mania in some patients who received it for postpartum galactorrhoea</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Amphetamine</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Increases dopamine release</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Induced mania-like symptom in healthy volunteers</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dietary tyrosine depletion</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Reduces dopamine level</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Reduced manic symptoms in patients</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AMPT administration</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Dopamine depletion</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Reduced manic symptoms in patients and animal model</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Antidopaminergics</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D2 blockers</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Reduces manic symptoms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Euthymia</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Olanzapine, quetiapine and ziprasidone</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D2 blockade and 5HT agonism</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Prolongs remission</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Mood stabilisers</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Act on dopamine downstream pathways</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Prolongs remission</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Depression</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pramipexole</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D2/3 agonist</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Short-term efficacy in bipolar depression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Methylphenidate and amphetamine</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Increase dopamine release</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Beneficial in group of bipolar depression patients with drowsiness and fatigue</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Olanzapine-fluoxetine combination, quetiapine and lurasidone</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">D2 blockade and serotonergic effects</td><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Efficacy in bipolar depression</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t5-fn1"><p>Abbreviation: AMPT, alpha-methyl-p-tyrosine.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><boxed-text id="box1"><caption><title>Future research direction</title></caption><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Animal models exhibiting bipolar depression-like phenotype need to be developed.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Development of better animal models of mood polarity switching coupled with longitudinal, translational assays (such as PET, fMRI and behavioural methods).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Longitudinal molecular imaging studies investigating dopaminergic function, particularly dopamine transporter and D2/3 receptor homoeostasis, in patients across different illness phases.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Trans-diagnostic comparisons of dopaminergic function in psychotic and non-psychotic mania and schizophrenia.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Imaging studies in mixed states and rapid cycling bipolar disorder.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Longitudinal studies investigating the effects of antidopaminergic and conventional mood stabilisers on dopaminergic pathways and the relationship between dopaminergic blockade and treatment response in bipolar disorder.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Future studies should also focus on integration of data from molecular imaging studies with functional MRI to elucidate specific anatomical circuits involved and the link to molecular changes.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Molecular imaging studies should investigate extra-striatal dopaminergic changes across different phases of bipolar disorder.Abbreviations: fMRI, functional magnetic resonance imaging; PET, positron emission tomography.</p></list-item></list></p></boxed-text></floats-group></article>