<?xml version="1.0"?>
Thyroid ResThyroid Research1756-6614BioMed Central31551091756-6614-4-S1-S32183505010.1186/1756-6614-4-S1-S3ReviewHypothyroidism and mood disorders: integrating novel insights from brain imaging techniquesPilhatschMaximilian1MarxenMichael1WinterChristine1SmolkaMichael N 1BauerMichael1michael.bauer@uniklinikum-dresden.de1Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University Hospital Carl Gustav Carus, Technische Universität Dresden, Dresden, Germany20113820114Suppl 1New aspects of thyroid hormone synthesis and actionHeike BiebermannS3S3Copyright ©2011 Pilhatsch et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.2011Pilhatsch et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.AbstractThyroid hormones play a critical role in brain development but also in the adult human brain by modulating metabolic activity. Hypothyroid states are associated with both functional and structural brain alterations also seen in patients with major depression. Recent animal experimental and preclinical data indicate subtle changes in myelination, microvascular density, local neurogenesis, and functional networks. The translational validity of such studies is obviously limited. Clinical evidence for neurobiological correlates of different stages and severities of hypothyroidism and effects of pharmacological intervention is lacking but may be achieved using advanced imaging techniques, e.g. functional and quantitative MRI techniques applied to patients with hypothyroidism before and after hormone replacement therapy.IntroductionThe profound influence of thyroid hormones on brain development in humans has been studied extensively [1-6]. Hypothyroidism is a clinical condition which is either characterized only by elevated levels of the thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH; “subclinical hypothyroidism”) or additional low levels of trijodothyronine (T3) and thyroxin (T4) respectively (overt hypothyroidism). Taken together overt (0.4%) and subclinical (9%) hypothyroisism is prevalent in about 9.4 % of the adult population [7] and commonly affects brain function. Conversely, 15% of patients with depression display hypothyroid states including subclinical hypothyroidism [8], and about 25-30% of depressed patients show a pathological response to the thyreotropine releasing hormone (TRH) stimulation test [9].The concepts of thyroid hormone action in the adult brain have changed dramatically along with rapid advances in basic science and methodological techniques over the past decades [10]. Particularly brain imaging techniques evaluating cerebral metabolism, perfusion, and anatomy enabled encouraging insights into the thyroid-brain relationship. As a result, it is now widely accepted that thyroid hormones play a critical role in the adult brain impacting mood and cognition. Even if crucial details of the underlying mechanisms still remain unknown [11], the therapeutic use of thyroid hormones in the clinical treatment of mood disorders has already been established in predominantly open trials with sometimes limited numbers of patients.Thyroid hormone treatment has been shown to accelerate and augment antidepressant pharmacotherapy and to support maintenance therapy of bipolar affective disorders, even in patients with euthyroid hormonal state [10,12]. Specifically, there is good evidence that trijodthyronine (T3) can accelerate [13] and augment [14] the therapeutic response to tricyclic antidepressants and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) in depression.Adjunctive treatment with supraphysiological doses of Levothyroxine (T4) was found to be effective in open clinical studies of patients with affective disorders [15-18]. In a subset of 21 patients with treatment-resistant affective disorder, very high doses of up to 600 μg per day L-T4 were required to achieve therapeutic response with a good tolerability even over mean treatment periods of up to 51 month [16].In the first double-blind randomized placebo-controlled trial (RCT) to evaluate efficacy and tolerability of supraphysiological doses of L-T4 in 63 patients, we found that bipolar depressed women treated with L-T4 showed a better improvement in depression scores than those treated with placebo. However including both genders, the study failed to detect an overall statistically significant treatment effect (Stamm et al., in preparation).Brain imaging methodsPrincipal brain imaging techniques mentioned in this article are single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT), positron emission tomography (PET), and different methods of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). PET and SPECT are nuclear imaging methods that require the injection of radioactive tracers into the circulatory system. Those tracers bind to molecular structures like transporters and receptors in the human brain. Measuring of the local distribution of the bound tracers allows an estimation of regional brain activation or availability of receptors. The glucose analog [18F]-Fluor-2-Desoxy-D-Glucose (FDG) is by far the most commonly used PET tracer and its metabolism reflects the amount of brain activity in different brain regions.In contrast to these nuclear imaging methods, MRI is non-invasive and uses magnetic fields and radio waves instead of ionizing radiation. Structural MRI methods allow creating images of anatomical structures in an excellent spatial resolution (less than 1 mm). Diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) characterizes the mobility of water molecules and, thus, the directionality and integrity of white matter tracts. Magnetization transfer (MT) is sensitive to myelin content and is therefore useful in detecting early demyelination processes.Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) has become the tool of choice to study functional aspects of the human brain. This method detects local increases of blood flow and the following decrease of deoxygenated hemoglobin during task related brain activity. The signal measured directly relies on the so-called BOLD (blood oxygen level dependent) effect. It is based on the different magnetic properties of oxygenated and deoxygenated hemoglobin. The origin of the BOLD signal is still a matter of discussion as it is also based on the complex interaction of neuronal metabolism, neuronal activity, blood flow and blood volume. Nevertheless fMRI enables the monitoring of active neuronal networks during the performance of specific paradigms, e.g. a memory task. Related to affective disorders, MRI allows the investigation of functional and structural deficits associated with neuropsychiatric symptoms as well as treatment effects.Major advantages of neuroimaging methods are that brain structure and function as well as molecular and neurochemical processes can be studied in the living human. An important limitation of the mentioned brain imaging techniques refers to temporal resolution. While neuronal activities occur in the range of milliseconds, processes detected by imaging methods currently ranges between seconds (fMRI) and minutes (PET). Additionally, all methods measure brain activity indirectly through changes in blood flow or glucose uptake. Consequently, alterations in baseline perfusion and metabolic rate of oxygen may affect the results. Moreover it is currently not possible to reliably distinguish between inhibitory and excitatory neuronal activities. Nevertheless, given the rapid developments in neuroimaging methods; many limitations may hopefully be overcome in the next decades [19].Mechanisms of actionOn the molecular level, thyroid hormones act via genomic and non-genomic effects. As part of the nuclear superfamily of ligand-modulated transcription factors, thyroid hormones bind to intracellular nuclear receptors [20]. Genomic actions of T3 are mediated through the control and usually increase of gene expression [12,21,22]. Genes that are regulated by thyroid hormones are known to encode for proteins such as myelin, neurotrophins, and proteins that are involved in intracellular signaling pathways [23].Non-genomic actions of thyroid hormones have been described in the brain and peripheral tissues. After binding to cytoplasmic thyroid hormone receptors, T3 appears to be able to rapidly activate the phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase protein pathway and thereby achieves vasodilatory and neuroprotective effects [24]. Additionally, an increase in serotonergic neurotransmission is mediated by a thyroid hormone induced reduction of the sensitivity of 5-HT1A autoreceptors in the raphe nuclei and increase in 5-HT2 receptor sensitivity [25,26]. The exact role of these non-genomic signaling mechanisms, their regulation, and interaction with the slower genomic pathways remains to be elucidated.Thyroid hormone homeostasis in the brain underlies a complex interaction of different autoregulative mechanisms [27,28]. The activity of specific thyroid hormone transporters (MCT8, LAT2) and the carrier transthyretin determines intracellular concentration of thyroid hormones via mediating their cellular influx and efflux under consideration of overall circulating levels of T4 and T3[27]. The activity of deiodinases [29,30] controls local bioavailability of T3 in concert with other less understood mechanisms, e.g. the local distribution of the different nuclear thyroid hormone receptors (TRα and TRβ in diverse isoforms) [31]. Thyroid hormone receptors are widely distributed in the brain with highest concentrations in cerebral cortex, hippocampus, amygdala, plexus choroideus and olfactory bulb [31].Interestingly, the limbic structures, where thyroid hormone receptors are prevalent, have repeatedly been shown to be implicated in the pathogenesis of mood disorders [32]. However, the neuropharmacological basis and the functional pathways for the modulatory effects of thyroid hormones on mood are yet to be understood, even though several studies revealed interactions with different neurotransmitter systems, which are generally believed to play a major role in the regulation of mood and behaviour, i.e norepinephrine or serotonine [26,33].Structural changes induced by hypothyroidismThyroid hormones are known to affect neuronal differentiation, migration, myelination, synaptogenesis, and dendritic branching [8,9,34,35]. Therefore, hypothyroidism will change brain structure and the changes will depend on the onset time of the condition. Hypothyroid rodents display a loss of neurons in several brain regions. Next to the visual cortex [36] and cerebellum [37], the hippocampal formations were studied repeatedly. The number of granule cells in the dentate gyrus was reduced [38] with a more severe effect of hypothyroidism during development than during adulthood [39]. Rats treated with methimazole, a hypothyroidism inducing drug, showed a reduced count of pyramidal neurons in the CA3 hippocampal region [40]. This was found even if methimazole was administered in adulthood. Animals could be fully protected with T4 replacement and partially protected with T3 replacement [41]. It is speculated that this protective potency is mediated through the activation of hippocampal progenitor cells of the supraventricular zone and the dentate gyrus [42]. Mice with a heterozygous mutation of the thyroid hormone receptor alpha 1 showed a reduced density of GABAergic inhibitory interneurons in the CA1 hippocampal region [40]. On the behavioural side, these mice show increases in markers for depression and anxiety [43,44]. Both the behavioural measures as well as the neuronal density normalized with high levels of T3 administered in adulthood. In contrast to the above findings, hypothyroid rats treated at age 0-30 days with propylthiouracil (PTU) showed a loss of pyramidal neurons in CA1, which did not ameliorate after withdrawal of the drug and approximate normalization of serum T4 levels [45]. A thyroidectomy at day 30 also reduced the number of neurons. The same study reported in CA3 a volume decrease of the pyramidal layer combined with an increase in neuronal density and no loss in the total number of pyramidal neurons. Only one study is known in this context that applied MRI in rodents [46]. Using manual segmentation, perinatal hypothyroidism induced with methimazole administered to mother rats was found to reduced total brain size of the litter but not the relative size of the hippocampus.Effects of T3 and T4 have also been reported in the process of myelination or remyelination in mice [47,48] and rats [49,50]. Harsan et al. [48] used Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI) in combination with histology to serve as a marker for remyelination in mice and found that cuprizone induced demyelination in adulthood was reversable through treatment with T3, which increased the number of oligodendrocyte progenitor cells. Using histology and electronmicroscopy, Franklin and Gilson [51] found that Schwann cell remyelination was decreased in thyroidectomized rats but not oligodendrocyte remyelination.While the efficacy of thyroid hormone treatments is generally accepted, human data on structural changes in the brain is sparse. Using proton MRS, Jagannathan et al. [52] found that abnormalities related to myelin maturation were reversible under T4 therapy in three mentally disabled patients with congential hypothyroidism. A more recent investigation [53] using similar MRS and MRI methodology demonstrated general atrophy and signs of demyelination in two children with monocarboxylate transporter 8 (MCT8) gene deficiency, which is associated with a syndrome combining thyroid and severe neurological abnormalities.Systematic group studies of structural brain changes due to hypothyroidism and thyroid hormone therapy are needed both during development and in adulthood. In addition to MRS, recent advances in structural MRI, quantitative MRI, and image analysis techniques could be utilized to test hypotheses derived from animal studies in human. Structural changes related to myelin can now be studied with quantitative T2 or quantitative magnetization transfer (MT) imaging [54]. Diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) can reveal information on white matter integrity. Changes in grey matter density [55] or cortical thickness [56,57] can be studied with T1-weighted images.Vascular Changes and PerfusionThyroid hormones are known to affect the vascular system. Hypothyroidism is associated with impaired fibrinolysis and blood coagulation resulting in cerebrovascular diseases [58]. It also compromises protective endothelial [59] and thrombocyte functions as well as lipid metabolism [60].In the rat forebrain, a significant reduction in blood vessel density was observed in untreated rats thyroidectomised shortly after birth compared to euthyroid control animals and thyroidectomized rats treated with T4 or the thyroid hormone analog 3,5-diiothyroprionic acid (DITPA) [61]. Treatment induced angiogenesis and improved functioning of endothelial cells with secondary impact on local oxygen consumption and metabolic activity.PET and SPECT measurements of cerebral blood flow under consideration of the thyroid system revealed partially conflicting results. Most consistently hypothyroidism was associated with global, diffuse hypoperfusion [62,63]. Several studies pointed to more regional effects including perfusion deficits pronounced in posterior brain regions [64-66] or in the parietal lobe [63].Interpretation of the findings regarding reversibility of perfusion abnormalities under treatment is especially challenging. Whereas several studies report partial normalization of perfusion [17,62,67], others demonstrate [64-66] ongoing regional hypoperfusion under hormone replacement therapy. In contrast to the hypoperfusion pattern reported for hypothyroidism by Kraus et al. [64] in otherwise healthy subjects with posterior hypoperfusion and slight hyperperfusion anteriorly, depressed patients showed hypoperfusion in limbic, subcortical and frontal brain regions [32], which normalized under therapy with supraphysiological dosages (300 mcg/day) of T4.Differences in the studied populations may be the reason for such variable findings. Published results refer either to severe cases of hypothyroidism [62,63] or mild cases [66,68]. Some studies excluded patients with co-morbid psychiatric diseases like depression [64,68], while other studies included also depressed patients [17,69]. In addition, the duration of the disease was variable. Only one study examined populations with varying severity and duration of the disease [17]. Taken together the existing data may indicate that long and severe hypothyroidism, presumably leading to irreversible structural neuronal and vascular changes, is associated with chronic perfusion and functional alterations, which may be ameliorated by treatment but not fully restored. In contrast, shorter and milder courses of hypothyroidism, presumably not being paralleled by irreversible structural changes, seem to be more accessible to substitution treatment.Glucose metabolismIn line with findings that general glucose metabolism is tightly coupled to perfusion [3], preclinical studies generally reported alterations of glucose metabolism in hypothyroid conditions [63,69]. More specifically, Bauer et al. related depressive symptoms in hypothyroidism to regionally decreased glucose metabolism, particularly in the peri-genual anterior cingulate cortex region and the hippocampus [17] in a glucose-PET study. After 3 months of T4 substitution therapy, activity patterns normalized. Circulating TSH levels before initiation of therapy showed a significant positive correlation with glucose metabolism in the right ACC and negative correlations in the hippocampus. Interestingly, these two regions express TSH receptors very densely according to topographic studies in rat and human [70], whereby suggesting a direct and relevant effect of elevated TSH levels on the limbic system is of course highly speculative.Cognitive and emotional functional changesIn line with the wide range of metabolic, perfusional and structural implications of the thyroid system, the literature on functional alterations related to thyroid diseases is large. Disturbances of the thyroid system, particularly if leading to a hypothyroid state, may profoundly alter mental functions influencing cognition and emotions. Severe hypothyroidism may lead to both severe depression and dementia [71] especially if left untreated [72].Neuropsychologically, several cognitive defects in general intelligence, psychomotor speed, visual-spatial skills, working and long-term memory have been observed ranging from minimal to severe [73-75]. It was suggested that hypothyroid-related memory defects are not attributable to an attention deficit but rather to specific retrieval deficits [73,76]. Motor skills, language, inhibitory efficiency, and sustained attention appear to be less impacted by hypothyroidism [73,75]. Older adults were more vulnerable to cognitive changes due to hypothyroidism [75].It is still a matter of discussion as to whether subclinical hypothyroidism is associated with cognitive impairments. In some studies, patients with subclinical hypothyroidism performed worse than controls on well established neuropsychological tests such as the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale or the Wechsler Memory scale [77,78], while other studies found no association between subclinical hypothyroidism and several aspects of cognition [75,79,80]. A consistent finding among many studies was a specific deficit in working memory tasks [73]. These neuropsychological findings were additionally underlined by a functional MRI (fMRI) study by Zhu et al. [68] who found that working memory was impaired in patients with subclinical hypothyroidism but not other memory functions. These impairments were reversible with l-thyroxine (L-T4) treatment.Despite clinical evidence of an increased vulnerability for affective disorders coming along with hypothyroid states, neurobiological correlates of this disposition are not systematically investigated yet. This is of particular interest because a study by Maheu et al. [81] demonstrated that fMRI could detect greater hippocampal and amygdala activation in 12 non-depressed adolescent patients with Cushing's syndrome, when encoding affective stimuli (i.e. emotional faces) compared to 22 healthy controls. A similar pattern of brain activation has previously been demonstrated in adolescents suffering from manifest depression in an equivalent paradigm [82]. CushingÂ´s syndrome is defined by hypercortisolemia and highly associated with prevalence of depressive symptoms in adults [83] and shows in this respect distinct parallels to hypothyroidism.ConclusionsHypothyroid states have a multitude of effects on structure, perfusion and function of the central nervous system. Recent research aims to combine modern brain imaging techniques with years of experience in neuropsychological and clinical evaluations of thyroid dysfunctions. The results are encouraging, and the description of the interactions between thyroid and affective disorders is taking on a new dimension. Nonetheless, the potential of modern techniques has hardly been exhausted. For example, non invasive measurements of brain perfusion like arterial-spin-labeling (ASL) – already established in characterisation of different cerebrovascular diseases [84] – would be suitable for transferring hypotheses about the influence of angiogenesis [85] from animal models into humans. fMRI in patients with thyroid diseases of different length and severity could help to identify functional aberrations such as memory impairments or altered emotional processing, which has long been suggested from animal studies. Structural changes related to myelin, which have been observed in various animal models, can now be studied with quantitative T2 or quantitative magnetization transfer (MT) imaging [86]. Finally diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) [54] can reveal information on white matter integrity.Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors' contributionsMP participated in the design and the preparation of the manuscript. MM participated in the preparation and revision of the manuscript. MNS, CW and MB participated in its design, revisions and coordination. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.AcknowledgementsThis article has been published as part of Thyroid Research Volume 4 Supplement 1, 2011: New aspects of thyroid hormone synthesis and action. The full contents of the supplement are available online at http://www.thyroidresearchjournal.com/supplements/4/S1BernalJNunezJGjessingRThyroid-Hormones and Brain-DevelopmentEuropean Journal of Endocrinology199513339039810.1530/eje.0.13303907581959AhmedOMEl GareibAWEl BakryAMAbd El-TawabSMAhmedRGThyroid hormones states and brain development interactionsInt J Dev Neurosci20082614720910.1016/j.ijdevneu.2007.09.01118031969GurRCRaglandJDReivichMGreenbergJHAlaviAGurRERegional Differences in the Coupling between Resting Cerebral Blood Flow and Metabolism may Indicate Action Preparedness as a Default StateCerebral Cortex20091937538218534991HornSHeuerHThyroid hormone action during brain development: more questions than answersMol Cell Endocrinol2010315192610.1016/j.mce.2009.09.00819765631KoibuchiNChinWWThyroid hormone action and brain developmentTrends Endocrinol Metab20001112312810.1016/S1043-2760(00)00238-110754532KoibuchiNEffects of thyroid hormone on function and development of the brainNippon Rinsho200563Suppl 10788316279607CanarisGJManowitzNRMayorGRidgwaECThe Colorado thyroid disease prevalence studyArch Intern Med200016045262410.1001/archinte.160.4.52610695693GoldMSPottashALCExteinIHypothyroidism and Depression - Evidence from Complete Thyroid-Function EvaluationJAMA1981245191919192210.1001/jama.245.19.19197230383LoosenPTThe Trh-Induced Tsh Response in Psychiatric-Patients - A Possible Neuro-Endocrine MarkerPsychoneuroendocrinology19851023726010.1016/0306-4530(85)90002-22865765OppenheimerJHEvolving concepts of thyroid hormone actionBiochimie19998153954310.1016/S0300-9084(99)80107-210403187BauerMGoetzTGlennTWhybrowPCGjessingRThe thyroid-brain interaction in thyroid disorders and mood disordersJournal of Neuroendocrinology2008201101111410.1111/j.1365-2826.2008.01774.x18673409BernalJAction of thyroid hormone in brainJournal of Endocrinological Investigation20022526828811936472AronsonROffmanHJJoffeRTNaylorCDTriiodothyronine augmentation in the treatment of refractory depression - A meta-analysisArchives of General Psychiatry1996538428488792761Cooper-KazazRApterJTCohenRKaragichevLMuhammed-MoussaSGrupperDDroriTNewmanMESackeimHAGlaserBCombined treatment with sertraline and liothyronine in major depression - A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trialArchives of General Psychiatry20076467968810.1001/archpsyc.64.6.67917548749BauerMHellwegRGrafKJBaumgartnerATreatment of refractory depression with high-dose thyroxineNeuropsychopharmacology19981844445510.1016/S0893-133X(97)00181-49571653BauerMBerghoferABschorTBaumgartnerAKiesslingerUHellwegRAdliMBaethgeCMuller-OerlinghausenBSupraphysiological doses of L-thyroxine in the maintenance treatment of prophylaxis-resistant affective disordersNeuropsychopharmacology20022762062812377398BauerMSilvermanDHSchlagenhaufFLondonEDGeistCLVan HerleKRasgonNMartinezDMillerKVan HerleABrain glucose metabolism in hypothyroidism: a positron emission tomography study before and after thyroid hormone replacement therapyJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2009942922292910.1210/jc.2008-223519435829BaumgartnerABauerMHellwegRTreatment of Intractable Non-Rapid Cycling Bipolar Affective-Disorder with High-Dose Thyroxine - An Open Clinical-TrialNeuropsychopharmacology1994101831897916915KobiellaASmolkaMNeuroimaging of nicotine and tobacco smoking in humansEncyclopedia of Addictive Behaviours2011Chapter 261LechanRMToniRThyroid hormones in neural tissue2002KoenigRJThyroid hormone receptor coactivators and corepressorsThyroid1998870371310.1089/thy.1998.8.7039737367YenPMPhysiological and molecular basis of thyroid hormone actionPhysiological Reviews2001811097114211427693BauerMLondonEDSilvermanDHRasgonNKirchheinerJWhybrowPCThyroid, brain and mood modulation in affective disorder: insights from molecular research and functional brain imagingPharmacopsychiatry200336Suppl 3S215S22114677082HiroiYKimHHYingHFuruyaFHuangZHSimonciniTNomaKUlekKNguyenNHScanlanTSRapid nongenomic actions of thyroid hormoneProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2006103141041410910.1073/pnas.060160010316966610BauerMBaurHBerghoferAStrohleAHellwegRMuller-OerlinghausenBBaumgartnerAEffects of supraphysiological thyroxine administration in healthy controls and patients with depressive disordersJournal of Affective Disorders20026828529410.1016/S0165-0327(00)00363-312063156WhybrowPCPrangeAJA Hypothesis of Thyroid-Catecholamine-Receptor Interaction - Its Relevance to Affective-IllnessArchives of General Psychiatry1981381061136257196HennemannGDocterRFriesemaECHDe JongMKrenningEPVisserTJPlasma membrane transport of thyroid hormones and its role in thyroid hormone metabolism and bioavailabilityEndocrine Reviews20012245147610.1210/er.22.4.45111493579SchreiberGThe evolutionary and integrative roles of transthyretin in thyroid hormone homeostasisJ Endocrinol20021751617310.1677/joe.0.1750061VisserTJThyroid hormone transportersHormone Research200768283018174701BaquiMBoteroDGerebenBCurcioCHarneyJWSalvatoreDSorimachiKLarsenPRBiancoACHuman type 3 iodothyronine selenodeiodinase is located in the plasma membrane and undergoes rapid internalization to endosomesJournal of Biological Chemistry20032781206121110.1074/jbc.M21026620012419801WilliamsGRNeurodevelopmental and neurophysiological actions of thyroid hormoneJournal of Neuroendocrinology20082078479410.1111/j.1365-2826.2008.01733.x18601701BauerMLondonEDRasgonNBermanSMFryeMAAltshulerLLMandelkernMABramenJVoytekBWoodsRSupraphysiological doses of levothyroxine alter regional cerebral metabolism and improve mood in bipolar depressionMol Psychiatry20051045646910.1038/sj.mp.400164715724143MarwahaJPrasadKNHypothyroidism Elicits Electro-Physiological Noradrenergic Subsensitivity in Rat CerebellumScience198121467567710.1126/science.62707926270792SurksMIOrtizEDanielsGHSawinCTColNFCobinRHFranklynJAHershmanJMBurmanKDDenkeMASubclinical thyroid disease - Scientific review and guidelines for diagnosis and managementJAMA2004291222823810.1001/jama.291.2.22814722150JoffeRTMarriottMThyroid hormone levels and recurrence of major depressionAmerican Journal of Psychiatry20001571689169110.1176/appi.ajp.157.10.168911007728RuizmarcosASancheztoscanoFObregonMJDelreyFEDeescobarGMThyroxine Treatment and Recovery of Hypothyroidism-Induced Pyramidal Cell-DamageBrain Research198223955957410.1016/0006-8993(82)90530-37093702MadeiraMDAzevedoFPPaula-BarbosaMMEffects of long-term hypothyroidism in the morphology and synaptic organization of cerebellar ectopic granule cellsHistol Histopathol198833513592980244AmbroginiPCuppiniRFerriPManciniCCiaroniSVociAGerdoniEGalloGThyroid hormones affect neurogenesis in the dentate gyrus of adult ratNeuroendocrinology20058124425310.1159/00008764816113586MadeiraMDCadete-LeiteAAndradeJPPaula-BarbosaMMEffects of hypothyroidism upon the granular layer of the dentate gyrus in male and female adult rats: a morphometric studyJ Comp Neurol199131417118610.1002/cne.9031401161797872Alva-SanchezCOrtiz-ButronRPacheco-RosadoJKainic acid does not affect CA3 hippocampal region pyramidal cells in hypothyroid ratsBrain Research Bulletin20046316717110.1016/j.brainresbull.2004.02.00215130707Alva-SanchezaCSanchez-HuertaKArroyo-HelqueraOAnquianoBAcevesCPacheco-RosadoJThe maintenance of hippocampal pyramidal neuron populations is dependent on the modulation of specific cell cycle regulators by thyroid hormonesBrain Research20091271273519269280PanagiotakosGAlshamyGChanBAbramsRGreenbergESaxenaABradburyMEdgarMGutinPTabarVLong-Term Impact of Radiation on the Stem Cell and Oligodendrocyte Precursors in the BrainPLoS One200727e58810.1371/journal.pone.000058817622341VeneroCGuadano-FerrazAHerreroAINordstromKManzanoJde EscobarGMBernalJVennstromBAnxiety, memory impairment, and locomotor dysfunction caused by a mutant thyroid hormone receptor alpha 1 can be ameliorated by T3 treatmentGenes &amp; Development2005192152216310.1101/gad.34610516131613PilhatschMWinterCNordströmKVennströmBBauerMJuckelGIncreased depressive behaviour in mice harboring the mutant thyroid receptor alpha 1Behav Brain Res2010214218719210.1016/j.bbr.2010.05.01620580649MadeiraMDSousaNLima-AndradeMTCalheirosFCadete-LeiteAPaula-BarbosaMMSelective vulnerability of the hippocampal pyramidal neurons to hypothyroidism in male and female ratsJ Comp Neurol199232250151810.1002/cne.9032204051401246HasegawaMKidaIWadaHA volumetric analysis of the brain and hippocampus of rats rendered perinatal hypothyroidNeuroscience Letters201047924024410.1016/j.neulet.2010.05.07020641164BaasDLegrandCSamarutJFlamantFPersistence of oligodendrocyte precursor cells and altered myelination in optic nerve associated to retina degeneration in mice devoid of all thyroid hormone receptorsProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2002992907291110.1073/pnas.05248229911867729HarsanLASteibelJZarembaAAginASapinRPouletPGuignardBParizelNGruckerDBoehmNRecovery from Chronic Demyelination by Thyroid Hormone Therapy: Myelinogenesis Induction and Assessment by Diffusion Tensor Magnetic Resonance ImagingJournal of Neuroscience200828141891420110.1523/JNEUROSCI.4453-08.200819109501FernandezMGiulianiAPirondiSD'IntinoGGiardinoLAloeLLevi-MontalciniRCalzaLThyroid hormone administration enhances remyelination in chronic demyelinating inflammatory diseaseProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America2004101163631636810.1073/pnas.040726210115534218FrancoPGSilvestroffLSotoEFPasquiniJMThyroid hormones promote differentiation of oligodendrocyte progenitor cells and improve remyelination after cuprizone-induced demyelinationExperimental Neurology200821245846710.1016/j.expneurol.2008.04.03918572165FranklinRJMGilsonJMRemyelination in the CNS of the hypothyroid ratNeuroreport199671526153010.1097/00001756-199606170-000188856713JagannathanNRTandonNRaghunathanPKochupillaiNReversal of abnormalities of myelination by thyroxine therapy in congenital hypothyroidism: localized in vivo proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) studyDevelopmental Brain Research199810917918610.1016/S0165-3806(98)00081-99729372SijensPERodigerLAMeinersLCLunsingRJH-1 magnetic resonance spectroscopy in monocarboxylate transporter 8 gene deficiencyJournal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism200893185410.1210/jc.2007-244118319316BasserPJJonesDKDiffusion-tensor MRI: theory, experimental design and data analyNMR Biomed20021545646710.1002/nbm.78312489095AshburnerJFristonKJVoxel-based morphometry--the methodsNeuroimage20001180582110.1006/nimg.2000.058210860804FischlBDaleAMMeasuring the thickness of the human cerebral cortex from magnetic resonance imagesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200097110501105510984517HuttonCDe VitaEAshburnerJDeichmannRTurnerRVoxel-based cortical thickness measurements in MRINeuroimage2008401701171010.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.01.02718325790LassPSlawekJDerejkoARubelloDNeurological and psychiatric disorders in thyroid dysfunctions. The role of nuclear medicine: SPECT and PET imagingMinerva Endocrinologica200833758418388853NapoliRApuzziVBossoGD'AnnaCDe SenaAPirozziCMaranoALupoliGACudemoGOlivieroURecombinant Human Thyrotropin Enhances Endothelial-Mediated Vasodilation of Conduit ArteriesJournal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism2009941012101619106266ErikciAAKaragozBOzturkACaglayanSOzisikGKaygusuzIOzataMThe effect of subclinical hypothyroidism on platelet parametersHematology20091411511710.1179/102453309X38512419298725SchlenkerEHHoraMLiuYRedetzkeRAMorkinEGerdesAMEffects of thyroidectomy, T-4, and DITPA replacement on brain blood vessel density in adult ratsAmerican Journal of Physiology-Regulatory Integrative and Comparative Physiology2008294R1504R150910.1152/ajpregu.00027.2008KinuyaSMichigishiTTonamiNAburanoTTsujiSHashimotoTReversible cerebral hypoperfusion observed with Tc-99m HMPAO SPECT in reversible dementia caused by hypothyroidismClinical Nuclear Medicine19992466666810.1097/00003072-199909000-0000510478741ConstantELDe VolderAGIvanoiuABolALabarDSeghersACosnardGMelinJDaumerieCCerebral blood flow and glucose metabolism in hypothyroidism: A positron emission tomography studyJournal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism2001863864387010.1210/jc.86.8.386411502825KrauszYFreedmanNLesterHNewmanJPBarkaiGBocherMChisinRBonneORegional cerebral blood flow in patients with mild hypothyroidismJournal of Nuclear Medicine2004451712171515471838NagamachiSJinnouchiSNishiiRIshidaYFujitaSFutamiSKodamaTTamuraSKawaiKCerebral blood flow abnormalities induced by transient hypothyroidism after thyroidectomy--analysis by tc-99m-HMPAO and SPM96Ann Nucl Med20041846947710.1007/BF0298456215515745KrauszYFreedmanNLesterHBarkaiGLevinTBocherMChisinRLererBBonneOBrain SPECT study of common ground between hypothyroidism and depressionInternational Journal of Neuropsychopharmacology2007109910610.1017/S146114570600648116674833ForchettiCMKatsamakisGGarronDCAutoimmune thyroiditis and a rapidly progressive dementia: Global hypoperfusion on SPECT scanning suggests a possible mechanismNeurology1997496236299270613ZhuDFWangZXZhangDRZhuangJZhouJNThe effects of subclinical hypothyroidism on working memory: An FMRI studyBrain2006192112923293016921178MarangellLBKetterTAGeorgeMSPazzagliaPJCallahanAMParekhPAndreasonPJHorwitzBHerscovitchPPostRMInverse relationship of peripheral thyrotropin-stimulating hormone levels to brain activity in mood disordersAmerican Journal of Psychiatry19971542242309016272CrisantiPOmriBHughesEJMeduriGHeryCClauserEJacqueminCSaunierBThe expression of thyrotropin receptor in the brainEndocrinology200114281282210.1210/en.142.2.81211159854WhybrowPBauerMBehavioural and psychiatric aspects of hypothyroidism2005HauptMKurzAReversibility of Dementia in HypothyroidismJournal of Neurology199324033333510.1007/BF008399628336171BurmeisterLAGanguliMDodgeHHToczekTDeKoskySTNebesRDHypothyroidism and cognition: Preliminary evidence for a specific defect in memoryThyroid2001111177118510.1089/1050725015274103712186506HaggertyJJPrangeAJBorderline Hypothyroidism and DepressionAnnual Review of Medicine199546374610.1146/annurev.med.46.1.377598471OsterweilDSyndulkoKCohenSNPettlerjenningsPDHershmanJMCummingsJLTourtellotteWWSolomonDHCognitive Function in Nondemented Older Adults with HypothyroidismJournal of the American Geriatrics Society1992403253351556359MillerKParsonsTRasgonNVan HerleKWhybrowPBauerMHypothyroidism and specific memory deficitsArchives of Clinical Neuropsychology200318729730MonzaniFDelguerraPCaraccioNPrunetiCAPucciELuisiMBaschieriLSubclinical Hypothyroidism - Neurobehavioral Features and Beneficial Effect of L-Thyroxine TreatmentClinical Investigator1993713673718508006BaldiniIMVitaAMauriMCAmodeiVCarrisiMBravinSCantalamessaLPsychopathological and cognitive features in subclinical hypothyroidismProgress in Neuro-Psychopharmacology &amp; Biological Psychiatry19972192593510.1016/S0278-5846(97)00089-49380789GusseklooJvan ExelEde CraenAJMMeindersAEFrolichMWestendorpRGJThyroid status, disability and cognitive function, and survival in old ageJAMA2004292212591259910.1001/jama.292.21.259115572717JordeRWaterlooKStorhaugHNyrnesASundsfjordJJenssenTGNeuropsychological function and symptoms in subjects with subclinical hypothyroidism and the effect of thyroxine treatmentJournal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism20069114515310.1210/jc.2005-177516263815MaheuFSMazzoneLMerkeDPKeilMStratakisCAPineDSErnstMAltered amygdala and hippocampus function in adolescents with hypercortisolemia: A functional magnetic resonance imaging study of Cushing syndromeDevelopment and Psychopathology2008201177118910.1017/S095457940800056418838037Roberson-NayRMcClureEBMonkCSNelsonEEGuyerAEFrommSJCharneyDSLeibenluftEBlairJErnstMPineDSIncreased amygdala activity during successful memory encoding in adolescent major depressive disorder: An FMRI studyBiol Psychiatry20066099667310.1016/j.biopsych.2006.02.01816603133WolkowitzOMBurkeHEpelESReusVLGlucocorticoids. Mood, memory, and mechanismsAnn N Y Acad Sci20091179194010.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04980.x19906230PaivaFFTannusASilvaACMeasurement of cerebral perfusion territories using arterial spin labellingNmr in Biomedicine20072063364210.1002/nbm.117717503440BarrettTBrechbielMBernardoMChoykePLMRI of tumor angiogenesisJournal of Magnetic Resonance Imaging20072623524910.1002/jmri.2099117623889LauleCVavasourIMKolindSHLiDKTraboulseeTLMooreGRMackayALMagnetic resonance imaging of myelinNeurotherapeutics2007446048410.1016/j.nurt.2007.05.00417599712
