<?xml version="1.0"?>
Transl PsychiatryTransl PsychiatryTranslational Psychiatry2158-3188Nature Publishing Group3731782tp20134310.1038/tp.2013.4323860483ReviewUse of functional imaging across clinical phases in CNS drug developmentfMRI in clinical trialsBorsookD123456*BecerraL123456FavaM2461Center for Pain and the Brain, MGH, Children's and Mclean Hospitals, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA2Clinical Trials and Network Institute (CTNI), Department of Psychiatry, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA, USA3Department of Anesthesia and Critical Care, P.A.I.N. Group, Boston Children's Hospital, MGH, Harvard Medical School, Waltham, MA, USA4Department of Psychiatry, MGH, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA5Department of Radiology, MGH, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA*Department of Anesthesia and Critical Care, P.A.I.N. Group, Boston Children's Hospital, MGH, Harvard Medical School, 9 Hope Avenue, Waltham, MA 02453, USA. E-mail: david.borsook@childrens.harvard.edu6These authors contributed equally to this work.0720131607201317201337e2822002201315032013Copyright © 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited2013Macmillan Publishers LimitedThis work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/The use of novel brain biomarkers using nuclear magnetic resonance imaging holds potential of making central nervous system (CNS) drug development more efficient. By evaluating changes in brain function in the disease state or drug effects on brain function, the technology opens up the possibility of obtaining objective data on drug effects in the living awake brain. By providing objective data, imaging may improve the probability of success of identifying useful drugs to treat CNS diseases across all clinical phases (I–IV) of drug development. The evolution of functional imaging and the promise it holds to contribute to drug development will require the development of standards (including good imaging practice), but, if well integrated into drug development, functional imaging can define markers of CNS penetration, drug dosing and target engagement (even for drugs that are not amenable to positron emission tomography imaging) in phase I; differentiate objective measures of efficacy and side effects and responders vs non-responders in phase II, evaluate differences between placebo and drug in phase III trials and provide insights into disease modification in phase IV trials.braindrug developmentdrugsfunctional imagingnetworksIntroductionAs noted in a historical review on drug development, the process has evolved from a chemistry-based process to integrating pharmacology and clinical sciences to the contributions of molecular biology and genomics.1 However, the complexity of the brain makes central nervous system (CNS) drug discovery a real challenge. In the past, even with significant investment in basic neuroscience, the majority of clinical trials have failed to translate into measurable clinical benefit. Notwithstanding the enormous developments in neuroscience, systems neurobiology, nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) imaging in health and disease are clearly making their mark in questioning new approaches to drug development. With the advent of new techniques in functional neuroimaging, the ability to evaluate disease state and drug effects on neural systems in clinical populations has opened the door to adopting new approaches to CNS drug development particularly in clinical trials.Over the past few decades, CNS drug development has been hampered by countless negative and failed double blind, placebo-controlled trials—trials that have failed to confirm the expected superiority of both novel and standard compounds over a placebo condition. Negative findings with promising new agents have often led to premature shelving of such compounds and many large pharmaceutical companies have gradually abandoned their focus on CNS drug development because of the perception that trials in this area are ‘risky,' given the greater than 50% of failure in adequately powered trials.2 These negative trials have also caused delays in bringing new treatments to the market, increased costs of drug development, and, in some cases, Food and Drug Administration (FDA) decisions not to approve new treatments (‘for the preponderance of negative data'). An analysis in JAMA3 of 75 double-blind antidepressant trials, which had been conducted among patients with major depressive disorder and had been published between January 1981 and December 2000, showed that the response to placebo was often substantial and progressively increasing, with a significant positive relationship between year of publication and response rate. The gradual increase in placebo response rates across psychiatric disorders is a worrisome phenomenon, which has had a dramatic impact on the clinical development of new therapeutic agents. The two biggest factors that contribute to the extremely high rate of failures of CNS clinical trials are misclassification of study subjects (for example, the patients do not have the disease under investigation or have much milder forms than those required) and the excessive placebo response. These issues are highly salient since, while there remains a high demand for new and effective treatments for CNS disorders (for example, depression, pain, Alzheimer's disease, seizure disorders and so on), the risk is such that many of the large pharmaceutical companies have withdrawn from this drug development arena. The lack of new drugs speaks to a problem that exists in the field—that old practices do not work and that new and innovative approaches are urgently needed.4 Indeed some have termed these difficulties as contributing to ‘the death of CNS drug development'.5 Large pharmaceutical company pullout of CNS indications is leaving a large gap in the CNS drug development line and the clinical unmet need will require other adaptive strategies such as smaller biotech or the advent of better approaches to discover and develop new agents for treating disorders of the brain and mind. An imaging approach across drug development (including proof of concept paradigms)6 will help drug discovery as will fully integrate the early development side (mainly bottom-up) with clinical trials (mainly top-down).Subjective ratings in CNS disordersSubjective ratings are highly variable. Yet this is by and large what has become a major determinant of outcome in CNS trials, which often rely on clinician-rated measurements that are subjects to various biases. It is a complex issue confounded by placebo effect, the lack of effect size, the undulating or changing nature of the disease. Inter-individual differences relate to biology, disease state, psychological phenomena and the consistency of the instrument/s used to measure outcomes. Even for the same stimulus, different scales have differences in reliability.7, 8 In these cases, we are not even considering an individual's ability (education, cognitive ability—innate or due to disease such as neurodegenerative conditions; depression and so on) that may bias the outcome. Inadequate response may also be a concern that relate to dosing, duration of treatment and other factors. The harbinger of clinical trial failure has included high placebo responses. Many contributing factors to high placebo response rates observed in CNS clinical trials have been identified, such as diagnostic misclassification, issues concerning inclusion/exclusion criteria, outcome measures' lack of sensitivity to change, measurement errors, misclassification of treatment outcome, waxing and waning of the natural course of illness, regression toward the mean phenomenon, study designs fostering high patient and clinician expectations, nonspecific therapeutic effects and high attrition rates.9 Three of these elements are thought to represent the most critical factors in yielding high placebo response rates: diagnostic misclassification, misclassification of treatment outcome and study designs fostering high patient and clinician expectations. Clinical trial design is becoming more sophisticated including enrichment trials (see Fava et al.
10and Chen et al.11). New approaches include the ‘Sequential Parallel Comparison Design',9 suitable for double-blind, placebo-controlled trials in CNS disorders. This design is aimed at reducing both the overall placebo response rate and the sample size required for such trials. The basic idea is to have two phases of treatment. The first phase involves an unbalanced randomization between placebo and active treatment with more patients randomized to placebo. In the second phase, non-responders treated with placebo are randomized to either active treatment or placebo. As patients on the second phase have already ‘failed placebo', their placebo response is expected to be reduced. The analysis pools the data from both phases in order to maximize power and reduce the required sample size (see http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/record/NCT01318434). Thus far, three Sequential Parallel Comparison Design trials of CNS compounds have been completed and published, yielding weighted averages of placebo response rates markedly lower than those observed in standard designs.12, 13Given the state of the art, there would appear to be some new impetus to utilizing new14 technologies to help improve trial information and outcomes. One such approach that is being applied with greater seriousness is that of functional imaging of brain systems. Here we review the nature of how imaging may contribute across Clinical Trials both as a contributor to new information and also providing insights into integration of information across phases of clinical trials. We have termed this as imaging in Drug Development.Current issues in CNS drug development and potential opportunities through imagingCapturing data of functional effects of drug action in the living human brain of healthy volunteers or patients bring with it new opportunities to understand drug effects on CNS circuits in a manner that should transform CNS drug development. We discuss some of these processes across each phase (I–IV), noting some of the issues that are faced and provide support for how the use of imaging may either overcome or at least mitigate some of these hurdles. The major contributions relate to objectifying information in a rapid and specific manner. Integration of imaging processes across the drug development process can determine short-term effects (for example, CNS penetration and dosing), intermediate effects (for example, targets for symptom relief, possible side effects) and long-term drug effects (for example, disease modification). As suggested in the discussion below, although imaging may find useful applications across each phase, there are dominant roles suggested for phase I (evaluative imaging); phase II (effective imaging—disease targeting); phase III (definitional imaging—diminishing the variance of trials, defining responders vs non-responders; disease modification).Imaging conceptsDetails of imaging methods can be found elsewhere but a few concepts that relate to what can be measured are noted in Box 1.Phase IPhase I trials ‘test an experimental drug or treatment in a small group of people20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49, 50, 51, 52, 53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66, 67, 68, 69, 70, 71, 72, 73, 74, 75, 76, 77, 78, 79 for the first time to evaluate its safety, determine a safe dosage range and identify side effects' (www.clinicaltrials.gov). Few drugs (approximately 1 in 10) that are evaluated in preclinical phases make it to phase I testing in humans. First-in-human (FIH) doses are clearly fraught with how best to protect subjects.35 Once a drug (new chemical entity) is approved for FIH by a federal agency (for example, the FDA or the European Medicines Agency (EMA)), initial phase I studies are conducted, usually in healthy volunteers, to determine safety and dosing (viz., toxicity, pharmacokinetics and metabolism). More recently, phase I studies are beginning to include subjects with the CNS disease that is ultimately targeted by the compound under development. When this happens, it becomes critical to ensure that subjects do suffer from the CNS disease under investigation, it is also critical to provide greater information on the CNS effects of the compound studied and subjective ratings are often grossly inadequate in providing information on CNS penetration and targeting. It is a this time and going forward, significant increases in costs are associated with drug development and processes that can provide objective data for go–nogo decisions are critical for efficient development programs. For those drugs with CNS indications, the additional focus on CNS-related processes is required (for example, CNS penetration). Clearly maximizing information at this and later stages of clinical trial, drug development is clearly desirable and warranted. As noted by Dresser,36 ethical issues are being spotlighted as translational science approaches are inevitably leading to increases in FIH trials.CNS penetration and targetingThe blood–brain barrier can limit penetration of drugs into the CNS37 and effective measures of drug penetration into the CNS for CNS-acting drugs are clearly critical—both from the point of view of how much crosses the blood–brain barrier and how best to choose an effective dose to achieve effective/therapeutic levels. CNS-acting drugs can be measured for their penetration using cerebrospinal fluid levels or specific brain markers (for example, positron emission tomographic-based receptor ligands). In addition, positron emission tomography (PET) tracers can define drug targets (target engagement) within the brain. However, there are issues that the ligand-based approach does not provide: (1) functional responses to the drug effective engagement; (2) functional dose responses related to the drug of interest; and (3) for many drugs, the development of a specific ligand for PET is not possible.29, 38Imaging opportunityPharmacological magnetic resonance imaging (phMRI) allows for the direct (effects of drug on brain systems) and indirect (effects of drug on responses) evaluation of drug action in humans in early phase studies.29 Examples of phMRI use for evaluation of drugs in humans are numerous (examples of direct measures include buprenorphine;22 fosaprepitant;39 mirtazapine).40 It should be pointed out that simple phMRI activation, while it may confer some information of drug-brain (receptor/s) activation, the efficacy of the drug might depend more on functional connectivity of how the drug affects certain brain circuits.22, 23 Thus, in a few patients important data on CNS penetration can be assessed. Taken into context with known pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profiles, the time for changes in brain systems can also validate expected timelines for effective CNS ‘functional dosing'. Here we define functional dosing as the minimal dose (or early dose effects) that produces significant activation or alteration in brain circuits. Thus, in a few subjects valuable early data can be obtained for most CNS-acting drugs in early or FIH trials. This is an initial but major opportunity for the utility of imaging to contribute to the clinical evaluation of CNS-acting drugs. This approach can be used early in clinical trials once an Investigational New Drug is obtained (without special preparation for PET ligands if these are possible); and where multiple receptor targets may be at play, such receptor-specific ligands are cannot be produced. Figure 1 shows details of the potential of the use of phMRI in defining CNS dosing and drug ‘target/s'. To date a number of phase I imaging studies have employed true phMRI measures as reported in the literature (for example, see Upadhyay et al.22, 23, 41). Imaging could help in determining potential side effects as well as dosing to obtain desired effect. Specifically, in the use of combined PET—magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) systems, it will be possible to determine whether 50% receptor occupancy (with PET) produces the desired brain response (with functional MRI (fMRI)). Examples of fMRI in phase I are noted in the public domain (http://clinicaltrials.gov, see Table 1; see section ‘Where we are now?' below). These include measures of acute effects of tetrahydrocannabinol on functional brain systems that included measures on reward and memory. In these studies, end points include PK/PD correlations of drug measures with brain function. The study of RO4917523 by Hoffman-La Roche is perhaps more indicative of the approach that is beginning to be used with phase I trials by the pharmaceutical industry. The compound is a negative modulator (antagonist) of the metabotopic glutamate receptor subtype 5 (mGluR5; GRM5). Here a new drug is compared with two other drugs and placebo in a randomized crossover trial as a safety efficacy trial in 25 healthy volunteers. The primary outcome is listed ‘To evaluate the ability of fMRI to detect and characterize the effect of the three drugs on brain activity at rest and during emotional stimuli' the secondary outcomes are noted as: (i) ‘To evaluate the ability of other behavioral paradigms/scales to detect drug effects' (ii) ‘To correlate the fMRI measures with the clinical/behavioral measures' and (iii) ‘To investigate the safety of single doses of RO4917523 in healthy volunteers'. This study also provides an example of comparing a novel agent with currently marketed drugs.Healthy vs patientsWhy use healthy subjects in clinical trials? There are numerous issues relating to differences in healthy vs patients including altered brain neurobiology, differences in brain penetration across the blood–brain barrier, many patients having had other medications or on medications, and side-effect profile risks. Although there are some significant benefits to evaluating CNS drug effects in patients using imaging (noted below), most FIH trials are in healthy volunteers. These are usually small, dose-escalation trials to determine appropriate dose (based on safety and side effects) for use in future trials.42 In general, healthy subjects are used if there is little chance of patients obtaining benefit; and patients may be used when there is a good chance of benefit (for example, in some oncology trials).Imaging opportunityImaging new drug candidate effects in healthy humans can provide data on networks affected by the drug (including those that are targeted for good effect and those systems that may be involved in side effects such as drowsiness, nausea and vomiting, addiction potential). Such data would provide a sound baseline for differences or similarities of the effects of the drug in a patient population (that could easily be integrated in phase II studies). For those who argue that phase I trials be conducted in patients who are targeted for the indication, the same principles apply—through the use of imaging, early definition of targets involved. In addition, neuroimaging could be used to independently validate the diagnosis of the CNS disorder in those instances where there is adequate sensitivity and specificity of the imaging tests.43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48
Figure 2 shows details of imaging data sets from healthy and patient populations that may provide useful information on the drug effect on normal and abnormal circuits. The issue is salient as much of the individual's brain may continue to have ‘normal function' and thus a drug may act on these normal systems to contribute to its efficacy. The potential for imaging in early clinical trials is that it would seem to provide highly valuable additional data that currently cannot be easily assayed in other ways. Such data may provide information that may confirm the diagnosis of the CNS disorder, may indicate which networks are affected by the drug and may modify the future trail design before larger more expensive trials are implemented. In addition, early comparisons of drug effects in healthy and patients would seem to provide optimal data on drug dosing. For example, we and others have shown that fMRI can contribute to understanding optimal drug dosing for CNS effects and that the efficacy may depend on the brain functional connectivity not simply phMRI regional activation.22, 23 One of the important missing pieces of data will be the comparison in future studies of healthy vs patient data for the effects of drugs to determine the value of healthy subjects as has been evaluated previously for non-CNS-acting drugs using a pharmacokinetic model.49 Imaging can provide this comparison in relatively few numbers of patients (Figure 2). Thus, imaging can provide a bridging process between the healthy and patient populations to determine appropriate dosing in the patient population (who differ from healthy controls) before designing phase II efficacy trials.50 This is particularly critical in CNS disorders such as major depressive disorder, where often half of the subjects are in the obese range of body mass index, in contrast to the typical leaner populations serving as healthy controls.Phase IIIn phase II trials, evaluation of the drug in patient populations is undertaken: ‘The experimental study drug or treatment is given to a larger group of subjects (100–300) to see if it is effective and to further evaluate its safety' (http://clinicaltrials.gov). Major issues here relate to measures of understanding efficacy rates, particularly, in the context that these trials are usually not that long in nature (see Figure 3). Without an objective marker, subjective ratings continue to be used, with consequences that include features such as large variance, poor inter-rater variability and rater biases. The diagnosis of most CNS disorders is based on the subjective interpretation of signs and symptoms on the part of the clinician. Even when objective tests are used, such as electroencephalography in epilepsy and polysomnography in sleep disorders, there is often a risk of over inclusion of atypical forms of illness, which are more likely to have spontaneous fluctuations of symptoms and may inflate rates of placebo response. Site clinicians' biases to enroll subjects into trials, coupled with a system of incentives for Clinical Research Organizations to reward rapidity and not quality of enrollment, make clearly necessary the independent verification of diagnosis through centralized systems such as remote raters and/or remote reviews of diagnostic tests. Patients enrolled in CNS clinical trials often present with a heterogeneous group of symptoms representing several syndromes or subtypes, subsumed under the same diagnosis in the classification system. As a result, enrolled patients may not have the valid illness characteristics of interest to the particular study. The recently proposed SAFER interview method51 represents an effort to address the problem of diagnostic misclassification in clinical trials of psychiatric disorders. This method was developed to delineate a more symptom specific and ecologically valid approach to the identification of the valid patient for clinical trials, as clinical drug development needs to focus on the primary nosological entity likely to be affected by a new drug entity's mode of action. Neuroimaging may allow the remote validation of the appropriateness of the inclusion of study subjects and may confirm the diagnosis. Opportunities to evaluate circuit-based measures of efficacy, potential new indications, make comparisons across similar or competitive drugs, and defining measures of response (variance) can all contribute to the traditional drug development model. In phase II studies, patients may either be included in the overall study or smaller ‘satellite' groups undergo imaging to determine a number of features of the drug including functional measures, evaluating sample size (that may change if specific imaging outcomes or measures are added), comparison with other drugs to get an understanding of potential competitive advantages and the like (discussed below). Phase II trials offer an ideal opportunity to integrate neuroimaging and new trial designs such as the Sequential Parallel Comparison Design,9 thereby providing an ability to evaluate novel therapies with greater confidence of the validity of conclusions, before their going into phase III trials. Examples of the use of NMR imaging in phase II include the GlaxoSmithKline evaluation of two doses 20 and 200 mg of a Corticotrophin Releasing Factor 1 Receptor Antagonist on brain responses in irritable bowel syndrome (see Table 1). The aim of the study was to assess if the drug-reduced/reversed stress-induced hypersensitivity in these patients. The primary outcome defined as ‘Signal reductions in the amygdala during viewing of emotional faces and during abdominal pain threat as measured by the fMRI' and a secondary outcome as ‘Questionnaires to assess irritable bowel syndrome symptoms and anxiety'. Again the numbers of subjects in the study were relatively few (n=40; assumed to represent both patients and controls). The effects of the drug on brain systems in irritable bowel syndrome vs healthy controls have been reported in a recent manuscript:52 increased activity in the hypothalamus and locus cerouleus with placebo and decreases in the hypothalamus after the drug that was moderated by anxiety.Circuitry-based measures of drug efficacyIdeally, producing a highly effective drug with few or no side effects would be an excellent outcome. Many drugs with good efficacy have side effects that are only detected in later clinical trials. Some CNS diseases are more difficult to get a handle on where there may be diffuse processes (for example, Alzheimer's disease) compared with rapid symptom effects (for example, movement in Parkinson's disease, pain and so on).Imaging opportunityIn relatively small sample (n=12–20) patients, evaluation of both disease state and drug effects can be performed. Outcomes such as reversal of abnormal circuitry or lack thereof and other specific measures can be evaluated. In addition, comparisons with other drugs or current standards normally require large number of patients. Although subjective measures are helpful, these are notoriously highly variable and subjected to significant biases and issues of inter-rater reliability. In addition, filtering out a circuit-based process may contribute to the evaluation of longer-term benefits of the drug. Measures of drug efficacy may be done through either resting state network or evoked stimuli. The advantage of the former is that the patients simply lie in the magnet and do not have to follow any instructions. Therefore, for some CNS diseases where cognitive abilities are altered, this may be a useful approach. As noted in Box 1, resting state networks can differentiate drug effects. Imaging can assess longitudinal changes associated with drug use.Sample sizePowering clinical studies usually involves large groups of patients because of variability. One of the big issues with clinical trials relates to the nature of the study design and the variability of data acquired, especially in subjective ratings.53, 54, 55 Clearly diminishing variance allows for a number of benefits including fewer patients required for adequate power of the study and fewer patients are exposed in a drug trial. Both elements have important cost-related benefits. Much of the variance has to do with factors such as inappropriate phenotyping of the population being studied, measurement error, inappropriate end points, problems with responders and non-responders, placebo response, quality of data collected even with good clinical practice standards56 including timeline for evaluation of responses.57Imaging opportunityImaging data can help decrease the variance within a study population by determining brain changes of drug vs placebo with or without correlations with subjective measures. Such data have come from some studies in healthy subjects in a paradigm evaluating pain using imaging, where activations showed less variance than pain reports.22 By implementing novel designs and end points for phase II trials would improve efficiency in defining those New Chemical Entities with potential and quickly eliminating those that have limited efficacy (see Adjei et al.58). Adding imaging (markers/biomarkers) into this part of the clinical development and specifically defining new end points. The evolution of this type of approach may also help in identifying responders and non-responders at an early stage for methodological considerations in larger phase III trials. New analysis techniques will also allow segregating patients according to subgroups based on their brain nasal states and responses to treatment.59Early comparators: differentiation of new entity with ‘Best in Class' or mechanism of actionThe placebo-controlled trial has been the standard method to demonstrate efficacy and safety, that is, most CNS clinical trials evaluate New Chemical Entity with a placebo (‘A placebo is an inactive pill, liquid, or powder that has no treatment value. In clinical trials, experimental treatments are often compared with placebos to assess the treatment's effectiveness' http://clinicaltrials.gov). Few CNS trials include an active comparator (see Leon60). So-called ‘active-control non-inferiority trials' take this into consideration.61, 62 phMRI data sets are accruing in a non-defined or non-organized manner (see Table 1), but nevertheless are providing the initial contributions to what could be the development of drug-specific databases that could be used as comparators for new drugs. Many CNS drugs have actions on the CNS that are not well understood.Imaging opportunityData banks on CNS activation of drugs that are now in the non-competitive space can provide a basis for evaluation of new drugs. Thus, the cumulative benefits, particularly if there is the development of a databank, could really help to understand in-vivo drug action in the CNS.Drugs and clinical relevance: the need for phenotyping and biomarkersMost drugs are focused on specific targets. Take the antidepressants as an example. The initial appeal of an aminergic target certainly seemed to be valid. Certain aspects clearly questioned the process including the time lag for efficacy. More recently, neural circuit adaptation has been postulated as a process that underlies the potential efficacy of antidepressant drugs. We now have a method to evaluate this. However, and perhaps, equally important is to understand that when we evaluate a drug in a particular population, these patients are of a particular ‘phenotype'. This seemingly obvious issue is difficult without the enabling processes afforded by biomarkers.63, 64 The development of biomarkers for CNS disease would revolutionize the approaches being taken in the drug development domain. Certainly, attempts in different domains are currently at the forefront of many research enterprises across the CNS domain. It is unlikely that many CNS disorders will have a single gene entity that can define the disorder like hemiplegic migraine or erythromelalgia or certain Parkinson's disease subtypes. Thus, other markers are essential to define the clinical phenotype in an objective manner. Accurate phenotyping is critical to any drug trial (see Founti et al.65). Imaging is one opportunity in the development of biomarkers for drug development.66, 67, 68Imaging opportunityCurrently, imaging offers a basis for a ‘marker' of drug effect. It has not developed yet to a level of an accepted, regulatory-approved biomarker. Recent advances suggest that imaging may contribute to improving success rates in drug development, but for this to happen, biomarkers need to be defined, validated, reproducible and adopted by regulatory agencies. Figure 4 conceptualizes the use of imaging biomarkers in drug evaluation. The approach may also evolve to have disease fingerprinting69 or disease evolution utilizing anatomical measures.70 Indeed, the Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative has provided a model for applications of imaging in disease and drug evaluation.71Phase IIIIn phase III trials, ‘the experimental study drug or treatment is given to large groups of people (1000–3000) to confirm its effectiveness, monitor side effects, compare it to commonly used treatments and collect information that will allow the experimental drug or treatment to be used safely' (http://clinicaltrials.gov). Here tremendous opportunities exist to add imaging information to clinical trial design improve study information. Issues pertaining to predicting natural course of the disease (for example, improvement independent of treatment), predicting responders vs non-responders based on an objective metric can, as in phase II trials, be incorporated into phase III trials. Examples of the use of NMR imaging in phase II include those listed in Table 1; as noted from the table, there are relatively few phase III trials (see section ‘Limitations of NMR imaging in drug development: difficulties to overcome as a useful tool in clinical trials' below).Temporal course of CNS diseasesSymptoms of most CNS diseases fluctuate over time; they are for the most part progressive (for example, Alzheimer's disease) or may be intermittent in severity (for example, depression) or may have a natural course that trends toward improvement (for example, chronic pain or migraine; see Parkinson's Progression Marker Initiative—that involves measures of imaging and other potential makers72). Thus, understanding if the drug has an effect during the trial or the change is a response to the fluctuation of the disease can critically affect response measures that may have little to do with the drug effect (see Johannsen et al.73). The issue may be implicated in the failure of clinical trials74 because of changes in clinical status (see Kemp et al.75 and Geisser et al.
76). Such changes may make the disease more resistant or less resistant, or in some cases may revert to a ‘normal' level, as is the case with chronic pain or depression.Imaging opportunityImaging can provide a specific effect of a drug or intervention (Figure 5). For example, the evolving or normalization of a network that may take place as a result of the drug treatment or for other reasons including spontaneous disease remission (for example, in depression). Ideally, imaging can provide two useful measures: (1) specificity of early markers of drug action and (2) disease state or drug effects over time.Imaging as an effective measure of drug responseAlthough placebo-controlled trials have been considered a standard for evaluating a drug, the improved understanding that the placebo effect may be a specific response of a subject based on psychological processes that drive neural systems.77, 78, 79 Differentiating drug–placebo differences are more difficult in the CNS domain80, 81, 82 than placebo. As shown in Figure 6, one may classify treated subjects in a CNS clinical trial based on each subject's propensity to respond to a given type of treatment. The D-P-population comprises subjects who are not responsive to both active and inactive treatments. In CNS trials in non-resistant neuropsychiatric disorders, the D−P− group typically represents 50% of the populations, based on the non-response rates frequently observed with active treatments. Such proportion, naturally, tends to be larger in more resistant populations. The D+P+ population comprises subjects who are responsive to either active or inactive treatments. In a very large meta-analysis of 182 antidepressant clinical trials pooled (n=36 385) from our group,83 the average placebo response rate in trials with two active treatments and placebo was about 40%, which is a proxy for the rate of D+P+ group. When the placebo response (and therefore the D+P+ group) is 40% in a given clinical trial, and the D−P− group is 50%, this means that only 10% of the treated subjects belong to the D+P− group, which includes patients who respond to active treatment but not to placebo. Therefore, the higher the placebo rate, the smaller the size of the D+P− group, the only informative group of patients. Thus, if the average placebo response rate in antidepressant trials is 40% or greater, this means that more than 50% of these adequately powered trials cannot possibly detect a signal, even when the compound is active, as 10% or less of the sample is informative. How can one improve outcome of category: (1) through differentiation of category, (2) by defining responders to the drug being evaluated vs responders to the placebo. Thus, the issue may be defined in terms of differentiation of responses and responders. These are seemingly straight forward; however, false positive (a good result reported when there actually is not one) and false negative responders (a poor result when there is actually a positive one) complicate the issue. Furthermore, evaluating responders vs non-responders also relates to the heterogeneity of the disease. A major issue related to response is the level of response—is it a complete response (the absence of the symptoms of the disease). Furthermore, a response may be relatively short lived for various reasons that may include pharmacodynamic, tachyphylaxis and alterations in response because of the course of the disease over time.Imaging opportunityAlthough the placebo (an inactive pill, liquid or powder that has no treatment value (http://clinicaltrials.gov)) would ideally be expected to show no effect because it is an inert substance, the placebo effect can confound results. Differentiation of the placebo effect (‘A physical or emotional change, occurring after a substance is taken or administered, that is not the result of any special property of the substance. The change may be beneficial, reflecting the expectations of the participant and, often, the expectations of the person giving the substance' (http://clinicaltrials.gov)) from the drug effect can be problematic. The effect of placebo response rates and how best to measure this in clinical trials has made clinical trials of the CNS a more complex issue.84, 85 As noted in Figure 7, some patients show clinical improvement in response to the placebo arm of a trial where an inactive compound is used. The variability in placebo response rates in CNS clinical trials may vary.3 The large variation makes the trial design challenging because of adequate statistical power and sample size requirements. Furthermore, if patients are not adequately screened or phenotyped, further variation in response to placebo may be observed (for example, between anxious vs non-anxious patients).Symptom effects vs disease modificationThere is no question that the quality of life can be significantly elevated with the control of symptoms. Measures of disease modification that stabilize, limit or reverse or prevent a CNS condition are clearly sought after75, 86 and are clearly challenges for neuroscience and pharmaceutical industries involved in CNS-related therapies.87 To date, however, there are no drugs that completely alleviate disease symptoms (for example, pain, depression and so on). Ideally, treatments that effectively reverse the condition would be a transformational in nature. The problem is that, for the most part, unless some phenomenal genetic or stem cell-type approach emerges, for most pharmacotherapeutics, the process will in all likelihood be slow.Imaging opportunityWhatever the disease-modifying treatment approaches are used, stem cell, biologicals and so on, defined measures will be required to evaluate disease modification over time. For some diseases (that is, Alzheimer's) prior work has provided some useful insights into the use of morphometric measures for drug effects on disease outcome (see Cummings88 and Weiner et al.89). Given that most CNS disorders are chronic in nature, brain measures of function and structure can be enormously helpful in measuring progressive changes. In addition, the benefits of multimodal imaging can provide congruent measures on the disease condition or a drug effect. For example, magnetic resonance spectroscopy (see Box 1) can provide a correlate of alterations in gray matter volume changes; gray matter volume changes may correlate with alterations in white matter connectivity that then has implications on functional processing.83, 90, 91Dosing and drug effectivenessOnce patients are prescribed drugs, they frequently stay on these medications without assessment of how they have altered the brain. Recent data, for example, have questioned the use of some drugs over the long term because of negative effects on brain systems. As such the opportunity to evaluate new approaches to drug therapy, with continued but lower doses, may contribute to equal or even higher efficacy rates in patients for a number of reasons including limiting side effects and thus compliance.Imaging opportunityImaging would provide measures of efficacy in chronic long-term dosing. The issue of long-term medications on the brain (for example, opioids) or long-term consequences of medication (for example, methylphenidate or anesthetics in children) clearly need to be established. Many medications are taken as prescribed for years without evaluation of potential good and bad effects. This is critical as the drug might induce positive changes (that is, tendency or return to ‘normal' brain function) or negative ones (for example, migraine chronification from medications including chronic opioids, chronic triptans92, 93).Implementing integrative imaging in clinical trialsAs noted by Kuhlman94 ‘The more thorough and profound studies have been carried out during this exploratory stage of development, the earlier a decision can be made on the continuation or discontinuation of further development. Taking responsibility as the link between research and development gives clinical pharmacology a major opportunity to assume a pivotal role in research and development of new drugs' Drug development has been a sequential process that has included preclinical evaluation (target selection, toxicity profiling for safety and side effects), FIH trials that include drug escalation for maximum tolerated dose (phase I, usually in healthy volunteers), drug efficacy in patients (phase II), efficacy and safety (phase III, with a specific indication usually for regulatory approval) and post-marketing evaluation to determine no unexpected side effects (phase IV). Ideally, the more information that can be collected in early trials predicting outcomes (both good or bad), the more efficient and less costly the process (as information may arise halting the program early or forcing an evaluation that may change the trial or even the indication) (Figure 8). Most trial phases are usually planned and implemented separately, potentially diminishing the benefits of a sequential integrated approach. Transferring useful information including imaging information across development would necessitate an integrated approach to the process. Figure 9 summarizes key points that imaging can bring to the evaluation of a CNS drug candidate in drug development. In other domains of clinical trials, some have supported a role for translational research across the various phases of clinical trials.95Biological considerationsComparative studies across drugs and conditionsThe FDA has encouraged the use of biomarker approaches to drug development. Hopefully over time, pharmaceutical and biotechnology companies will provide more exciting and useful information on how imaging can help make smart choices in drug development. Through such processes as well as evaluation of drugs in academic centers, an accumulation of a body of knowledge on drug ‘fingerprints' on brain systems will allow for a Brain-Drug-Catalogue. The value will be to provide a comparative evaluation of similar drugs (by class or by mechanism of action) in which to compare new drugs. Perhaps this may even become a process that will achieve a consensus to be performed in all phase II studies. Such comparisons could also apply to bio-similar products.Integrated multimodal imaging approachesAs imaging technologies develop, rapid magnetic resonance sequences can capture a number of brain functional, structural and chemical measures. Integrating such measure can provide further information including response to drugs, predict responders vs non-responders, or early changes in brain systems that may be markers of drug efficacy. More sensitive imaging technologies have already provided novel insights into stroke severity and prediction of outcome, the nature of underlying brain changes in mild traumatic brain injury and so on. Alterations in structure usually accompany changes in function (see Upadhyay et al.32).Early evidence of subclinical side effectsMany CNS drugs fail because of side effects. Some brain-defined side-effects (for example, nausea and vomiting, drowsiness) or unwarranted effects (for example, addition, cognitive changes) can be observed in imaging in small groups of subjects as potential changes would focus attention in early trials and allow for changes to be made in the larger trial design (for example, dosing) or for the drug to stop in its development based on these appraisals. The flip side of this is that unexpected side effects can provide new insights into brain systems and human surrogate models. Perhaps a good example of this is the antimalarial agent mefloquine-producing drug-induced psychosis in otherwise healthy subjects.96, 97Clinical trials considerationsA number of issues arise when considering imaging in clinical trials. The first is integration of imaging into trials without confounding regulatory processes and including risks to the trial. If done in a manner that can show enhanced outcomes, this could lead to fewer patients to be exposed to new drugs early in clinical trials (for example, phase II). The second is applying good imaging practice in trials98, 99 to ensure standards across the industry. As noted in Table 1, there are more clinical trials using imaging, but this is still relatively new and on an ‘ad hoc' basis without agreed upon standards and known measures such as sensitivity and specificity (see above). The data listed in the Table 1 are derived from all registered trials from clinicaltrials.gov (http://www.clinicaltrials.gov; see details in section ‘Where we are now?' below). The third issue that imaging may evolve into is the validation of surrogate end points. Such information provides a correlate of a clinical end point and is defined as ‘a biomarker intended to substitute for a clinical end point' (see Lesko et al.100 and Lathia et al.101).Financial considerationsRisk-benefit assessment aided by objective metricsDecreasing the risk of drug development including the ability to get objective data from relatively small cohorts of individuals, the cost benefits of discontinuing work on drug are critical elements in go–nogo decisions. Obviously, decisions to fund trials are critical to financial success of the drug. However, the risk for investigational drugs is high, especially in the CNS domain where the overall success rates has been around 15%.102 The average cost of a drug from inception/discovery to approval following phase III trials is close to a billion dollars. The costs of drug development from discovery to phase II trials is around $100 million. At least three pharmaceutical companies initiated clinical drug development efforts of NK-1 receptor antagonists for a pain indication. The total number of patients evaluated for NK-1 Receptor Antagonist for pain in known investigator-initiated or company-initiated phase II clinical trials is based on available data in the public domain is around 500 individuals (see Borsook et al.38). If one assumes an investigator (academic, Clinical Research Organization) costs of approximately $25 000–$35 000 per patient, it is around $12 500 000–17 500 000, notwithstanding, the potential risk for side effects that overall is reported to be relatively minor (for example, diarrhea). These do not take into account a pharmaceutical company's costs; estimates are $17 million per year on drugs in phase I, $34 million on drugs in phase II and $27 million per year on drugs in phase III of the human clinical trials.103 Thus, in the case of the NK-1 receptor antagonists, a conservative estimate of the phase I–II trials across four companies is estimated to cost over $100 million. Given the extremely low-side-effect profile of the drug and early preclinical suggestions of alternate indications, the drug has successfully made it into the antiemetic arena, and looks promising in other areas of psychiatric disease. The additional costs for fMRI of a small group of subjects in early phase development (drug has received Investigational New Drug and therefore can be administered to subjects) is around $1 million. However, the potential cost-benefits based on the data obtained at this early stage may be enormous (see Borsook et al.38).Limitations of NMR imaging in drug development: difficulties to overcome as a useful tool in clinical trialsAlthough the potential of imaging across the three phases of clinical trials may be great, enthusiasm should be tempered by current limitations or issues that need to be improved or overcome. Some of these are noted below and in Box 2.Technical issuesWith all imaging methodologies that measure indirectly brain activity through physiological changes, the underlying issue relates to how much of the change is neural vs physiological. This is especially important in clinical trials in which drug effects are assessed as the drug itself might induce global physiological changes. Although blood oxygenation level dependence is the main approach to perform fMRI experiments, it could be highly affected by drugs altering brain perfusion or reactivity in any manner. Several approaches exist to mitigate or quantify physiological effects on blood oxygenation level-dependent signals and include: the recording of physiological parameters (heart rate, blood pressure, end tidal CO2 and so on) to be considered in the analysis, the addition of control scans/experiments of systems that are not affected by the drug and should remain constant (for example, visual system activation) or measure actual physiological changes in brain perfusion such as blood flow measurements with arterial spin labeling. Another technical issues potentially affecting neuroimaging measurements include patient compliance: excessive motion, not following instructions could affect or render useless the acquired data set and without proper monitoring during the scans such data sets can contaminate the overall assessment. However, new imaging analytic approaches including machine vector learning can now be employed to objectively differential subjects, disease subtype and drug effects.104, 105 Such developments when deployed into the drug trial armamentarium should significantly help further the use of NMR imaging in clinical drug development at the individual and population level.105, 106Correlation with disease pathologyWe acknowledge that we do not presently have a good understanding of the pathophysiology of the majority of psychiatric disorders. Recently, there has been a change in the field to move from discrete disorders to dimensions and continuous degrees of dysfunction (for example, Research Domain Criteria). Research domain criteria is an approach that aims to define basic dimensions of functioning to be studied across multiple domains of analysis (that is, genes to neural circuits to behaviors). This certainly will impact on the role of imaging in drug development. The correlation of current science and disease with respect to imaging has seen breakthroughs such as markers of disease progression (for example, Alzheimer's disease)107 or regression (for example, chronic pain)108 and such brain metrics may correlate with changes in gray matter volume that may correlate with dendritic arborization by disease or stress109, 110 or drugs;111 changes in systems involved in known processes related to the disease (for example, stress and hippocampal changes112).Standardization and harmonizationLikely for phase III studies, a multisite approach will be the approach. The use of different scanner manufactures, imaging protocols, could result in an exceeding variance that renders the data unusable. Harmonization of scanner parameters, following validation of imaging sequences across manufacturers, will significantly reduce this problem. The need to define standard methodologies for good imaging practice is essential in order to understand and compare results. A procedural framework for good imaging practice has been suggested.113, 114 If the applications of NMR measures in clinical drug development are to be implemented, accepted guidelines would need to be adopted. Adoption of such standards will become necessary for imaging to be incorporated into regulatory processes and acceptance by the FDA (http://www.fda.gov) and EMA (http://www.ema.europa.eu). With respect to the latter, issues that will need to be accepted include definition of imaging end points. The issue is not that imaging would usurp clinical end points, but may enhance the process by which clinical end points are reached.What value would the imaging add to clinical measures?It is not argued that imaging would replace current clinical outcomes, but improve the clinical trial approach by decreasing the risk of the trial to both patients and the drug developers. Right now having an objective diagnosis for many CNS disease states has eluded us, particularly, for psychiatric disease. In the complexity of comorbidity for many diseases including neurological disease is a critical issue. For example, in most neurological diseases, comorbid depression is present.115 In addition, disease state varies over time, and therefore evaluation of a drug targeted against a specific disease may have a different efficacy profile depending on the ‘intransigence' of the disease that relates to its duration and severity. Similar issues may relate to sensitivity of side-effect profiles. Finally, clinical measures of disease modification are difficult to determine and imaging may have a specific niche in this domain. Trials in Alzheimer's disease (refs) and chronic pain (refs) have provided some examples of specific morphometric measures of such changes.Validity and acceptanceNMR imaging meets some of the Daubert Criteria for use in a legal sense (http://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/daubert_standard) in that it can be tested and therefore validated and the procedure can be peer reviewed. Issues pertaining to the rate of error for NMR imaging in patients or for drug effects is a path forward but that needs to be further evaluated and defined. Although NMR imaging is generally accepted in some of the scientific community, it has not made it to routine clinical use at this time. More stringent measures of sensitivity and specificity will allow for this, and for its potential use in drug development, its acceptance as a method and potentially as a biomarker by regulatory agencies.Where we are now?Table 1 is data collated by searching http://www.clinicaltrials.gov; the search strategy was performed in two phases; the first was for trials listed, a search strategy included ‘fMRI', ‘phase I' or ‘phase II or phase III' and ‘drug trial' the second was a cross check for specific diseases (for example, pain, depression) and for age groups (for example, children). The table provides a number of interesting insights into the use of imaging in evaluating drug effects. As noted in the table, some 70 drugs are represented, suggesting a reasonably active use of fMRI in drug evaluation, use that has really increased steadily since 2010.First, a number of companies are using fMRI to evaluate novel drugs. Examples are those being developed by Novartis (#), Glaxo-Smith-Kline (#24–27, 29), Astra-Zeneca (#7), Eli-Lilly,29 Merck (#43), Hoffman-LaRoche (#'s60, 61) and some smaller biotechnology companies (Biotie Therapies Inc., #67). This does not include other drugs being evaluated for chronic disease at Academic institutions supported by pharmaceutical companies or the NIH. Thus, it would seem that despite ongoing reservations, the use of fMRI, albeit in a limited manner is gaining acceptance across the pharmaceutical industry. Although this adoption may be as an ‘add-on' to standard approaches in clinical drug development, more experience and data will provide further insights into the utility of the approach. A recent paper epitomizes ongoing efforts to further understand the utility of imaging in drug development: ‘Quantifying the attenuation of the ketamine phMRI response in humans: a validation using antipsychotic and glutamatergic agents'124 and test–retest reliability to the same drug in healthy subjects.125 Thus, through these developments, specific assays for drug evaluation are contributing to greater acceptance in the field.Second, the use of the technology spans all phases of clinical drug development (see Table 1; phase 1: n=25 studies; phase II: n=11 studies; phase III: n=4 studies; and phase IV: n=34 studies). As noted from Table 1, all clinical phases (phase I: n=25 studies; phase II: n=11 studies; phase III: n=4 studies and phase IV: n=34 studies). Some studies noted in clinicaltrials.gov are listed with no phase defined and some are listed as combined (that is, I.II). The frequency spread on the use of imaging toward early phase (I) and later phase (IV) may relate to regulatory processes imposed by the FDA or its European equivalent, the EMA. The relative value of use of imaging at different phases is still unclear. Costs of adapting this will probably offset those of ongoing trials that would have either been halted or redirected with insights from functional imaging, the NK-1 receptor antagonist providing a good example.126Third, use of the technology for drugs with different indications (see #'s 5, 6, 11, 18, 19, 20, 22, 30, 33, 36, 40, 50 and 55) is observed in addition to the use of comparator drugs (for example, 3, 5, 6, 7, 9, 17, 22, 24–26, 423, 54, 55, 60, 64). Notable among these are those that are in pharmaceutical trials. The use of a comparator (either by function or best in class) allows for the evaluation of new insights into a drug being developed. For example, many CNS-acting drug have no clear definition of how they affect brain systems and therefore function in the short and long term. Imaging can define such parameters that may be difficult to ascertain clinically Thus, for example, the evaluation of antidepressants in clinical trials may be helped with the added objective assay in terms of producing a more effective agent.Fourth, the technology is being used in children and adults. Obviously, many of the major CNS disorders such as attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, autism spectrum disorders, chronic pain (for example, abdominal pain) are conditions that have few effective drugs, and methods to enhance the clinical trial process that includes imaging, may provide useful methods of targeting more effective drugs. This is obviously not an ‘an alone state' but dependent on our understanding of neurobiology of disease. The latter has seen advances across many CNS disorders, but clearly this area is still a major confound.Fifth, for some uses, a model of disease can be defined as exemplified by #12 and the mefloquine example noted above where a drug produces an abnormal brain state.127, 128 Imaging can provide a method for assaying circuit function, a basis for behavior. The use of healthy human surrogates in a safe and effective manner to produce reversible alterations in brain function may provide novel insights into disease process, but also models to test drugs without other confounds such as duration of disease, co-morbidities and so on.Sixth, what is clearly missing from the current state is how best to integrate information from genetic, questionnaire, phenotypic and other criteria currently used to enroll patients into clinical trials. This is clearly an area of opportunity that is being deployed by some groups including ours at Massachusetts General Hospital (Clinical Trials Network and Institute; http://www.massgeneral.org/psychiatry/research/ctni_home.aspx).This study was supported by the Herland's Fund for Pain Research.David Borsook:
Research support: Public—Glaxo-Smith Kline; Merck and Company; Eli Lilly; Abbvie; Bristol Myers Squibb; Gruenthal; Vertex; Repligen; Peptimmune; Adolor; Locus; Infinity; National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke; National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (NCCAM); National Institute of Drug Abuse (NIDA). Private—Mayday Fund; Herlands Fund; Childrens Hospital Anesthesia and Radiology Foundations. Advisory/consulting: Merck and Co—Purdue Frederick; Sanofi; Johnson and Johnson; Allergan; Demerx; Dara Pharmaceuticals; Eli Lilly. Speaking/publishing: Speaking—American Society of Clinical Psychopharmacology; Pfizer; Merck and Co; Eli Lilly; Johnson and Johnson; Wyeth; International Association for Pain; International Headache Society. Equity holdings: Stocks—None in public companies; Demerx. Patent—Kirin 5500—licensed to DARA from MGH. Royalty payments: Books—Borsook D, Becerra L, Bullmore E, Hargreaves R, editors. fMRI in CNS Drug Development. Springer 2009. Borsook D, Hargreaves R, Goadsby P, May A. Imaging the Migraine Brain. Oxford University Press. 2012. Copyright: Saving the Child's Brain.Lino Becerra:
Research support: National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS); National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS); National Institutes of Health National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (NCCAM), National Institute of Drug Abuse (NIDA); Glaxo-Smith Kline, Merck and Company. Advisory/Consulting: Pain Research Services, Massachusetts General Hospital; Medical Imaging Center of Southern California, Santa Monica, CA. Speaking/Publishing: Book—fMRI in CNS Drug Development. Springer 2009.Equity holdings: N/A. Royalty payments: Borsook D, Becerra L, Bullmore E, Hargreaves R, editors. fMRI in CNS Drug Development. Springer 2009.Maurizio Fava:
Research support: Abbot Laboratories; Alkermes, Inc.; Aspect Medical Systems; AstraZeneca; BioResearch; BrainCells Inc.; Bristol-Myers Squibb; CeNeRx BioPharma; Cephalon; Clintara, LLC; Covance; Covidien; Eli Lilly and Company; ElMindA, Ltd.; EnVivo Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Euthymics Bioscience, Inc.; Forest Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Ganeden Biotech, Inc.; GlaxoSmithKline; Harvard Clinical Research Institute; Icon Clinical Research; i3 Innovus/Ingenix; Janssen R&amp;D, LLC; Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development; Lichtwer Pharma GmbH; Lorex Pharmaceuticals; MedAvante; National Alliance for Research on Schizophrenia &amp; Depression (NARSAD); National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine (NCCAM); National Institute of Drug Abuse (NIDA); National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH); Neuralstem, Inc.; Novartis AG; Organon Pharmaceuticals; PamLab, LLC.; Pfizer Inc.; Pharmaceutical Research Associates., Inc.; Pharmavite® LLC; PharmoRx Therapeutics; Photothera; Roche Pharmaceuticals; RCT Logic, LLC (formerly Clinical Trials Solutions, LLC); Sanofi-Aventis US LLC; Shire; Solvay Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Synthelabo; Wyeth-Ayerst Laboratories. Advisory/consulting: Abbott Laboratories; Affectis Pharmaceuticals AG; Alkermes, Inc.; Amarin Pharma Inc.; Aspect Medical Systems; AstraZeneca; Auspex Pharmaceuticals; Bayer AG; Best Practice Project Management, Inc.; BioMarin Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Biovail Corporation; BrainCells Inc; Bristol-Myers Squibb; CeNeRx BioPharma; Cephalon, Inc.; CNS Response, Inc.; Compellis Pharmaceuticals; Cypress Pharmaceutical, Inc.; DiagnoSearch Life Sciences (P) Ltd.; Dinippon Sumitomo Pharma Co. Inc.; Dov Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Edgemont Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Eisai Inc.; Eli Lilly and Company; EnVivo Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; ePharmaSolutions; EPIX Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Euthymics Bioscience, Inc.; Fabre-Kramer Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Forest Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; GenOmind, LLC; GlaxoSmithKline; Grunenthal GmbH; i3 Innovus/Ingenis; Janssen Pharmaceutica; Jazz Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, LLC; Knoll Pharmaceuticals Corp.; Labopharm Inc.; Lorex Pharmaceuticals; Lundbeck Inc.; MedAvante, Inc.; Merck &amp; Co., Inc.; MSI Methylation Sciences, Inc.; Naurex, Inc.; Neuralstem, Inc.; Neuronetics, Inc.; NextWave Pharmaceuticals; Novartis AG; NuPathe; Nutrition 21; Orexigen Therapeutics, Inc.; Organon Pharmaceuticals; Otsuka Pharmaceuticals; Pamlab, LLC.; Pfizer Inc.; PharmaStar; Pharmavite® LLC.; PharmoRx Therapeutics; Precision Human Biolaboratory; Prexa Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Puretech Ventures; PsychoGenics; Psylin Neurosciences, Inc.; Rexahn Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Ridge Diagnostics, Inc.; Roche; Sanofi-Aventis US LLC.; Sepracor Inc.; Servier Laboratories; Schering-Plough Corporation; Solvay Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Somaxon Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Somerset Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Sunovion Pharmaceuticals; Supernus Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Synthelabo; Takeda Pharmaceutical Company Limited; Tal Medical, Inc.; Tetragenex Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Teva; TransForm Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Transcept Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Vanda Pharmaceuticals, Inc. Speaking/publishing: Adamed, Co; Advanced Meeting Partners; American Psychiatric Association; American Society of Clinical Psychopharmacology; AstraZeneca; Belvoir Media Group; Boehringer Ingelheim GmbH; Bristol-Myers Squibb; Cephalon, Inc.; CME Institute/Physicians Postgraduate Press, Inc.; Eli Lilly and Company; Forest Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; GlaxoSmithKline; Imedex, LLC; MGH Psychiatry Academy/Primedia; MGH Psychiatry Academy/Reed Elsevier; Novartis AG; Organon Pharmaceuticals; Pfizer Inc.; PharmaStar; United BioSource, Corp.; Wyeth-Ayerst Laboratories. Equity holdings: Compellis; PsyBrain, Inc. Royalty/patent, other income: Patent for Sequential Parallel Comparison Design (SPCD), which are licensed by MGH to RCT Logic, LLC; and patent application for a combination of azapirones and bupropion in major depressive disorder (MDD). Copyright for the MGH Cognitive &amp; Physical Functioning Questionnaire (CPFQ), Sexual Functioning Inventory (SFI), Antidepressant Treatment Response Questionnaire (ATRQ), Discontinuation-Emergent Signs &amp; Symptoms (DESS), and SAFER; Lippincott, Williams &amp; Wilkins; Wolkers Kluwer; World Scientific Publishing Co. Pte. Ltd.DrewsJDrug discovery: a historical perspectiveScience20002871960196410720314FavaMRushAJTrivediMHNierenbergAAThaseMESackeimHABackground and rationale for the sequenced treatment alternatives to relieve depression (STAR*D) studyPsychiatr Clin North Am20032645749412778843WalshBTSeidmanSNSyskoRGouldMPlacebo response in studies of major depression: variable, substantial, and growingJAMA20022871840184711939870PangalosMNSchechterLEHurkoODrug development for CNS disorders: strategies for balancing risk and reducing attritionNat Rev Drug Discov2007652153217599084CutlerRWorldwide Clinical Trials2011Available from
http://www.wwctrials.com
.
WongDFTauscherJGrunderGThe role of imaging in proof of concept for CNS drug discovery and developmentNeuropsychopharmacology20093418720318843264BreivikEKBjornssonGASkovlundEA comparison of pain rating scales by sampling from clinical trial dataClin J Pain200016222810741815Ponce de LeonSLara-MunozCFeinsteinARWellsCKA comparison of three rating scales for measuring subjective phenomena in clinical research. II. Use of experimentally controlled visual stimuliArch Med Res20043515716215010197FavaMEvinsAEDorerDJSchoenfeldDAThe problem of the placebo response in clinical trials for psychiatric disorders: culprits, possible remedies, and a novel study design approachPsychother Psychosom20037211512712707478FavaMRushAJTrivediMHNierenbergAAThaseMESackeimHABackground and rationale for the sequenced treatment alternatives to relieve depression (STAR*D) studyPsychiatr Clin North Am20032645749412778843ChenYFYangYHungHMWangSJEvaluation of performance of some enrichment designs dealing with high placebo response in psychiatric clinical trialsContemp Clin Trials20113259260421540126FavaMMischoulonDIosifescuDWitteJPencinaMFlynnMA double-blind, placebo-controlled study of aripiprazole adjunctive to antidepressant therapy among depressed outpatients with inadequate response to prior antidepressant therapy (ADAPT-A Study)Psychother Psychosomatics2012818797PapakostasGISheltonRCZajeckaJMEtemadBRickelsKClainAL-methylfolate as adjunctive therapy for SSRI-resistant major depression: results of two randomized, double-blind, parallel-sequential trialsAm J Psychiatry20121691267127423212058AminDVDoctorRBGirdharAOShahUHThe effect of beta-adrenergic stimulation and blockade on the efflux of PGE1-like material from the isolated perfused rabbit heartExperientia198036141014116110563van WingenGAZyliczSAPietersSMatternCVerkesRJBuitelaarJKTestosterone increases amygdala reactivity in middle-aged women to a young adulthood levelNeuropsychopharmacology20093453954718235425KraftELoichingerWDiepersMLuleDSchwarzJLudolphACLevodopa-induced striatal activation in Parkinson's disease: a functional MRI studyParkinsonism Relat Disord20091555856319467909PontariMAMohamedFBLebovitchSMoonatSLebedBRuggieriMRCentral nervous system findings on functional magnetic resonance imaging in patients before and after treatment with anticholinergic medicationJ Urol20101831899190520303095LuiSLiTDengWJiangLWuQTangHShort-term effects of antipsychotic treatment on cerebral function in drug-naive first-episode schizophrenia revealed by ‘resting state' functional magnetic resonance imagingArch Gen Psychiatry20106778379220679586DiersMYilmazPRanceMThiemeKGracelyRHRolkoCTreatment-related changes in brain activation in patients with fibromyalgia syndromeExp Brain Res201221861962822427134BellECWillsonMCWilmanAHDaveSSilverstone PH. Differential effects of chronic lithium and valproate on brain activation in healthy volunteersHum Psychopharmacol20052041542416106488BorsookDPendseGAiello-LammensMGlicksmanMGosticJShermanSCNS response to a thermal stressor in human volunteers and awake rats may predict clinical utility of analgesicsDrug Dev Res2007682341UpadhyayJAndersonJSchwarzAJCoimbraABaumgartnerRPendseGImaging drugs with and without clinical analgesic efficacyNeuropsychopharmacology2011362659267321849979UpadhyayJAndersonJBaumgartnerRCoimbraASchwarzAJPendseGModulation of CNS pain circuitry by intravenous and sublingual doses of buprenorphineNeuroImage2012593762377322119647DamoiseauxJSRomboutsSABarkhofFScheltensPStamCJSmithSMConsistent resting-state networks across healthy subjectsProc Natl Acad Sci USA2006103138481385316945915BoverouxPVanhaudenhuyseABrunoMANoirhommeQLauwickSLuxenABreakdown of within- and between-network resting state functional magnetic resonance imaging connectivity during propofol-induced loss of consciousnessAnesthesiology20101131038105320885292TanabeJNybergEMartinLFMartinJCordesDKronbergENicotine effects on default mode network during resting statePsychopharmacology (Berl)201121628729521331518Khalili-MahaniNZoethoutRMBeckmannCFBaerendsEde KamMLSoeterRPEffects of morphine and alcohol on functional brain connectivity during ‘resting state': a placebo-controlled crossover study in healthy young menHum Brain Mapp2012331003101821391283NewhousePAPotterASDumasJAThielCMFunctional brain imaging of nicotinic effects on higher cognitive processesBiochem Pharmacol20118294395121684262JenkinsBGPharmacologic magnetic resonance imaging (phMRI): imaging drug action in the brainNeuroimage2012621072108522495143DetreJARaoHWangDJChenYFWangZApplications of arterial spin labeled MRI in the brainJ Magn Reson Imaging2012351026103722246782YukselCMcCarthyJShinnAPfaffDLBakerJTHeckersSGray matter volume in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder with psychotic featuresSchizophr Res201213817718222445668UpadhyayJMalekiNPotterJElmanIRudraufDKnudsenJAlterations in brain structure and functional connectivity in prescription opioid-dependent patientsBrain2010133(Pt 72098211420558415LiaoYTangJMaMWuZYangMWangXFrontal white matter abnormalities following chronic ketamine use: a diffusion tensor imaging studyBrain2010133(Pt 72115212220519326HarrisRESundgrenPCPangYHsuMPetrouMKimSHDynamic levels of glutamate within the insula are associated with improvements in multiple pain domains in fibromyalgiaArthritis Rheum20085890390718311814TibbittsJCavagnaroJAHallerCAMarafinoBAndrewsPASullivanJTPractical approaches to dose selection for first-in-human clinical trials with novel biopharmaceuticalsRegul Toxicol Pharmacol20105824325120558225DresserRFirst-in-human trial participants: not a vulnerable population, but vulnerable nonethelessJ Law Med Ethics2009Spring37385019245601PotschkaHTargeting the brain--surmounting or bypassing the blood-brain barrierHandb Exp Pharmacol201019741143120217538BorsookDUpadhyayJKlimasMSchwarzACoimbraABaumgartnerRDecision-making using fMRI in clinical drug development: revisiting the NK-1 receptor antagonist for painDrug Discov Today20121796497322579743UpadhyayJAndersonJSchwarzAJCoimbraABaumgartnerRPendseGImaging drugs with and without clinical analgesic efficacyNeuropsychopharmacology2011362659267321849979McKieSRichardsonPElliottRVollmBADolanMCWilliamsSRMirtazapine antagonises the subjective, hormonal and neuronal effects of m-chlorophenylpiperazine (mCPP) infusion: a pharmacological-challenge fMRI (phMRI) studyNeuroimage20115849750721726650GearRBecerraLUpadhyayJBishopJWallinDPendseGPain facilitation brain regions activated by nalbuphine are revealed by pharmacological FMRIPLoS One20138e5016923341872BuoenCBjerrumOJThomsenMSHow first-time-in-human studies are being performed: a survey of phase I dose-escalation trials in healthy volunteers published between 1995 and 2004J Clin Pharmacol2005451123113616172177DamoiseauxJSResting-state fMRI as a biomarker for Alzheimer's diseaseAlzheimers Res Ther20124822423634PostonKLTangCCEckertTDhawanVFruchtSVonsattelJPNetwork correlates of disease severity in multiple system atrophyNeurology2012781237124422491861MusenGJacobsonAMBoloNRSimonsonDCShentonMEMcCartneyRLResting-state brain functional connectivity is altered in type 2 diabetesDiabetes2012612375237922664957FarbotaKDBendlinBBAlexanderALRowleyHADempseyRJJohnsonSCLongitudinal diffusion tensor imaging and neuropsychological correlates in traumatic brain injury patientsFront Hum Neurosci2012616022723773BrierMRThomasJBSnyderAZBenzingerTLZhangDRaichleMELoss of intranetwork and internetwork resting state functional connections with Alzheimer's disease progressionJ Neurosci2012328890889922745490BalikiMNPetreBTorbeySHerrmannKMHuangLSchnitzerTJCorticostriatal functional connectivity predicts transition to chronic back painNat Neurosci2012151117111922751038ZhouSYShuCKorth-BradleyJRaibleDPalmisanoMWadjulaJIntegrated population pharmacokinetics of etanercept in healthy subjects and in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and ankylosing spondylitisJ Clin Pharmacol20115186487520852002CutlerNRSramekJJExploratory studies: implications for drug development in Alzheimer's diseaseRev Neurol (Paris)1998154(Suppl 2S131S1369834554TargumSDPollackMHFavaMRedefining affective disorders: relevance for drug developmentCNS Neurosci Ther2008Spring142918482094HubbardCSLabusJSBuellerJStainsJSuyenobuBDukesGECorticotropin-releasing factor receptor 1 antagonist alters regional activation and effective connectivity in an emotional-arousal circuit during expectation of abdominal painJ Neurosci201131124911250021880911JensenKKieserMBlinded sample size recalculation in multicentre trials with normally distributed outcomeBiom J20105237739920394080RidenourTAHallDLBostJEA small sample randomized clinical trial methodology using N-of-1 designs and mixed model analysisAm J Drug Alcohol Abuse20093526026620180679PerlsteinIBologneseJAKrishnaRWagnerJAEvaluation of agile designs in first-in-human (FIH) trials-a simulation studyAaps J20091165366319763840NahmMLPieperCFCunninghamMMQuantifying data quality for clinical trials using electronic data capturePLoS One20083e304918725958TedeschiniEFavaMPapakostasGIPlacebo-controlled, antidepressant clinical trials cannot be shortened to less than 4 weeks' duration: a pooled analysis of randomized clinical trials employing a diagnostic odds ratio-based approachJ Clin Psychiatry2011729811821208576AdjeiAAChristianMIvyPNovel designs and end points for phase II clinical trialsClin Cancer Res2009151866187219276272YangZZuoXNWangPLiZLaConteSMBandettiniPAGeneralized RAICAR: discover homogeneous subject (sub)groups by reproducibility of their intrinsic connectivity networksNeuroImage20126340341422789741LeonACComparative effectiveness clinical trials in psychiatry: superiority, noninferiority, and the role of active comparatorsJ Clin Psychiatry2011721344134921367350FleischhackerWWCzoborPHummerMKemmlerGKohnenRVolavkaJPlacebo or active control trials of antipsychotic drugsArch Gen Psychiatry20036045846412742866Le HenanffAGiraudeauBBaronGRavaudPQuality of reporting of noninferiority and equivalence randomized trialsJAMA20062951147115116522835BorsookDBecerraLHargreavesRBiomarkers for chronic pain and analgesia. Part 1: the need, reality, challenges, and solutionsDiscov Med20111119720721447279BorsookDBecerraLHargreavesRBiomarkers for chronic pain and analgesia. Part 2: how, where, and what to look for using functional imagingDiscov Med20111120921921447280FountiPTopouzisFvan KoolwijkLTraversoCEPfeifferNViswanathanACBiobanks and the importance of detailed phenotyping: a case study-the European Glaucoma Society GlaucoGENE projectBr J Ophthalmol20099357758119244267WongDFGrunderGBrasicJRBrain imaging research: does the science serve clinical practiceInt Rev Psychiatry20071954155817896234WiedemannKBiomarkers in development of psychotropic drugsDialogues Clin Neurosci20111322523421842620HampelHPrvulovicDTeipelSJBokdeALRecent developments of functional magnetic resonance imaging research for drug development in Alzheimer's diseaseProg Neurobiol20119557057821777651MattilaJKoikkalainenJVirkkiASimonsenAvan GilsMWaldemarGA disease state fingerprint for evaluation of Alzheimer's diseaseJ Alzheimer's Dis20112716317621799247RisacherSLShenLWestJDKimSMcDonaldBCBeckettLALongitudinal MRI atrophy biomarkers: relationship to conversion in the ADNI cohortNeurobiol Aging2010311401141820620664WeinerMWVeitchDPAisenPSBeckettLACairnsNJGreenRCThe Alzheimer's disease neuroimaging initiative: a review of papers published since its inceptionAlzheimer's Demen20128(1 SupplS168MarekKJenningsDLaschSSiderowfATannerCThe Parkinson Progression Marker Initiative (PPMI)Prog Neurobiol20119562963521930184JohannsenPSalmonEHampelHXuYRichardsonSQvitzauSAssessing therapeutic efficacy in a progressive disease: a study of donepezil in Alzheimer's diseaseCNS Drugs20062031132516599649DolginEFluctuating baseline pain implicated in failure of clinical trialsNat Med2010161053KempASGrossbergGTRomanoSJArnoldDLRyanJMBullockRTrial designs likely to meet valid long-term Alzheimer's disease progression effects: learning from the past, preparing for the futureInt J Alzheimers Dis2009200994927120798873GeisserMEClauwDJStrandVGendreauRMPalmerRWilliamsDAContributions of change in clinical status parameters to Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) scores among persons with fibromyalgia treated with milnacipranPain201014937337820332060OeltjenbrunsJSchaferM[Clinical significance of the placebo effect]Anaesthesist20085744746318437321PolloABenedettiFThe placebo response: neurobiological and clinical issues of neurological relevanceProg Brain Res200917528329419660663BenedettiFCarlinoEPolloAHow placebos change the patient's brainNeuropsychopharmacology20113633935420592717DworkinRHKatzJGitlinMJPlacebo response in clinical trials of depression and its implications for research on chronic neuropathic painNeurology200565(12 Suppl 4S7S1916385107CutlerNRSramekJJMurphyMFRiordanHBiekPCartaACritical Pathways to Success in CNS Drug Development1 edn2010KempASSchoolerNRKalaliAHAlphsLAnandRAwadGWhat is causing the reduced drug-placebo difference in recent schizophrenia clinical trials and what can be done about itSchizophr Bull20103650450918723840PapakostasGIFavaMDoes the probability of receiving placebo influence clinical trial outcome? A meta-regression of double-blind, randomized clinical trials in MDDEur Neuropsychopharmacol200919344018823760SinyorMLevittAJCheungAHSchafferAKissADowlatiYDoes inclusion of a placebo arm influence response to active antidepressant treatment in randomized controlled trials? Results from pooled and meta-analysesJ Clin Psychiatry20107127027920122371HughesJGabbayMFunnellEDowrickCExploratory review of placebo characteristics reported in randomised placebo controlled antidepressant drug trialsPharmacopsychiatry201245202721979925GoodinDSFrohmanEMGarmanyGPJr.HalperJLikoskyWHLublinFDDisease modifying therapies in multiple sclerosis: report of the Therapeutics and Technology Assessment Subcommittee of the American Academy of Neurology and the MS Council for Clinical Practice GuidelinesNeurology20025816917811805241LangAEClinical trials of disease-modifying therapies for neurodegenerative diseases: the challenges and the futureNat Med2010161223122621052078CummingsJLIntegrating ADNI results into Alzheimer's disease drug development programsNeurobiol Aging2010311481149220447734WeinerMWVeitchDPAisenPSBeckettLACairnsNJGreenRCThe Alzheimer's disease neuroimaging initiative: a review of papers published since its inceptionAlzheimer's Dement20128(1 SupplS16822047634O'MuircheartaighJVollmarCBarkerGJKumariVSymmsMRThompsonPAbnormal thalamocortical structural and functional connectivity in juvenile myoclonic epilepsyBrain2012135(Pt 123635364423250883AmadACachiaAGorwoodPPinsDDelmaireCRollandBThe multimodal connectivity of the hippocampal complex in auditory and visual hallucinationsMol Psychiatry2013; PubMed PMID: 23318999, volume 24; pp 483–490.BigalMERapoportAMSheftellFDTepperSJLiptonRBTransformed migraine and medication overuse in a tertiary headache centre--clinical characteristics and treatment outcomesCephalalgia20042448349015154858BigalMELiptonRBOveruse of acute migraine medications and migraine chronificationCurr Pain Headache Rep20091330130719586594KuhlmannJAlternative strategies in drug development: clinical pharmacological aspectsInt J Clin Pharmacol Ther19993757558310599949LonningPEStrength and weakness of phase I to IV trials, with an emphasis on translational aspectsBreast Cancer Res200810(Suppl 4S2219128436TooveySMefloquine neurotoxicity: a literature reviewTravel Med Infect Dis200972619174293NevinRLMefloquine prescriptions in the presence of contraindications: prevalence among US military personnel deployed to Afghanistan, 2007Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf20101920621019998269SchwarzAJBecerraLUpadhyayJAndersonJBaumgartnerRCoimbraAA procedural framework for good imaging practice in pharmacological fMRI studies applied to drug development #1: processes and requirementsDrug Discov Today20111658359321635967SchwarzAJBecerraLUpadhyayJAndersonJBaumgartnerRCoimbraAA procedural framework for good imaging practice in pharmacological fMRI studies applied to drug development #2: protocol optimization and best practicesDrug Discov Today20111667168221477664LeskoLJAtkinsonAJJrUse of biomarkers and surrogate endpoints in drug development and regulatory decision making: criteria, validation, strategiesAnnu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol20014134736611264461LathiaCDBiomarkers and surrogate endpoints: how and when might they impact drug developmentDis Markers200218839012364814DimasiJARisks in new drug development: approval success rates for investigational drugsClin Pharmacol Ther20016929730711371997AdamsCPBrantnerVVSpending on new drug development1Health Econ20101913014119247981O'DwyerLLambertonFBokdeALEwersMFaluyiYOTannerCUsing support vector machines with multiple indices of diffusion for automated classification of mild cognitive impairmentPLoS One20127e3244122384251HallerSNguyenDRodriguezCEmchJGoldGBartschAIndividual prediction of cognitive decline in mild cognitive impairment using support vector machine-based analysis of diffusion tensor imaging dataJ Alzheimer's Dis20102231532720847435GrosenickLKlingenbergBKatovichKKnutsonBTaylorJEInterpretable whole-brain prediction analysis with GraphNetNeuroImage20137230432123298747DouaudGMenkeRAGassAMonschAURaoAWhitcherBBrain microstructure reveals early abnormalities more than two years prior to clinical progression from mild cognitive impairment to Alzheimer's diseaseJ Neurosci2013332147215523365250SeminowiczDAWidemanTHNasoLHatami-KhoroushahiZFallatahSWareMAEffective treatment of chronic low back pain in humans reverses abnormal brain anatomy and functionJ Neurosci2011317540755021593339MetzAEYauHJCentenoMVApkarianAVMartinaMMorphological and functional reorganization of rat medial prefrontal cortex in neuropathic painProc Natl Acad Sci USA20091062423242819171885RadleyJJSistiHMHaoJRocherABMcCallTHofPRChronic behavioral stress induces apical dendritic reorganization in pyramidal neurons of the medial prefrontal cortexNeuroscience20041251615051139RobinsonTEKolbBStructural plasticity associated with exposure to drugs of abuseNeuropharmacology200447(Suppl 1334615464124OliveiraJFDiasNSCorreiaMGama-PereiraFSardinhaVMLimaAChronic stress disrupts neural coherence between cortico-limbic structuresFront Neural Circuits201371023390414SchwarzAJBecerraLUpadhyayJAndersonJBaumgartnerRCoimbraAA procedural framework for good imaging practice in pharmacological fMRI studies applied to drug development #1: processes and requirementsDrug Discov Today20111658359321635967SchwarzAJBecerraLUpadhyayJAndersonJBaumgartnerRCoimbraAA procedural framework for good imaging practice in pharmacological fMRI studies applied to drug development #2: protocol optimization and best practicesDrug Discov Today20111667168221477664BorsookDNeurological diseases and painBrain2012135(Pt 232034422067541GountounaVEJobDEMcIntoshAMMoorheadTWLymerGKWhalleyHCFunctional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) reproducibility and variance components across visits and scanning sites with a finger tapping taskNeuroImage20104955256019631757ZouKHGreveDNWangMPieperSDWarfieldSKWhiteNSReproducibility of functional MR imaging: preliminary results of prospective multi-institutional study performed by Biomedical Informatics Research NetworkRadiology200523778178916304101LoubinouxICarelCAlaryFBoulanouarKViallardGManelfeCWithin-session and between-session reproducibility of cerebral sensorimotor activation: a test--retest effect evidenced with functional magnetic resonance imagingJ Cerebral Blood Flow Metab200121592607ThirionBPinelPMeriauxSRocheADehaeneSPolineJBAnalysis of a large fMRI cohort: Statistical and methodological issues for group analysesNeuroImage20073510512017239619ThirionBPinelPTucholkaARocheACiuciuPManginJFStructural analysis of fMRI data revisited: improving the sensitivity and reliability of fMRI group studiesIEEE Trans Med Imaging2007261256126917896597OlmanCAYacoubEHigh-field FMRI for human applications: an overview of spatial resolution and signal specificityOpen Neuroimaging J201157489ChenWUgurbilKHigh spatial resolution functional magnetic resonance imaging at very-high-magnetic fieldTop Magn Resonan Imaging1999106378YacoubEHarelNUgurbilKHigh-field fMRI unveils orientation columns in humansProc Natl Acad Sci USA2008105106071061218641121DoyleOMDe SimoniSSchwarzAJBrittainCO'DalyOGWilliamsSCQuantifying the attenuation of the ketamine phMRI response in humans: a validation using antipsychotic and glutamatergic agentsJ Pharmacol Exper Ther201334515116023370794De SimoniSSchwarzAJO'DalyOGMarquandAFBrittainCGonzalesCTest-retest reliability of the BOLD pharmacological MRI response to ketamine in healthy volunteersNeuroImage201364759023009959BorsookDUpadhyayJKlimasMSchwarzAJCoimbraABaumgartnerRDecision-making using fMRI in clinical drug development: revisiting NK-1 receptor antagonists for painDrug Discov Today20121796497322579743van RiemsdijkMMSturkenboomMCPepplinkhuizenLStrickerBHMefloquine increases the risk of serious psychiatric events during travel abroad: a nationwide case-control study in the NetherlandsJ Clin Psychiatry20056619920415705005TooveySMefloquine neurotoxicity: a literature reviewTravel Med Infect Dis200972619174293MurphySEMackayCEUsing MRI to measure drug action: caveats and new directionsJ Psychopharmacol2011251168117420584993BecerraLSchwartzmanRJKieferRTRohrPMoultonEAWallinDCNS measures of pain responses pre- and post-anesthetic ketamine in a patient with complex regional pain syndromePain Med2009PubMed PMID: 19254342. Epub 2009/03/04. Eng.BrooksDJPaveseNImaging biomarkers in Parkinson's diseaseProg Neurobiol20119561462821896306SperlingRPotential of functional MRI as a biomarker in early Alzheimer's diseaseNeurobiol Aging201132(Suppl 1S37S4322078171ZengLLShenHLiuLWangLLiBFangPIdentifying major depression using whole-brain functional connectivity: a multivariate pattern analysisBrain2012135(Pt 51498150722418737Figure 1Specific outcomes for magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) imaging in phase I trials. Top: Measures of CNS penetration and brain activation. Bottom: Indirect measures of central nervous system (CNS) dosing. The latter can be evaluated in two ways—either through such modeling of effective increasing doses based on concentrations evolving to Cmax. Further functional MRI (fMRI) studies using different doses can further define effective dosing as defined by activation. Such dosing has been shown to differentiate drug activity.23 PK, pharmacokinetics.Figure 2Imaging healthy subjects vs patient populations in phase I. Functional magnetic resonance imaging evaluation of drug measures using healthy subjects or patients in early phase trials (for example, (‘1a') can provide information on central nervous system (CNS) penetration and dosing). However, the equivalence in the clinical population may not be the same because of numerous factors (disease state, prior drug effects, altered effects on specific circuits and so on). As noted below, the use of healthy subjects and later comparison in patients will further define the utility of early imaging for newly approved Investigational New Drugs. The later parallel and replicated study in patients will confirm or provide data to suggest finessing dosing for later trails.Figure 3Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) measures in phase II. Top: Normalization of circuits has been observed in a few functional MRI studies, consistent with behavioral effects.130 Middle: Comparative drug effects allows for a number of observations including (1) comparison with best in class; (2) comparison with known mechanism of action type drugs. Bottom: Side-effect profiles may be subclinical or not significant in smaller cohorts but present as potential issues that can be defined in early studies.Figure 4Biomarkers and central nervous system (CNS) drug development (modified from Borsook et al.63). Imaging biomarkers for specific CNS disease are the focus of a number of research initiatives (Parkinson's disease;131 Alzheimer's disease;132 depression;133 pain63, 64). However, with the exception morphometric imaging in Alzheimer's disease, few have yet to be adopted by regulatory agencies. Nevertheless, the Food and Drug Administration's critical pathway initiative has encouraged the development and use of imaging in drug trials through their Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative program (http://www.adni-info.org). Having validated biomarkers of the disease state (imaging or other) will contribute enormously in clinical trials.Figure 5Imaging markers of disease course. Many central nervous system diseases have a progressive and/or undulating course that includes partial or complete remission. A clinical study based on subjective criteria cannot adequately (objectively) evaluate drug effect on disease load (how severe or a relative stage of progression of the disease). These are important factors as for the same dose of a drug (as shown in the lower panels) the effect on brain systems may show diminished efficacy based on disease load. Importantly, such efficacy may be enhanced over time as the drug may have effects over time.Figure 6Classification of populations based on propensity to respond to types of treatment (drug (D) or placebo (P)). In controlled trials, differentiation of D from P effects can be difficult. Part of the reason for this is that drugs do not provide high degree of efficacy that make this differentiation obvious. As noted above, reasons include three basic outcomes: outcome 1: clear differentiation of D vs P; outcome 2: unclear differentiation of D vs P; and outcome 3: unclear differentiation of lack of efficacy. Taken together, the contribution of outcome 2 in particular, because of lack of effective methods to differentiate D from P, can contribute to a false negative result of the trial.Figure 7Differentiation of drug effects vs placebo effects with imaging. An imaging readout can define a drug effect or placebo effect. More difficult is a placebo response where drug and the induced placebo response may be similar because similar pathways are involved (for example, in opioids analgesics). However, differences in responders vs non-responders based on integrating subjective and objective (imaging readouts) can help segregate true drug effects from placebo responses. Patients could be segregated into responders and non-responders according to psychometric criteria. Imaging their response to a drug challenge will further allow the determination of specific changes in brain activation and networks as compared with a placebo arm or to non-responders. It will be expected that non-responders will present a reduced drug effect as well as potential differences in brain networks responses. The inherent difference of responders vs non-responders will also be reflected as difference in brain activity patterns and networks even to a placebo challenge. One of the issues raised in this differentiation is whether drug non-responders are more resistant and thus require increased doses.Figure 8Use of imaging in drug development (adapted from Borsook et al.64). Imaging can define brain regions involved in symptomatic effects before these become subjectively apparent because of specific circuits activated and their progress to correlative changes with symptoms at a later stage. CNS, central nervous system.Figure 9Integrating imaging for central nervous system (CNS)-related clinical trials (modified from Borsook et al.64). (1) Phase Ia and imaging—Defining CNS targeting in small groups (&lt;12 subjects); from these studies information on CNS penetration (as evidenced by activation in putative target brain regions); CNS dosing (as determined by correlative measures of plasma PK and CNS effects); and CNS ‘target interactions' as determined by brain regions activated by drug (particularly useful if drug is not amenable to positron emission tomography methods) that may be positive (therapeutic) or negative (side effects). (2) Phase II and imaging—Early insights into efficacy and side effects. Specifically, knowledge of how a drug activates circuits postulated to affect disease; early objective measures of responder vs non-responder; combined with subjective measures decreases the variance and thus fewer subjects needed to adequately power the study; and imaging defined markers of potential side effects (for example, drowsiness, addiction potential, nausea and vomiting, cognitive changes and so on); (3) Phase III and Imaging—Responders vs non-responders can further be differentiated. (4) Phase IV and Imaging—Disease modification. PD, pharmacodynamics; PK, pharmacokinetics; SE, side effects.Table 1Examples of CNS acting drug trials using imaging (data collected from clinicaltrials.gov)Drug (comparators)IndicationPhaseImaging modalityClinicalTrials.gov identifier1. AdalimumabRheumatoid arthritisNIfMRINCT011971442. AlprazolamGeneral anxiety disorderIVfMRINCT006622593. Amisulpride (Olanzapine) (Haloperidol)SchizophreniaIVfMRI/DTINCT004196534. AQW051SchizophreniaIfMRINCT008255395. Aripiprazole (𝒟-Cycloserine)Autistic disorderIIIfMRINCT00198107 AripiprazoleAutistic disorderIVfMRINCT01028820 Aripiprazole (Haloperidol)SchizophreniaIphMRINCT011612776. AtomoxetineMethamphetamine abuseIfMRINCT01019707 Atomexitine (Methylphenidate)ADHDIVfMRINCT01678209 AtomoxetineADHDIVfMRINCT007162747. AZD6765 (Ketamine)Major depressionIfMRINCT010466308. Botulinum toxin ACerebral palsyI/IIfMRINCT005036209. Buproprion (Escitalopram)DepressionIVfMRI/MRSNCT01541475 BuproprionHealthyIfMRINCT0020594610. CGRPMigraineNIfMRINCT0036353211. CitrolamDepressionNIfMRI/MRSNCT01568684 CitalopramAutism spectrum disordersIfMRINCT00609531 Citalopram+mood StabBipolar depressionII/IIIfMRI/PETNCT0056286112. Cytokine**Model of depression0fMRINCT0094984513. Delta9-tetra-hydrocannabinolAddictionIfMRINCT0062870614. DesipramineIrritable bowel syndromeNIfMRINCT0088059415. DesvenlafaxineDepressionIIIfMRINCT0088886216. DiacetylmorphineStress/healthyI/IIfMRINCT0117492717. Diazepam (Lorazepam)HealthyNIfMRINCT0069603318. DonazepilAlzheimer's diseaseIVfMRINCT00477659 DonazepilAlzheimer's diseaseI/IIfMRINCT00408525 DonazepilFragile-XIfMRINCT0022058419. DuloxetineDysthymic orderIVfMRINCT00360724 DuloxetineDepressionIVfMRINCT01051466 DuloxetineDepressionIVfMRINCT00532480 DuloxetineDepressionIVfMRINCT00889369 DuloxetineInteroceptive awarenessIVfMRINCT0033701220. EszopicloneSleep/painIVfMRINCT00414037 EszopicloneDepressionNIfMRINCT0092665321. Exendin-4Alzheimer's diseaseIIfMRI/MrophNCT0125516322. FluoxetineDepressionIVfMRINCT00188942 FluoxetineDepression (children)NIfMRINCT00018057 Fluoxetine+olanzepine (olanzepine)DepressionIVfMRINCT00188942 Fluoxetine (children)DepressionNIfMRINCT00018057 Fluoxetine (children)DepressionNIfMRINCT0174072623. Glatiramer acetate (IFN-β-1a)Multiple sclerosisIVfMRINCT0039852824. GSK561679 (Lorazepam)DepressionIfMRINCT0051356525. GW679769 (Alprazolam)Social anxiety disorderIfMRINCT0033204626. GSK561679 (GW876008) (Alprazolam)Social anxiety disorderIfMRINCT0055513927. GSK598809Food addictionIfMRINCT0103945428. Guanfacine HydrochlorideADHDIVfMRINCT0170969529. GW876008Irritable bowel syndromeIfMRINCT0037689630. KetamineAttentivenessIfMRINCT01165294 KetamineDepressionIIfMRINCT0113575831. LamotrigineNeuropathic painNIfMRINCT0024315232. Leptin (Pramlintide)ObesityNIfMRINCT0069115833. LeviracetamAlzheimer'sIIfMRINCT01044758 LeviracetamMild cognitive impairmentIIfMRINCT0104475834. LevodopaAlzheimer's diseaseIVfMRINCT00306124 LevadopaTourette's syndromeNIfMRINCT0063455635. LidocaineHealthyNIfMRINCT0072550436. Lithium (Quetiapine)Bipolar maniaIVfMRINCT00609193 LithiumBipolar disorderIVfMRINCT00596622 LithiumBipolar disorderIVMorphomNCT01543724 LithiumMultiple systems atrophyIIfMRI (RSN)NCT00097672 LithiumSpinocerebellar ataxia 2IIfMRI(RSN)/MorphNCT0099863437. LidodermBack painIVfMRINCT0151554038. LisdexamfetamineBipolar depressionIVfMRINCT0105144039. LY686017 (NK1 antagonist)Alcohol cravingIIfMRINCT0031042740. Methylphenidate (children)ADHDIVfMRINCT00778310 MethylphenidateTBI memoryNIfMRINXT0045392141. MDMA (3,4-Methylene dioxymethamphetamineAddictionIfMRINCT0114834242. MilnacipranFibromyalgiaIIIfMRINCT0079352043. MK3134 (Donezapil)CognitionIfMRINCT0088760144. MorphineHealthyIVfMRINCT0124524445. N-Acetyl cysteineSchizophreniaIVfMRINCT0133985846. NefazodoneSocial anxiety disorderIVfMRINCT0023134847. NaproxenOsteoarthritis0fMRINCT0083005048. OxytocinAutismIfMRINCT0026379649. OxytocinSocial cognitionIfMRINCT0160646250. ParacetamolHealthyIfMRINCT01562704 ParacetamolPain/healthyIfMRINCT01562704 ParacetamolOsteoarthtriisIVfMRINCT0110593651. ParoxetinePTSDIVfMRINCT00700999 ParoxetineDepressionIVfRMINCT0042916952. PioglitazoneCognitionIfMRINCT0145611753. Pituitary adenylate cyclase-activating polypeptide-38 (VIP)MigraineNIfMRINCT0147199054. Pramipexole (Amisulpride)Obsessive compulsive disorderIfMRINCT0047158855. PregabalinNeuropathic painNIMRSNCT01180608 PregabalinFibromyalgiaIMRSNCT00760474 PregabalinAnxietyIVfMRINCT00706836 Pregabalin (Tramadol)Traumatic neuropathyIVfMRINCT0061015556. QuetiapineDepressionIVfMRINCT0120090157. Razadyne (Aricept)Alzheimer'sIVfMRINCT0036960358. RisperidaoneAutismIIfMRINCT01171937 RisperidoneAutism spectrum disordersIIfMRINCT0117193759. RivastigmineAlzheimer'sNIfMRINCT0062784860. RO4917523 (escitalopram) (methylphenidate)DepressionIIafMRINCT0104508361. RO5285119HealthyIphMRINCT0141896362. RPh201Vegetative stateI/IIfMRINCT0143868463. SapropterinPhenylketonuriaNIfMRI/DTINCT0073008064. Scopolamine (Donazepil)Healthy/cholinergic functionNIASLNCT0137900165. SertralinePTSDIVfMRINCT0039143066. SilbutramineObesityIfMRINCT0091421267. SYN115Parkinson's diseaseIIfMRINCT0060555368. ValproateBipolar disorderIVMorphom/MRSNCT0043152269. VareniclineAlcohol addictionI/IIfMRINCT0069550070. VyvansemTBIIIIfMRINCT01000064Abbreviations: ADHD, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder; ASL, arterial spin labeling; CGRP, Calcitonin-Gene-Related Peptide; DTI, diffusion tensor imaging; fMRI, functional magnetic resonance imaging; MRS, magnetic resonance spectroscopy; mTBI, mild traumatic brain injury; PET, positron emission tomography; PTSD, post traumatic stress disorder; RSN, resting state network; TBI, traumatic brain injury.Box 1: Imaging concepts in measures of drug effectsBold: The blood oxygenation level dependence is the main approach to measure brain activity through fMRI. Based on an interplay of local brain blood flow and volume associated with neuronal activity assesses indirectly the level of neuronal responses to stimuli, such as sensory or pharmacological inputs. Effectiveness of pharmacological treatments in patients can be evaluated across CNS disease-related function (examples: see refs.15, 16, 17, 18, 19) or differentiation of drugs20, 21 or drug dosing 22,23).Resting state networks (RSNs): One of the exciting development is the use of BOLD to measure RSNs; these are low-level spontaneous fluctuations in the BOLD signal during rest that reflect the neuronal baseline activity of the brain.24 As such, they can differentiate disease state or drug effects.25, 26, 27Connectivity measurements: Repeated BOLD measurements of brain activity have been utilized to determine brain networks associated with basal brain function as well as alteration in the disease state or drug effects.22, 28 Recently, series of basal networks in the healthy state have been identified and their modification in different diseases established. Inspection of the functional role of each of these networks permits correlate observed behavioral outcomes in diseases and the concomitant correction of these changes when disease is resolved or ameliorated.Pharmacological fMRI (phMRI): phMRI is variant of fMRI and refers to a particular approach of fMRI in which the specific brain response to a CNS-acting drug is measured.29Arterial spin labeling (ASL): Arterial spin labeling is a technique that allows the measure of perfusion without the use of external agents (such as contrast agents).30 More quantitative than BOLD but with less spatial and temporal resolution permits to capture snapshots of basal perfusion and if necessary brain activity. Quantitative pharmacological effects on brain activation can be evaluated using this approach.Morphometric measurements: Voxel base measures (VBM) and surface base methods allow the examination of changes in brain structures in volume and thickness. Such measures have shown that, in the disease state, dilation and shrinkage occur and that treatment can resolve these changes. Disease state31 and long-term effects of drugs on brain morphometry may be evaluated using this approach.32Diffusion tensor imaging (DTI): DTI is an MRI technique that measures the apparent diffusion coefficient of water molecules in tissue. Improvements in the ability to capture DTI data and analysis tools have resulted in new measurements of white matter integrity as well as determine potential tracks among different brain regions. Drugs (for example, ketamine or opioids) may produce changes in white matter tracts33 that may reflect either direct actions or effects on neuronal bodies.Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS): MRS provides measures of brain neurochemistry (for example, glutamate, gamma-amino-butyric acid and so on). Chemical measures can provide insights into drug modulation of excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmitters systems and the potential to predict responders and non-responders (see Harris et al.34).Box 2 Uses and limitations of NMR imaging
