<?xml version="1.0"?>
PLoS OnePLoS ONEplosplosonePLoS ONE1932-6203Public Library of ScienceSan Francisco, CA USA45037172617737810.1371/journal.pone.0132989PONE-D-15-03144Research ArticleSham Acupressure Controls Used in Randomized Controlled Trials: A Systematic Review and CritiqueSham Acupressure Controls Used in Randomized Controlled TrialsTanJing-Yu
1

2
SuenLorna K. P.
1
WangTao
3
MolassiotisAlexander
1
*
1
School of Nursing, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong SAR, China

2
School of Nursing, Fujian University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Fuzhou, Fujian, China

3
The Second Affiliated People’s Hospital, Fujian University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Fuzhou, Fujian, China
HuyNguyen TienEditor
Institute of Tropical Medicine (NEKKEN), Nagasaki University, JAPAN
Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: JYT LKPS AM. Performed the experiments: JYT TW. Analyzed the data: JYT AM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TW. Wrote the paper: JYT. Revised the manuscript: JYT AM LKPS WT.* E-mail: alex.molasiotis@polyu.edu.hk15720152015107e013298922120152362015© 2015 Tan et al2015Tan et alThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.ObjectivesTo explore the commonly utilized sham acupressure procedures in existing acupressure trials, and to assess whether different types of sham interventions yield different therapeutic outcomes, and, as far as possible, to identify directions for the future development of an adequate sham acupressure method.MethodsRandomized controlled trials comparing true acupressure with sham interventions were included. Thirteen electronic databases were adopted to locate relevant studies from inception to July 3, 2014. Meanwhile, eight Chinese journals on complementary and alternative medicine were manually searched to locate eligible articles. In addition, eligible studies listed in the reference lists of the included papers and other related systematic reviews on acupressure were also screened to further search any potentially eligible trials. Methodological quality of the included studies was evaluated using the risk of bias assessment tool developed by the Cochrane Back Review Group. Descriptive analysis was adopted to summarize the therapeutic outcomes.ResultsSixty-six studies with 7265 participants were included. Methodological quality of the included trials was generally satisfactory. Six types of sham acupressure approaches were identified and “non-acupoint” stimulation was the most frequently utilized sham point while an acupressure device was the most commonly used approach for administering sham treatments. Acupressure therapy was a beneficial approach in managing a variety of health problems and the therapeutic effect was found to be more effective in the true acupressure groups than that in the sham comparative groups. No clear association could be identified between different sham acupressure modalities and the reported treatment outcomes.ConclusionsA great diversity of sham acupressure controls have been used in clinical practice and research. A solid conclusion whether different sham alternatives are related to different treatment outcomes cannot be derived because of significant clinical heterogeneity among the analyzed trials. Non-acupoints are generally recommended but the definite locations should be identified with caution. For studies using single sham acupoints on hands or legs, it is suggested to apply identical acupressure devices on the same acupoint as in the active intervention without any stimulation. While for studies on pain, stimulation of sham acupoints should be avoided.These authors have no support or funding to report.Data AvailabilityAll relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.Data AvailabilityAll relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec006"><title>Methods</title><p>This study is a systematic review of the literature <bold>(<xref rid="pone.0132989.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref>)</bold>. A review protocol was created by the first author and it was approved by two experts with experience in acupressure before the commencement of the study <bold>(<xref rid="pone.0132989.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 File</xref>)</bold>.</p><sec id="sec007"><title>Data Sources and Search Strategies</title><p>Both electronic and manual searches were used to locate relevant studies. Thirteen electronic databases were accessed including PubMed, EMBase, Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (CENTRAL), CINAHL, Allied and Complementary Medicine (AMED), PsycINFO, Thomson Reuters Web of Science, Science Direct, Foreign Medical Journal Service (FMJS), China National Knowledge Infrastructure (CNKI), WanFang Data, Chinese Scientific Journal Database (CQVIP) and Chinese Biomedical Literature Database (CBM), from inception to July 3, 2014. There was no language restriction set for electronic searches. Meanwhile, eight Chinese journals on complementary and alternative medicine (issues published within the latest three years) were manually searched to possibly identify some latest publications which were still not included in the online databases. In addition, eligible studies listed in the reference lists of the included papers and other related systematic reviews on acupressure were also screened to further search any potentially eligible trials. Literature searches were performed independently by two reviewers with Chinese medicine background (JYT and TW). Mesh terms, entry terms, key words and free words such as “acupressure”, “acupress*”, “wristband*” “shiatsu” and “chih ya” were used in the searching strategies. Four selected English and Chinese search strategies are listed in <bold><xref rid="pone.0132989.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref></bold>.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria</title><p>RCTs comparing true acupressure with a sham intervention were included. Both true and sham acupressure can be manipulated through either manual intervention or acupressure devices (e.g., wristbands or attached acupressure beads, etc.). To eliminate the effect of electrical stimulation on the therapeutic outcomes of acupressure, studies on electronic acupressure devices were excluded. At the same time, studies on other modalities of acupuncture-point stimulation such as manual/electronic/laser acupuncture and moxibustion, as well as all kinds of auricular therapy were excluded. Studies published in languages other than English and Chinese were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Methodological Quality Evaluation</title><p>Methodological quality of the included studies was evaluated using the risk of bias assessment tool developed by the Cochrane Back Review Group [<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The tool can be viewed as an extension of the original criteria recommended by the Cochrane Handbook. It not only includes all the necessary items described in the latest version of the Cochrane risk of bias tool, but also provides more detailed criteria for assessing “incomplete outcome data” and “other sources of potential bias”. The tool consists of 12 items including: (1) “Was the method of randomization adequate?”; (2) “Was the treatment allocation concealed?”; (3) “Was the patient blinded to the intervention?”; (4) “Was the care provider blinded to the intervention?”; (5) “Was the outcome assessor blinded to the intervention?”; (6) “Was the drop-out rate described and acceptable?”; (7) “Were all randomized participants analyzed in the group to which they were allocated?”; (8) “Are reports of the study free of suggestion of selective outcome reporting?”; (9) “Were the groups similar at baseline regarding the most important prognostic indicators?”; (10) “Were co-interventions avoided or similar?”; (11) “Was the compliance acceptable in all groups?” and (12) “Was the timing of the outcome assessment similar in all groups?” [<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Each item can be rated as of “yes”, “no” or “unclear” where “yes” indicates a low risk of bias [<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Importantly, different from the original Cochrane risk of bias criteria, the tool used in this study can provide an overall methodological quality assessment for a single trial. The overall quality can be assessed as “low risk of bias” when at least six items are scored as “yes” and no serious methodological flaws are identified (e.g. 80% dropout rate found in one study arm) [<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In this review, only RCTs with low risk of bias were eligible for final analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Data Extraction</title><p>For each of the included studies, the following data was extracted independently by the same two reviewers: (1) study general information (first author, year of publication, full name of journal, country of origin, type of study design, and study setting); (2) participant characteristics (age, gender, sample size, dropout rate, diagnostic criteria, inclusion and exclusion criteria, and reason for acupressure); (3) true/sham acupressure protocols (practitioner, acupressure equipment, selected acupoints, treatment duration and number of sessions, and acupressure intensity and frequency, etc.); (4) main outcome(s) and results of the therapeutic effects; (5) adverse events associated with acupressure; and (6) assessment of methodological quality (12 items of the risk of bias tool plus examination of the credibility of blinding). For studies comprising more than two active treatment arms, only data from true and sham acupressure arms were extracted for analysis. Meanwhile, for studies including another control group with standard methods of care, data from the standard care arm were also extracted accordingly. Disagreement between the two reviewers was resolved by discussion or by consulting a third reviewer (AM).</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Classification of Sham Acupressure Methods</title><p>After going through all of the sham acupressure protocols of the included studies as well as reviewing the sham control classifications for body and auricular acupuncture in previous studies [<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], sham methods in this study were classified into six types which are described in <bold><xref rid="pone.0132989.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></bold>.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0132989.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0132989.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Classification of Sham Acupressure Methods.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0132989.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0132989.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Types of Sham Methods</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type 1</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham Acupressure at Non-acupoints by Manual Pressure</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type 2</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham Acupressure at Non-acupoints by Employing Acupressure Devices</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type 3</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudo-intervention at the Same Acupoints as True Treatment Arm by Manual Light-Touch</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type 4</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudo-intervention at the Same Acupoints as True Treatment Arm by using Placebo Devices</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type 5</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manual Acupressure at Non-Therapeutic (Irrelevant) Acupoints</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type 6</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham Acupressure at Non-Therapeutic (Irrelevant) Acupoints by Adopting Acupressure Devices</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>A quantitative synthesis of the main outcomes was originally proposed in the study protocol. However, a precise meta-analysis was deemed impossible due to the significant clinical heterogeneity identified in the health conditions, patient characteristics, intervention protocols and outcome measures among studies. A subgroup meta-analysis for the same health conditions within each sham acupressure type was also considered but finally abandoned for the reasons that clinical heterogeneity was still considerable within each sham modality, and the number of trials in some sham types was insufficient for data synthesis. To provide an exploratory analysis of the study outcomes, responder rate and responder rate ratio (responder rate in true acupressure group/responder rate in sham group) for each study presenting dichotomous data were calculated, and a risk ratio (RR) with 95% confidence interval (CI) was used to present the responder rate ratio. Descriptive analysis was also used to summarize the therapeutic outcomes of acupressure, for both the overall effect and the subgroup effect by each sham alternative. The overall assessment was to investigate whether true acupressure is superior to sham comparisons while the subgroup analysis was used to assess whether different types of sham methods could induce different therapeutic effects.</p><p>Results of the treatment effect for each main outcome in each individual study were extracted by two reviewers according to the following vote counts [<xref rid="pone.0132989.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]: “++”: true acupressure is significantly better than sham control for the main outcome; “+”: trend of the main outcome in favor of true acupressure but without statistical significance; “<bold>0”</bold>: no difference between true and sham acupressure; “−”:trend of the main outcome in favor of sham acupressure but without statistical significance; and “− −”: sham intervention is significantly better than true acupressure for the main outcome. For studies reporting multiple main outcomes, all such outcomes were included for analysis. For studies not indicating the main outcomes, all variables with between-group comparison were extracted accordingly.</p><p>In addition, subgroup descriptive analyses for different types of health problems, intervention duration and frequency as well as acupressure intensity were also considered when data were available. Based on the analyzed trials, length of treatment was categorized into “extremely short-term” (less than one hour), “short-term” (more than one hour but less than one day), “mid-term” (more than one day but less than one week), and “long-term” (more than one week). For studies on postoperative issue (e.g. nausea, vomiting and pain, etc.) which employed multiple assessment time points, postoperative data within the first 24 hours were abstracted for analysis. The chi-square test was used to assess the difference in dropout rates between the true and sham acupressure arms.</p></sec></sec>Implications for Future Research and PracticeVerbal and non-verbal interactions between practitioners/researchers and participants should be pre-standardized to avoid increasing participants’ expectations to the treatment which may exaggerate the non-specific psychological effects of the treatment [89, 90]. In studies utilizing an acupressure device, it is suggested that researchers and care providers are not involved in the application of acupressure equipment in order to retain satisfactory blinding. Furthermore, it would be better for future studies to recruit participants without any previous experience in acupressure. Acupressure-naive subjects do not have any experience of deqi sensation, which may increase the chance of reaching successful blinding of participants [6]. To equalize the treatment expectations among participants, if possible, participants’ characteristics such as educational background, religion, and lifestyle, etc. should be kept similar at the baseline, as these elements are considered to be potential social-psychological factors that could affect participants’ expectations to treatment [85].Selection of the sham methods should be in accordance with the study objectives and the actual requirements of the intervention and participants, as well as the nature of the disease being treated. For example, if a study intends to test the specificity of some particular acupoints, the true and sham acupressure protocols should be the same with the only difference in the selected acupoints. To minimize potential therapeutic effects of sham interventions and to maintain a satisfactory blinding design, non-acupoints located near the targeted true acupoints are generally recommended but the definite locations should be identified with caution, and an acupoint detector (a commonly utilized device for accurately locating effective body/auricular acupoints) could be considered to distinguish ineffective non-acupoints from active true acupoints. For acupressure intensity, future studies are suggested to exert only light or no stimulation to the sham acupoints to prevent the generation of the deqi sensation. Particularly, acupoint stimulation should be avoided in pain studies adopting sham acupressure. While for studies using single sham acupoints on hands or legs, it is suggested to apply identical acupressure devices on the same acupoints as in the true intervention groups without any stimulation.To facilitate the blinding of participants and/or care providers, some methods could be considered to prevent them from observing the treatment procedure, for instance, letting participants wear eye patches when administering the intervention [91], or using bandages to cover the wrist bands during surgical acupressure trials. Moreover, some studies also pointed out that the effects of acupoint stimulation can be reflected on the neural activities in the limbic system and subcortical structures which provides a possible direction for future research to use the functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) to adequately evaluate sham procedures based on the neural activities of the brain [92,93].As subjective outcomes (e.g. questionnaire and visual analogue scale, etc.) could be affected by the participants’ expectations to treatment, which subsequently exaggerates therapeutic effects, future studies could consider including some objective measures. Some scholars point out that instead of using the word of “sham” or “placebo”, informing participants that the aim of study is to compare two different treatment procedures would be more credible to reach a successful blinding of study subjects [2, 94]. This kind of incomplete informed consent may be in debate for ethical reasons [2]. However, according to the results of a nested qualitative study within a RCT using acupressure (both true and sham) for controlling chemotherapy-induced nausea, it was acceptable for the study participants to receive this kind of consent process [94]. Meanwhile, from the findings of this review as well as other studies on sham acupoint stimulation [92, 95], sham interventions can also contribute to symptom improvement, and thus, it seems plausible to view the sham acupressure as a non-specific treatment approach in nature. Finally, the methodological quality of future trial needs to be improved. More detailed information on the theoretical background of the selection and identification of true and sham acupoints should be provided. Treatment duration, number of sessions, and acupressure intensity should be described in detail in the acupressure protocols. Even if it is difficult to incorporate blinding of the practitioner in manual acupressure trials, a double-blind design for both participants and outcome assessors is still possible. Credibility of blinding should also be tested to investigate the successfulness of blinding design and subsequent to identify the potential risk of performance and/or detection biases. Related guidelines such as the CONSORT [96] and STRICTA [97] guidelines should be followed in the development and reporting of acupressure trials.References1
McGovernDPB. Randomized controlled trials In: McGovernDPB, ValoriRM, SummerskillWSM, eds. Key topics in evidence based medicine. Oxford: BIOS Scientific Publishers, 2001:pp. 26–29.2
DincerF, LindeK. Sham interventions in randomized clinical trials of acupuncture-a review. Complement Ther Med, 2003, 11(4), 235–242.
150226563
ShapiroAK, MorrisLA. The placebo effect in medical and psychological therapies In: GarfieldSL, BerginAE, editors. Handbook of psychotherapy and behavior change. New York: Wiley; 1978: p. 371.4
LundI, NäslundJ, LundebergT. Minimal acupuncture is not a valid placebo control in randomised controlled trials of acupuncture: a physiologist’s perspective. Chin Med, 2009, 4(1), 1.191834545
VickersAJ, CroninAM, MaschinoAC, LewithG, MacPhersonH, FosterNE
et al
Acupuncture for chronic pain: individual patient data meta-analysis. Arch Intern Med, 2012, 172(19), 1444–1453. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2012.3654
229651866
ZhangHW, TangJL. Development and selection of sham approaches in clinical trials of acupuncture. Zhongguo Zhong Xi Yi Jie He Za Zhi, 2003, 23(4), 247–250.
127649027
ItohK, KatsumiY, HirotaS, KitakojiH. Effects of trigger point acupuncture on chronic low back pain in elderly patients—a sham-controlled randomised trial. Acupunct Med, 2006, 24(1), 5–12.
166180438
SunY, GanTJ. Acupuncture for the management of chronic headache: a systematic review. Anesth Analg, 2008, 107(6), 2038–2047. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e318187c76a
190201569
MolsbergerAF, SchneiderT, GotthardtH, DrabikA. German Randomized Acupuncture Trial for chronic shoulder pain (GRASP)—a pragmatic, controlled, patient-blinded, multi-centre trial in an outpatient care environment. Pain, 2010, 151(1), 146–154. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2010.06.036
2065566010
LindeK, StrengA, JürgensS, HoppeA, BrinkhausB, WittC, et al
Acupuncture for patients with migraine: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA, 2005, 293(17), 2118–2125.
1587041511
ErnstE. Acupuncture as a symptomatic treatment of osteoarthritis. Scand J Rheumatol, 1997, 26(6), 444–447.
943340512
ScharfHP, MansmannU, StreitbergerK, WitteS, KrämerJ, MaierC, et al
Acupuncture and Knee Osteoarthritis: A Three-Armed Randomized Trial. Ann Intern Med, 2006, 145(1), 12–20.
1681892413
FurlanAD, PennickV, BombardierC, van TulderM. 2009 updated method guidelines for systematic reviews in the Cochrane Back Review Group. Spine, 2009, 34(18), 1929–1941. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e3181b1c99f
1968010114
ZhangCS, YangAW, ZhangAL, MayBH, XueCC. Sham control methods used in ear-acupuncture/ear-acupressure randomized controlled trials: a systematic review. J Altern Complement Med, 2014, 20(3), 147–161. doi: 10.1089/acm.2013.0238
2413833315
ZhangH, BianZ, LinZ. Are acupoints specific for diseases? A systematic review of the randomized controlled trials with sham acupuncture controls. Chin Med, 2010, 5(1). doi: 10.1186/1749-8546-5-1
2014573316
TangWR, ChenWJ, YuCT, ChangYC, ChenCM, WangCH, et al
Effects of acupressure on fatigue of lung cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy: An experimental pilot study. Complement Ther Med, 2014, 22(4), 581–591. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2014.05.006
2514605917
AtrianMK, AbbaszadehF, SarviehM, SarafrazN, JafarabadiMA. Investigating the effect of pressure on third liver point on primary dysmenorrhea: a randomized controlled clinical trial. Iran Red Crescent Med J, 2013, 15(9), 848–853. doi: 10.5812/ircmj.12719
2461679818
Sehhatie-ShafaieF, AmaniF, HeshmatR. The effect of acupressure on Sanyinjiao and Hugo points on labor pain in nulliparous women: a randomized clinical trial. J Caring Sci, 2013, 2(2), 123–129. doi: 10.5681/jcs.2013.015
2527671819
ChaoHL, MiaoSJ, LiuPF, LeeHHC, ChenYM, YaoCT, et al
The beneficial effect of ST-36 (Zusanli) acupressure on postoperative gastrointestinal function in patients with colorectal cancer. Oncol Nurs Forum, 2013, 40(2), E61–E68. doi: 10.1188/13.ONF.E61-E68
2344874620
McFaddenKL, HealyKM, HoverstenKP, ItoTA, HernándezTD. Efficacy of acupressure for non-pharmacological stress reduction in college students. Complement Ther Med, 2012, 20(4), 175–182. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2011.12.003
2257942821
ValieeS, BassampourSS, NasrabadiAN, PouresmaeilZ, MehranA. Effect of acupressure on preoperative anxiety: a clinical trial. J Perianesth Nurs, 2012, 27(4), 259–266. doi: 10.1016/j.jopan.2012.05.003
2282802222
RadMN, LamyianM, HeshmatR, JaafarabadiMA, YazdaniS. A randomized clinical trial of the efficacy of KID21 point (Youmen) acupressure on nausea and vomiting of pregnancy. Iran Red Crescent Med J, 2012, 14(11), 697–701. doi: 10.5812/ircmj.2153
2339706423
ChangKKP, WongTKS, WongTHK, ChungJWY. LeungAWN. Effect of acupressure in treating urodynamic stress incontinence: A randomized controlled trial. Am J Chin Med, 2011, 39(6), 1139–1159.
2208398724
McFaddenKL, HealyKM, DettmannML, KayeJT, ItoTA, HernándezTD. Acupressure as a non-pharmacological intervention for traumatic brain injury (TBI). J Neurotrauma, 2011, 28(1), 21–34. doi: 10.1089/neu.2010.1515
2097946025
KashefiF, KhajeheiM, AshrafAR, JafariP. The efficacy of acupressure at the Sanyinjiao point in the improvement of women's general health. J Altern Complement Med, 2011, 17(12), 1141–1147. doi: 10.1089/acm.2010.0589
2208243226
RezaH, KianN, PouresmailZ, MasoodK, SadatSeyed Bagher M, CheraghiMA. The effect of acupressure on quality of sleep in Iranian elderly nursing home residents. Complement Ther Clin Pract, 2010, 16(2), 81–85. doi: 10.1016/j.ctcp.2009.07.003
2034783827
McFaddenKL, HernándezTD. Cardiovascular benefits of acupressure (Jin Shin) following stroke. Complement Ther Med, 2010, 18(1), 42–48. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2010.01.001
2017887728
MaaSH, TsouTS, WangKY, WangCH, LinHC, HuangYH. Self-administered acupressure reduces the symptoms that limit daily activities in bronchiectasis patients: pilot study findings. J Clin Nurs, 2007, 16(4), 794–804.
1740296229
ShinHS, SongYA, SeoS. Effect of Nei-Guan point (P6) acupressure on ketonuria levels, nausea and vomiting in women with hyperemesis gravidarum. J Adv Nurs, 2007, 59(5), 510–519.
1764549430
BertalanffyP, HoeraufK, FleischhacklR, StrasserH, WickeF, GreherM. Korean hand acupressure for motion sickness in prehospital trauma care: a prospective, randomized, double-blinded trial in a geriatric population. Anesth Analg, 2004, 98(1), 220–223.
1469362331
ChenLL, HsuSF, WangMH, ChenCL, LinYD, LaiJS. Use of acupressure to improve gastrointestinal motility in women after trans-abdominal hysterectomy. Am J Chin Med, 2003, 31(5), 781–790.
1469668132
TsaySL, ChenML. Acupressure and quality of sleep in patients with end-stage renal disease—a randomized controlled trial. Int J Nurs Stud, 2003, 40(1), 1–7.
1255014533
KoberA, ScheckT, GreherM, LiebaF, FleischhacklR, FleischhacklS, et al
Prehospital analgesia with acupressure in victims of minor trauma: a prospective, randomized, double-blinded trial. Anesth Analg, 2002, 95(3), 723–727.
1219806034
BelluominiJ, LittRC, LeeKA, KatzM. Acupressure for nausea and vomiting of pregnancy: a randomized, blinded study. Obstet Gynecol, 1994, 84(2), 245–248.
804153935
Adib-HajbagheryM, EtriM. Effect of acupressure of Ex-Le7 point on pain, nausea and vomiting after appendectomy: A randomized trial. J Res Med Sci, 2013, 18(6), 482–486.
2425069636
AlessandriniM, NapolitanoB, MicarelliA, De PadovaA, BrunoE. P6 acupressure effectiveness on acute vertiginous patients: a double blind randomized study. J Altern Complement Med, 2012, 18(12), 1121–1126. doi: 10.1089/acm.2011.0384
2295082937
SoltaniARE, MohammadinasabH, GoudarziM, ArbabiS, MohammadinasabA, MohammadinasabF, et al
Comparing the efficacy of prophylactic p6 acupressure, ondansetron, metoclopramide and placebo in the prevention of vomiting and nausea after strabismus surgery. Acta Med Iran, 2011, 49(4), 208–212.
2171372938
BaoT, YeX, SkinnerJ, CaoB, FisherJ, NesbitS, et al
The analgesic effect of magnetic acupressure in cancer patients undergoing bone marrow aspiration and biopsy: a randomized, blinded, controlled trial. J Pain Symptom Manage, 41(6), 995–1002. doi: 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2010.08.012
39
MajholmB, MøllerAM. Acupressure at acupoint P6 for prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting: a randomised clinical trial. Eur J Anaesthesiol, 2011, 28(6), 412–419. doi: 10.1097/EJA.0b013e32833f6f42
2154402040
SinhaA, PaechMJ, ThewME, RhodesM, LuscombeK, NathanE. A randomised, double-blinded, placebo-controlled study of acupressure wristbands for the prevention of nausea and vomiting during labour and delivery. Int J Obstet Anesth, 2011, 20(2), 110–117. doi: 10.1016/j.ijoa.2010.10.005
2119492141
WangSM, EscaleraS, LinEC, MaranetsI, KainZN. Extra-1 acupressure for children undergoing anesthesia. Anesth Analg, 2008, 107(3), 811–816. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e3181804441
1871388942
TurgutS, OzalpG, DikmenS, SavliS, TuncelG, KadiogullariN. Acupressure for postoperative nausea and vomiting in gynaecological patients receiving patient-controlled analgesia. Eur J Anaesthesiol, 2007, 24(1), 87–91.
1689561843
HeazellA, ThorneycroftJ, WaltonV, EtheringtonI. Acupressure for the in-patient treatment of nausea and vomiting in early pregnancy: a randomized control trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol, 2006, 194(3), 815–820.
1652241844
WangSM, GaalD, MaranetsI, Caldwell-AndrewsA, KainZN. Acupressure and preoperative parental anxiety: a pilot study. Anesth Analg, 2005, 101(3), 666–669.
1611597245
AlkaissiA, LedinT, OdkvistLM, KalmanS. P6 acupressure increases tolerance to nauseogenic motion stimulation in women at high risk for PONV. Can J Anaesth, 2005, 52(7), 703–709.
1610338246
SamadK, AfshanG, KamalR. Effect of acupressure on postoperative nausea and vomiting in laparoscopic cholecystectomy. J Pak Med Assoc, 2003, 53(2), 68–71.
1270548847
AlkaissiA, EvertssonK, JohnssonVA, OfenbartlL, KalmanS. P6 acupressure may relieve nausea and vomiting after gynecological surgery: an effectiveness study in 410 women. Can J Anaesth, 2002, 49(10), 1034–1039.
1247767348
AgarwalA, PathakA, GaurA. Acupressure wristbands do not prevent postoperative nausea and vomiting after urological endoscopic surgery. Can J Anaesth, 2000, 47(4), 319–324.
1076417549
HarmonD, RyanM, KellyA, BowenM. Acupressure and prevention of nausea and vomiting during and after spinal anaesthesia for caesarean section. Br J Anaesth, 2000, 84(4), 463–467.
1082309750
HarmonD, GardinerJ, HarrisonR, KellyA. Acupressure and the prevention of nausea and vomiting after laparoscopy. Br J Anaesth, 1999, 82(3), 387–390.
1043482151
AlkaissiA, StålnertM, KalmanS. Effect and placebo effect of acupressure (P6) on nausea and vomiting after outpatient gynaecological surgery. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand, 1999, 43(3), 270–274.
1008153252
FanCF, TanhuiE, JoshiS, TrivediS, HongY, ShevdeK. Acupressure treatment for prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting. Anesth Analg, 1997, 84(4), 821–825.
908596553
O'BrienB, RelyeaMJ, TaerumT. Efficacy of P6 acupressure in the treatment of nausea and vomiting during pregnancy. Am J Obstet Gynecol, 1996, 174(2), 708–715.
862381154
FelhendlerD, LisanderB. Pressure on acupoints decreases postoperative pain. Clin J Pain, 1996, 12(4), 326–329.
896987855
BayreutherJ, PickeringR, LewithGT. A double-blind cross-over study to evaluate the effectiveness of acupressure at pericardium 6 (P6) in the treatment of early morning sickness (EMS). Complement Ther Med, 1994, 2(2), 70–76.56
HamidzadehA, ShahpourianF, OrakRJ, MontazeriAS, KhosraviA. Effects of LI4 acupressure on labor pain in the first stage of labor. J Midwifery Womens Health, 2012, 57(2), 133–138. doi: 10.1111/j.1542-2011.2011.00138.x
2243248457
Mirbagher-AjorpazN, Adib-HajbagheryM, MosaebiF. The effects of acupressure on primary dysmenorrhea: a randomized controlled trial. Complement Ther Clin Pract, 2011, 17(1), 33–36. doi: 10.1016/j.ctcp.2010.06.005
2116811258
SunJL, SungMS, HuangMY, ChengGC, LinCC. Effectiveness of acupressure for residents of long-term care facilities with insomnia: a randomized controlled trial. Int J Nurs Stud, 2010, 47(7), 798–805. doi: 10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2009.12.003
2005622159
KashanianM, ShahaliS. Effects of acupressure at the Sanyinjiao point (SP6) on the process of active phase of labor in nulliparas women. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med, 2010, 23(7), 638–641.60
HjelmstedtA, ShenoyST, Stener-VictorinE, LekanderM, BhatM, BalakumaranL, et al
Acupressure to reduce labor pain: a randomized controlled trial. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand, 2010, 89(11), 1453–1459. doi: 10.3109/00016349.2010.514323
2082247461
HsuW, HsuHY, SunJL. Effects of shenmen acupressure on improving the condition of institutional residents with insomnia. J Evid Based Nurs, 2006, 2(4), 331–338.62
LeeMK, ChangSB, KangDH. Effects of SP6 acupressure on labor pain and length of delivery time in women during labor. J Altern Complement Med, 2004, 10(6), 959–965.
1567398963
NilssonI, KarlssonA, LindgrenL, BergenheimT, KoskinenLO, NilssonU. The efficacy of P6 acupressure with sea-band in reducing postoperative nausea and vomiting in patients undergoing craniotomy: a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled Study. J Neurosurg Anesthesiol, 2015, 27(1), 42–50. doi: 10.1097/ANA.0000000000000089
2497806264
MolassiotisA, RussellW, HughesJ, BreckonsM, LloydWilliams M, RichardsonJ, et al
The effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of acupressure for the control and management of chemotherapy-related acute and delayed nausea: assessment of Nausea in Chemotherapy Research (ANCHoR), a randomised controlled trial. Health Technol Assess, 2013, 17, 26.65
NorooziniaH, MahooriA, HasaniE, Gerami-FahimM, SepehrvandN. The effect of acupressure on nausea and vomiting after cesarean section under spinal anesthesia. Acta Med Iran, 2013, 51(3), 163–167.
2360560066
SoltanzadehM, BehaeenK, PourmehdiZ, SafarimohsenabadiA. Effects of acupressure on nausea and vomiting after gynecological laparoscopy surgery for infertility investigations. Life Sci J, 2012, 9(3), 871–875.67
WhitePF, ZhaoM, TangJ, WenderRH, YumulR, SloninskyAV, et al
Use of a disposable acupressure device as part of a multimodal antiemetic strategy for reducing postoperative nausea and vomiting. Anesth Analg, 2012, 115(1), 31–37. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3182536f27
2250421468
HoCM, TsaiHJ, ChanKH, TsaiSK. P6 acupressure does not prevent emesis during spinal anesthesia for cesarean delivery. Anesth Analg, 2006, 102(3), 900–903.
1649284869
KleinAA, DjaianiG, KarskiJ, CarrollJ, KarkoutiK, McCluskeyS, et al
Acupressure wristbands for the prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting in adults undergoing cardiac surgery. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth, 2004, 18(1), 68–71.
1497380370
SchultzAA, AndrewsAL, GoranSF, MathewT, SturdevantN. Comparison of acupressure bands and droperidol for reducing post-operative nausea and vomiting in gynecologic surgery patients. Appl Nurs Res, 2003, 16(4), 256–265.
1460855971
DentHE, DewhurstNG, MillsSY, WilloughbyM. Continuous PC6 wristband acupressure for relief of nausea and vomiting associated with acute myocardial infarction: a partially randomised, placebo-controlled trial. Complement Ther Med, 2003, 11(2), 72–77.
1280149172
NorheimAJ, PedersenEJ, FønnebøV, BergeL. Acupressure treatment of morning sickness in pregnancy. A randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Scand J Prim Health Care, 2001, 19(1), 43–47.
1130354773
SteeleNM, FrenchJ, Gatherer-BoylesJ, NewmanS, LeclaireS. Effect of acupressure by sea-bands on nausea and vomiting of pregnancy. J Obstet Gynecol Neonatal Nurs, 2001, 30(1), 61–70.
1127716374Woods RM. Pericardium-6 acupressure for the prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting. Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, 1999.75
DuggalKN, DouglasMJ, PeteruEA, MerrickPM. Acupressure for intrathecal narcotic-induced nausea and vomiting after caesarean section. Int J Obstet Anesth, 1998, 7(4), 231–236.
1532118576
LewisIH, PrynSJ, ReynoldsPI, PanditUA, WiltonNCT. Effect of P6 acupressure on postoperative vomiting in children undergoing outpatient strabismus correction. Br J Anaesth, 1991, 67(1), 73–78.
185976477
SuhEE. The effects of P6 acupressure and nurse-provided counseling on chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in patients with breast cancer. Oncol Nurs Forum, 39(1), E1–E9. doi: 10.1188/12.ONF.E1-E9
2220166378
LangT, HagerH, FunovitsV, BarkerR, SteinlechnerB, HoeraufK, et al
Prehospital analgesia with acupressure at the Baihui and Hegu points in patients with radial fractures: a prospective, randomized, double-blind trial. Am J Emerg Med, 2007, 25(8), 887–893.
1792097279
WuHS, LinLC, WuSC, LinJG. The psychologic consequences of chronic dyspnea in chronic pulmonary obstruction disease: the effects of acupressure on depression. J Altern Complement Med, 2007, 13(2), 253–261.
1738876980
WuHS, WuSC, LinJG, LinLC. Effectiveness of acupressure in improving dyspnoea in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. J Adv Nurs, 2004, 45(3), 252–259.
1472024281
NordioM, RomanelliF. Efficacy of wrists overnight compression (HT 7 point) on insomniacs: possible role of melatonin?
Minerva Medica, 2008, 99(6), 539–547.
1903425382Lundeberg T, Lund I, Sing A, Näslund J. Is placebo acupuncture what it is intended to be?. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med, 2011. Article ID 932407. doi: 10.1093/ecam/nep049
83
LindeK, NiemannK, MeissnerK. Are sham acupuncture interventions more effective than (other) placebos? A re-analysis of data from the Cochrane review on placebo effects. Forsch Komplementarmed, 2010, 17(5), 259–264.84Hróbjartsson A, Gøtzsche PC. Placebo interventions for all clinical conditions. Cochrane Database Syst Rev, 2010, CD003974. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD003974.pub3
85
PanLJ, ChenB, ZhaoX, GuoY. Thinking on designation of sham acupuncture in clinical research. Zhongguo Zhen Jiu, 2014, 34(1), 83–86.
2467306986
OlaussonH, LamarreY, BacklundH, MorinC, WallinBG, StarckG, et al
Unmyelinated tactile afferents signal touch and project to insular cortex. Nat Neurosci,
2002, 5(9), 900–904.1214563687
LundebergT, LundI. Are reviews based on sham acupuncture procedures in fibromyalgia syndrome (FMS) valid?
Acupunct Med, 2007, 25(3), 100–106.
1790660588
WoodL, EggerM, GluudLL, SchulzKF, JüniP, AltmanDG, et al
Empirical evidence of bias in treatment effect estimates in controlled trials with different interventions and outcomes: meta-epidemiological study. BMJ, 2008, 336(7644), 601–605. doi: 10.1136/bmj.39465.451748.AD
1831634089
AzadA, JohnT. Do randomized acupuncture studies in patients with cancer need a sham acupuncture control arm?
J Clin Oncol, 2013, 31(16), 2057–2058. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2012.47.8750
2361010990
KelleyJM, LemboAJ, AblonJS, VillanuevaJJ, ConboyLA, LevyR, et al
Patient and practitioner influences on the placebo effect in irritable bowel syndrome. Psychosom Med, 2009, 71(7), 789–797. doi: 10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181acee12
1966119591
KondziolkaD, LemleyT, KestleJR, LunsfordLD, FrommGH, JannettaPJ. The effect of single-application topical ophthalmic anesthesia in patients with trigeminal neuralgia: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial. J Neurosurg, 1994, 80(6), 993–997.
818928092
LundebergT, LundI, NäslundJ, ThomasM. The Emperors sham-wrong assumption that sham needling is sham. Acupunct Med, 2008, 26(4), 239–242.
1909869693
HuiKK, LiuJ, MakrisN, GollubRL, ChenAJ, I MooreC, et al
Acupuncture modulates the limbic system and subcortical gray structures of the human brain: evidence from fMRI studies in normal subjects. Hum Brain Mapp, 2000, 9(1), 13–25.
1064372694
HughesJG, RussellW, BreckonsM., RichardsonJ, Lloyd-WilliamsM, MolassiotisA. (2014). “I assumed that one was a placebo”: Exploring the consent process in a sham controlled acupressure trial. Complement Ther Med, 22(5), 903–908. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2014.07.005
2544038295
HughesJG, RussellW, BreckonsM, RichardsonJ, Lloyd-WilliamsM, MolassiotisA. “Until the trial is complete you can’t really say whether it helped you or not, can you?”: exploring cancer patients’ perceptions of taking part in a trial of acupressure wristbands. BMC Complement Altern Med, 2013, 13(1), 1–10.2328036196
MoherD, SchulzKF, AltmanDG. The CONSORT statement: revised recommendations for improving the quality of reports of parallel group randomized trials. BMC Med Res Methodol, 2001, 1(1), 2.1133666397
MacPhersonH, AltmanDG, HammerschlagR, YoupingL, TaixiangW, et al
Revised STandards for Reporting Interventions in Clinical Trials of Acupuncture (STRICTA): Extending the CONSORT Statement. PLoS Med, 2010, 7(6): e1000261
doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000261
20543992
