<?xml version="1.0"?>
CephalalgiaCephalalgiaCEPspcepCephalalgia0333-10241468-2982SAGE PublicationsSage UK: London, England556048110.1177/033310241665611810.1177_0333102416656118Original ArticlesCerebral metabolism before and after external trigeminal nerve stimulation in episodic migraineMagisDelphineD’OstilioKevinThibautAuroreDe PasquaVictorGerardPascaleHustinxRolandLaureysStevenSchoenenJeanUniversity of Liège, Liège, BelgiumDelphine Magis, University of Liège, Headache Research Unit, Department of Neurology, CHR Citadelle, Boulevard du 12ème de Ligne 1, Liège, 4000 Belgium. Email: dmagis@chu.ulg.ac.be2362016820173798818911011201527520163052016© International Headache Society 20162016International Headache SocietyThis article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 License (http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage).Background and aimA recent sham-controlled trial showed that external trigeminal nerve stimulation (eTNS) is effective in episodic migraine (MO) prevention. However, its mechanism of action remains unknown. We performed 18-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) to evaluate brain metabolic changes before and after eTNS in episodic migraineurs.MethodsTwenty-eight individuals were recruited: 14 with MO and 20 healthy volunteers (HVs). HVs underwent a single FDG-PET, whereas patients were scanned at baseline, directly after a first prolonged session of eTNS (Cefaly®) and after three months of treatment (uncontrolled study).ResultsThe frequency of migraine attacks significantly decreased in compliant patients (N = 10). Baseline FDG-PET revealed a significant hypometabolism in fronto-temporal areas, especially in the orbitofrontal (OFC) and rostral anterior cingulate cortices (rACC) in MO patients. This hypometabolism was reduced after three months of eTNS treatment.ConclusionOur study shows that metabolic activity of OFC and rACC, which are pivotal areas in central pain and behaviour control, is decreased in migraine. This hypometabolism is reduced after three months of eTNS. eTNS might thus exert its beneficial effects via slow neuromodulation of central pain-controlling areas, a mechanism also previously reported in chronic migraine and cluster headache after percutaneous occipital nerve stimulation. However, this finding needs to be confirmed by further studies using a sham condition.Migraineorbitofrontal cortextreatmentexternal trigeminal nerve stimulationimagingbrain metabolism<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="sec2-0333102416656118"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec3-0333102416656118"><title>Population</title><p>Twenty-eight individuals participated in the study: 14 patients with episodic migraine without aura (MO, International Classification of Headache Disorders, third edition beta (ICHD3 beta) criteria (<xref rid="bibr1-0333102416656118" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)) having between four and 14 days of migraine/month (three males, 11 females, mean age: 39 ± 14 years) and 20 HVs of similar sex and age distribution (five males, 15 females, mean age: 36 ± 11 years). Patients were recruited by headache-specialised neurologists (DM and JS) and came from the outpatient clinic of the University Department of Neurology, CHR Liège, Belgium. HVs were recruited through an announcement on the university and hospital websites. They were interviewed face to face before the recordings and filled in the extended French version of the ID-Migraine questionnaire (<xref rid="bibr11-0333102416656118" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) to rule out any current or past history of recurrent headaches. They were excluded if they had a family history of headaches, chronic pain, psychiatric or current systemic disorders and if they were taking medications regularly. MO patients had no other headache disorder, no psychiatric or somatic disorder, nor regular drug treatment except for the contraceptive pill. They were not allowed to have prophylactic treatment since at least two months before inclusion or to use opioid derivatives as acute therapy, but were allowed to take painkillers and/or triptans for migraine attacks. Moreover, none of the participants underwent PET imaging and/or used eTNS before.</p><p>We conducted the study in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, version 2013. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants and the local Ethics Committee approved the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-0333102416656118" sec-type="methods"><title>Procedure</title><sec id="sec5-0333102416656118"><title>18-FDG-PET</title><p>The PET acquisitions were made in the Nuclear Medicine Department of the CHU Sart-Tilman, Liège, Belgium using a Gemini TF PET/computed tomography (CT) scanner (Philips®, Eindhoven, The Netherlands). Resting cerebral metabolism was studied 30 minutes after intravenous injection of 150 MBq FDG. Blood glucose level was measured and was lower than 150 mg/dl in all individuals. Participants were injected and scanned in a dark room with minimal environmental noise. Images were reconstructed using an iterative list mode time-of-flight algorithm. Corrections for attenuation, dead-time, random and scatter events were applied.</p><p>HVs had only one PET scan (PET1), whereas MO underwent three PET scans: at baseline (before any stimulation, PET1), immediately after a session of eTNS (PET2), and after three months of daily eTNS therapy (PET3, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0333102416656118">Figure 1</xref> flowchart). PET2 could not be performed the same day as PET1 for technical and safety reasons. Just before PET2 acquisition, MO patients received in the Nuclear Medicine Department a first prolonged eTNS session that lasted one hour and started immediately after the 18-FDG isotope injection, during the incubation period of 18-FDG, using a pre-programmed Cefaly® device placed by the same investigator (VDP) in order to ensure an adequate stimulation. The PET2 acquisition was performed immediately after the end of the first eTNS session. The one-hour duration of this session was set after a discussion with the nuclear medicine specialist. We hypothesised that this duration would be potent enough to induce brain metabolic changes detectable by the FDG-PET scan technique. Finally, PET3 was conducted at the end of the 12-week eTNS prophylactic therapy.
<fig id="fig1-0333102416656118" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Study design.</p><p>PET: positron emission tomography; eTNS: external Trigeminal Nerve Stimulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0333102416656118-fig1"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6-0333102416656118"><title>External trigeminal nerve stimulation (eTNS)</title><p>eTNS was delivered using the portable Cefaly® device (Cefaly Technology®, Grâce-Hollogne, Belgium). Patients were stimulated for the first time in the hospital before PET2 (see above) and thus trained to use the device properly. Subsequently, they received a Cefaly® device and were asked to apply eTNS at home daily for 20 minutes for three months as preventive treatment (its use as acute therapy was not recommended). Neurostimulation was administered with a 30 mm × 94 mm self-adhesive electrode placed on the forehead and covering the supratrochlear and supraorbital nerves bilaterally (first trigeminal division). The Cefaly® device provided to patients had a single stimulation program (contrary to the commercially available Cefaly® device, which has three programs with different stimulation parameters). It generated biphasic rectangular impulses with an electrical mean equal to zero and the following characteristics: pulse width 250 µs, frequency 60 Hz, and maximal intensity 16 mA. Built-in electronic software allowed recording time of use per patient and hence verifying compliance at the end of the study.</p><p>Eligible patients were asked to fill in headache diaries for four successive months: one month of baseline and three months with eTNS treatment. They recorded headache occurrence, intensity (on a three-point scale: 1-mild to 3-severe), presence of nausea/vomiting, phonophobia and/or photophobia and intake of acute migraine drugs (analgesics, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), triptans).</p></sec><sec id="sec7-0333102416656118"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Clinical data provided by the migraine diaries were analysed using non-parametric tests (Wilcoxon paired test or Friedman analysis of variance (ANOVA), Statistica® version 8.0, StatSoft, France).</p><p>PET acquisitions were analysed using Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM8, Wellcome Trust Centre for Neuroimaging, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm">http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm</ext-link>) implemented in MATLAB 7.4.0 (MathWorks Inc, Sherborn, MA, USA). Images were spatially normalised into a standard stereotactic space using an MNI PET template (Montreal Neurological Institute) and smoothed using an 8 mm full-width-half-maximum (FWHM) isotropic kernel. We performed global normalisation by applying proportional scaling. Significance level of resulting SPM maps was set at a <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 uncorrected, with an extended threshold of 20 voxels or a <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 using a family-wise error (FWE) correction for multiple comparisons at a cluster level. The FDG-PET analyses were performed by two investigators blinded to diagnosis (KD and AT).</p><p>The first analysis identified brain regions that were significantly hypo- or hypermetabolic in MO (<italic>n</italic> = 11) at baseline compared to HVs (<italic>n</italic> = 20) using a two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test. Three MO patients had been removed from this analysis because they had a migraine attack the day of PET acquisition, while the remaining 11 patients were pain free for at least 48 hours. Age and gender were entered as confounding covariates in the design matrix. We subsequently repeated the analysis by excluding two patients who had a history of acute medication-overuse headache (MOH) up to six months before PET1. Thus, the latter analysis was performed in patients who were interictal and free from acute medication overuse.</p><p>We then performed <italic>t</italic>-tests to compare brain metabolism in MO before and after three months of treatment, as compared to HVs. For this analysis, we included only patients who used eTNS at least one-third of the recommended time (i.e. 10 patients). We chose the 30% compliance threshold on an empirical basis, having experienced from clinical practice and previous trials (<xref rid="bibr4-0333102416656118" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-0333102416656118" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) that patients may report a therapeutic benefit with non-daily use of the device. As before, we excluded from the analysis three patients who were in an ictal phase the day of the PET, which left seven analysed MO patients.</p><p>Additionally, we performed a parametric analysis to model the neuromodulatory effect of eTNS. The contrast modelling the effect of each variable within the design matrix was set according to the expected modulation of brain metabolism (i.e. PET1 patients: –2; PET2 patients: –1; PET3 patients: +1; PET1 controls: +2).</p><p>Finally, in a separate analysis without HVs, we compared metabolism between PET1 and PET2, PET1 and PET3, PET2 and PET3. In order to have reasonable power, we included all 10 compliant MO patients in this analysis and controlled for attack-related modifications by adding the factor ‘attack’ as a covariate in the design matrix.</p><p>The WFU PickAtlas 2.5.2 (Wake Forest University, NC, USA) was used as an anatomical reference.</p></sec></sec>Key findings
Orbitofrontal and rostral anterior cingulate cortices are significantly hypometabolic in episodic migraineurs at rest compared to healthy controls.Episodic migraine, like chronic migraine with medication overuse, seems to be associated with a dysfunction of medial frontal areas involved in affective and cognitive dimensions of pain control.A three-month preventive treatment with external trigeminal nerve stimulation (eTNS) is associated with normalisation of this hypometabolism and significantly reduces migraine attack frequency.Assuming that the 18-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) changes are causally related to eTNS, the effect on the medial prefrontal cortex seems similar to that reported after invasive pericranial nerve stimulation therapies.
AcknowledgementsCefaly Technology® provided the eTNS devices used for this study, as well as technical assistance (compliance analysis). The manuscript was reviewed by a qualified English-speaking medical writer.Author contributions include the following:
– DM conceived and wrote the study protocol, recruited and followed-up MO patients, interpreted the results, reviewed the introduction, methods and results parts of the manuscript, conducted the literature search and wrote the discussion and conclusion.– KD recruited HVs, compiled the statistics, wrote the first draft of introduction, methods and results, and designed the tables and figures.– AT helped with neuroimaging processing.– VDP escorted patients to the Nuclear Medicine Department for the one-hour eTNS session (PET2).– PG ensured the logistics of the study (appointments, eTNS training and headache diaries).– RH is head of the Nuclear Medicine Department where PETs were performed, and reviewed the methods.– SL supervised AT.– JS conceived and reviewed the study protocol, recruited and followed-up MO patients, and reviewed the final manuscript.– The final version of the manuscript was sent to all coauthors for approval before submission.Declaration of conflicting interestsThe authors declared the following potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: SL and JS are consultants for Cefaly Technology.FundingThe authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This work was funded by the Walloon Region, DG06, Direction Générale Opérationnelle de l’Économie, de l’Emploi et de la Recherche (TRADONI convention 1117427), and by the European Union (EUROHEADPAIN, Seventh framework programme, grant agreement number 602633).References1TorelliPJensenRHTavanaiepourDet al.
The International Classification of Headache Disorders, 3rd edition (beta version). Cephalalgia
2013; 53: 137–146.2BlumenfeldAMBloudekLMBeckerWJet al.
Patterns of use and reasons for discontinuation of prophylactic medications for episodic migraine and chronic migraine: Results from the second International Burden of Migraine Study (IBMS-II). Headache
2013; 53: 644–655.234584963MagisD
Neuromodulation in migraine: State of the art and perspectives. Expert Rev Med Devices
2015; 12: 329–339.256338854SchoenenJVandersmissenBJeangetteSet al.
Migraine prevention with a supraorbital transcutaneous stimulator: A randomized controlled trial. Neurology
2013; 80: 697–704.233901775RussoATessitoreAConteFet al.
Transcutaneous supraorbital neurostimulation in “de novo” patients with migraine without aura: The first Italian experience. J Headache Pain
2015; 16: 69–69.261979776MagisDSavaSD’EliaTSet al.
Safety and patients’ satisfaction of transcutaneous supraorbital neurostimulation (tSNS) with the Cefaly® device in headache treatment: A survey of 2,313 headache sufferers in the general population. J Headache Pain
2013; 14: 95–95.242898257WillochFGamringerUMedeleRet al.
Analgesia by electrostimulation of the trigeminal ganglion in patients with trigeminopathic pain: A PET activation study. Pain
2003; 103: 119–130.127499668MagisDBrunoMAFumalAet al.
Central modulation in cluster headache patients treated with occipital nerve stimulation: An FDG-PET study. BMC Neurol
2011; 11: 25–25.213491869MatharuMSBartschTWardNet al.
Central neuromodulation in chronic migraine patients with suboccipital stimulators: A PET study. Brain
2004; 127: 220–230.1460779210KovacsSPeetersRDe RidderDet al.
Central effects of occipital nerve electrical stimulation studied by functional magnetic resonance imaging. Neuromodulation
2011; 14: 46–47.2199216211StreelSDonneauAFDardenneNet al.
Validation of an extended French version of ID Migraine as a migraine-screening tool. Cephalalgia
2015; 35: 437–442.2511584312PetrovicPKalsoEPeterssonKMet al.
Placebo and opioid analgesia – imaging a shared neuronal network. Science
2002; 295: 1737–1740.1183478113FumalALaureysSDi ClementeLet al.
Orbitofrontal cortex involvement in chronic analgesic-overuse headache evolving from episodic migraine. Brain
2006; 129: 543–550.1633050514RiedererFGantenbeinARMartiMet al.
Decrease of gray matter volume in the midbrain is associated with treatment response in medication-overuse headache: Possible influence of orbitofrontal cortex. J Neurosci
2013; 33: 15343–15349.2406880115FerraroSGrazziLMandelliMLet al.
Pain processing in medication overuse headache: A functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) study. Pain Med
2012; 13: 255–262.2174963516SprengerTBorsookD
Migraine changes the brain: Neuroimaging makes its mark.
2012; 25: 252–262.17ManiyarFHSprengerTMonteithTet al.
Brain activations in the premonitory phase of nitroglycerin-triggered migraine attacks. Brain
2014; 137: 232–241.2427771818KimJHKimSSuhSIet al.
Interictal metabolic changes in episodic migraine: A voxel-based FDG-PET study. Cephalalgia
2010; 30: 53–61.1948988719SprengerTRuetherKVBoeckerHet al.
Altered metabolism in frontal brain circuits in cluster headache. Cephalalgia
2007; 27: 1033–1042.1766608320AderjanDStankewitzAMayA
Neuronal mechanisms during repetitive trigemino-nociceptive stimulation in migraine patients. Pain
2010; 151: 97–103.2063817821BashirALiptonRBAshinaSet al.
Migraine and structural changes in the brain. Neurology
2013; 81: 1260–1268.2398630122DaiZZhongJXiaoPet al.
Gray matter correlates of migraine and gender effect: A meta-analysis of voxel-based morphometry studies. Neuroscience
2015; 299: 88–96.2594347823SchwedtTJChiangCChongCDet al.
Functional MRI of migraine. Lancet Neurol
2015; 14: 81–91.2549689924MaquetPDiveDSalmonEet al.
Reproducibility of cerebral glucose utilization measured by PET and the [18F]-2-fluoro-2-deoxy-d-glucose method in resting, healthy human subjects. Eur J Nucl Med
1990; 16: 267–273.235117525SchaeferSAbercrombieHLindgrenK
Six-month test-retest reliability of MRI-defined PET measures of regional cerebral glucose metabolic rate in selected subcortical structures. Hum Brain Mapp
2000; 10: 1–9.1084351326BariAAPouratianN
Brain imaging correlates of peripheral nerve stimulation. Surg Neurol Int
2012; 3 (Suppl 4): 260–268.27MayALeoneMBoeckerHet al.
Hypothalamic deep brain stimulation in positron emission tomography. J Neurosci
2006; 26: 3589–3593.1657176728RamseyRRRyanJLHersheyADet al.
Treatment adherence in patients with headache: A systematic review. Headache
2014; 54: 795–816.24750017
