<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Phys Ther Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Phys Ther Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPTS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Physical Therapy Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0915-5287</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2187-5626</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Society of Physical Therapy Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5462676</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28603349</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jpts-2016-925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1589/jpts.29.801</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Neural manual vs. robotic assisted mobilization to improve motion and reduce
pain hypersensitivity in hand osteoarthritis: study protocol for a randomized controlled
trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>Jorge Hugo</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, MSc</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>Kristin</given-names></name><degrees>OTD, OT, CHT</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Imperio</surname><given-names>Grace</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borboni</surname><given-names>Alberto</given-names></name><degrees>Eng, MSx, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cantero-T&#x000e9;llez</surname><given-names>Raquel</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, PT</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Galeri</surname><given-names>Silvia</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Negrini</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label> IRCCS Fondazione Don Carlo Gnocchi, Italy</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label> Gannon University, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label> Mechanical and Industrial Engineering Department,
University of Brescia, Italy</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4)</label> Physical Therapy Section, Faculty of Health Sciences,
University of Malaga, Spain</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5)</label> Department of Clinical and Experimental Sciences,
University of Brescia, Italy</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Jorge Hugo Villafa&#x000f1;e, IRCCS Fondazione Don Carlo Gnocchi: Piazzale Morandi 6-20121 Milano, Italy. (E-mail:
<email xlink:href="mail@villafane.it">mail@villafane.it</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>2017&#x000a9;by the Society of Physical Therapy Science. Published by IPEC
Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. (CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>[Purpose] The aim of the present study is to detail the protocol for a randomised
controlled trial (RCT) of neural manual vs. robotic assisted on pain in sensitivity as
well as analyse the quantitative and qualitative movement of hand in subjects with hand
osteoarthritis. [Subjects and Methods] Seventy-two patients, aged 50 to 90&#x02005;years old of
both genders, with a diagnosis of hand Osteoarthritis (OA), will be recruited. Two groups
of 36 participants will receive an experimental intervention (neurodynamic mobilization
intervention plus exercise) or a control intervention (robotic assisted passive
mobilization plus exercise) for 12 sessions over 4 weeks. Assessment points will be at
baseline, end of therapy, and 1 and 3 months after end of therapy. The outcomes of this
intervention will be pain and determine the central pain processing mechanisms. [Result]
Not applicable. [Conclusion] If there is a reduction in pain hypersensitivity in hand OA
patients it can suggest that supraspinal pain-inhibitory areas, including the
periaqueductal gray matter, can be stimulated by joint mobilization.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Osteoarthritis</kwd><kwd>Hand</kwd><kwd>Rehabilitation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Pain in osteoarthritis (OA) is considered a complex integration of sensory and cognitive
processes involving several abnormal cellular mechanisms at peripheral and central levels of
the nervous system<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><sup>)</sup>. The peripherally directed therapies may modulate pain perception
bilaterally<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><sup>)</sup>. This hypothesis opens
avenues for future research in the modulation of pain pathways, perhaps offering targets to
optimize peripheral manual and physical therapies for pain management in hand OA.
Furthermore, patients with hand OA who underwent fMRI analysis, showed increased activation
in the thalamus, cingulate, frontal and somatosensory cortex as a consequence of central
sensitization<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><sup>)</sup>. Several studies have
reported the outcomes of multimodal approach to central sensitization evaluated by
generalized pressure pain hypersensitivity in patients with carpometacarpal (CMC) OA<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><sup>)</sup>. Neurodynamic techniques are a form of
manual therapy directed to the neural structures through positioning and movement of
multiple joints<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><sup>)</sup>. In multiple studies,
Villafa&#x000f1;e et al. examined the outcomes of patients with CMC OA treated with a neural
mobilization technique in the median and radial nerves<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><sup>)</sup>. Conservative therapy has been shown to relieve symptoms for
patients categorized with early stages of hand OA disease to stave off surgical
interventions either temporarily or in the long term<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><sup>)</sup>. Recent technologies have facilitated the use of robots as tools to
assist patients in the rehabilitation process thus maximizing patient outcomes<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><sup>)</sup>. These robotic tools assist the patient
with carrying out exercise protocols, among these devices the glove (Gloreha), may represent
a solution for the control group<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>We hypothesized that these patients would show hypoalgesia of neural mobilization as
compared to robotic assisted mobilization. Therefore, the purpose of this randomized
controlled trial is to examine the effects of radial, ulnar and median nerve mobilization
vs. robotic assisted passive mobilization of the hand on pain in sensitivity, hand function,
and analyze the quantitative and qualitative movement of hand in subjects with hand
osteoarthritis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>SUBJECTS AND METHODS</title><p>This is a double-blind randomized-controlled trial. The patient will sign the informed
consent for study and procedures will be conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki.
This research protocol has been approved by the Local Ethical Committee of &#x0201c;IRCCS D.G.F&#x0201d;,
Italy on 24 February 2016 and is registered with ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT02701335). This
trial is financed by the National Health System of Italy (Project Code:
GR-2013-02358472).</p><p>Our study will include 72 patients, aged 50 to 90&#x02005;years old of both genders, with a
diagnosis of hand OA. To ensure the precision of results of this trial, subjects who meet
the following eligible criteria will be included in this study. All subjects will have OA of
the dominant hand. A physiatrist (physician) will establish the diagnosis of hand OA. Each
subject will undergo subjective and physical examination performed by a physical therapist
experienced in musculoskeletal physiotherapy to evaluate inclusion and exclusion criteria.
To be included in the study, the subjects need to have a history of repetitive use of their
dominant hand (eg, ex-factory worker) and a diagnosis of hand OA in the dominant hand,
according on radiographic findings. The exclusion criteria are: if they score greater than 6
points on the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) or more than 30 points in the State Trait
Anxiety Inventory (STAI)<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><sup>)</sup>. Patients with
a medical history of carpal tunnel syndrome, surgical interventions to the hand,
DeQuervain&#x02019;s tenosynovitis, or with degenerative or non-degenerative neurological conditions
in which pain perception is altered will be excluded. None of the individuals in this study
will have received prior interventions for hand OA.</p><p>Recruitment will take place between December 2016 and April 2018. Those who will be
considered eligible for the study will be invited for a first interview at which point
informed written consent will be completed, inclusion and exclusion criteria confirmed, and
a medical history and physical examination will be completed.</p><p>Two groups of thirty participants will receive an experimental intervention (neurodynamic
intervention plus exercise) or a control intervention (robotic assisted passive mobilization
of the hand (Gloreha, Idrogenet, Italy) plus exercise) for 12 sessions over 4 weeks and will
be applied to the dominant hand. The variables will be collected in the following order:
pain and function (measured by the visual analogue scale, [VAS], pressure pain threshold
[PPT] and the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand Score [QuickDASH] questionnaire).
Nerve conduction (NC) (measured by the electromyography, [EMG]), and hand mobility (measured
by kinematic analysis) will then be assessed. All outcomes measures will be captured at
baseline, immediately post-intervention, and at 1- and 3-month post-interventions.</p><p>The present document was prepared according to the editorial form of medical publishing and
CONSORT publishing rules<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p><italic>Experimental Intervention.</italic> Neural mobilization is a maneuver that produces
a sliding movement of the neural structures in relation to their anatomical adjacent
tissues. A nerve slider is a maneuver producing a sliding movement of the neural structures
in relation to their anatomical adjacent tissues. It involves a combination of movement of
surrounding so that tension on one end of the nerve increases while the tension on the other
end relieves<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>For the medial nerve, The sequence of movement performed on the patient by the physical
therapist for initial positioning for the nerve slider technique is: shoulder girdle
depression, glenohumeral abduction and external rotation, supination of the forearm, and
wrist, thumb, and finger extension, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1a</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Nerve slider exercise used to target the median, radial and ulnar nerves</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jpts-29-801-g001"/></fig>). Then, the nerve slider technique for the median nerve consists of alternating i)
the combination of elbow extension (which increases tension on the median nerve) and wrist
flexion (which decreases tension on the median nerve) movement with ii) the combination of
elbow flexion (decreasing tension) and wrist extension (increasing tension) movement. The
imposed range of motion are: i) from 0&#x000b0; to 60&#x000b0; of extension at the wrist, and ii) from 15 to
90&#x000b0; of flexion of the wrist depending on tissue resistance<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>For the radial nerve, the sequence of movement performed on the patient by the physical
therapist for initial positioning consists of shoulder girdle depression, glenohumeral
internal rotation, pronation of the forearm, elbow extension, and wrist, thumb, and finger
flexion<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><sup>)</sup>. Finally, ulnar deviation of
the wrist is added. The slider neurodynamic technique for the radial nerve consists of
alternating the combination of shoulder depression (loads the radial nerve) and elbow
flexion-wrist extension (unloads the radial nerve) with shoulder elevation (unloading) and
elbow-wrist extension (loading) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1b)</xref>.</p><p>Finally, for the ulnar nerve, the wrist is placed in extension, the elbow is flexed and the
shoulder abducted. Sliding technique: elbow extension (unloads the ulnar nerve) and shoulder
abduction (loads the ulnar nerve) is alternated with elbow flexion (loading) and shoulder
adduction (unloading)<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><sup>)</sup>. Throughout the
sliding technique, the wrist is maintained in 60&#x000b0; extension and the forearm in supination
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1c)</xref>.</p><p>The nerves slider technique will be performed twice for 3 minutes each time with a 1-minute
rest between sets. Speed and amplitude of movement are adjusted such that no pain is
produced during the technique.</p><p><italic>Control Intervention.</italic> Each patient will use the Gloreha device for passive
mobilization of the hand twice a day for 4 consecutive weeks. Treatment will include, half
an hour of treatment during the morning with the &#x0201c;program&#x0201d; (each finger is mobilized
individually) and half an hour of treatment during the afternoon with the &#x0201c;synchronous&#x0201d;
(II-III-IV-V finger are mobilized simultaneously, the thumb individually) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Hand exercises with Gloreha</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jpts-29-801-g002"/></fig>). The fingers of the patients are hooked to individual thimbles connectable through a
nylon thread to a device fixed on the glove that interfaced with a hybrid system (compressed
air and oil) performing the passive movement of flexion-extension of the fingers. The
presence of these flexible cables allows the Gloreha glove to gradually moderate the
intensity of forces applied on subject&#x02019;s hand and fingers. The length of every cable can be
adjusted in the aim to guarantee a progressive and specific adaptation of each finger
according to order of the treatment, the type of exercise and the clinical condition of the
subject (level of resistance, pain and etc.).</p><p>Subjects in both groups will receive the same standardized exercise protocol as described
by Villafa&#x000f1;e et al<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><sup>)</sup>. The first 6 exercises
consist of active range of motion movements of the hand designed to improve joint
flexibility. The remaining 3 exercises are designed to strengthen grip and pinch by using a
non-latex polymer ball: the Thera-Band Hand Exerciser (The Hygenic Corporation, Akron, OH,
USA) (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Hand exercises</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exercise</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tabletop</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The hand and wrist are held in a neutral position; the subject
flexes at the second to fifth meta-carpo-phalangeal (MCP) joints only, and then
returns to neutral.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small fist</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">From neutral position; the subject flexes at the second to fifth
proximal inter-phalangeal joint and distal inter-phalangeal joint only, and then
returns to neutral.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large Fist</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">From neutral position; the subject flexes all joints to form a fist
and then returns to neutral.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okay signs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">From neutral position; the subject flexes to form an &#x02018;&#x02018;O&#x02019;&#x02019; with the
tip of the thumb to the tip of each finger, in turn, returning to neutral after
each</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finger spread</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">From neutral position; hand is placed on flat table top and fingers
are spread apart as wide as possible before returning to neutral.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thumb reach</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">From neutral position, the subject reaches across the palm of the
hand and touches tip of thumb to fifth MCP and then returns to neutral.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gripping</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subject holds the Thera-Band Hand Exerciser ball in palm of hand
and squeezes until ball is about 50% depressed.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key pinch</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subject holds the Thera-Band Hand Exerciser ball between the side
of the thumb and side of the index finger and squeezes until ball is about 50%
depressed.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fingertip pinch</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subject holds the Thera-Band Hand Exerciser ball between the tip of
the thumb and the tip of the index finger and squeezes until the ball is about 50%
depressed; this is repeated for digits three to five.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>). The hand exerciser is color coded based on the approximate resistance
provided at 50% compression, with yellow at 0.68&#x02005;kg, red at 1.36&#x02005;kg, green at 2.27&#x02005;kg, and
blue at 3.64&#x02005;kg<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><sup>)</sup>. All participants
started with a yellow ball, and depending on clinical presentation, subjects could be
assigned to use more than 1 colored ball. Subjects began with 10 repetitions the first 4
sessions, progressed to 12 repetitions the next 2 sessions, then 15 (2 sessions), and
finally 20, if able, during the last sessions<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>All participants will receive 12 treatment sessions scheduled on separate days, at least 48
hours apart and at the same time of day, 3 days per week, for 4 weeks. Treatment will be
only applied to the affected hand.</p><p>The outcome measure will be pain intensity of hand, which will be assessed with a visual
analogue scale (VAS). (VAS; 0: no pain, 100: maximum pain)<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><sup>)</sup>. This will be used to
assess 3 separate pain status levels: (a) level of pain while executing a grip strength
during daily life activities, (b) average level of pain over the last 24 hours, and (c)
average level of pain over the last week.</p><p>The valid and reliable, QuickDASH questionnaire will be used to measure upper extremity
function<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><sup>)</sup>. It consists of 11 items
providing a total score ranging from 0 to 100. Eight items include questions about the
ability of the patient to perform certain daily activities, whereas the remaining 3 items
are related to upper limb symptoms<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Pressure pain threshold (PPT) is a quantitative sensory test of tissue sensitivity and it
is defined as the minimal amount of pressure that produces pain, measured via a pressure
algometer<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><sup>)</sup>. PPT will be assessed
bilaterally over the hand (first CMC at the center of the anatomical snuffbox, and unciform
apophysis of the hamate bone), the C5&#x02013;C6 zygapophyseal joint, the median, ulnar and radial
nerves, and tibialis anterior muscle by an assessor blinded to the subjects condition<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Nerve conduction (NC) and kinematic analysis of hand. NC will be performed a &#x0201c;Quattro
electromyography&#x0201d; (OT Bioelettronica s.n.c, Turin, Italy), with standard techniques, using
surface stimulation and recording electrodes. Motor conduction velocity (MCV) and sensory
conduction velocity (SCV) of the median, radial and ulnar nerves, will be recorded on both
right and left side<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><sup>)</sup>. Patients will be
evaluated by a validated functional test (Action Research Arm Test (ARAT)<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><sup>)</sup>, which measures the patient&#x02019;s ability to
perform different tasks of daily living. An investigator will rate each task on a four point
ordinal scale (0=unable to perform the task, 3=able to perform the task normally) and the
maximal score obtainable is 57 points.</p><p>Sixteen retro-reflective hemispheric markers, with diameter of 3&#x02005;mm will be attached on the
affected hand of the subjects in the following bony landmarks: heads of the metacarpals,
heads of the proximal phalanges and heads of the middle phalanges of the fingers and the
head of thumb metacarpal, head of the proximal phalanx and the head of distal phalanx, and
the dorsal tubercle of the radius. The markers configuration is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Markers placement and local reference system</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jpts-29-801-g003"/></fig>.</p><p>Subjects will be asked to sit upright in a chair behind a table positioned in front of a
Smart-DX optoelectronic system (BTS Bioengineering s.p.a., Milan, Italy) made up of the
eight infrared cameras. The chair height and position will be adjusted to provide a 90&#x000b0; of
elbow flexion. In the subjects, marker coordinates will be acquired during two dynamic tasks
of the hand, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_004">Fig. 4</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_004" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Tasks analysed in the experimental protocol</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jpts-29-801-g004"/></fig>: Task 1 (hand grasping a cylinder with a diameter of 40&#x02005;mm, H4), Task 2 (Primary
pinch).</p><p>All outcomes measures will be captured at baseline, immediately post-intervention, and at
1- and 3-month post-interventions.</p><p>Data will be analyzed using SPSS version 22.0 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL, USA), conducted
following an intention-to-treat analysis using the last value forward method. After the
completion of all baseline measurements, using a computer program
(<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/randomize1.cfm">http://www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/randomize1.cfm</uri>), subjects will be randomly assigned by
an external assistant into one of 2 groups: an experimental or control group. Group data
will be summarized using means and standard deviations. Baseline characteristics of the
groups will be compared. Mixed-model analyses of variance will be used to examine the
effects of the interventions on each outcome, with the group allotment defined as the
between-subject variable and time as the within-subject variable. The sample size and power
calculations will be performed with the ENE 3.0 software (GlaxoSmithKline<sup>&#x000a9;</sup>,
Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma, Barcelona). The calculations are based on detecting a mean difference
of 2&#x02005;cm minimal clinically important difference (MCID)<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><sup>)</sup> on a 10&#x02005;cm VAS assuming a standard deviation of 2&#x02005;cm, a 2-tailed
test, an alpha level of 0.05, and a desired power of 90%. The estimated desired sample size
is 30 individuals per group. To accommodate for expected dropouts before study completion, a
total of 36 participants will be included in each group.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This protocol was designed to outline the design of an RCT to test whether the presence of
widespread pressure pain hypersensitivity and the absence of correlation between symptoms
and radiological findings suggest that central sensitization mechanisms may play an
important role in OA related-pain. We hypothesize that these patients with hand OA will
demonstrate a widespread hypersensitivity to mechanical pressure stimuli. We expect to find,
like previously in other populations, that the central pain processing mechanisms might be a
feature of this pain population<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><sup>)</sup>. Reliable results allow the professional to reach conclusions that
are minimally affected by external factors, thereby reducing the chances of error. This is
useful information needed by clinicians to determine the appropriate treatment interventions
for patients with hand OA. For treatment to be efficacious, it may need to address the
central pain mechanism.</p><p>Both the neural manual or robotic assisted mobilization should improve hand range of motion
and reduce pain hypersensitivity in the subjects with hand OA. If true, we also expect to
know which treatment produced the greatest effect on pain, hand range of motion, and
function. Gains in hand range of motion and pain reduction may not equate to increased hand
function. This study incorporates subjects&#x02019; self report assessment of function to determine
improvement in the performance of basic self-care activities. If the improvements found are
clinically relevant, the carry over of the interventions will be assessed at clinically
relevant time points.</p><p>This is the first randomized controlled trial to compare the effect of robot-assisted
mobilization on the OA hand to therapist provided range of motion exercise. The results of
this study can be implemented in clinical practice to help clinicians deal with this
challenging patient population. Hand range of motion exercises combined with neural
mobilization techniques is a cost effective intervention that may improve hand OA patients&#x02019;
quality of life and function.</p><sec><title>Trial status</title><p>Recruitment, going to commence in December 2016.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was supported by a grant from the Ministry of Health, Italy, 2016, (Project
Code: GR-2013-02358472).</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Dieppe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Pathogenesis and management of pain in
osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <year>2005</year>,
<volume>365</volume>: <fpage>965</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>973</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15766999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Dray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Arthritis and pain. Future targets to control
osteoarthritis pain</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res Ther</source>,
<year>2007</year>, <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-de-Las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Radial nerve mobilisation had bilateral sensory effects in
people with thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis: a randomised trial</article-title>.
<source>J Physiother</source>, <year>2013</year>, <volume>59</volume>:
<fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23419912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez de-Las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Contralateral sensory and motor effects of unilateral
kaltenborn mobilization in patients with thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis: a
secondary analysis</article-title>. <source>J Phys Ther Sci</source>, <year>2014</year>,
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>812</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25013272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-de-Las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Bilateral sensory effects of unilateral passive accessory
mobilization in patients with thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis</article-title>.
<source>J Manipulative Physiol Ther</source>, <year>2013</year>, <volume>36</volume>:
<fpage>232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23719518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sofat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Smee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermansson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Functional MRI demonstrates pain perception in hand
osteoarthritis has features of central pain processing</article-title>. <source>J Biomed
Graph Comput</source>, <year>2013</year>, <volume>3</volume>. </mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bissolotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis: are we closer to
gold standards?</article-title><source>Eur J Phys Rehabil Med</source>,
<year>2016</year>, <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>908</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26956899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-de-Las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>The effectiveness of a manual therapy and exercise
protocol in patients with thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis: a randomized controlled
trial</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source>, <year>2013</year>,
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23485660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>: Mobilisation of the nervous system. Churchill Livingstone,
<year>1991</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Carnero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Short-term effects of neurodynamic mobilization in 15
patients with secondary thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>J
Manipulative Physiol Ther</source>, <year>2011</year>, <volume>34</volume>:
<fpage>449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>456</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21875519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Radial nerve mobilization decreases pain sensitivity and
improves motor performance in patients with thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis: a
randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source>,
<year>2012</year>, <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>403</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22218138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bertozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Investigation of the effect of conservative interventions
in thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis: systematic review and
meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Disabil Rehabil</source>, <year>2015</year>,
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>2025</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2043</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25559974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Berjano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Clinical update: conservative management of
carpometacarpal joint osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>,
<year>2015</year>, <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1728</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1729</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26330130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Letter regarding &#x0201c;conservative treatment of thumb base
osteoarthritis: a systematic review&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>,
<year>2015</year>, <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1058</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1059</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25911214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Three upper limb robotic devices for stroke
rehabilitation: a review and clinical perspective</article-title>.
<source>NeuroRehabilitation</source>, <year>2013</year>, <volume>33</volume>:
<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23949043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bissolotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaffurini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Changes in skeletal muscle perfusion and spasticity in
patients with poststroke hemiparesis treated by robotic assistance (Gloreha) of the
hand</article-title>. <source>J Phys Ther Sci</source>, <year>2016</year>,
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>773</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27134356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Angulo-Diaz-Parre&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Ulnar digits contribution to grip strength in patients
with thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis is less than in normal
controls</article-title>. <source>Hand (NY)</source>, <year>2015</year>,
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>. </mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Submitting manuscripts to biomedical journals: common
errors and helpful solutions</article-title>. <source>J Manipulative Physiol
Ther</source>, <year>2009</year>, <volume>32</volume>:
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coppieters</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Do &#x02018;sliders&#x02019; slide and &#x02018;tensioners&#x02019; tension? An analysis
of neurodynamic techniques and considerations regarding their
application</article-title>. <source>Man Ther</source>, <year>2008</year>,
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17398140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilder</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Exercise and hand osteoarthritis symptomatology: a
controlled crossover trial</article-title>. <source>J Hand Ther</source>,
<year>2009</year>, <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17, discussion 19&#x02013;20,
quiz 18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19013758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Comparative reliability and validity of chronic pain
intensity measures</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>, <year>1999</year>,
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10534586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Beaton</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group>, Upper Extremity Collaborative Group: <article-title>Development of the
QuickDASH: comparison of three item-reduction approaches</article-title>. <source>J Bone
Joint Surg Am</source>, <year>2005</year>, <volume>87</volume>:
<fpage>1038</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1046</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15866967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Franchignoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferriero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Psychometric properties of QuickDASH&#x02014;a classical test
theory and Rasch analysis study</article-title>. <source>Man Ther</source>,
<year>2011</year>, <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21044859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Villafa&#x000f1;e</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Carnero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Effect of thumb joint mobilization on pressure pain
threshold in elderly patients with thumb carpometacarpal osteoarthritis</article-title>.
<source>J Manipulative Physiol Ther</source>, <year>2012</year>, <volume>35</volume>:
<fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22257943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tacconi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamburini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Electroneurography index based on nerve conduction study
data: method and findings in control subjects</article-title>. <source>Muscle
Nerve</source>, <year>2004</year>, <volume>29</volume>:
<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14694503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>A performance test for assessment of upper limb function
in physical rehabilitation treatment and research</article-title>. <source>Int J Rehabil
Res</source>, <year>1981</year>, <volume>4</volume>:
<fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7333761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Emshoff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Emshoff</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Clinically important difference thresholds of the visual
analog scale: a conceptual model for identifying meaningful intraindividual changes for
pain intensity</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>, <year>2011</year>,
<volume>152</volume>: <fpage>2277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21726939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>