<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Hum Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Hum Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Hum. Neurosci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Human Neuroscience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1662-5161</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4029020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2014.00245</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Structural Changes Induced by Daily Music Listening in the Recovering Brain after Middle Cerebral Artery Stroke: A Voxel-Based Morphometry Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>Teppo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/29446"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ripoll&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/134775"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Veps&#x000e4;l&#x000e4;inen</surname><given-names>Henna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Autti</surname><given-names>Taina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/15807"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silvennoinen</surname><given-names>Heli M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salli</surname><given-names>Eero</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/139087"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>Sari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/84336"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Forsblom</surname><given-names>Anita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/71375"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soinila</surname><given-names>Seppo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Fornells</surname><given-names>Antoni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9"><sup>9</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/344"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Cognitive Brain Research Unit, Cognitive Science, Institute of Behavioural Sciences, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Finnish Centre of Interdisciplinary Music Research, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Cognition and Brain Plasticity Group, Bellvitge Biomedical Research Institute (IDIBELL), L&#x02019;Hospitalet de Llobregat</institution>, <addr-line>Barcelona</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Basic Psychology, University of Barcelona</institution>, <addr-line>Barcelona</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Radiology, HUS Medical Imaging Center, Helsinki University Central Hospital, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Miina Sillanp&#x000e4;&#x000e4; Foundation</institution>, <addr-line>Helsinki</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup><institution>Department of Music, University of Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;</institution>, <addr-line>Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><sup>8</sup><institution>Department of Neurology, Turku University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Turku</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><sup>9</sup><institution>Instituci&#x000f3; Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avan&#x000e7;ats (ICREA)</institution>, <addr-line>Barcelona</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Eckart Altenm&#x000fc;ller, University of Music and Drama Hannover, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Jens Dieter Rollnik, BDH-Klinik Hessisch Oldendorf, Germany; Bernhard Haslinger, Technische Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen, Germany</p></fn><corresp content-type="corresp" id="cor1">*Correspondence: Teppo S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;, Cognitive Brain Research Unit, Cognitive Science, Institute of Behavioural Sciences, University of Helsinki, Siltavuorenpenger 1B, P.O. Box 9, Helsinki FI-00014, Finland e-mail: <email>teppo.sarkamo@helsinki.fi</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Human Neuroscience.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>245</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;, Ripoll&#x000e9;s, Veps&#x000e4;l&#x000e4;inen, Autti, Silvennoinen, Salli, Laitinen, Forsblom, Soinila and Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Fornells.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Music is a highly complex and versatile stimulus for the brain that engages many temporal, frontal, parietal, cerebellar, and subcortical areas involved in auditory, cognitive, emotional, and motor processing. Regular musical activities have been shown to effectively enhance the structure and function of many brain areas, making music a potential tool also in neurological rehabilitation. In our previous randomized controlled study, we found that listening to music on a daily basis can improve cognitive recovery and improve mood after an acute middle cerebral artery stroke. Extending this study, a voxel-based morphometry (VBM) analysis utilizing cost function masking was performed on the acute and 6-month post-stroke stage structural magnetic resonance imaging data of the patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;49) who either listened to their favorite music [music group (MG), <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;16] or verbal material [audio book group (ABG), <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;18] or did not receive any listening material [control group (CG), <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15] during the 6-month recovery period. Although all groups showed significant gray matter volume (GMV) increases from the acute to the 6-month stage, there was a specific network of frontal areas [left and right superior frontal gyrus (SFG), right medial SFG] and limbic areas [left ventral/subgenual anterior cingulate cortex (SACC) and right ventral striatum (VS)] in patients with left hemisphere damage in which the GMV increases were larger in the MG than in the ABG and in the CG. Moreover, the GM reorganization in the frontal areas correlated with enhanced recovery of verbal memory, focused attention, and language skills, whereas the GM reorganization in the SACC correlated with reduced negative mood. This study adds on previous results, showing that music listening after stroke not only enhances behavioral recovery, but also induces fine-grained neuroanatomical changes in the recovering brain.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>music</kwd><kwd>speech</kwd><kwd>stroke</kwd><kwd>magnetic resonance imaging</kwd><kwd>voxel-based morphometry</kwd><kwd>environmental enrichment</kwd><kwd>neuroplasticity</kwd><kwd>rehabilitation</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="113"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="11769"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p>During the past 10&#x02009;years, advanced magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) analysis methods, such as voxel-based morphometry (VBM) and diffusion tensor imaging (DTI), have provided novel information about the dynamics of the structural neuroplastic changes underlying spontaneous recovery and rehabilitation after stroke. Based on longitudinal VBM and DTI studies of stroke patients, the recovery of cognitive and motor deficits is associated with gray matter volume (GMV) changes in many frontal, temporal, cerebellar, and subcortical (e.g., hippocampus) areas (Grau-Olivares et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Dang et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Fan et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) as well as changes in the integrity of the white matter (WM) tracts connecting and projecting from these areas (Liang et al., <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; van Meer et al., <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Thiebaut de Schotten et al., <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In longitudinal intervention studies, intensive motor rehabilitation using constraint-induced movement therapy (CIMT) has been shown to increase GMV in frontal and parietal sensory&#x02013;motor areas and in the hippocampus (Gauthier et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and intensive aphasia rehabilitation using constraint-induced language therapy (CILT) or melodic intonation therapy (MIT) has been observed to enhance the integrity of the WM tracks connecting frontal and temporal regions (arcuate fasciculus) in the left (Breier et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and right (Schlaug et al., <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) hemispheres, respectively. All in all, these findings suggest that both behavioral recovery and active rehabilitation after stroke are closely linked to fine-grained neuroanatomical changes in the recovering brain. However, very little is known about the wider potential effects of the <italic>recovery environment</italic> on structural brain plasticity after stroke in humans.</p><p>Converging evidence from both animal (Johansson, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Nithianantharajah and Hannan, <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) and human studies (Johansson, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Janssen et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) indicates that an environmental enrichment (EE), which provides additional sensory, cognitive, motor, and/or social stimulation compared to a standard environment, plays an important role in enhancing behavioral recovery after an acute stroke. In addition, evidence from animal studies suggests that the post-stroke EE can induce a number of cellular and molecular neuroplastic effects in the brain, including increase in dendritic complexity (Biernaskie and Corbett, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Johansson and Belichenko, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>), neural stem and progenitor cells (Komitova et al., <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Matsumori et al., <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), and neurotrophic and neural growth factor levels (Gobbo and O&#x02019;Mara, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; S&#x000f6;derstr&#x000f6;m et al., <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and that these changes are associated with better cognitive or motor recovery. Interestingly, especially a multisensory EE, which includes auditory, visual, and olfactory stimuli, has been found to be effective in improving cognitive and motor recovery and reducing lesion volume (Maegele et al., <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2005a</xref>,<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Also evidence from developmental animal studies shows that a purely auditory EE, which contains complex sounds or music, can enhance the structure and function of the auditory cortex (Engineer et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Bose et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) as well as improve learning and memory and upregulate various neurotransmitters (e.g., dopamine, glutamate) and neurotrophins associated with them (Sutoo and Akiyama, <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Angelucci et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Nichols et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Overall, these findings indicate that auditory enrichment can be beneficial for the brain and suggest that it could potentially contribute to better cognitive and neural recovery also after stroke.</p><p>In the human brain, music and speech constitute the two most complex and versatile auditory stimuli in terms of their acoustic richness and the breadth of the neural networks involved in their perception and learning (Zatorre, <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Neuroimaging studies of healthy subjects have demonstrated that music processing engages a vast bilateral network of temporal, frontal, parietal, cerebellar, and limbic/paralimbic areas associated with the perception of complex acoustic features (e.g., melody, rhythm), syntactic and semantic processing, attention and working memory, episodic and semantic memory, motor and rhythm processing, and experiencing emotions and reward (Blood and Zatorre, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Janata et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2002a</xref>,<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; Platel et al., <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Koelsch et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Menon and Levitin, <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Bengtsson et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Salimpoor et al., <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Alluri et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Herdener et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; for recent reviews see, Koelsch, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Zatorre, <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Evidence from VBM and DTI studies also indicates that frequent musical activities, such as playing an instrument or singing, can lead to long-term structural changes in the brain, especially in frontal, temporal, and parietal areas and in the WM pathways (e.g., corpus callosum, arcuate fasciculus) connecting them (Gaser and Schlaug, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Hyde et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Halwani et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; James et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Improvements in attention and executive functioning have also been reported in healthy older adults after regular music playing activities, such as piano playing (Bugos et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), and one longitudinal study also highlighted the role of playing musical instruments and dancing as leisure activities associated with a reduced risk of developing dementia (Verghese et al., <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Regarding the potential rehabilitative use of music after stroke, results from recent clinical studies suggest that active music-based interventions that utilize singing (MIT) or instrument playing (music-supported therapy, MST), can be effective in improving speech and motor recovery through enhancing the functioning and connectivity of temporal auditory and frontal motor areas (Schlaug et al., <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>, <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Altenm&#x000fc;ller et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Rojo et al., <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Fornells et al., <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Grau-S&#x000e1;nchez et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Very little, however, is known about the potential neuroplastic changes induced by everyday musical activities, such as music listening, after stroke.</p><p>Previously, we performed a randomized controlled trial (RCT) concerning the potential rehabilitative effects of an enriched sound environment on stroke recovery. Sixty patients with an acute left (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;29) or right (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31) hemisphere middle cerebral artery (MCA) brain infarction were randomized to a music group (MG) (daily listening to self-selected music), an audio book group (ABG) (daily listening to self-selected audio books), and a control group (CG) (standard care only) and their recovery was followed for 6&#x02009;months using behavioral measures (neuropsychological tests and questionnaires on mood), an auditory magnetoencephalography (MEG) measurement, and structural MRI. Fifty-four patients completed the whole 6-month follow-up. Behavioral results showed that verbal memory and focused attention improved more in the MG than in the ABG or CG after the intervention period at the 3-month follow-up and also remained better at the longitudinal 6-month follow-up (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), suggesting that regular music listening enhanced cognitive recovery. Compared to the CG, the MG also experienced less depressed and confused mood at the 3-month follow-up (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). MEG results showed that the mismatch negativity (MMN) response to frequency changes strengthened more in the MG and ABG compared to the CG at the 6-month follow-up, indicating that regular exposure to both music and speech enhanced early auditory encoding in the recovering brain (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>).</p><p>In the present study, our aim was to determine with a VBM analysis of the longitudinal structural MRI data (baseline acute stage and 6-month stage) from the same patient sample whether daily music listening could also lead to structural GM and WM reorganization in the brain and if this change would also be related to the previously found positive effects of music on cognitive and emotional recovery after stroke.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2-1"><title>Subjects and study design</title><p>Sixty stroke patients were recruited during 2004&#x02013;2006 from the Department of Neurology of the Helsinki University Central Hospital (HUCH). All patients had an acute ischemic MCA stroke in the left (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;29) or right (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31) temporal, frontal, parietal, or subcortical brain regions. Additional inclusion criteria were: no prior neurological/psychiatric disease, drug/alcohol abuse, or hearing deficit; right-handed; &#x02264;75&#x02009;years old; Finnish-speaking; and able to co-operate. Recruited patients were randomly assigned to one of three groups (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20 in each): an MG, an ABG, or a CG. Randomization was performed with a random number generator by a researcher not involved in the patient enrollment. The study was approved by the HUCH Ethics Committee, and all patients signed an informed consent. All patients received standard treatment for stroke in terms of medical care and rehabilitation.</p><p>During the follow-up, the patients underwent a neuropsychological assessment (including cognitive tests and questionnaires) and an auditory MEG measurement 1&#x02009;week (baseline), 3&#x02009;months, and 6&#x02009;months post-stroke, and a structural MRI within 2&#x02009;weeks of the stroke onset and 6&#x02009;months post-stroke. Details regarding the methodology and results of the neuropsychological assessments and the MEG experiment are available in the previous published articles (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>, <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">2010a</xref>).</p><p>Of the 60 patients originally recruited into the study, 55 completed the study up to the 3-month stage and 54 up to the 6-month stage. For the purpose of the longitudinal VBM analyses, appropriate MRI data were unavailable in three patients and the image quality was insufficient in two further patients. Thus, data from 49 patients were used in the present study. Demographic and clinical characteristics as well as the musical and linguistic activities of the patients are shown in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, presented separately for the patients with left hemisphere damage (LHD, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23) and right hemisphere damage (RHD, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;26). There were no significant differences between the MG, ACG, and CG on any demographic or clinical variables, prior musical or linguistic activities, or in other rehabilitation received during the 6-month follow-up whereas the frequency of listening to music and audio books differed highly significantly between the groups both at the 3-month and the 6-month stage. However, there were no statistically significant differences between the MG and ABG on how many hours per day the patients listened to the provided material (music in the MG, audio books in the ABG) on average, although within the RHD patients the daily listening amounts were slightly higher in the MG than in the ABG. Overall, these results indicate that the groups were comparable and that the intervention protocol worked well.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;49)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Left hemisphere damage (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23)<hr/></th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Right hemisphere damage (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;26)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:DarkGray;" rowspan="1"><bold>DEMOGRAPHICAL CHARACTERISTICS</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3 (11.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.9 (7.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0 (8.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.615 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.6 (7.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.4 (9.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.4 (4.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519 (F)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (male/female)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.439 (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111 (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (years)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (4.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 (3.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9 (3.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1 (4.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 (2.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3 (3.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.518 (F)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:DarkGray;" rowspan="1"><bold>CLINICAL CHARACTERISTICS</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from stroke onset to acute MRI (days)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (3.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (3.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (2.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.922 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (1.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 (3.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 (4.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366 (F)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from stroke onset to 6-month MRI (days)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184.4 (6.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184.6 (15.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192.4 (16.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189.0 (5.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.7 (8.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.9 (22.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228 (F)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemiparesis (yes/no)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.409 (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aphasia (yes/no)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.701 (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lesion size (max. diameter in cm)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0 (17.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7 (18.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5 (17.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.384 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3 (28.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.5 (20.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.1 (25.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924 (F)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:DarkGray;" rowspan="1"><bold>OTHER REHABILITATION DURING THE 6-MONTH FOLLOW-UP<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical therapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7 (30.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 (30.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (9.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.732 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.9 (41.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2 (37.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1 (26.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupational therapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 (22.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 (20.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 (12.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 (14.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 (6.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.886 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Speech therapy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3 (20.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (9.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (11.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3 (20.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (9.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (11.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuropsychological rehabilitation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (10.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (4.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.851 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (5.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (4.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (1.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976 (K)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Data are mean (SD) unless otherwise stated. MG, music group; ABG, audio book group; CG, control group; <italic>F</italic>, one-way ANOVA; &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>, chi-square test (likelihood ratio); K, Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test</italic>.</p><fn id="tfn1"><p><italic><sup>a</sup>Number of therapy sessions</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Musical and linguistic activities of the patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;49)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Left hemisphere damage (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23)<hr/></th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Right hemisphere damage (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;26)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:DarkGray;" rowspan="1"><bold>BEFORE STROKE</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Listening to music</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.592 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rarely</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (28.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 Times a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (50)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (28.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (55.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Listening to radio</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rarely</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 Times a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (71.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (88.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (60)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reading</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rarely</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (44.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (40)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 Times a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (50)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (40)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:DarkGray;" rowspan="1"><bold>DURING THE FIRST 3&#x02009;MONTHS POST-STROKE</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Listening to music</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Data missing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rarely</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 Times a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (28.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (85.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (88.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Listening to audio books</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Data missing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (71.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (100)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (85.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rarely</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 Times a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hours per day listening to group material<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.484 (T)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (0.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076 (T)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:DarkGray;" rowspan="1"><bold>DURING 3&#x02013;6&#x02009;MONTHS POST-STROKE</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Listening to music</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Data missing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (28.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rarely</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (30)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 Times a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (28.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (57.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (50)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (44.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Listening to audio books</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001 (K)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004 (K)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Data missing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (85.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (88.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (85.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rarely</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Once a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 Times a week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (40)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Data shown as frequency (percentage) unless otherwise stated. MG, music group; ABG, audio book group; CG, control group; K, Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test; T, <italic>t</italic>-test</italic>.</p><fn id="tfn2"><p><italic><sup>a</sup>Music listening in the MG and audio book listening in the ABG [data are mean (SD)]</italic>/</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S2-2"><title>Intervention</title><p>As soon as possible after their enrollment to the study (mean 8.8&#x02009;days post-stroke, range 3&#x02013;21&#x02009;days), the MG and ABG patients were individually contacted by a music therapist. In the MG, the therapist provided the patients with portable CD players and CDs of their own favorite music in any musical genre (mostly popular music with lyrics but also jazz, folk, or classical music). Similarly, the therapist provided the ABG with portable players and self-selected narrated audio books. The patients were trained in using the players and were instructed to listen to the material by themselves daily (for a minimum of 1&#x02009;h per day) for the following 2&#x02009;months in addition to standard care and rehabilitation. After this intervention period (3-month stage), they were encouraged to continue listening to the material on their own. In order to ensure that the patients were able to engage in the listening protocol, the therapist kept close weekly contact with the patients and the nurses and/or relatives of the patients were asked to help. Frequency of listening was verified from the listening diaries, which the patients kept during the intervention period and from questionnaires at the 3- and 6-month stages. The CG was not given any listening material and received only the standard care and rehabilitation during the follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="S2-3"><title>MRI data acquisition</title><p>Structural MRI was performed within 2&#x02009;weeks of stroke onset and 6&#x02009;months post-stroke using the 1.5&#x02009;T Siemens Vision scanner of the HUCH Department of Radiology. Clinically, the MRI was used by two experienced neuroradiologists (authors Taina Autti and Heli M. Silvennoinen) to verify the stroke diagnosis and to evaluate the size and location of the lesion. The MRI sequence included a 3D set of high-resolution T1 images (<italic>T</italic><sub>E</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.68&#x02009;ms, <italic>T</italic><sub>R</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1900&#x02009;ms, <italic>T</italic><sub>I</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1100&#x02009;ms, flip angle 15&#x000b0;, isotropic voxel size of 1&#x02009;mm<sup>3</sup>), which were used in the present VBM analysis. In addition, also a smaller set of fluid-attenuated inversion recovery (2D FLAIR) images, which are sensitive to acute infarcts, were acquired and used in accurately locating the lesion area, especially in the acute stage.</p></sec><sec id="S2-4"><title>Voxel-based morphometry analysis</title><p>Morphometric analysis was carried out using VBM (Ashburner and Friston, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) and Statistical Parametric Mapping software (SPM8; The Welcome Department of Imaging Neuroscience, London) under MATLAB 7.8.0 (The MathWorks Inc., Natick, MA, USA). The normalization of brain images is a prerequisite in any multi-subject voxel-wise MRI data analysis and especially important when dealing with abnormal brains. In order to achieve an accurate segmentation and normalization of lesioned GM and WM tissue, Unified Segmentation (Ashburner and Friston, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) with medium regularization and cost function masking (CFM) was applied to the structural T1-weighted images of each subject (Brett et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). The cost function masks were defined by manually depicting for each patient at each time (acute and 6-month stage) binary lesion masks of the lesioned tissue using the MRIcron software package<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref> (Rorden and Brett, <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). This technique has been widely used with patients suffering from stroke (Crinion et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Andersen et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Ripoll&#x000e9;s et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), achieving optimal normalization with no post-registration lesion shrinkage or out-of-brain distortion (Ripoll&#x000e9;s et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). During normalization, the GM and WM images were modulated in order to preserve the total amount of the signal. The resulting normalized GM and WM tissue probability maps were smoothed by using an isotropic spatial filter (FWHM&#x02009;=&#x02009;6&#x02009;mm) to reduce residual inter-individual variability.</p><p>All normalized and smoothed GM and WM images were further analyzed in order to compare the differences in the GMV or white matter volume (WMV). Because the processing of music and speech are generally known to involve the left and right hemispheres to a different degree (e.g., Zatorre et al., <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Tervaniemi and Hugdahl, <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) and they are therefore differentially affected by lesion laterality, we performed separate analyses for the LHD patients (MG: <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7, ABG: <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8, CG: <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) and the RHD patients (MG: <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9, ABG: <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10, CG: <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7). Thus, four separate mixed-design analysis of variance (ANOVA) models (GMV&#x02013;LHD, GMV&#x02013;RHD, WMV&#x02013;LHD, WMV&#x02013;RHD) were built with Group (MG/ABG/CG) as a between-subjects variable and Time (acute stage/6-month stage) as a within-subjects variable (thereby ensuring that each subject acted as its own control). Total intracranial volume (TIV) was included as a nuisance variable in order to correct for global differences for head size. Three different Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interactions were calculated: MG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CG and ABG, ABG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CG and MG, CG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;MG and ABG. In other words, we tested if the increments in post&#x02013;pre GMV in one group (e.g., MG) were greater than in the other two groups (e.g., CG and ABG). In addition, <italic>post hoc</italic> paired <italic>t</italic>-tests were planned to check the direction of the effect of Time within each Group (6&#x02009;months&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;acute). It has been suggested that combined intensity and cluster size thresholds such as <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005 with a 10 voxel extent produce a desirable balance between Type I and Type II errors (Lieberman and Cunningham, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Taking a slightly more stringent approach, the results are reported in tables at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 (uncorrected threshold) with a cluster size of &#x02265;50 voxels of spatial extent. For the sake of visual clarity, results are shown in figures at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (uncorrected threshold), although only clusters reported in the tables are labeled and commented throughout the text. Anatomical and cytoarchitectonical areas were identified using the Automated Anatomical Labeling (Tzourio-Mazoyer et al., <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) and the Talairach Daemon database atlases (Lancaster et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) included in the xjView toolbox<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref>.</p><p>Finally, for any cluster of voxels where a significant Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interaction was found, mean GMV or WMV increase (6&#x02009;months&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute stage) was calculated for each patient and correlated with behavioral changes (also 6&#x02009;months&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute stage) in cognitive tests and mood scales. For the cognitive measures, changes in the summary scores of the tests measuring the following cognitive domains were included: verbal memory, short-term and working memory, language skills, visuospatial cognition, executive functions, focused attention (correct responses and reactions times), and sustained attention (correct responses and reactions times; for details, see S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Similarly, for the mood measures, changes in the eight Profile of Mood States (POMS) scales (tension, depression, irritability, vigor, fatigue, inertia, confusion, and forgetfulness) were included (for details, see S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3-5"><title>Gray and white matter volume changes during recovery</title><p>Significant GMV increases were found post-intervention (6&#x02009;months&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) for all three groups of LHD patients (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) and RHD patients (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Areas identified were mostly located in the temporal, frontal, motor, limbic, and cerebellar brain regions, especially in the contralesional hemisphere, with the largest and most extensive volume increases occurring in the MG.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><bold>GMV increases (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in LHD patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical area</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNI coordinates</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left cerebellum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;14 &#x02212;59 &#x02212;40</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right temporal pole (BA 38)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 5 &#x02212;20</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right cerebellum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 &#x02212;59 &#x02212;42</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left pons</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7 &#x02212;29 &#x02212;35</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right posterior cingulate gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 &#x02212;40 24</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right calcarine/cuneus (BA 17, 18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 &#x02212;77 12</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1084</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left cerebellum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7 &#x02212;53 &#x02212;17</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right pons</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18 &#x02212;35 &#x02212;42</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right calcarine (BA 17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#x02212;82 4</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right precentral gyrus (BA 6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 0 31</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left ventral/subgenual anterior cingulate cortex (BA 10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10 34 &#x02212;3</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior frontal gyrus (BA 32, 6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 4 51</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">588</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right middle frontal gyrus (BA 32, 9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 24 39</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1367</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 13 21</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right ventral striatum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 15 &#x02212;11</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">484</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right fusiform gyrus (BA 19)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 &#x02212;45 &#x02212;9</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right orbitofrontal cortex (BA 11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 44 &#x02212;6</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior frontal gyrus (BA 10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 51 2</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">490</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior medial frontal gyrus (BA 8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 32 51</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right precuneus (BA 7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 &#x02212;53 46</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right posterior cingulate gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 &#x02212;40 25</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">471</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right ventral striatum/globus pallidum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 6 &#x02212;2</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left supplementary motor area</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11 10 50</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Results are reported at a <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 (uncorrected threshold) with 50 voxels of spatial extent. CG, control group; ABG, audio book group; MG, music group; BA, Brodmann area</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>GMV increases (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in LHD patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;23)</bold>. Lesion overlap indicating the number of patients with damage at a particular voxel and GMV increases within the three groups are shown in blue&#x02013;green&#x02013;red and red&#x02013;yellow, respectively. Neurological convention is used. Results are shown at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (uncorrected) with &#x02265;50 voxels of spatial extent and overlaid over a canonical template with MNI coordinates at the bottom right of each slice. Only clusters surviving a <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 threshold are labeled (see also Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). TP, temporal pole; PCG, posterior cingulate gyrus; Cr, cerebellum; PrCG, precentral gyrus; Calc, calcarine; Prec, precuneus; SFG, superior frontal gyrus; VS, ventral striatum; IFG, inferior frontal gyrus; SACC, ventral/subgenual anterior cingulate cortex; OFC, orbitofrontal cortex; FfG, fusiform gyrus; L, left hemisphere; R, right hemisphere.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00245-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><bold>GMV increases (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in RHD patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;26)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical area</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNI coordinates</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left supramarginal gyrus (BA 40)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44 &#x02212;28 28</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1597</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left thalamus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15 &#x02212;6 6</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">946</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left brainstem</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4 &#x02212;20 &#x02212;10</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">695</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior temporal lobe (BA 20, 21)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;44 &#x02212;5 &#x02212;35</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right cerebellum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 &#x02212;42 &#x02212;25</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left sup./mid. occipital gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21 &#x02212;86 12</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left cuneus (BA 18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5 &#x02212;85 22</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left orbitofrontal cortex (BA 47)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16 25 &#x02212;21</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left cerebellum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9 &#x02212;52 &#x02212;40</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">874</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left posterior cingulum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12 &#x02212;43 21</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right posterior cingulum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 &#x02212;43 26</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left middle cingulum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12 &#x02212;11 35</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">546</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right orbitofrontal cortex (BA 10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 53 1</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right cerebellum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 &#x02212;71 &#x02212;51</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left thalamus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15 &#x02212;6 11</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left insula</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33 &#x02212;14 10</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left precuneus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20 &#x02212;50 14</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left precentral gyrus (BA 6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;29 &#x02212;11 45</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left postcentral gyrus (BA 4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;43 &#x02212;17 51</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right precuneus (BA 31)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 &#x02212;45 21</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1544</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left post/middle/ant cingulate gyrus; left sup./mid. frontal gyrus; left supp. motor area; left inferior frontal gyrus; <italic>pars triangularis</italic> (BA 32, 31, 24, 9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10 &#x02212;12 34</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11173</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left supramarginal gyrus; left postcentral gyrus (BA 40)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48 &#x02212;23 27</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1472</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior frontal gyrus; left precentral gyrus (BA 6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42 9 17</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">799</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right middle cingulate gyrus (BA 24)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 30 26</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">970</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left orbitofrontal cortex (BA 47, 11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;25 23 &#x02212;16</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1661</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inf./mid. temporal gyrus (BA 20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;46 &#x02212;5 &#x02212;31</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">717</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left fusiform gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34 &#x02212;17 &#x02212;27</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left insula</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34 &#x02212;12 &#x02212;7</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">387</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left parahippocampal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 &#x02212;65 &#x02212;38</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right cerebellum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 31 &#x02212;11</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right anterior cingulate (BA 32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 43 4</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left precentral gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34 5 35</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;56 &#x02212;46 &#x02212;8</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right fusiform gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 &#x02212;42 &#x02212;16</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Results are reported at a <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 (uncorrected threshold) with 50 voxels of spatial extent. CG, control group; ABG, audio book group; MG, music group; BA, Brodmann area</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>GMV increases (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in RHD patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;26)</bold>. Lesion overlap indicating the number of patients with damage at a particular voxel and GMV increases within the three groups are shown in blue&#x02013;green&#x02013;red and red&#x02013;yellow, respectively. Neurological convention is used. Results are shown at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (uncorrected) with &#x02265;50 voxels of spatial extent and overlaid over a canonical template with MNI coordinates at the bottom right of each slice. Only clusters surviving a <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 threshold are labeled (see also Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). SMG, supramarginal gyrus; Th, thalamus; ITG, inferior temporal gyrus; Bstm, brainstem; MCG, middle cingulate gyrus; PCG, posterior cingulate gyrus; Cr, cerebellum; PrCG, precentral gyrus; In, insula; PoCG, postcentral gyrus; IFG, inferior frontal gyrus; MTG, middle temporal gyrus; FfG, fusiform gyrus; L, left hemisphere; R, right hemisphere.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00245-g002"/></fig><p>In LHD patients, significant Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interactions in GMV were found for the MG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;ABG and CG contrast (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) in five different clusters: three in frontal areas [left and right superior frontal gyrus (SFG) and right medial SFG] and two in limbic areas [left ventral/subgenual anterior cingulate cortex (SACC) and right ventral striatum (VS) / globus pallidum). The reversed contrasts (ABG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CG and MG, CG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;MG and ABG) did not yield any significant regions.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><bold>GMV increases (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in the MG compared to the ABG and CG (LHD patients)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical area</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNI coordinates</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior frontal gyrus (BA 32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 25 38</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left ventral/subgenual anterior cingulate cortex (BA 10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10 37 &#x02212;4</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right medial superior frontal gyrus (BA 8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 32 51</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right ventral striatum/globus pallidum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 5 &#x02212;3</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left superior frontal gyrus (BA 32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;13 21 38</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Time&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Group interaction (MG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;ABG and CG) at a <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 (uncorrected threshold) with 50 voxels of spatial extent. BA, Brodmann area</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>GMV increases (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in the MG compared to the ABG and CG (LHD patients)</bold>. Blue&#x02013;green&#x02013;red: lesion overlap indicating the number of patients showing damage at a particular voxel. Red&#x02013;yellow: GMV increases for the MG compared to the ABG and CG (Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interaction, MG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;ABG and CG contrast). Bar graphs indicate GMV increases (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM) for each of the clusters showing an interaction effect (white: CG, gray: ABG, black: MG). Neurological convention is used. Results are shown at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (uncorrected) with &#x02265;50 voxels of spatial extent and overlaid over a canonical template with MNI coordinates at the bottom right of each slice (see also Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). L, left hemisphere.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00245-g003"/></fig><p>In RHD patients, there were no significant Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interactions in GMV in any area at the selected threshold (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 uncorrected). However, when using a slightly more lenient threshold (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005 uncorrected), a single cluster emerged in the left insula (MNI &#x02212;33 &#x02212;6 &#x02212;8; 73 voxels of extent; <italic>t</italic>(22)&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.36) for the MG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;ABG and CG contrast (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Again, no other clusters were found using the reversed contrasts (ABG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CG and MG, CG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;MG and ABG) at this same threshold.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>GMV increases (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in the MG compared to the ABG and CG (RHD patients)</bold>. Blue&#x02013;green&#x02013;red: lesion overlap indicating the number of patients showing damage at a particular voxel. Red&#x02013;yellow: GMV increases for the MG compared to the ABG and CG (Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interaction, MG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;ABG, and CG contrast). Bar graphs (left) indicate GMV increases (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM) for the only cluster (left insula) showing an interaction effect (white: CG, gray: ABG, black: MG). The scatter plot (right) shows the relationship between GMV increase in the insula cluster and improvement in language skills. Neurological convention is used. Results are shown at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (uncorrected) with &#x02265;50 voxels of spatial extent and overlaid over a canonical template with MNI coordinates at the bottom right of each slice. L, left hemisphere.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00245-g004"/></fig><p>There were no significant Time effects or Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interactions in the WMV in LHD or RHD patients.</p></sec><sec id="S3-6"><title>Correlation between gray matter changes and behavioral recovery</title><p>In order to determine the functional relevance of the observed GMV increases induced by the music listening intervention, we performed correlation analyses with the longitudinal behavioral data (also 6&#x02009;months&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute). In LHD patients, the increase in GMV in the identified frontal areas correlated significantly with improvement in verbal memory, language skills, and focused attention (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref> for individual cluster correlations; in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> the frontal clusters are pooled together for illustrative purposes). Similarly, increase in GMV in the limbic regions (left SACC) was significantly correlated with a decrease in self-reported depression, tension, fatigue, forgetfulness, and irritability and marginally correlated also with a decrease in self-reported confusion. In RHD patients, the GMV increases in the left insula cluster were also found to correlate with the improvement of language skills (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.63, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.002; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). There were no other significant correlations.</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p><bold>Correlation between GMV increase and behavioral change (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in LHD patients</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical area</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioral measure</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>r</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frontal clusters pooled together</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verbal memory</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focused attention (correct responses)</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focused attention (reaction times)</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.45</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Right superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verbal memory</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focused attention (correct responses)</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Left superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verbal memory</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focused attention (reaction times)</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.61</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Right medial superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focused attention (correct responses)</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limbic cluster spooled together</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Left ventral/subgenual anterior cingulate gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.61</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.41</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tension</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.48</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.65</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forgetfulness</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.55</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irritability</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.45</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Right ventral striatum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." charoff="50" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) correlations and linear trends (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1) between the GM volume increases and changes in the summary scores of cognitive tests and the Profile of Mood States (POMS) mood scores [see S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al. (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) for details] during follow-up (6&#x02009;months&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute). Correlations are shown for individual clusters and for groups of clusters within frontal and limbic areas</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Correlation between GMV increase and behavioral change (6-month&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;acute) in LHD patients</bold>. Red&#x02013;yellow: GMV increases for the MG compared to the ABG and CG (Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interaction). Scatter plots show the relationship between GMV increases and improvements in mood (left ventral/subgenual anterior cingulate cluster) and cognitive variables (three frontal clusters pooled together). Neurological convention is used. Results are shown at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (uncorrected) with &#x02265;50 voxels of spatial extent and overlaid over a canonical template with MNI coordinates at the bottom right of each slice (see also Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). L, left hemisphere.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnhum-08-00245-g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The novel key finding of the present VBM study was that regular music listening during the 6-month post-stroke stage can lead to structural reorganization in the recovering brain. Specifically, compared with patients who listened daily to audio books (ABG) or who did not receive any additional listening material (CG), the patients who listened daily to their own favorite music (MG) showed more increase in GMV from the acute to the 6-month stage in a network of frontolimbic areas, primarily in the healthy contralesional side but also perilesionally. Importantly, the observed GMV increases in this network were directly associated with the behavioral improvement in cognitive functioning and reduction in negative mood shown previously for music listening (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Forsblom et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The area-specific correlations obtained (attention, memory, and language for frontal areas; mood for limbic regions), the lack of differences in the reversed contrasts (ABG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CG and MG, CG&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;MG and ABG), and the fact that effects emerge in areas that have previously been found to be closely associated with music processing and cognitive/emotional processing (see below), argue against our results being false positives. Moreover, given that the patient groups were comparable at baseline and the potential effects of other types of rehabilitation (standard stroke rehabilitation) and activities (audio book listening) were controlled for, these findings suggest that a musically enriched environment can be beneficial for acute stroke recovery and that neuroplastic changes in the frontolimbic network may underlie its efficacy.</p><p>In the present study, the frontal GMV increases associated with music listening in LHD patients were located in the left and right SFG and the right medial SFG and correlated with the improvement of verbal memory, language skills, and focused attention over the 6-month follow-up. These correlations are well in line with the previous findings of the study showing that music listening enhanced the recovery of verbal memory and focused attention more than audio book listening or standard care both 3 and 6&#x02009;months post-stroke (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). In addition, in the original data (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;54), there was also a slight trend toward a group difference in the domain of language [mixed-model ANOVA, Group&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Time interaction, <italic>F</italic>(2.4, 51.9)&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.2, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.108)] over the 6-month follow-up, with more improvement in the MG than in the ABG (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.096), suggesting that the correlation between GMV and language skills is also meaningful. In previous MEG and fMRI studies on music, the activity of the SFG has been linked to melody discrimination and production (Brown et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Lappe et al., <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), processing the emotional valence of music (Escoffier et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and musical episodic memory (Platel et al., <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Cognitively, evidence from neuroimaging and lesion studies suggests that the SFG is involved in many domain-general cognitive functions, such as attention and working memory (du Boisgueheneuc et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Huang et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and together with the dorsal anterior cingulate cortex (DACC) it forms one key component of the <italic>salience/central executive network</italic> (Dosenbach et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Interestingly, the DACC/SFG area seems to have a role also in language processing, including internally generated speech (Blank et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), and its activity has recently been linked also to aphasia recovery (Brownsett et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Structural and functional changes in the SFG have also been reported following meditation practice (Kang et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and cognitive training (Hoekzema et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), suggesting that changes in SFG are associated with improved cognition.</p><p>In addition to the frontal areas, we also found GMV increases induced by the music listening in LHD patients in two limbic areas: the left SACC and the right VS. Moreover, the GMV increase in the left SACC correlated with the reduction of negative mood (depression, confusion, tension, fatigue, forgetfulness, and irritability) in the POMS questionnaire. Again, this finding is well in line with our previous behavioral results showing that the music listening reduced depression and confusion more than standard care (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and was also subjectively associated with better relaxation and positive mood than the audio book listening (Forsblom et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Generally, the VS is considered to be a key part of the neural circuitry for reward and pleasure, and its dysfunction is associated with anhedonia, a hallmark symptom of depression (Der-Avakian and Markou, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Eslinger et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The nucleus accumbens (NAc) and parts of the caudate nucleus and putamen, the dopaminergic VS, have been strongly implicated in neuroimaging studies as underlying the emotional experience of music (Blood and Zatorre, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Brown et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Menon and Levitin, <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Koelsch et al., <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Mitterschiffthaler et al., <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Montag et al., <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Salimpoor et al., <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). fMRI studies have implicated also the anterior cingulate in processing musical emotions (Brown et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Mitterschiffthaler et al., <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Green et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Janata, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Escoffier et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), musical preferences (Berns et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Kitayama et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), rhythm and melody perception (Jerde et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Lee et al., <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and production (Brown et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Berkowitz and Ansari, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), and singing (Kleber et al., <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Zarate and Zatorre, <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Generally, the ventral-rostral part of the ACC has a regulatory role in generating emotional responses, and its abnormal functioning has been linked to many psychiatric conditions (Etkin et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In depressed patients, the activity of both the ACC and the VS to pleasant music has been found to be reduced compared to healthy controls (Osuch et al., <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Aust et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In VBM studies, GM loss in the ACC has been linked to impaired recognition of musical emotions in frontotemporal dementia (Omar et al., <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and has also been documented as a key neuroanatomical component in the etiology of major depression (Grieve et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Lai, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>One possible interpretation for the increase in GMV in the subgenual part of the ACC could be related to the role of this subregion in affective appraisal, integration of emotional and motivational states, self-referential mental processing, and introspective thought (Northoff and Bermpohl, <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Vago and Silbersweig, <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Interestingly, Greicius et al. (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) found using PET that the resting-state SACC activity was linked to the <italic>default-mode network</italic> in depressed patients and also correlated with the length of the depressive episode. In a recent fMRI study (Yoshimura et al., <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">in press</xref>), the activity of medial prefrontal cortex and ventral ACC during a task of self-referential processing of positive emotional trait words was also observed to increase in depressed patients following cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), suggesting that these areas are also linked to the amelioration of depression. Thus, given that pleasant and autobiographically salient music can activate the ventral ACC (Janata, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) and that music listening was also observed to evoke thoughts and memories about the past and improve mood in our stroke patients (Forsblom et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), it is possible that positive self-referential emotional processing associated with music listening could be driving the observed structural enhancement of the SACC and the concurrent reduction in depressed mood.</p><p>Within the RHD subgroup of patients, we observed more GMV increase in the MG compared to the other groups in a single contralesional (left) cluster in the insula, which also correlated with the recovery of language skills. Since this was seen only using a slightly less stringent statistical threshold (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005 uncorrected) and the RHD&#x02013;MG listened to the intervention material slightly more often than the RHD&#x02013;ABG (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.076), this result should thus be interpreted with some caution. Although less is known about the specific role of the insula in music or language, current evidence from neuroimaging links it to the affective processing of music (Brown et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Menon and Levitin, <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Koelsch et al., <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Montag et al., <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Omar et al., <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Trost et al., <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) and voice (Blasi et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), musical creativity and improvisation (Brown et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Engel and Keller, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Villarreal et al., <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and perception of melody (Wehrum et al., <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and chords (Koelsch et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) as well as to verbal functions, especially speech articulation (Ackermann and Riecker, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Price, <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Baldo et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Overall, there was clearly less music-induced GM reorganization in RHD patients than in LHD patients. One reason for this could be that the lesions in the right hemisphere were, on the average, larger and more extensive than in the left hemisphere (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.044). Coupled with the fact that there is a level of right hemisphere dominance for music processing (Zatorre et al., <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Tervaniemi and Hugdahl, <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) and, consequently, the majority of the RHD patients had some degree of amusia (see S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>, <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2010b</xref>), it is possible that the music was not to able to engage the musical brain network in RHD patients to the same degree as in LHD patients. In addition, our sample size was relatively small (26 RHD patients and 23 LHD patients) and there was also considerable variability in the location and size of the lesions (see Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, top row), which together can affect the sensitivity of the VBM analysis to detect potential volumetric changes over time, especially in the lesioned hemisphere. Thus, larger studies with more homogenous lesion characteristics are called for in the future to verify and extend the current findings.</p><p>In general, the exact anatomical nature of the GM and WM changes observed with the VBM method is still not understood very well - in VBM, a change in &#x0201c;volume&#x0201d; essentially refers to a change in GM intensity in the images (not the real volume of neurons, for instance) and is therefore non-specific with respect to the underlying tissue characteristics. According to the current view, the potential mechanisms for GM reorganization include axon sprouting, dendritic branching and synaptogenesis, neurogenesis, changes in glial number and morphology, and angiogenesis (Zatorre et al., <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). These cellular changes as well as changes in neurotrophic and neural growth factor levels have been documented also in animal studies of post-stroke EE (Biernaskie and Corbett, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Johansson and Belichenko, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Gobbo and O&#x02019;Mara, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Komitova et al., <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Matsumori et al., <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; S&#x000f6;derstr&#x000f6;m et al., <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) and auditory EE in healthy developing animals (Engineer et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Angelucci et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Nichols et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Bose et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), providing experimental support for the enhanced cerebral reorganization induced by the musically enriched recovery environment in the present study.</p><p>In conclusion, the present study shows that daily music listening during the first month post-stroke stage can lead to fine-grained structural reorganization (as indicated by increased GMV) in a network of frontolimbic brain areas. Importantly, given that the frontolimbic plastic changes were also directly related to the cognitive and emotional recovery previously shown to be enhanced by music (S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6; et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Forsblom et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), these findings provide a plausible neuroanatomical correlate for the efficacy of music after stroke. At a more general level, they also provide the first evidence in humans that not only active therapist-led rehabilitation but also environmental enrichment has the potential to shape the structure of the recovering brain.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We wish to express our gratitude to the staff of the HUCH Department of Neurology and Department of Radiology and other rehabilitation hospitals in the Helsinki metropolitan area for their collaboration, and especially to the patient subjects and their families for their participation and effort. We also wish to thank Mari Tervaniemi, Isabelle Peretz, Matti Laine, and Marja Hietanen for their assistance and expertise in planning the study. This work was funded by the Academy of Finland (grants no 77322, 141106, and 257077), the Jenny and Antti Wihuri Foundation (Helsinki, Finland), the National Doctoral Programme on Psychology (Finland), and the Finnish Brain Foundation.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mccauslandcenter.sc.edu/mricro/mricron/index.html">http://www.mccauslandcenter.sc.edu/mricro/mricron/index.html</uri></p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.alivelearn.net/xjview8/">http://www.alivelearn.net/xjview8/</uri></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ackermann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riecker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The contribution(s) of the insula to speech production: a review of the clinical and functional imaging literature</article-title>. <source>Brain Struct. Funct.</source><volume>214</volume>, <fpage>419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-010-0257-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20512374?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20512374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alluri</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toiviainen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000e4;&#x000e4;skel&#x000e4;inen</surname><given-names>I. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glerean</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sams</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brattico</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Large-scale brain networks emerge from dynamic processing of musical timbre, key and rhythm</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>3677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.11.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22116038?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22116038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altenm&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marco-Pallar&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nte</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Neural reorganization underlies improvement in stroke-induced motor dysfunction by music-supported therapy</article-title>. <source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>1169</volume>, <fpage>395</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04580.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19673814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19673814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapcsak</surname><given-names>S. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeson</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Cost function masking during normalization of brains with focal lesions: still a necessity?</article-title>
<source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.06.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20542122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20542122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angelucci</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Padua</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonali</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Investigating the neurobiology of music: brain-derived neurotrophic factor modulation in the hippocampus of young adult mice</article-title>. <source>Behav. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/fbp.0b013e3282d28f50</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17762517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17762517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Voxel-based morphometry &#x02013; the methods</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2000.0582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10860804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Unified segmentation</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.02.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15955494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15955494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aust</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filip</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koelsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bajbouj</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Music in depression: neural correlates of emotional experience in remitted depression</article-title>. <source>World J. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5498/wjp.v3.i2.8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24175181?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24175181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldo</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dronkers</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Role of the precentralgyrus of the insula in complex articulation</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>800</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cortex.2010.07.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20691968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20691968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ull&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrsson</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kito</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Listening to rhythms activates motor and premotor cortices</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cortex.2008.07.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19041965?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19041965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkowitz</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Generation of novel motor sequences: the neural correlates of musical improvisation</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.02.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18420426?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18420426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berns</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capra</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noussair</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Neural mechanisms of the influence of popularity on adolescent ratings of music</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>2687</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.070</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19879365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19879365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biernaskie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Enriched rehabilitative training promotes improved forelimb motor function and enhanced dendritic growth after focal ischemic injury</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>5272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5280</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11438602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Speech production: Wernicke, Broca and beyond</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<volume>125</volume>, <fpage>1829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awf191</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12135973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blasi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercure</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd-Fox</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brammer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Early specialization for voice and emotion processing in the infant brain</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1220</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2011.06.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21723130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21723130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blood</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Intensely pleasurable responses to music correlate with activity in brain regions implicated in reward and emotion</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>11818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.191355898</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11573015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11573015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Llancao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roychowdhury</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakkamsetti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Effect of the environment on the dendritic morphology of the rat auditory cortex</article-title>. <source>Synapse</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/syn.20710</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19771593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19771593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breier</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juranek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papanicolaou</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Changes in maps of language function and the integrity of the arcuate fasciculus after therapy for chronic aphasia</article-title>. <source>Neurocase</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13554794.2010.547505</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22111962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22111962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leff</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rorden</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Spatial normalization of brain images with focal lesions using cost function masking</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2001.0845</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11467921?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11467921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Passive music listening spontaneously engages limbic and paralimbic systems</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>2033</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/wnr.0b013e3282fd0dd8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15486477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15486477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Music and language side by side in the brain: a PET study of the generation of melodies and sentences</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2006.04785.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16817882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16817882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brownsett</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geranmayeh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodhead</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leech</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Cognitive control and its impact on recovery from aphasic stroke</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<volume>137</volume>, <fpage>242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awt289</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24163248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24163248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bugos</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlstein</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrae</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brophy</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedenbaugh</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Individualized piano instruction enhances executive functioning and working memory in older adults</article-title>. <source>Aging Ment. Health</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13607860601086504</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17612811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17612811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crinion</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Spatial normalization of lesioned brains: performance evaluation and impact on fMRI analyses</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>866</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.04.065</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17616402?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Longitudinal cortical volume changes correlate with motor recovery in patients after acute local subcortical infarction</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>2795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.113.000971</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23929747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23929747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Der-Avakian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The neurobiology of anhedonia and other reward-related deficits</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2011.11.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22177980?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22177980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dosenbach</surname><given-names>N. U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fair</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaggar</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A dual-networks architecture of top-down control</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2008.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18262825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18262825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>du Boisgueheneuc</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Volle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seassau</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffau</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinkingnehun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Functions of the left superior frontal gyrus in humans: a lesion study</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>3315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awl244</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16984899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16984899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The perception of musical spontaneity in improvised and imitated jazz performances</article-title>. <source>Front. Psychol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2011.00083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21738518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21738518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engineer</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Percaccio</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandya</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moucha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathbun</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilgard</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Environmental enrichment improves response strength, threshold, selectivity, and latency of auditory cortex neurons</article-title>. <source>J. Neurophysiol.</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00059.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15014105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escoffier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schirmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Emotional expressions in voice and music: same code, same effect?</article-title>
<source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.22029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22505222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22505222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eslinger</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Apathy in frontotemporal dementia: behavioral and neuroimaging correlates</article-title>. <source>Behav. Neurol.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/ben-2011-0351</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22425723?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22425723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalisch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Emotional processing in anterior cingulate and medial prefrontal cortex</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2010.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Dynamic brain structural changes after left hemisphere subcortical stroke</article-title>. <source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.22034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22431281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22431281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forsblom</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tervaniemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The effect of music and audio book listening on people recovering from stroke: the patient&#x02019;s point of view</article-title>. <source>Music Med.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1943862110378110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Brain structures differ between musicians and non-musicians</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>9240</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1053-8119(01)92488-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14534258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14534258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>L. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taub</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>V. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uswatte</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Remodeling the brain: plastic structural brain changes produced by different motor therapies after stroke</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1520</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.107.502229</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18323492?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18323492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gobbo</surname><given-names>O. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Mara</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Impact of enriched-environment housing on brain-derived neurotrophic factor and on cognitive performance after a transient global ischemia</article-title>. <source>Behav. Brain Res.</source>
<volume>152</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2003.10.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15196790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15196790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grau-Olivares</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arboix</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Junqu&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenaza-Urquijo</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovira</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartr&#x000e9;s-Faz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Progressive gray matter atrophy in lacunar patients with vascular mild cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source>Cerebrovasc. Dis.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000316059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20551631?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grau-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amengual</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veciana de Las Heras</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Plasticity in the sensorimotor cortex induced by music-supported therapy in stroke patients: a TMS study</article-title>. <source>Front. Hum. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2013.00494</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24027507?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24027507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baerentsen</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000f8;dkilde-J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallentin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roepstorff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuust</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Music in minor activates limbic structures: a relationship with dissonance?</article-title>
<source>Neuroreport</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WNR.0b013e3282fd0dd8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18418244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18418244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greicius</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solvason</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenna</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Resting-state functional connectivity in major depression: abnormally increased contributions from subgenual cingulate cortex and thalamus</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2006.09.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17210143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17210143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grieve</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korgaonkar</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koslow</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Widespread reductions in gray matter volume in depression</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage Clin.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>332</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2013.08.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24273717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halwani</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loui</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;ber</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Effects of practice and experience on the arcuate fasciculus: comparing singers, instrumentalists, and non-musicians</article-title>. <source>Front. Psychol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2011.00156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21779271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21779271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herdener</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Humbel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Habermeyer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattapan-Ludewig</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seifritz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Jazz drummers recruit language-specific areas for the processing of rhythmic structure</article-title>. <source>Cereb. Cortex</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>836</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhs367</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23183709?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23183709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoekzema</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremols</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gispert</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guitart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauquet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Enhanced neural activity in frontal and cerebellar circuits after cognitive training in children with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1942</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20988</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20336653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidman</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahveninen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Distinct cortical networks activated by auditory attention and working memory load</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>1098</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.07.074</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23921102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23921102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forgeard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Musical training shapes structural brain development</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>3019</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.5118-08.2009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19279238?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19279238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oechslin</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van De Ville</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauert</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Descloux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazyras</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Musical training yields opposite effects on grey matter density in cognitive versus sensorimotor networks</article-title>. <source>Brain Struct. Funct.</source>
<volume>219</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-013-0504-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23408267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23408267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janata</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The neural architecture of music-evoked autobiographical memories</article-title>. <source>Cereb. Cortex</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>2579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhp008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19240137?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19240137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janata</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birk</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Horn</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tillmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bharucha</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002a</year>). <article-title>The cortical topography of tonal structures underlying Western music</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>298</volume>, <fpage>2167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1076262</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12481131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12481131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janata</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tillmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bharucha</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002b</year>). <article-title>Listening to polyphonic music recruits domain-general attention and working memory circuits</article-title>. <source>Cogn. Aff. Behav. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/CABN.2.2.121</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12455680?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12455680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ada</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhardt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McElduff</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>An enriched environment increases activity in stroke patients undergoing rehabilitation in a mixed rehabilitation unit: a pilot non-randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Disabil. Rehabil.</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09638288.2013.788218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23627534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jerde</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handy</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagode</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Dissociable systems of working memory for rhythm and melody</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>1572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.05.061</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21645625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21645625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Functional and cellular effects of environmental enrichment after experimental brain infarcts</article-title>. <source>Restor. Neurol. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15502263?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15502263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Multisensory stimulation in stroke rehabilitation</article-title>. <source>Front. Hum. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2012.00060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22509159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belichenko</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Neuronal plasticity and dendritic spines: effect of environmental enrichment on intact and postischemic rat brain</article-title>. <source>J. Cereb. Blood Flow. Metab.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004647-200201000-00011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11807398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11807398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The effect of meditation on brain structure: cortical thickness mapping and diffusion tensor imaging</article-title>. <source>Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nss056</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22569185?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22569185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitayama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>H. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tompson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Neural mechanisms of dissonance: an fMRI investigation of choice justification</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.11.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23238432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23238432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleber</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birbaumer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veit</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trevorrow</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Overt and imagined singing of an Italian aria</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.02.053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17478107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17478107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koelsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Towards a neural basis of music-evoked emotions</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2010.01.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20153242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20153242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koelsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Toward a neural basis of music perception &#x02013; a review and updated model</article-title>. <source>Front. Psychol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2011.00110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21713060?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21713060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koelsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsop</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Adults and children processing music: an fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1068</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.12.050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15850725?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15850725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koelsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>V Cramon</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friederici</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Investigating emotion with music: an fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16078183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koelsch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sammler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friederici</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Music, language and meaning: brain signatures of semantic processing</article-title>. <source>Nat. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn1197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14983184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14983184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komitova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattsson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Enriched environment increases neural stem/progenitor cell proliferation and neurogenesis in the subventricular zone of stroke-lesioned adult rats</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>1278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.str.0000166197.94147.59</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15879324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15879324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Gray matter volume in major depressive disorder: a meta-analysis of voxel-based morphometry studies</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res.</source>
<volume>211</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pscychresns.2012.06.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23146253?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23146253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woldorff</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liotti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rainey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Automated Talairach atlas labels for functional brain mapping</article-title>. <source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0193(200007)</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10912591?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10912591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lappe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinstr&#x000e4;ter</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantev</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Rhythmic and melodic deviations in musical sequences recruit different cortical areas for mismatch detection</article-title>. <source>Front. Hum. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2013.00260</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23759929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23759929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janata</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Investigation of melodic contour processing in the brain using multivariate pattern-based fMRI</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.02.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21315158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21315158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Longitudinal investigations on the anterograde and retrograde degeneration in the pyramidal tract following pontine infarction with diffusion tensor imaging</article-title>. <source>Cerebrovasc. Dis.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000113858</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18216462?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Type I and Type II error concerns in fMRI research: re-balancing the scale</article-title>. <source>Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nsp052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20035017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20035017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maegele</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippert-Gruener</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ester-Bode</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouillon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neugebauer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005a</year>). <article-title>Multimodal early onset stimulation combined with enriched environment is associated with reduced CNS lesion volume and enhanced reversal of neuromotor dysfunction after traumatic brain injury in rats</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2005.04070.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15932599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15932599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maegele</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippert-Gruener</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ester-Bode</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauerland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;fer</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molcanyi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005b</year>). <article-title>Reversal of neuromotor and cognitive dysfunction in an enriched environment combined with multimodal early onset stimulation after traumatic brain injury in rats</article-title>. <source>J. Neurotrauma</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/neu.2005.22.772</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16004580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16004580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumori</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kayama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Enriched environment and spatial learning enhance hippocampal neurogenesis and salvages ischemic penumbra after focal cerebral ischemia</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol. Dis.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2005.10.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16361108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16361108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitin</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The rewards of music listening: response and physiological connectivity of the mesolimbic system</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.05.053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16023376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16023376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitterschiffthaler</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A functional MRI study of happy and sad affective states induced by classical music</article-title>. <source>Hum. Brain Mapp.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20337</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17290372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17290372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montag</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Axmacher</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>How one&#x02019;s favorite song activates the reward circuitry of the brain: personality matters! Behav</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>225</volume>, <fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2011.08.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21856337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21856337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakkamsetti</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgado</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinh</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilgard</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atzori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Environmental enrichment selectively increases glutamatergic responses in layer II/III of the auditory cortex of the rat</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>145</volume>, <fpage>832</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2006.12.061</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17291690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nithianantharajah</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Enriched environments, experience-dependent plasticity and disorders of the nervous system</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn1970</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16924259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16924259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Northoff</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bermpohl</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Cortical midline structures and the self</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2004.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15301749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henley</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailstone</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The structural neuroanatomy of music emotion recognition: evidence from frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>1814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.03.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21385617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21385617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osuch</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluhm</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000e9;berge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Brain activation to favorite music in healthy controls and depressed patients</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/wnr.0b013e32832f4da3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19617860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19617860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Platel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desgranges</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eustache</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Semantic and episodic memory of music are subserved by distinct neural networks</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>244</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1053-8119(03)00287-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14527585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The anatomy of language: a review of 100 fMRI studies published in 2009</article-title>. <source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>1191</volume>, <fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05444.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20392276?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20392276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ripoll&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marco-Pallar&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Diego-Balaguer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falip</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juncadella</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Analysis of automated methods for spatial normalization of lesioned brains</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>1296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.01.094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22305954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Fornells</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amengual</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripoll&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altenm&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nte</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The involvement of audio-motor coupling in the music-supported therapy applied to stroke patients</article-title>. <source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>1252</volume>, <fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2011.06425.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22524370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22524370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amengual</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juncadella</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camara</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marco-Pallar&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Music-supported therapy induces plasticity in the sensorimotor cortex in chronic stroke: a single-case study using multimodal imaging (fMRI-TMS)</article-title>. <source>Brain Inj.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/02699052.2011.576305</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21561296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21561296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rorden</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Stereotaxic display of brain lesions</article-title>. <source>Behav. Neurol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2000/421719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11568431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salimpoor</surname><given-names>V. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benovoy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larcher</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Anatomically distinct dopamine release during anticipation and experience of peak emotion to music</article-title>. <source>Nat. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2726</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21217764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salimpoor</surname><given-names>V. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Bosch</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacevic</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Interactions between the nucleus accumbens and auditory cortices predict music reward value</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>340</volume>, <fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1231059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23580531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23580531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pihko</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsblom</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soinila</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkonen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>). <article-title>Music and speech listening enhance the recovery of early sensory processing after stroke</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2009.21376</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19925203?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19925203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tervaniemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soinila</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Autti</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvennoinen</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>). <article-title>Auditory and cognitive deficits associated with acquired amusia after stroke: a magnetoencephalography and neuropsychological follow-up study</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e15157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015157</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21152040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21152040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tervaniemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsblom</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soinila</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkonen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Music listening enhances cognitive recovery and mood after middle cerebral artery stroke</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>866</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awn013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18287122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18287122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rk&#x000e4;m&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tervaniemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soinila</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Autti</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvennoinen</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Cognitive deficits associated with acquired amusia after stroke: a neuropsychological follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>2642</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2009.05.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19500606?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19500606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>From singing to speaking: why singing may lead to recovery of expressive language function in patients with Broca&#x02019;s aphasia</article-title>. <source>Music Percept.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/mp.2008.25.4.315</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21197418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21197418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlaug</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Evidence for plasticity in white-matter tracts of patients with chronic Broca&#x02019;s aphasia undergoing intense intonation-based speech therapy</article-title>. <source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>2009</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04587.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19673813?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19673813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000f6;derstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingridsson</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>17beta-estradiol and enriched environment accelerate cognitive recovery after focal brain ischemia</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2009.06662.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19302156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19302156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutoo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Music improves dopaminergic neurotransmission: demonstration based on the effect of music on blood pressure regulation</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>1016</volume>, <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2004.05.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15246862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15246862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tervaniemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugdahl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Lateralization of auditory-cortex functions</article-title>. <source>Brain Res. Rev.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainresrev.2003.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14629926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiebaut de Schotten</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomaiuolo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aiello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merola</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecce</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Damage to white matter pathways in subacute and chronic spatial neglect: a group study and 2 single-case studies with complete virtual &#x0201c;in vivo&#x0201d; tractography dissection</article-title>. <source>Cereb. Cortex</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>691</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhs351</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23162045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23162045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trost</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ethofer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zentner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuilleumier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Mapping aesthetic musical emotions in the brain</article-title>. <source>Cereb. Cortex</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhr353</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22178712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22178712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzourio-Mazoyer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landeau</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papathanassiou</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crivello</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Etard</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delcroix</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Automated anatomical labeling of activations in SPM using a macroscopic anatomical parcellation of the MNI MRI single-subject brain</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2001.0978</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11771995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11771995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vago</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silbersweig</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Self-awareness, self-regulation, and self-transcendence (S-ART): a framework for understanding the neurobiological mechanisms of mindfulness</article-title>. <source>Front. Hum. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>296</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2012.00296</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23112770?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Meer</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>van derMarel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijboer</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavelaars</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van derSprenkel</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Extent of bilateral neuronal network reorganization and functional recovery in relation to stroke severity</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>4495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.3662-11.2012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22457497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22457497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verghese</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derby</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuslansky</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Leisure activities and the risk of dementia in the elderly</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>348</volume>, <fpage>2508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa022252</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12815136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villarreal</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerquetti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>SchwarczL&#x000f3;pezAranguren</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerschcovich</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frega</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Neural correlates of musical creativity: differences between high and low creative subjects</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e75427</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075427</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24069414?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24069414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wehrum</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deg&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stippekohl</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagerer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Can you hear a difference? Neuronal correlates of melodic deviance processing in children</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>1402</volume>, <fpage>80</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2011.05.057</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21676378?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21676378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onoda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunisato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (in press). <article-title>Cognitive behavioral therapy for depression changes medial prefrontal and ventral anterior cingulate cortex activity associated with self-referential processing</article-title>. <source>Soc. Cogn. Affect. Neurosci.</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nst009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23327934?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23327934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B110"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarate</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Experience-dependent neural substrates involved in vocal pitch regulation during singing</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.01.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18343163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18343163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B111"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Predispositions and plasticity in music and speech learning: neural correlates and implications</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>342</volume>, <fpage>585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1238414</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24179219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24179219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B112"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penhune</surname><given-names>V. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Structure and function of auditory cortex: music and speech</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1364-6613(00)01816-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11849614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B113"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zatorre</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen-Berg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Plasticity in gray and white: neuroimaging changes in brain structure during learning</article-title>. <source>Nat. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>528</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3045</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22426254?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22426254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>