<?xml version="1.0"?>
Eur J PsychotraumatolEur J PsychotraumatolZEPTzept20European Journal of Psychotraumatology2000-8066Taylor &amp; Francis5400019130265210.1080/20008198.2017.1302652OtherPhD SummaryPreventing PTSD with oxytocin: effects of oxytocin administration on fear neurocircuitry and PTSD symptom development in recently trauma-exposed individualsFrijlingJessie L.
a

*
aDepartment of Psychiatry, Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, the NetherlandsCONTACT Jessie L. Frijling J.L.Frijling@amc.uva.nlDepartment of Psychiatry, Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, the Netherlands
Mentors
Miranda Olff (Department of Psychiatry, Academic Medical Centre, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, the Netherlands. Arq Psychotrauma Expert Group, Diemen, the Netherlands)Dick J. Veltman (Department of Psychiatry, VU University Medical Centre, Amsterdam, the Netherlands)Mirjam van Zuiden (Academic Medical Centre, University of Amsterdam, Department of Psychiatry, Amsterdam, the Netherlands)2017114201781130265212220171522017132017© 2017 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group.2017The Author(s)This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.ABSTRACT
Background: Posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is a debilitating psychiatric disorder which develops in approximately 10% of trauma-exposed individuals. Currently, there are few early preventive interventions available for PTSD. Intranasal oxytocin administration early posttrauma may prevent PTSD symptom development, as oxytocin administration was previously found to beneficially impact neurobiological (e.g. amygdala reactivity) and socio-emotional PTSD vulnerability factors.
Objective: The overall aim of this dissertation was to investigate the potential of intranasal oxytocin administration as early preventive intervention for PTSD.
Methods: We performed a functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) study to assess the acute effects of a single administration of oxytocin on the functional fear neurocircuitry – consisting of the amygdala and (pre)frontal brain regions – in recently trauma-exposed emergency department patients (range n = 37–41). In addition, we performed a multicentre randomized double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial (RCT) to assess the efficacy of repeated intranasal oxytocin administration early after trauma for preventing PTSD symptom development up to six months posttrauma (n = 107).
Results: In our fMRI experiments we observed acutely increased amygdala reactivity to fearful faces and attenuated amygdala-ventromedial and ventrolateral prefrontal cortex functional connectivity after a single oxytocin administration in recently trauma-exposed individuals. However, in our RCT we found that repeated intranasal oxytocin administration early posttrauma reduced subsequent PTSD symptom development in recently trauma-exposed emergency department patients with high acute PTSD symptoms.
Conclusions: These findings indicate that repeated intranasal oxytocin is a promising early preventive intervention for PTSD for individuals at increased risk for PTSD due to high acute symptom severity. Administration frequency dependent effects of oxytocin or the effects of oxytocin administration on salience processing may serve as explanatory frameworks for the contrasting oxytocin effects on anxiety-related measures in our clinical and neuroimaging studies.KEYWORDSPTSDearly interventionpreventionoxytocinamygdalafMRIAcademic Medical Center Research Council110614ZonMw10.13039/50110000182691210041This work was supported by the Academic Medical Centre Research Council [110614]; ZonMw [91210041].2. AimsThe overall aim of this dissertation was to investigate the potential of intranasal oxytocin administration as early preventive intervention for PTSD, by assessing the effects of intranasal oxytocin early after trauma on acute functioning of the fear neurocircuitry and on PTSD symptom development in recently trauma-exposed individuals. To this end, we performed a functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) study to assess the acute effects of a single administration of oxytocin on the functional fear neurocircuitry – consisting of the amygdala and (pre)frontal brain regions – in recently trauma-exposed emergency department patients. In addition, we performed a randomized controlled clinical trial to assess the efficacy of repeated intranasal oxytocin administration early after trauma for preventing PTSD symptom development.3. Summary of findings3.1. Part I – backgroundIn chapter 2 (Frijling et al., 2014b) we discussed the rationale behind our hypothesis that intranasal oxytocin administration may prevent the development of PTSD symptoms. Increased risk for PTSD development is associated with low levels of perceived social support, high heart rate, low heart rate variability, low cortisol levels, and high amygdala reactivity to negative stimuli as assessed early posttrauma. Modification of these vulnerability factors early posttrauma may reduce PTSD risk. A large body of evidence suggests that autonomic and glucocorticoid stress reactivity, neural fear responsiveness and social behaviour are all beneficially affected by endogenous oxytocin and (a single) oxytocin administration. Therefore, risk for PTSD may be attenuated by stimulating the oxytocin system in recently trauma-exposed individuals, for example by administering intranasal oxytocin.In chapter 3 (Olff et al., 2013) we described that oxytocin administration may improve mental health, as oxytocin administration appears to beneficially affect stress regulation and social behaviour. However, we showed based on previously published findings and novel experimental data that effects of oxytocin administration depend on context and interindividual differences. We argued that such differential effects of oxytocin administration may be related to oxytocin administration enhancing salience processing. Increased salience processing refers to increased processing of contextual cues that normally attract attention (i.e. emotional facial expressions, danger signals). Therefore, although evidence suggests that oxytocin administration may promote mental health given its important role in regulating social behaviour and stress, context and interindividual differences that influence the effects of oxytocin administration should be carefully considered in clinical studies on intranasal oxytocin.3.2. Part II – functional neuroimaging studiesWe assessed the acute effects of a single administration of intranasal oxytocin on the fear neurocircuitry in a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) study in trauma-exposed emergency department patients within 11 days posttrauma. In chapter 4 (Frijling et al., 2016a) we assessed the effects of oxytocin administration on amygdala reactivity to emotional faces, using a face-matching task with fearful, happy and neutral faces (n = 41). We observed that the effects of oxytocin administration on amygdala reactivity to emotional faces depended on stimulus valence and on sex. In all participants, oxytocin administration increased amygdala reactivity to fearful faces. Additionally, in women only, oxytocin administration increased amygdala reactivity to neutral faces. Our exploratory analysis showed that acute PTSD symptom severity was not associated with differential intranasal oxytocin administration effects on amygdala reactivity. Given these results we argued that a single intranasal administration of oxytocin may increase neural fear processing, possibly as a result of oxytocin-induced enhanced salience processing.In chapter 5 (Frijling et al., 2016b) we investigated oxytocin administration effects on amygdala-centred emotion and salience network functional connectivity after a trauma reminder, using neutral and trauma script-driven imagery (n = 37). For each participant two resting-state fMRI scans were acquired: one after listening to a personal neutral script, and the second after listening to a personal trauma script which was based on the recent traumatic event. We observed that oxytocin-treated participants had diminished amygdala-left ventrolateral prefrontal cortex (vlPFC) functional connectivity in response to the trauma script compared to the neutral script, whereas an increase in amygdala-left vlPFC functional connectivity was observed in placebo-treated participants. In addition, irrespective of script condition, oxytocin administration enhanced amygdala-left (posterior) insula functional connectivity and decreased amygdala-ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) functional connectivity. These neural oxytocin administration effects were accompanied by lower levels of sleepiness and higher flashback intensity after the trauma script in oxytocin-treated participants. Taken together, these observations indicate that that a single intranasal oxytocin administration may acutely impede emotion regulation in recently trauma-exposed individuals.3.3. Part III – randomized controlled clinical trialChapter 6 (Frijling et al., 2014a) describes the study protocol of our randomized double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial, in which we investigated the effects of repeated intranasal oxytocin administration on PTSD symptom development in distressed recently trauma-exposed emergency department patients. The primary aim was to investigate the effects of an eight-day intranasal oxytocin treatment regimen initiated within 12 days posttrauma on PTSD symptoms at 1.5 month posttrauma. One of our secondary aims was to assess the effects of repeated oxytocin administration on PTSD, depression and anxiety symptoms at 1.5, three and six months posttrauma. We additionally investigated whether baseline characteristics moderated the effects of repeated oxytocin administration on symptom severity scores, given previous observations that oxytocin administration effects depend on interindividual differences.In chapter 7 (van Zuiden et al., 2016) the results of our clinical trial are presented. We demonstrated that there was no overall effect of repeated oxytocin administration on PTSD, depression and anxiety symptoms up to six months posttrauma (n = 107). However, the effects of oxytocin administration were moderated by acute PTSD symptom severity assessed prior to the intervention. Oxytocin administration reduced PTSD symptoms up to six months posttrauma in trauma-exposed individuals with high acute PTSD symptoms only. These findings suggest that an eight-day intranasal oxytocin treatment regimen is a promising preventive early intervention for PTSD, specifically for individuals with high acute PTSD symptoms.4. General discussion4.1. Integration of findings4.1.1. Clinical and functional neuroimaging studiesThere is a large body of literature that indicates that oxytocin administration beneficially affects neurobiological and socio-emotional vulnerability factors for PTSD that are likely etiologically involved in PTSD development (chapter 2; Frijling et al., 2014b). We hypothesized that intranasal oxytocin administration early posttrauma could reduce PTSD risk by attenuating amygdala hyperreactivity to fearful stimuli and by enhancing amygdala-centred functional connectivity of emotion regulation networks (i.e. amygdala-ventral PFC functional connectivity), especially in response to trauma-related stimuli. In line with our hypothesis, we observed that repeated oxytocin administration reduced PTSD symptoms up to six months posttrauma in recently trauma-exposed emergency department patients with high acute PTSD symptoms (chapter 7; van Zuiden et al., 2016). Contrary to our hypothesis, however, we demonstrated that a single intranasal oxytocin administration acutely increased neural fear processing (chapter 4; Frijling et al., 2016a) and potentially impeded neural emotion regulation (chapter 5; Frijling et al., 2016b) in recently trauma-exposed individuals. Based on our neuroimaging findings, we initially suggested that caution was warranted in administering intranasal oxytocin in recently trauma-exposed individuals (chapter 5; Frijling et al., 2016b). However, given the results of our clinical study – which were available at a later time point than the neuroimaging results – we eventually concluded that intranasal oxytocin administration is a promising novel preventive intervention in recently trauma-exposed individuals at increased PTSD risk due to high acute PTSD symptoms (chapter 7; van Zuiden et al., 2016).There are several explanations for the discrepancy between the beneficial oxytocin effects in our clinical study and the seemingly adverse oxytocin effects in the neuroimaging study. First, considering the salience processing theory as explanation of context dependent oxytocin effects (chapter 3; Olff et al., 2013) (see section below for more detailed discussion), it may be argued that the context of the neuroimaging study (e.g. unfamiliarity with the scanner and procedures, small space, limited light, anticipation of the trauma script) was likely perceived as unsafe or threatening by our participants, who were already distressed by their recent traumatic experience. Consequently, oxytocin-induced increased salience processing for these threat-related signals during scanning may have resulted in acute anxiogenic effects in our neuroimaging studies, which may be inferred from our observations of increased amygdala reactivity to fearful faces, generally decreased amygdala-vmPFC functional connectivity, decreased amygdala-vlPFC functional connectivity in response to the trauma script, and increased flashback intensity during the trauma script after oxytocin administration (chapters 4, 5; Frijling et al., 2016a, 2016b). In contrast, administering oxytocin in the safe home environment may have enhanced positive perceptions of safety signals associated with the familiar home environment, leading to reduced anxiety – and PTSD symptoms – in the long-term (chapter 7; van Zuiden et al., 2016).Second, the effects of oxytocin administration on either neural functioning or clinical outcome measures associated with anxiety may depend on oxytocin administration frequency (i.e. single versus repeated administration). An administration frequency dependent effect on anxiety is a well-known phenomenon for selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs). A single SSRI administration acutely increased fear learning in rodents and may potentiate anxiety in humans (for review see Burghardt &amp; Bauer, 2013) – a process that that is dependent on SSRI effects on amygdala function (Ravinder, Burghardt, Brodsky, Bauer, &amp; Chattarji, 2013); chronic SSRIs administration reduces anxiety and is therefore used to treat anxiety disorders (Baldwin et al., 2014). In high anxiety rats, chronic central oxytocin administration for six days reduced anxiety-related behaviour, whereas there was no effect on anxiety-related behaviour after a single administration (Slattery &amp; Neumann, 2010). Furthermore, differential effects of a single, repeated (i.e. four administrations over seven days) and chronic subcutaneous oxytocin administrations on memory consolidation and fear-related behaviour were recently observed in a rat model of PTSD. In this model, rats were shocked and subsequently re-exposed to the shock context without the shock two, five, and seven days later, during which contextual fear behaviour was assessed. Generalized fear behaviour was assessed two weeks after shock exposure. Although a single administration of oxytocin immediately after shock exposure enhanced contextual fear behaviour two days later without affecting subsequent fear behaviour, repeated and chronic subcutaneous oxytocin administration for seven to 14 days initiated after shock exposure reduced generalized fear behaviour at 14 days after shock exposure (Janezic et al., 2016). As the increase in contextual fear behaviour after a single oxytocin administration immediately after shock exposure may represent an oxytocin-induced increase in (fear) memory consolidation, the authors suggest that the long-term anxiolytic effect of repeated and chronic oxytocin administration may be the result of an oxytocin-mediated increase of (extinction) memory consolidation during re-exposure to the trauma context in safe conditions (Janezic et al., 2016). These observations are in line with findings in rodents (Zoicas, Slattery, &amp; Neumann, 2014) and humans (Acheson et al., 2013; Eckstein et al., 2015) indicating that oxytocin administration prior to fear extinction increases fear extinction (recall) (but see also Acheson, Feifel, Kamenski, Mckinney, &amp; Risbrough, 2015; Eskandarian et al., 2013; Toth, Neumann, &amp; Slattery, 2012; for contrasting results).Third, it may be suggested that intranasal oxytocin administration does not reduce PTSD symptoms by affecting amygdala function and anxiety as primary mechanism; the beneficial effects of oxytocin administration on PTSD symptom development may be related to its effects on other vulnerability or etiological factors for PTSD. Repeated oxytocin administration may have increased social support seeking behaviour (Cardoso, Valkanas, Serravalle, &amp; Ellenbogen, 2016; Preckel et al., 2014) – potentially by affecting neural reward functioning (Groppe et al., 2013; e.g. Nawijn et al., 2016a, 2016b) – or may have affected autonomic or glucocorticoid stress reactivity (Cohen et al., 2010). Considering the latter pathway, in rats it was previously observed that central oxytocin administration to the hippocampus immediately after exposure to a reminder of a severe stressor reduced PTSD-like behaviour one week later, which was accompanied by an oxytocin-induced decrease in glucocorticoid receptor (GR) expression in the hippocampus (Cohen et al., 2010). As PTSD vulnerability is associated with pre-existing high GR number and GR-sensitivity to glucocorticoids (van Zuiden et al., 2013), oxytocin administration may attenuate the negative effects of high GR-sensitivity associated with PTSD vulnerability by downregulating the total number of GRs expressed. Of note, glucocorticoid signalling in the hippocampal-medial PFC circuitry mediates memory contextualization (Liberzon &amp; Abelson, 2016; Van Ast, Cornelisse, Meeter, Joëls, &amp; Kindt, 2013). Memory contextualization refers to storing memories within the original encoding context, which may prevent memory generalization. Memory generalization is a process which is likely augmented in PTSD (Elzinga &amp; Bremner, 2002) which can lead to trauma-related fear responses to neutral stimuli, potentially as a consequence of inadequate memory contextualization (Liberzon &amp; Abelson, 2016). Deficits in hippocampal-mPFC circuit dependent contextual processing and associated aberrant glucocorticoid stress reactivity may thus be an important psychobiological correlate of PTSD (vulnerability), which may be potentially modified by oxytocin administration affecting hippocampal GR expression. The results of the study discussed above showing increased acute contextual fear but reduced more long-term generalized fear behaviour in severely stressed rats (Janezic et al., 2016) may also be explained in light of this hypothesis. Therefore, oxytocin administration effects on glucocorticoid stress reactivity and associated hippocampal-mPFC circuit dependent memory contextualization could be a neurobiological mechanism underlying the observed beneficial effects of oxytocin administration early after trauma on subsequent PTSD symptom severity.Although we did observe long-term reduced anxiety in parallel to decreased PTSD symptoms in our clinical study, it remains unclear whether this effect is mediated by the initially hypothesized oxytocin effects on amygdala function. However, the neuroimaging results add important additional insights into acute effects of a single administration of oxytocin on amygdala function. We were not the first to report increased amygdala reactivity and increased amygdala-PFC functional connectivity after intranasal oxytocin administration. In healthy women oxytocin administration increased amygdala reactivity to emotional stimuli (Domes et al., 2010; Lischke et al., 2012). The healthy control groups in studies with patients with PTSD, generalized social anxiety disorder and borderline personality disorder also showed increased amygdala reactivity (Bertsch et al., 2013; Koch et al., 2016a), decreased amygdala-medial PFC functional connectivity (Dodhia et al., 2014), or no effect on amygdala function (Labuschagne et al., 2010) after oxytocin. As our sample consisted of recently trauma-exposed individuals without a current PTSD diagnosis, our results may be best comparable to results of the healthy trauma-exposed control group in the PTSD study, which showed increased amygdala reactivity to emotional faces after oxytocin (Koch et al., 2016a).Taken together, the results of our clinical study provide stronger evidence than our neuroimaging study findings of our conclusion that intranasal oxytocin is a promising novel preventive intervention for PTSD. Our findings encourage further research into the clinical efficacy and feasibility of repeated oxytocin administration for PTSD prevention. However, it remains unclear whether observed long-term clinically beneficial effects are mediated by the initially hypothesized oxytocin effects on amygdala function. It may be argued that there is an administration frequency dependent effect of oxytocin on anxiety and amygdala function in recently trauma-exposed individuals, or that the beneficial effects or oxytocin are mediated by oxytocin effects on glucocorticoid-signalling dependent context processing.4.1.2. Explaining context and interindividual differences dependent effects of intranasal oxytocin administrationAs hypothesized (chapters 2, 3, 4; Frijling et al., 2016a, 2016b; Olff et al., 2013), we observed context and/or interindividual differences dependent effects of oxytocin administration in all our intranasal oxytocin studies. In our clinical study, oxytocin reduced PTSD symptom development only in individuals with high acute PTSD symptoms (chapter 7; van Zuiden et al., 2016). In our emotional face-matching fMRI paradigm, we found both stimulus valence (i.e. context) and sex (i.e. interindividual) dependent effects of oxytocin on amygdala reactivity (chapter 4; Frijling et al., 2016a). We also observed an oxytocin-induced attenuation of amygdala left-vlPFC functional connectivity after a trauma reminder only, not after the neutral script (i.e. context effect depending on script-condition valence) (chapter 5; Frijling et al., 2016b). These differential effects of oxytocin administration may be explained by oxytocin enhancing salience processing (chapter 3; Olff et al., 2013). The salience theory of oxytocin administration effects postulates that in contexts perceived as positive, supportive or safe, oxytocin will enhance the salience safety signals, consequently attenuating stress and anxiety. In unpredictable threatening situations however, oxytocin will increase salience of threat signals, and increase stress and anxiety (chapter 3, Olff et al., 2013; Shamay-Tsoory &amp; Abu-Akel, 2016). Interindividual differences (e.g. attachment representations, childhood trauma, prior psychopathology, sex) may affect the initial perception of a given a context as safe or threatening.In our study describing results of the face-matching paradigm (chapter 4; Frijling et al., 2016a), we argued that it is likely that individuals who were recently exposed to a potentially life threatening event experience fear-related stimuli as more salient than neutral and happy stimuli; a response that may be further enhanced as result of oxytocin-induced increased salience processing. However, in our amygdala-centred functional connectivity paradigm (chapter 5; Frijling et al., 2016b), we concluded that the observed effects of oxytocin administration did not fit the salience processing theory, as oxytocin increased amygdala-posterior insula functional connectivity, whereas anterior insula function is generally implicated in salience processing (Menon &amp; Uddin, 2010; Seeley et al., 2007). Of note, we did not investigate whether oxytocin administration affected (anterior) insula functional reactivity, which would have provided important additional information with respect to oxytocin administration effects on salience processing. Therefore, rejecting the salience theory solely based on the lack of an oxytocin-induced increase in amygdala-anterior insula functional connectivity may be premature. It may be argued that the unfamiliar scanner context, and (the anticipation of) the trauma-script, may have resulted in perceiving the context as threatening. This could have led to oxytocin-induced enhanced salience of threat-related stimuli and thus seemingly anxiogenic neural oxytocin effects in our amygdala-centred functional connectivity paradigm (chapter 3; Olff et al., 2013). The interindividual differences dependent effect of oxytocin in our clinical study, i.e. a beneficial oxytocin effect on PTSD symptom development in individuals with high acute PTSD symptom severity only, is in line with previous observations that intranasal oxytocin effects depend on the presence and/or severity of psychiatric symptom (Bertsch et al., 2013; Cardoso et al., 2014; Dodhia et al., 2014; Koch et al., 2016a; Nawijn et al., 2016b).It should be noted that the salience theory was based on a large body of literature on the effects of a single intranasal oxytocin administration on (predominantly) socio-emotional functioning; there is no direct evidence that the salience theory also holds for repeated oxytocin administration effects. An alternative suggestion for previously observed differential effects of oxytocin administration between healthy individuals and patients with a psychiatric disorder is that oxytocin administration may only have beneficial effects in individuals who have something to gain with regard to social or emotional functioning (Macdonald &amp; Feifel, 2013; Weisman &amp; Feldman, 2013) and associated neurobiological processes.Taken together, oxytocin administration effects that depend on context and interindividual differences as observed in our studies still fit with the model that oxytocin increases salience processing, but may also result from other processes that have yet to be further elucidated. To further evaluate the validity of the salience processing model, for explaining (repeated) oxytocin administration effects on reducing PTSD symptom development, (perception of) context factors should be explicitly assessed and tested as moderators of oxytocin effects in future studies.4.2. LimitationsAlthough we were the first to study intranasal oxytocin effects in recently trauma-exposed individuals, meanwhile conducting the largest clinical RCT with intranasal oxytocin to date, some limitations of our studies need to be addressed. First, the statistical power of our clinical study was limited. We halted our study halfway, as our pre-planned interim analysis indicated low conditional power to detect a significant overall effect of oxytocin administration on PTSD symptoms at our primary outcome (1.5 month posttrauma follow-up). As results from studies with low statistical power are at increased risk for Type I error, replication of our findings is clearly warranted. In addition, the sample size of our imaging studies was also modest, therefore it was not possible to reliably test whether the effects of oxytocin administration on amygdala function were moderated by interindividual differences as we observed in our clinical study. We did explore whether acute PTSD symptom severity was differently associated with amygdala reactivity to fearful faces and found no differential effect (chapter 4; Frijling et al., 2016a), but it should be noted that the sample size was small for such analysis. Because we were limited in statistical power, we could not investigate sex-differential effects of oxytocin, even though there are indications that oxytocin administration has differential (neural) effects in men and women (Koch et al., 2016b; Rilling et al., 2014). Also, as over 80% of our participants experienced an accidental trauma, we were not able to investigate whether type of trauma exposure was associated with differential oxytocin effects. Previously, rape victims benefited more from exposure therapy initiated immediately after trauma than individuals exposed to other trauma types (Rothbaum et al., 2012) and oxytocin administration in rodents promoted fear extinction of social fear (Toth et al., 2012), but impaired fear extinction of non-social fear (Zoicas et al., 2014). Further, as we did not have sufficient participants taking part in both the fMRI and clinical study, we were not able to investigate whether acute effects of a single oxytocin administration on amygdala function were in fact related to PTSD symptom development (after repeated administration). An additional limitation of the neuroimaging study is that we did not scan a recently trauma-exposed group with low levels of initial distress, which would have aided in interpreting our neuroimaging results, i.e. whether oxytocin effects were likely beneficial or not.4.3. Future perspectivesFirst, as we were the first to assess intranasal oxytocin effects in recently trauma-exposed individuals, our results should be replicated in similar and different samples of recently trauma-exposed individuals. Second, it should be investigated whether effects of repeated oxytocin administration on PTSD symptom development are mediated by oxytocin effects on autonomic and glucocorticoid stress reactivity (and associated contextual processing), functional fear neurocircuitry and/or other socio-emotional processes (e.g. related to reward functioning).Furthermore, considering the potential future use of intranasal oxytocin in routine clinical practice – for PTSD prevention but for also other psychiatric indications – it is highly desirable to better understand when beneficial, null or even potentially non-beneficial effects of oxytocin administration can be expected. Particularly, oxytocin effects on fear memory consolidation and fear extinction should be studied, as there are indications that oxytocin-mediated enhanced fear and extinction memory consolidation may have either anxiolytic or anxiogenic effects, depending on administration frequency and timing in relation to fear conditioning (Janezic et al., 2016; Toth et al., 2012), and whether the conditioned stimulus is social or not (Toth et al., 2012; Zoicas et al., 2014). How intranasal oxytocin affects fear consolidation and fear extinction may have implications for determining the optimal timing, and duration of intranasal administration in clinical settings. Additionally, considering the salience processing theory, (the perception of) contextual factors moderating oxytocin administration effects on short and long-term anxiety-related outcome measures should be better understood. Furthermore, dose-response effects of oxytocin administration on anxiety should be further investigated: in mice it was demonstrated that a high dose of (chronic) oxytocin administration increased anxiety, whereas a low dose (chronic) oxytocin administration had the opposite effect (Peters, Slattery, Uschold-Schmidt, Reber, &amp; Neumann, 2014). This dose-dependent effect may be mediated by oxytocin binding to arginine vasopressin receptors, which has been associated with enhanced fear expression and anxiety (Huber et al., 2005), but the exact mechanisms explaining these dose-dependent effects of oxytocin on anxiety are not yet understood.In addition, a better understanding of the pharmacodynamics of intranasally administered oxytocin is needed. Oxytocin has a half-life of 3–20 min in blood, and the peptide is immediately degraded upon oral ingestion. There is no clear consensus on if and how intranasally administered oxytocin reaches the brain. Although intranasal oxytocin administration increased salivary (van IJzendoorn, Bhandari, van der Veen, Grewen, &amp; Bakermans-Kranenburg, 2012), plasma (Striepens et al., 2013) and cerebrospinal fluid (Striepens et al., 2013) concentrations of oxytocin, it remains unknown whether these observations reflect amplified endogenous oxytocin release upon intranasal oxytocin administration (potentially as a result of positive feedback mechanisms (Ludwig, 2014; van IJzendoorn et al., 2012)) or the exogenously administered compound. However, recent studies in which oxytocin was administered both intravenously and intranasally suggest a direct nose-to-brain route for oxytocin (Quintana, Alvares, Hickie, &amp; Guastella, 2015; Quintana et al., 2016). In addition, the exact duration of oxytocin administration effects on brain function, stress reactivity and socio-emotional behaviour remain unknown, although it was recently demonstrated that neural effects of intranasal oxytocin may be observed up to at least 80 min post-administration (Paloyelis et al., 2014).If our findings are replicated, intranasal oxytocin may be a safe and cheap preventive intervention for PTSD (MacDonald et al., 2011). However, another important avenue for future research is whether intranasal oxytocin can be implemented in routine clinical practice as preventive intervention for PTSD. Within our research setting we have shown that it is feasible to screen a large number of – but not all – trauma-exposed emergency department patients early after trauma, to initiate the intervention and to provide follow-up assessments. However, it is unclear whether these actions and responsibilities can be translated to clinical practice and whether this would be cost-effective. Additionally, we used the trauma screening questionnaire (TSQ) (Brewin et al., 2002) and peritraumatic distress inventory (PDI) (Brunet et al., 2001) early posttrauma to identify and include trauma-exposed individuals at increased PTSD risk within one to seven days posttrauma. As these measures of early posttrauma distress did not moderate the effects of oxytocin on PTSD symptom development (potentially due to its limited specificity for PTSD when applied within the first week posttrauma), they are not suitable to determine which trauma-exposed individuals should be offered an intranasal oxytocin intervention early posttrauma. As administering the clinician-administered PTSD scale (CAPS) to (a selection of) trauma-exposed individuals is likely not feasible in clinical practice – considering the duration of the interview – other clinically applicable screeners for increased PTSD risk and moderators of intranasal oxytocin effects on PTSD symptom development should be assessed before intranasal oxytocin administration for the prevention of PTSD may eventually be feasible in clinical practice. Novel technology solutions to screen for increased risk for PTSD that can be more easily implemented at emergency departments (and other trauma settings) could be of help in future (implementation) studies on early preventive interventions for PTSD (Olff, Van Zuiden, &amp; Bakker, 2015).Finally, there is only limited evidence linking functioning of the oxytocin system directly to PTSD risk (Lucas-Thompson &amp; Holman, 2013). In addition, the neurocircuitry model of PTSD vulnerability as proposed by Admon, Milad, and Hendler (2013) is largely based on indirect evidence from studies demonstrating associations between genetics and/or childhood trauma – both risk factors for (adulthood) PTSD – and neural abnormalities. Therefore, prospective studies should assess whether pre- or early posttrauma measures of oxytocin system functioning and the structure and function of the fear neurocircuitry predict subsequent PTSD development, as knowledge on neurobiological risk factors that may be etiologically involved in PTSD development may yield new targets for preventive interventions for PTSD.5. ConclusionWe observed that repeated intranasal oxytocin administration early posttrauma reduced subsequent PTSD symptom development in recently trauma-exposed emergency department patients with high acute PTSD symptoms. Although replication is necessary, these findings indicate that intranasal oxytocin is a promising novel preventive intervention for individuals at increased risk for PTSD due to high acute symptom severity. However, we also observed acutely increased neural fear processing and impeded neural emotion regulation after a single oxytocin administration in recently trauma-exposed individuals. It remains unknown whether the positive clinical effects after repeated oxytocin administration are mediated by oxytocin effects on amygdala function, or whether the beneficial effects in our clinical study are mediated by other neurobiological and/or socio-emotional processes. Administration frequency dependent effects of oxytocin may be related to these seemingly contrasting effects on anxiety-related measures in our clinical and neuroimaging studies. In addition, the salience processing theory of oxytocin effects may serve as an explanatory framework for these seemingly contrasting results between the two study paradigms. Clinically relevant contextual and interindividual moderators of oxytocin effects should be investigated in the future, as well as underlying neurobiological and socio-emotional mechanisms that mediate oxytocin effects on anxiety-related outcomes and the development of PTSD symptoms. In all, our findings encourage further research into the clinical efficacy and feasibility of repeated oxytocin administration as early preventive intervention for PTSD, in order to try and reduce the high individual and societal burden associated with trauma exposure and PTSD.Highlights
Oxytocin administration may prevent posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) by affecting PTSD vulnerability factors (e.g. neural fear processing).We investigated intranasal oxytocin effects on acute neural fear processing and subsequent PTSD symptoms in recently trauma-exposed individuals.A single oxytocin administration increased neural fear processing.Repeated oxytocin administration reduced PTSD symptoms up to six months posttrauma in participants with high acute PTSD symptoms, and is therefore a promising early preventive intervention for PTSD.
Disclosure statementNo potential conflict of interest was reported by the author.References
AchesonD.FeifelD.de WildeS.MckinneyR.LohrJ.RisbroughV.
2013
The effect of intranasal oxytocin treatment on conditioned fear extinction and recall in a healthy human sample
Psychopharmacology
229
1
199
13
10.1007/s00213-013-3130-9
23644911
AchesonD. T.FeifelD.KamenskiM.MckinneyR.RisbroughV. B.
2015
Intranasal oxytocin administration prior to exposure therapy for arachnophobia impedes treatment response
Depression and Anxiety
32
6
400
407
10.1002/da.22362
25826649
AdmonR.LubinG.SternO.RosenbergK.SelaL.Ben-AmiH.HendlerT.
2009
Human vulnerability to stress depends on amygdala’s predisposition and hippocampal plasticity
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America
106
33
14120
14125
10.1073/pnas.0903183106
19666562
AdmonR.MiladM. R.HendlerT.
2013
A causal model of post-traumatic stress disorder: Disentangling predisposed from acquired neural abnormalities
Trends in Cognitive Sciences
17
7
337
347
10.1016/j.tics.2013.05.005
23768722
BaldwinD. S.AndersonI. M.NuttD. J.AllgulanderC.BandelowB.den BoerJ. A.WittchenH.-U.
2014
Evidence-based pharmacological treatment of anxiety disorders, post-traumatic stress disorder and obsessive-compulsive disorder: A revision of the 2005 guidelines from the British Association for Psychopharmacology
Journal of Psychopharmacology (Oxford, England)
28
5
403
439
10.1177/0269881114525674

BenjetC.BrometE.KaramE. G.KesslerR. C.McLaughlinK. A.RuscioA. M.KoenenK. C.
2015
The epidemiology of traumatic event exposure worldwide: Results from the World Mental Health Survey Consortium
Psychological Medicine
46
2
1
17
26482368
BertschK.GamerM.SchmidtB.SchmidingerI.WaltherS.KästelT.HerpertzS. C.
2013
Oxytocin and reduction of social threat hypersensitivity in women with borderline personality disorder
American Journal of Psychiatry
170
10
1169
1177
10.1176/appi.ajp.2013.13020263
23982273
BocciaM. L.PetruszP.SuzukiK.MarsonL.PedersenC. A.
2013
Immunohistochemical localization of oxytocin receptors in human brain
Neuroscience
253
(October 2016)
155
164
10.1016/j.neuroscience.2013.08.046
24012742
BradleyR.GreeneJ.RussE.DutraL.WestenD.
2005
A multidimensional meta-analysis of psychotherapy for PTSD
American Journal of Psychiatry
162
2
214
227
10.1176/appi.ajp.162.2.214
15677582
BrewinC. R.AndrewsB.ValentineJ. D.
2000
Meta-analysis of risk factors for posttraumatic stress disorder in trauma-exposed adults
Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology
68
5
748
766
10.1037/0022-006X.68.5.748
11068961
BrewinC. R.RoseS.AndrewsB.GreenJ.TataP.McEvedyC.FoaE. B.
2002
Brief screening instrument for post-traumatic stress disorder
The British Journal of Psychiatry; the Journal of Mental Science
181
158
162
12151288
BrunetA.WeissD. S.MetzlerT. J.BestS. R.NeylanT. C.RogersC.MarmarC. R.
2001
The peritraumatic distress inventory: A proposed measure of PTSD criterion A2
The American Journal of Psychiatry
158
9
1480
1485
10.1176/appi.ajp.158.9.1480
11532735
BurghardtN. S.BauerE. P.
2013
Acute and chronic effects of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor treatment on fear conditioning: Implications for underlying fear circuits
Neuroscience
247
253
272
10.1016/j.neuroscience.2013.05.050
23732229
CardosoC.KingdonD.EllenbogenM. A.
2014
A meta-analytic review of the impact of intranasal oxytocin administration on cortisol concentrations during laboratory tasks: Moderation by method and mental health
Psychoneuroendocrinology
49
161
170
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2014.07.014
25086828
CardosoC.ValkanasH.SerravalleL.EllenbogenM. A.
2016
Oxytocin and social context moderate social support seeking in women during negative memory recall
Psychoneuroendocrinology
70
63
69
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2016.05.001
27164224
CarsonD. S.YuanH.LabuschagneI.
2016
Improving research standards to restore trust in intranasal oxytocin
Biological Psychiatry
79
8
e53
e54
10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.08.031
26435223
CarterC. S.
1998
Neuroendocrine perspectives on social attachment and love
Psychoneuroendocrinology
23
8

CohenH.KaplanZ.KozlovskyN.GidronY.MatarM. A.ZoharJ.
2010
Hippocampal microinfusion of oxytocin attenuates the behavioural response to stress by means of dynamic interplay with the glucocorticoid-catecholamine responses
Journal of Neuroendocrinology
22
8
889
904
20403087
CoronasR.GallardoO.MorenoM. J.SuárezD.García-ParésG.MenchónJ. M.
2011
Heart rate measured in the acute aftermath of trauma can predict post-traumatic stress disorder: A prospective study in motor vehicle accident survivors
European Psychiatry
26
8
508
512
10.1016/j.eurpsy.2010.06.006
20813504
de JongT. R.MenonR.BludauA.GrundT.BiermeierV.KlampflS. M.NeumannI. D.
2015
Salivary oxytocin concentrations in response to running, sexual self-stimulation, breastfeeding and the TSST: The Regensburg Oxytocin Challenge (ROC) study
Psychoneuroendocrinology
62
381
388
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2015.08.027
26385109
de VriesG.-J.OlffM.
2009
The lifetime prevalence of traumatic events and posttraumatic stress disorder in the Netherlands
Journal of Traumatic Stress
22
4
259
267
10.1002/jts.v22:4
19645050
DelahantyD. L.Gabert-QuillenC.OstrowskiS. A.NugentN. R.FischerB.MorrisA.FallonW.
2013
The efficacy of initial hydrocortisone administration at preventing posttraumatic distress in adult trauma patients: A randomized trial
CNS Spectrums
18
2
103
111
10.1017/S1092852913000096
23557627
DodhiaS.HosanagarA.FitzgeraldD. A.LabuschagneI.WoodA. G.NathanP. J.PhanK. L.
2014
Modulation of resting-state amygdala-frontal functional connectivity by oxytocin in generalized social anxiety disorder
Neuropsychopharmacology
39
9
2061
2069
10.1038/npp.2014.53
24594871
DomesG.LischkeA.BergerC.GrossmannA.HauensteinK.HeinrichsM.HerpertzS. C.
2010
Effects of intranasal oxytocin on emotional face processing in women
Psychoneuroendocrinology
35
1
83
93
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.12.003
19632787
EcksteinM.BeckerB.ScheeleD.ScholzC.PreckelK.SchlaepferT. E.HurlemannR.
2015
Oxytocin facilitates the extinction of conditioned fear in humans
Biological Psychiatry
78
3
194
202
10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.10.015
25542304
ElzingaB. M.BremnerJ. D.
2002
Are the neural substrates of memory the final common pathway in posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD)?
Journal of Affective Disorders
70
1
1
17
10.1016/S0165-0327(01)00351-2
12113915
EskandarianS.VafaeiA. A.VaeziG. H.TaherianF.KashefiA.Rashidy-PourA.
2013
Effects of systemic administration of oxytocin on contextual fear extinction in a rat model of post-traumatic stress disorder
Basic and Clinical Neuroscience
4
4
315
322
25337363
FeldmanR.
2012
Oxytocin and social affiliation in humans
Hormones and Behavior
61
3
380
391
10.1016/j.yhbeh.2012.01.008
22285934
FeldmanR.GordonI.SchneidermanI.WeismanO.Zagoory-SharonO.
2010
Natural variations in maternal and paternal care are associated with systematic changes in oxytocin following parent-infant contact
Psychoneuroendocrinology
35
8
1133
1141
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.12.003
20153585
ForbesD.ParslowR.CreamerM.O’DonnellM.BryantR.McFarlaneA.ShalevA.
2010
A longitudinal analysis of posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms and their relationship with fear and anxious-misery disorders: Implications for DSM-V
Journal of Affective Disorders
127
1–3
147
152
10.1016/j.jad.2010.05.003
20605220
FrijlingJ. L.van ZuidenM.KochS. B. J.NawijnL.VeltmanD. J.OlffM.
2016a
Effects of intranasal oxytocin on amygdala reactivity to emotional faces in recently trauma-exposed individuals
Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience
11
2
327
336
10.1093/scan/nsv116
26382634
FrijlingJ. L.van ZuidenM.KochS. B. J.NawijnL.GoslingsJ. C.LuitseJ. S.DenysD.
2014a
Efficacy of oxytocin administration early after psychotrauma in preventing the development of PTSD: Study protocol of a randomized controlled trial
BMC Psychiatry
14
1
92
10.1186/1471-244X-14-92
24679046
FrijlingJ. L.van ZuidenM.KochS. B. J.NawijnL.VeltmanD. J.OlffM.
2016b
Intranasal oxytocin affects amygdala functional connectivity after trauma script-driven imagery in distressed recently trauma-exposed individuals
Neuropsychopharmacology
41
5
1286
1296
10.1038/npp.2015.278
26346640
FrijlingJ. L.van ZuidenM.KochS. B. J.NawijnL.VeltmanD. J.OlffM.
2014b
Promoting resilience after trauma: Clinical stimulation of the oxytocin system
KentM.DavisC.ReichJ. W.
The resilience handbook: Approaches to stress and trauma
299
308
New York, NY
Routledge

Galatzer-LevyI. R.AnkriY.FreedmanS.Israeli-ShalevY.RoitmanP.GiladM.ShalevA. Y.
2013
Early PTSD symptom trajectories: Persistence, recovery, and response to treatment: Results from the Jerusalem Trauma Outreach and Prevention Study (J-TOPS)
PLoS One
8
8
e70084
10.1371/journal.pone.0070084
23990895
GelpinE.BonneO.PeriT.BrandesD.ShalevA. Y.
1996
Treatment of recent trauma survivors with benzodiazepines: A prospective study
The Journal of Clinical Psychiatry
57
9
390
394
9746445
Graugaard-JensenC.HvistendahlG. M.FrøkiaerJ.BieP.DjurhuusJ. C.
2014
Urinary concentration does not exclusively rely on plasma vasopressin. A study between genders. Gender and diurnal urine regulation
Acta Physiologica (Oxford, England)
212
1
97
105
10.1111/apha.12337

GroppeS. E.GossenA.RademacherL.HahnA.WestphalL.GründerG.SpreckelmeyerK. N.
2013
Oxytocin influences processing of socially relevant cues in the ventral tegmental area of the human brain
Biological Psychiatry
74
3
172
179
10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.12.023
23419544
HeinrichsM.BaumgartnerT.KirschbaumC.EhlertU.
2003
Social support and oxytocin interact to suppress cortisol and subjective responses to psychosocial stress
Biological Psychiatry
54
1389
1398
10.1016/S0006-3223(03)00465-7
14675803
HogeE. A.WorthingtonJ. J.NagurneyJ. T.ChangY.KayE. B.FeterowskiC. M.PitmanR. K.
2012
Effect of acute posttrauma propranolol on PTSD outcome and physiological responses during script-driven imagery
CNS Neuroscience &amp; Therapeutics
18
1
21
27
10.1111/j.1755-5949.2010.00227.x
22070357
HuberD.VeinanteP.StoopR.
2005
Vasopressin and oxytocin excite distinct neuronal populations in the central amygdala
Science
308
5719
245
248
10.1126/science.1105636
15821089
JanezicE. M.UppalapatiS.NaglS.ContrerasM.FrenchE. D.FellousJ.
2016
Beneficial effects of chronic oxytocin administration and social co-housing in a rodent model of post-traumatic stress disorder
Behavioural Pharmacology

KesslerR. C.PetukhovaM.SampsonN. A.ZaslavskyA. M.WittchenH.-U.
2012
Twelve-month and lifetime prevalence and lifetime morbid risk of anxiety and mood disorders in the United States
International Journal of Methods in Psychiatric Research
21
3
169
184
10.1002/mpr.1359
22865617
KirschP.EsslingerC.ChenQ.MierD.LisS.SiddhantiS.Meyer-LindenbergA.
2005
Oxytocin modulates neural circuitry for social cognition and fear in humans
Journal of Neuroscience
25
49
11489
11493
10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3984-05.2005
16339042
KnoblochH. S.CharletA.HoffmannL. C.EliavaM.KhrulevS.CetinA. H.StoopR.
2012
Evoked axonal oxytocin release in the central amygdala attenuates fear response
Neuron
73
3
553
566
10.1016/j.neuron.2012.02.014
22325206
KochS. B. J.van ZuidenM.NawijnL.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM.
2016a
Intranasal oxytocin administration dampens amygdala reactivity towards emotional faces in male and female PTSD patients
Neuropsychopharmacology: Official Publication of the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology
41
6
1495
1504
10.1038/npp.2015.299
26404844
KochS. B. J.van ZuidenM.NawijnL.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM.
2016b
Intranasal oxytocin normalizes amygdala functional connectivity in posttraumatic stress disorder
Neuropsychopharmacology: Official Publication of the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology
41
8
2041
2051
10.1038/npp.2016.1
26741286
KubzanskyL. D.MendesW. B.AppletonA. A.BlockJ.AdlerG. K.
2012
A heartfelt response: Oxytocin effects on response to social stress in men and women
Biological Psychology
90
1
1
9
10.1016/j.biopsycho.2012.02.010
22387929
LabuschagneI.PhanK. L.WoodA.AngstadtM.ChuaP.HeinrichsM.NathanP. J.
2010
Oxytocin attenuates amygdala reactivity to fear in generalized social anxiety disorder
Neuropsychopharmacology
35
12
2403
2413
10.1038/npp.2010.123
20720535
LengG.LudwigM.
2016
Intranasal oxytocin: Myths and delusions
Biological Psychiatry
79
3
243
250
10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.05.003
26049207
LiberzonI.AbelsonJ. L.
2016
Context processing and the neurobiology of post-traumatic stress disorder
Neuron
92
1
14
30
10.1016/j.neuron.2016.09.039
27710783
LischkeA.GamerM.BergerC.GrossmannA.HauensteinK.HeinrichsM.DomesG.
2012
Oxytocin increases amygdala reactivity to threatening scenes in females
Psychoneuroendocrinology
35
1
83
93

Lucas-ThompsonR. G.HolmanE. A.
2013
Environmental stress, oxytocin receptor gene (OXTR) polymorphism, and mental health following collective stress
Hormones and Behavior
63
4
615
624
10.1016/j.yhbeh.2013.02.015
23470776
LudwigM.
2014
Dendritic release of the neuropeptides vasopressin and oxytocin
Neurophysiology of neuroendocrine neurons
207
223
Chichester
John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd

MacDonaldE.DaddsM. R.BrennanJ. L.WilliamsK.LevyF.CauchiA. J.
2011
A review of safety, side-effects and subjective reactions to intranasal oxytocin in human research
Psychoneuroendocrinology
36
8
1114
1126
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2011.02.015
21429671
MacdonaldK.FeifelD.
2013
Helping oxytocin deliver: Considerations in the development of oxytocin-based therapeutics for brain disorders
Frontiers in Neuroscience
7
10.3389/fnins.2013.00035

MagruderK. M.Kassam-AdamsN.ThoresenS.OlffM.
2016
Prevention and public health approaches to trauma and traumatic stress: A rationale and a call to action
European Journal of Psychotraumatology
7
1
9
10.3402/ejpt.v7.29715

MarciniakM. D.LageM. J.DunayevichE.RussellJ. M.BowmanL.LandbloomR. P.LevineL. R.
2005
The cost of treating anxiety: The medical and demographic correlates that impact total medical costs
Depression and Anxiety
21
4
178
184
10.1002/(ISSN)1520-6394
16075454
McCauleyJ.KileenT.GrosD. F.BradyK.BackS. E.
2012
Posttraumatic stress disorder and co-occurring substance use disorders: Advances in assessment and treatment
Clinical Psychology
19
3
1
27

McLaughlinK. A.BussoD. S.DuysA.GreenJ. G.AlvesS.WayM.SheridanM. A.
2014
Amygdala response to negative stimuli predicts PTSD symptom onset following a terrorist attack
Depression and Anxiety
31
10
834
842
10.1002/da.2014.31.issue-10
24995938
MellmanT. A.BustamanteV.DavidD.FinsA. I.
2002
Hypnotic medication in the aftermath of trauma
The Journal of Clinical Psychiatry
63
12
1183
1184
10.4088/JCP.v63n1214h

MenonV.UddinL. Q.
2010
Saliency, switching, attention and control: A network model of insula function
Brain Structure and Function
214
5–6
655
667
10.1007/s00429-010-0262-0
20512370
NawijnL.van ZuidenM.KochS. B. J.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM.
2016a
Intranasal oxytocin enhances neural processing of monetary reward and loss in post-traumatic stress disorder and traumatized controls
Psychoneuroendocrinology
66
228
237
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2016.01.020
26851698
NawijnL.van ZuidenM.KochS. B. J.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.OlffM.
2016b
Intranasal oxytocin increases neural responses to social reward in post-traumatic stress disorder
Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience
nsw123
10.1093/scan/nsw123

NeumannI. D.
2007
Oxytocin: The neuropeptide of love reveals some of its secrets
Cell Metabolism
5
4
231
233
10.1016/j.cmet.2007.03.008
17403367
OlffM.
2012
Bonding after trauma: On the role of social support and the oxytocin system in traumatic stress
European Journal of Psychotraumatology
3
18597
10.3402/ejpt.v3i0.18597

OlffM.FrijlingJ. L.KubzanskyL. D.BradleyB.EllenbogenM. A.CardosoC.van ZuidenM.
2013
The role of oxytocin in social bonding, stress regulation and mental health: An update on the moderating effects of context and interindividual differences
Psychoneuroendocrinology
38
9
1883
1894
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2013.06.019
23856187
OlffM.Van ZuidenM.BakkerA.
2015
Early interventions: From e-health to neurobiology
European Journal of Psychotraumatology
6
28545
10.3402/ejpt.v6.28545
26073209
OlffM.Van ZuidenM.KochS. B. J.NawijnL.FrijlingJ. L.VeltmanD. J.
2015
Intranasal oxytocin: Miracle cure after trauma?
European Journal of Psychotraumatology
6
27631
10.3402/ejpt.v6.27631

PaloyelisY.DoyleO. M.ZelayaF. O.MaltezosS.WilliamsS. C.FotopoulouA.HowardM. A.
2014
A spatiotemporal profile of in vivo cerebral blood flow changes following intranasal oxytocin in humans
Biological Psychiatry, Biological Psychiatry, 79(8), 693–705
http://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2014.10.005

PetersS.SlatteryD. A.Uschold-SchmidtN.ReberS. O.NeumannI. D.
2014
Dose-dependent effects of chronic central infusion of oxytocin on anxiety, oxytocin receptor binding and stress-related parameters in mice
Psychoneuroendocrinology
42
225
236
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2013.12.001
24636519
PoleN.NeylanT. C.OtteC.Henn-HasseC.MetzlerT. J.MarmarC. R.
2009
Prospective prediction of posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms using fear potentiated auditory startle responses
Biological Psychiatry
65
3
235
240
10.1016/j.biopsych.2008.07.015
18722593
PreckelK.ScheeleD.KendrickK. M.MaierW.HurlemannR.
2014
Oxytocin facilitates social approach behavior in women
Frontiers in Behavioral Neuroscience
8
191
10.3389/fnbeh.2014.00191
24904342
PullC. N.PullC. B.
2014
Current status of treatment for posttraumatic stress disorder: Focus on treatments combining pharmacotherapy and cognitive-behavioral therapy
International Journal of Cognitive Therapy
7
2
149
161
10.1521/ijct.2014.7.2.149

QuintanaD. S.AlvaresG. A.HickieI. B.GuastellaA. J.
2015
Do delivery routes of intranasally administered oxytocin account for observed effects on social cognition and behavior? A two-level model
Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews
49
182
192
10.1016/j.neubiorev.2014.12.011
25526824
QuintanaD. S.WestlyeL. T.AlnæsD.RustanØ. G.KaufmannT.SmerudK. T.AndreassenO. A.
2016
Low dose intranasal oxytocin delivered with breath powered device dampens amygdala response to emotional stimuli: A peripheral effect-controlled within-subjects randomized dose-response fMRI trial
Psychoneuroendocrinology
69
180
188
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2016.04.010
27107209
RavinderS.BurghardtN. S.BrodskyR.BauerE. P.ChattarjiS.
2013
A role for the extended amygdala in the fear-enhancing effects of acute selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor treatment
Translational Psychiatry
3
1
e209
10.1038/tp.2012.137
23321806
RillingJ. K.DeMarcoA. C.HackettP. D.ChenX.GautamP.StairS.PatelR.
2014
Sex differences in the neural and behavioral response to intranasal oxytocin and vasopressin during human social interaction
Psychoneuroendocrinology
39
237
248
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2013.09.022
24157401
RobertsN. P.KitchinerN. J.KenardyJ.BissonJ. I.
2009
Systematic review and meta-analysis of multiple-session early interventions following traumatic events
The American Journal of Psychiatry
166
3
293
301
10.1176/appi.ajp.2008.08040590
19188285
RoseS.BissonJ.ChurchillR.WesselyS.
2002
Psychological debriefing for preventing post traumatic stress disorder (PTSD)
Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews
2
2
http://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD000560

RothbaumB. O.KearnsM. C.PriceM.MalcounE.DavisM.ResslerK. J.HouryD.
2012
Early intervention may prevent the development of posttraumatic stress disorder: A randomized pilot civilian study with modified prolonged exposure
Biological Psychiatry
72
11
957
963
10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.06.002
22766415
SeeleyW. W.MenonV.SchatzbergA. F.KellerJ.GloverG. H.KennaH.GreiciusM. D.
2007
Dissociable intrinsic connectivity networks for salience processing and executive control
The Journal of Neuroscience: The Official Journal of the Society for Neuroscience
27
9
2349
2356
10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3105-06.2007
17329432
Shamay-TsooryS. G.Abu-AkelA.
2016
The social salience hypothesis of oxytocin
Biological Psychiatry
79
3
194
202
10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.07.020
26321019
SijbrandijM.KleiboerA.BissonJ. I.BarbuiC.CuijpersP.
2015
Pharmacological prevention of post-traumatic stress disorder and acute stress disorder: A systematic review and meta-analysis
The Lancet Psychiatry
2
5
413
421
10.1016/S2215-0366(14)00121-7
26360285
SijbrandijM.OlffM.ReitsmaJ. B.CarlierI. V.GersonsB. P.
2006
Emotional or educational debriefing after psychological trauma: Randomised controlled trial
The British Journal of Psychiatry: The Journal of Mental Science
189
150
155
10.1192/bjp.bp.105.021121
16880485
SlatteryD. A.NeumannI. D.
2010
Chronic icv oxytocin attenuates the pathological high anxiety state of selectively bred Wistar rats
Neuropharmacology
58
1
56
61
10.1016/j.neuropharm.2009.06.038
19589349
SteinM. B.KerridgeC.DimsdaleJ. E.HoytD. B.
2007
Pharmacotherapy to prevent PTSD: Results from a randomized controlled proof-of-concept trial in physically injured patients
Journal of Traumatic Stress
20
6
923
932
10.1002/(ISSN)1573-6598
18157888
StriepensN.KendrickK. M.HankingV.LandgrafR.WüllnerU.MaierW.HurlemannR.
2013
Elevated cerebrospinal fluid and blood concentrations of oxytocin following its intranasal administration in humans
Scientific Reports
3
3440
10.1038/srep03440
24310737
TothI.NeumannI. D.SlatteryD. A.
2012
Central administration of oxytocin receptor ligands affects cued fear extinction in rats and mice in a timepoint-dependent manner
Psychopharmacology
223
2
149
158
10.1007/s00213-012-2702-4
22526533
Van AstV. A.CornelisseS.MeeterM.JoëlsM.KindtM.
2013
Time-dependent effects of cortisol on the contextualization of emotional memories
Biological Psychiatry
74
11
809
816
10.1016/j.biopsych.2013.06.022
23972529
van IJzendoornM. H.Bakermans-KranenburgM. J.
2012
A sniff of trust: Meta-analysis of the effects of intranasal oxytocin administration on face recognition, trust to in-group, and trust to out-group
Psychoneuroendocrinology
37
3
438
443
10.1016/j.psyneuen.2011.07.008
21802859
van IJzendoornM. H.BhandariR.van der VeenR.GrewenK. M.Bakermans-KranenburgM. J.
2012
Elevated salivary levels of oxytocin persist more than 7 h after intranasal administration
Frontiers in Neuroscience
6
174
10.3389/fnins.2012.00174
23233832
van ZuidenM.FrijlingJ. L.NawijnL.KochS. B. J.GoslingsJ. C.LuitseJ. S.OlffM.
in press
Intranasal oxytocin to prevent posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms: A randomized controlled trial in emergency department patients
Biological Psychiatry
1
11

van ZuidenM.KavelaarsA.GeuzeE.OlffM.HeijnenC. J.
2013
Predicting PTSD: Pre-existing vulnerabilities in glucocorticoid-signaling and implications for preventive interventions
Brain, Behavior, and Immunity
30
12
21
10.1016/j.bbi.2012.08.015

VivianiD.CharletA.van den BurgE.RobinetC.HurniN.AbatisM.StoopR.
2011
Oxytocin selectively gates fear responses through distinct outputs from the central amygdala
Science
333
6038
104
107
10.1126/science.1205623
21719680
WangP. S.LaneM.OlfsonM.PincusH. A.WellsK. B.KesslerR. C.
2005
Twelve-month use of mental health services in the United States: Results from the National Comorbidity Survey Replication
Archives of General Psychiatry
62
6
629
640
10.1001/archpsyc.62.6.629
15939840
WeismanO.FeldmanR.
2013
Oxytocin effects on the human brain: Findings, questions, and future directions
Biological Psychiatry
74
3
158
159
10.1016/j.biopsych.2013.05.026
23845580
ZoharJ.YahalomH.KozlovskyN.Cwikel-HamzanyS.MatarM. A.KaplanZ.CohenH.
2011
High dose hydrocortisone immediately after trauma may alter the trajectory of PTSD: Interplay between clinical and animal studies
European Neuropsychopharmacology: the Journal of the European College of Neuropsychopharmacology
21
11
796
809
10.1016/j.euroneuro.2011.06.001
21741804
ZoicasI.SlatteryD. A.NeumannI. D.
2014
Brain oxytocin in social fear conditioning and its extinction: Involvement of the lateral septum
Neuropsychopharmacology
39
13
3027
3035
10.1038/npp.2014.156
24964815
