<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="systematic-review"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Aging Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Aging Neurosci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Aging Neurosci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1663-4365</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5915963</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2018.00110</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Systematic Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Effects of Tai Chi Intervention on Healthy Elderly by Means of Neuroimaging and EEG: A Systematic Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Zhujun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/348587/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Xiwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/510842/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Qun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/533340/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Lijuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/329989/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Younghan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/533341/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chih C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lamberth</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Mi-Lyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Kinesiology, Mississippi State University</institution>, <addr-line>Starkville, MS</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Exercise Physiology Laboratory, College of Physical Education and Sports, Beijing Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Sports, Leisure and Recreation, Soonchunhyang University</institution>, <addr-line>Asan</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Sarah A. Schoen, STAR Institute for Sensory Processing Disorder, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Xu Lei, Southwest University, China; Deep R. Sharma, SUNY Downstate Medical Center, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Zhujun Pan <email>zp147@msstate.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>110</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Pan, Su, Fang, Hou, Lee, Chen, Lamberth and Kim.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pan, Su, Fang, Hou, Lee, Chen, Lamberth and Kim</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Aging is a process associated with a decline in cognitive and motor functions, which can be attributed to neurological changes in the brain. Tai Chi, a multimodal mind-body exercise, can be practiced by people across all ages. Previous research identified effects of Tai Chi practice on delaying cognitive and motor degeneration. Benefits in behavioral performance included improved fine and gross motor skills, postural control, muscle strength, and so forth. Neural plasticity remained in the aging brain implies that Tai Chi-associated benefits may not be limited to the behavioral level. Instead, neurological changes in the human brain play a significant role in corresponding to the behavioral improvement. However, previous studies mainly focused on the effects of behavioral performance, leaving neurological changes largely unknown. This systematic review summarized extant studies that used brain imaging techniques and EEG to examine the effects of Tai Chi on older adults. Eleven articles were eligible for the final review. Three neuroimaging techniques including fMRI (<italic>N</italic> = 6), EEG (<italic>N</italic> = 4), and MRI (<italic>N</italic> = 1), were employed for different study interests. Significant changes were reported on subjects' cortical thickness, functional connectivity and homogeneity of the brain, and executive network neural function after Tai Chi intervention. The findings suggested that Tai Chi intervention give rise to beneficial neurological changes in the human brain. Future research should develop valid and convincing study design by applying neuroimaging techniques to detect effects of Tai Chi intervention on the central nervous system of older adults. By integrating neuroimaging techniques into randomized controlled trials involved with Tai Chi intervention, researchers can extend the current research focus from behavioral domain to neurological level.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Tai Chi</kwd><kwd>aging</kwd><kwd>neuroimaging</kwd><kwd>EEG</kwd><kwd>neural plasticity</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">NSFC31401018</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Ministry of Education<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002701</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">NRF-2017S1A2A2039405</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="52"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="7630"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Older adults experience gradual regression of abilities. In addition to the physiological changes such as loss of muscular strength and declined vision, neurological ability declines with advanced aging. Tomasi and Volkow (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) proposed that age-related decrease in motor and cognitive functions is associated with degeneration of the brain networks and changes in brain anatomy. Other studies indicated that decrease in functional connectivity as well as atrophy in gray matter and basal ganglia result in lack of motor control in older adults (Seidler et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Hoffstaedter et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, aging process is reversible due to the plasticity and adaptivity of the human brain to experience-specific tasks (Adkins et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Petzinger et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Brain plasticity implies that reorganization of brain structure and functional connectivity is possible in older adults (Erickson et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). The finding suggested that appropriate intervention protocols such as exercise and motor training can counteract declines associated with advanced aging (Erickson et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Seidler et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). For example, older adults participating in a 6-month aerobic exercise demonstrated better cardiovascular fitness and enhanced brain plasticity than the sedentary counterparts. Specifically, increased brain volume in gray and white matter were considered evidence of intact central nervous system and contributed to cognitive improvement (Colcombe et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Bearing with the perception as to the significant role of brain plasticity in mitigating or even reversing the course of aging, researchers attempt to understand the neural mechanisms underlying exercise-related improvement in cognitive and motor performance.</p><p>Regular exercise is a practical approach to enhancing brain plasticity (Erickson et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Voss et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Tai Chi, a multimodal mind-body exercise integrating gracefulness, mindfulness, and gentleness, is a recommended form of physical activity for older adults (Wong et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Benefits of practicing Tai Chi were reported in cognitive performance (Lam et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Wayne et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and motor functions such as postural control (Ni et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), fall prevention (Tousignant et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Jain et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), muscle strength (Reid et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and agility (Wayne et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Given that neural plasticity shapes performance modification (Par&#x000e9; and Munoz, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>), it is reasonable to assume that evolution of behavior associated with Tai Chi practice should be detected in the corresponding brain regions. Noninvasive neuroimaging techniques allow researchers to identify neural correlates of exercise-induced changes in the aging brain. Electroencephalography (EEG) produces spontaneous neuroelectric feedback on brain activity (Hatta et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Fong et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) provides <italic>in vivo</italic> measures of brain anatomy and physiology (Giedd et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Researchers used the technique to investigate structural changes in brain volume (Colcombe et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) and cortical thickness (Wei et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) detects brain connectivity based on blood oxygenation level-dependent (BOLD) signal in distinct brain regions (Fox et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). This technique has been applied to probe exercise-induced changes in brain activation and functional connection (Erickson et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Seidler et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>The current review summarized extant studies that applied Tai Chi to promote health for the following reasons. First, Tai Chi is an increasingly popular physical activity, which has been recommended for older adults and people with chronic disease. Second, despite the encouraging outcomes observed at the behavioral level, neural mechanisms underlying the promoted functions remain largely unknown (Voss et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Neuroimaging (fMRI and MRI) and neuroelectric techniques (EEG) are the instruments that expand current knowledge on the correlates between neural plasticity and modified function. In this context, we aim to investigate three main issues: (1) Tai Chi-incurred benefits in older adults; (2) improved functions and corresponding changes in the brain; and (3) the direction of future study. To our knowledge, it is the first review to systematically investigate the benefits of Tai Chi exercise from the perspective of neural plasticity. With an increasing application of neuroimaging techniques, researchers should elevate the current study of interest from mere performance to neurological level.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Literature search</title><p>Five electronic databases (Google scholar, PubMed, Cochrane Library, Scopus, and Web of science) were searched for relevant studies published since 1990. The following terms were entered in multiple combinations, including older adults, elderly, seniors, aging, Tai Chi Chuan, Tai chi, Taichi, and Tai Ji. Terms for neuroimaging techniques include brain imaging, electroencephalography (EEG), event-related potentials (ERP) diffuse optical tomography (DOT), diffuse optical imaging (DOI), event-related optical signal (EROS), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) arterial spin labeling (ASL), magnetoencephalography (MEG), computed tomography (CT), positron emission tomography (PET), and single-photon emission computerized tomography (SPECT). Manual search was conducted for known articles in the area by titles instead of keywords search.</p></sec><sec><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>Studies were eligible for inclusion if the following criteria were met: (1) subjects were healthy older adults or middle-aged adults (average age of Tai Chi group must be over 50); (2) Tai Chi was applied to exercise intervention; (3) brain imaging methods including MRI, fMRI, EEG, ERP etc. were used to assess variables of interest. The screening process consisted of two phases. First, two reviewers (XS &#x00026; ZP) independently examined title, keywords, and abstracts of retrieved articles. In the second phase, a third author (QF) was responsible to deal with any disagreement between the reviewers.</p><p>Studies that failed to conform to one of the specified criteria were considered ineligible. To gain a comprehensive understanding of Tai Chi-related changes in the central nervous system of older adults, there were no restrictions on the types of studies. However, conference abstracts, review articles, monograph, and videos were excluded.</p></sec><sec><title>Quality assessment</title><p>The methodological quality was assessed by Delphi list for quality assessment (Verhagen et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). To reduce the risk of bias in assessment, two reviewers (XS &#x00026; ZP) independently scored the quality of the included articles. Inconsistencies between the two reviewers were solved after discussing with a third author.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction</title><p>Study characteristics encompass basic information of the selected articles, including author(s) of study and year of publication, study design, place of study, sample size and attribution rate, intervention frequency and duration, age of subjects, and measures. Age of subjects refers to the average group age, which should be above 50. Measures applied to the studies must include neuroimaging (fMRI or MRI) or neuroelectric techniques (EEG). Rationale, findings, and practical implications were summarized according to the purpose, results, and conclusions of the retrieved studies.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Study selection</title><p>A total of 40 articles were retrieved from the initial search. Examination of titles and abstracts excluded 13 irrelevant articles. Further analysis of the remaining 27 items screened off 16 articles for the following reasons: lack of Tai Chi intervention (<italic>N</italic> = 10), participants with health issues (<italic>N</italic> = 2), non-journal articles (<italic>N</italic> = 2), lack of brain imaging method (<italic>N</italic> = 1), and review paper (<italic>N</italic> = 1). Finally, 11 studies were eligible for full-text critical appraisal. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> indicates the study selection process.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Article selection process.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fnagi-10-00110-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Study characteristics</title><p>Effects of Tai Chi intervention on participants' neurological changes received an increasing attention in recent years as nine of the included studies (<italic>N</italic> = 11) were published in the past 5 years. China is the major country where relevant studies were conducted (<italic>N</italic> = 8) due to the prevalence of Tai Chi in the region. Subjects were mostly seniors. The average age of Tai Chi group in the studies ranged between 50.5 and 68.6 years. The study design included pre- and post-tests (<italic>N</italic> = 1), RCT (<italic>N</italic> = 5), and Quasi-experiment (<italic>N</italic> = 5). Seven studies compared the subjects' performance of Tai Chi group with that of control group before and after the intervention. The other four studies examined the difference between experienced Tai Chi practitioners and people with a relatively sedentary lifestyle.</p><p>Scales and instruments such as Attention Network Test (ANT) and Memory Scale (MS) were used to assess behavioral and cognitive performance. On the other hand, MRI, fMRI, and EEG provided evidence of neural plasticity. MRI presented the image of brain structures (Wei et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zheng et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). fMRI examined functional connectivity (Li et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Tao et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and brain neural activity (Yin et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). EEG detected the spontaneous electric activity when a subject is performing a specific task (Liu et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Field et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Fong et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Hawkes et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Combining performance assessment with neuroimaging evidence allows researchers to investigate Tai Chi-induced outcomes at both behavioral and neural levels. Study characteristics are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of reviewed articles.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>References</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Aim/Purpose</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Design</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Place of study</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sample size (attribution%)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age group (year)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Intervention frequency &#x00026; duration</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Measurment instruments/Measures</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Results</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Conclusion</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tao et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate the impact of Tai chi chuan and Baduanjin on the cognitive control network (CCN) especially on the DLPFC part.<break/>To explain the underlying mechanism of the fact that Taichi and Baduanjin can help improve mental control function.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gulou District, Fuzhou City, China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC: 21<break/>BDJ:16<break/>CG:25<break/><italic>N</italic> = 62</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;70 years<break/>TC: 62.38 &#x000b1; 4.55<break/>BDJ: 62.33 &#x000b1; 3.88<break/>CG: 59.76 &#x000b1; 4.83</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC: 60 min/d, 5d/week, last for 12 weeks.<break/>BDJ: 60 min/d, 5d/ week, last for 12 weeks.<break/>CG: maintain original physical activity habits for 12 weeks.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WMS-CR<break/>fMRI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In TC, the rsFC decreases significantly between the DLPFC and the left SFG and ACC.<break/>In BDJ, the rsFC decreases significantly between the DLPFC and the left putamen and insula.<break/>Mental control improvement was negatively associated with rsFC DLPFC-putamen changes across all subjects.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The practice of Tai Chi and Baduanjin could significantly increases the participant's mental control function.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tao et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate how longitudinal Tai Chi Chuan and Baduanjin can modulate memory function and HPC resting-state functional connectivity (rs-FC) in elderly adults and the relation between them.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gulou District, Fuzhou City, China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC: 21<break/>BDJ:16<break/>CG:25<break/><italic>N</italic> = 62</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02013;70 years TC: 62.38 &#x000b1; 4.55 BDJ: 62.33 &#x000b1; 3.88 CG: 59.76 &#x000b1; 4.83</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC: 60min/d, 5d/week, last for 12 weeks.<break/>BDJ: 60min/d, 5d/week, last for 12 weeks.<break/>CG: maintain original physical activity habits for 12 weeks.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MQ (WMS-CR)<break/>fMRI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The MQ significantly increased in TC and BDJ compared to CG.<break/>The rs-FC between the bilateral HPC and mPFC significantly increased in the TC compared to the CG.<break/>The rs-FC increases between the bilateral HPC and mPFC were significantly associated with corresponding memory function improvement across all subjects.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both Tai Chi Chuan and Baduanjin may be effective exercises to prevent memory decline during aging.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine the immediate effects of a combined form of Tai chi/yoga.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pretest/posttest</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coral Gables, Florida, United States.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic> = 38<break/><italic>M</italic> = 2.7 on the HSI<break/>(57% Caucasian, 14% Hispanic, 14% Asian, 5% Black, and 10% other.)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x02013;59 years (averaged 41.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 min long, including 10min of Taichi movements and 10 min of yoga postures.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI<break/>EKG<break/>EEG<break/>Math computations</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A trend for increased EEG theta activity was detected but the result was not significant enough (<italic>p</italic> = 0.10).</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The increased relaxation may have contributed to the increased speed and accuracy noted on math computations following the Tai chi/yoga class.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wei et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate whether brain structural difference existed between highly experienced TCC practitioners and healthy control non-TCC practitioners.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quasi-experiment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beijing, China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETC: 22(7 males)<break/>CG: 18<break/><italic>N</italic> = 40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETC: 52 &#x000b1; 6 years<break/>CG: 54 &#x000b1; 6 years</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No intervention.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANT (RT &#x00026; error scores)<break/>MRI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETC showed significantly thicker cortex in the right PG, IS and MFS, also in the left MOTS and LS.<break/>Thicker cortex in left MOTS and LS was associated with greater intensity of TCC practice.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCC practice could induce regional structural change in the brain.<break/>TCC might share similar patterns of neural correlates with meditation and aerobic exercise.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wei et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine TCC-associated changes in the human brain's intrinsic architecture and the relevant gains in behavioral performance.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quasi-experiment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beijing, China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETC: 22(7 males)<break/>CG: 18(8 males)<break/><italic>N</italic> = 40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETC: 52.4 &#x000b1; 6.8 years<break/>CG: 54.8 &#x000b1; 6.8 years</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No intervention.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANT<break/>R-fMRI<break/>2dReHo</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The ETC had significantly greater fHo in the right PosCG and less fHo in the left ACC and the right DLPFC.<break/>Increased functional homogeneity in the PosCG was correlated with TCC experience.<break/>Decreases in fHo in the left ACC and increases in fHo in the right PosCG both predicted performance gains on ANT.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">These findings provide evidence for the functional plasticity of the brain's intrinsic architecture toward optimizing locally functional organization.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fong et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine the relationship between physical activity and the task-switching aspect of executive function. (by investigating the modulating roles of age, modality of physical activity, and type of cognitive function using behavioral and event-related potential (ERP) assessments.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quasi-experiment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei, Taiwan</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OEE: 16<break/>OTC: 16<break/>OSL: 16<break/>YA: 16<break/><italic>N</italic> = 64</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OA: 65&#x02013;75 years<break/>OEE: 68.37 &#x000b1; 3.68<break/>OTC:67.31 &#x000b1; 4.92<break/>OSL: 68.93 &#x000b1; 4.28<break/>YA: 20&#x02013;30 years (22.43 &#x000b1; 2.58)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No intervention</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questionnaire<break/>MMSE<break/>IPAQ ERP</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YA, OEE, and OTC had significantly larger P3 amplitude compared with OSL under homogeneous and heterogeneous conditions, while no differences were observed among the former three groups.<break/>YA exhibited shorter P3 latency than OSL.<break/>The ERP findings support the model of the STAC.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regular participation in endurance exercise and Tai Chi Chuan may have equivalent beneficial effects on cognition at the behavioral and neuroelectric levels.<break/>Age and participation in physical activity influence the relationship between physical activity and task-switching, and a positive relationship was observed regardless of the modality of physical activity and type of cognitive function.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate the functional plasticity in resting-state connectivity of the prefrontal cortex and MTL in older adults.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beijing, China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IG: 17(9 men)<break/>CG: 17(11 men)<break/><italic>N</italic> = 34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IG: 68.6 &#x000b1; 5.7 years<break/>CG: 71.7 &#x000b1; 4.0 years</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cognitive intervention (MT&#x00026; EFT): 1-h session, 3 sessions/week, last for 6 weeks<break/>Tai Chi: 1-h session, 3 sessions/week, last for 6 weeks, Yang-Style 24-form Tai Chi<break/>Group counseling: 90-min session, 1 time/week, last for 6 weeks<break/>CG: two 120 min health-related lectures</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants criteria: MoCA<break/>CES-D<break/>ADL<break/>standardized assessments:<break/>PALT<break/>digit span<break/>TMT<break/>Stroop Test<break/>CFT<break/>Health status:<break/>MOS SF-36<break/>SSRS<break/>SWLS<break/>IWB<break/>Image acquisition: fMRI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After the training activities, IG showed dramatic increment in functional correlation between mPFC and PHC.L, and significantly increased functional connectivity between the mPFC and left PHG.<break/>CG showed significantly decreased connectivity between mPFC and MFG.<break/>IG showed significant correlation between the changes in the FC of mPFC-PHG and the changes in cognitive performance (CFT).<break/>IG's level of mPFC-PHC.L connectivity at the post-training scan correlated significantly with individual performance on the TMT.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multimodal intervention could postpone the effects of aging and improve the function of the regions that are most heavily influenced by aging, as well as play an important role in preserving the brain and cognition during old age.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yin et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the effects of a multimodal intervention on spontaneous brain activity in healthy older adults, and the relationship between individual differences in baseline spontaneous activity and intervention-induced changes in behavioral performance.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beijing, China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IG: 17(9 men)<break/>CG: 17(11 men)<break/><italic>N</italic> = 34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61&#x02013;79 years<break/>IG: 68.6 &#x000b1; 5.7 years<break/>CG: 71.7 &#x000b1; 4.0 years</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cognitive intervention (MT&#x00026; EFT): 1-h session, 3 sessions/week, last for 6 weeks<break/>Tai Chi: 1-h session, 3 sessions/week, last for 6 weeks, Yang-Style 24-form Tai Chi<break/>Group counseling: 90-min session, 1 time/week, last for 6 weeks<break/>CG: two 120 min health-related lectures</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants criteria: MoCA<break/>CES-D<break/>ADL<break/>standardized assessments:<break/>PALT<break/>digit span<break/>TMT<break/>Stroop Test<break/>CFT<break/>Health status:<break/>MOS SF-36<break/>SSRS<break/>SWLS<break/>IWB<break/>Image acquisition: fMRI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IG showed significantly increased ALFF in the right MFG, left SFG and left ACL, while the mean ALFF in all three ROIs was significantly reduced in CG.<break/>In IG, increased ALFF in the right MFG was significantly correlated with changes in the TMT and SWLS, and in the left ACL the ALFF increase was significantly correlated with changes in social support.<break/>The baseline ALFF in the right MFG was significantly correlated with changes in the TMT and SWLS.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multimodal intervention is effective in improving cognitive functions and well-being and can induce functional changes in the aging brain.<break/>The study suggested resting-state ALFF as a marker of intervention-induced plasticity in older adults.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zheng et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the regionally functional plasticity by using the ReHo method to do an exploratory analysis in the whole brain.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beijing, China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IG: 17(9 men)<break/>CG: 17(11 men)<break/><italic>N</italic> = 34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IG: 68.59 &#x000b1; 5.65 years<break/>CG: 71.65 &#x000b1; 4.00 years</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cognitive intervention (MT&#x00026; EFT): 1-h session, 3 sessions/week, last for 6 weeks<break/>Tai Chi: 1-h session, 3 sessions/week, last for 6 weeks, Yang-Style 24-form Tai Chi<break/>Group counseling: 90-min session, 1 time/week, last for 6 weeks<break/>CG: two 120 min health-related lectures</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants criteria: MoCA<break/>CES-D<break/>ADL<break/>standardized assessments:<break/>PALT<break/>digit span<break/>TMT<break/>Stroop Test<break/>CFT<break/>Health status:<break/>MOS SF-36<break/>SSRS<break/>SWLS<break/>IWB<break/>Image acquisition: fMRI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In IG, ReHo significantly increased in the left STG and left PCL, but decreased in the left MTG.<break/>In CG, ReHo significantly decreased in the left STG and PCL and increased in bilateral MTG.<break/>In IG, the intervention-related ReHo changes in the left STG were significantly positively correlated with changes in the CFT, and changes in the right MTG were negatively correlated with increase in the total PALT scores.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The present study confirms that the combined intervention induces regionally brain functional reorganization, and it could optimize the intrinsic functional brain architecture in the temporal cortex and cerebellum in the normal elderly.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hawkes et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine if people who were long-term Tai Chi practitioners would show enhancements to executive function and aerobic capacity.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quasi-experiment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eugene and Springfield, Oregon</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC: 10(3 female)<break/>MEG: 16(6 female)<break/>AEG: 16(8 female)<break/>SG: 12(10 female)<break/><italic>N</italic> = 54</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC: 55.4 &#x000b1; 12.99<break/>MEG: 48.63 &#x000b1; 15.00<break/>AEG: 44.09 &#x000b1; 16.2<break/>SG: 46.92 &#x000b1; 12.81</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No intervention</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rockport 1-mile walk<break/>VSTS test with EEG<break/>Button press response</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC and MEG showed significantly larger P3b switch amplitudes than sedentary controls, while AEG and SG did not differ significantly on this key executive function measure.<break/>P3b switch latency showed no significant differences between groups.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-term practice of Tai Chi may benefit a neurophysiological index of executive function.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the different physiological and psychological effects of 24TJQ in middle-aged women.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quasi-experiment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osaka, Japan</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SkG: 10<break/>NG: 10<break/><italic>N</italic> = 20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SkG: 50.56 &#x000b1; 5.45<break/>NG: 53.66 &#x000b1; 4.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-min 24TJQ exercise, with 3-min rest (before) and recovery (after)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concurrently measure with the exercise:<break/>HR<break/>RR<break/>exercise intensity<break/>physical fitness test<break/>EEG (used telemeter system to avoid noise)<break/>EMG<break/>ST</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SkG showed significantly higher values of alpha%-power in eye-closed rest and recovery period compared to NG, but they have nearly the same values during exercise.<break/>SG showed a tendency of higher beta%-power during experiment than NG.<break/>SG showed a significant increase of alpha%-power in central region compared to occipital region after exercise while there was no significant change in NG.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24TJQ is beneficial to keep or improve agility, flexibility, and muscle strength or endurance ability in middle-aged women, and gives a special effect on the cardio-respiratory system.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>RCT, randomized controlled trial; TC, Tai chi group; BDJ, Baduanjin group; CG: control group; WMS-CR, Wechsler Memory Scale&#x02013;Chinese Revision; fMRI, functional magnetic resonance imaging; resting state functional connectivity, rsFC; DFPLC, bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex; SFG, superior frontal gyrus; ACC, anterior cingulate cortex; MQ, memory quotient; HPC, hippocampus; mPFC, medial prefrontal cortex; HIS, Hollingshead Socioeconomic Index; STAI, the State Anxiety Inventory; HIS, Hollingshead Socioeconomic Index; STAI, State Anxiety Inventory; EKG, Electrocardiogram; EEG, Electroencephalogram; ETC, experienced Taichi practitioners; ANT, Attention Network Test; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; PG, precentral gyrus; IS, insula sulcus; MFS, middle frontal sulcus; STG, superior temporal gyrus; MOTS, medial occipitotemporal sulcus; LS, lingual sulcus; R-fMRI, Resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging; 2dReHo, 2d surface-based regional homogeneity; fHo, functional homogeneity; PosCG, post-central gyrus; ERP, event-related potential; OEE, older adults performing endurance exercise; OTC, older adults practicing Tai Chi Chuan; OSL, older adults with a sedentary lifestyle; YA, young adults; OA, older adults; MMSE, Mini-Mental State Examination; IPAQ, International Physical Activity Questionnaire; STAC, scaffolding theory of aging and cognition; MTL, medial temporal lobe; IG, Intervention group; MT, mnemonic training; EFT, executive function training; MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; CES-D, Center for Epidemiologic Depression Scale; ADL, activities of daily living; PALT, Paired Associative Learning Test; TMT, Trail Making Test; CFT, Category Fluency Test; MOS SF-36, Medical Outcomes Study Short Form-36; SSRS, Social Support Rating Scale; SWLS, Satisfaction with Life Scale; IWB, Index of Well-Being; mPFC, medial prefrontal cortex; HF, hippocampal formation; PHC, parahippocampal cortex; MFG, medial frontal gyrus; PHG, parahippocampal gyrus; FC, functional connectivity; SFG, superior frontal gyrus; ACL, anterior cerebellum lobe; ROI, region of interest; STG, superior temporal gyrus; PCL, posterior lobe of cerebellum; MTG, middle temporal gyrus; MEG, meditation plus exercise group; AEG, aerobic exercise group; SG, sedentary group; VSTS, Visuo-spatial task switch; 24TJQ, 24-style Taijiquan; SkG, skilled group; NG, novices' group; HR, heart rate; RR, respiratory rate; EMG, electromyography; ST, surface thermograph</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Quality assessment of eligible studies</title><p>Most of the included studies exhibited moderate (<italic>N</italic> = 5) to high (<italic>N</italic> = 5) quality of study design, with only one being categorized as low quality. Five cross-sectional studies aimed to identify different features between experienced Tai Chi practitioners and sedentary counterparts. Participants were recruited and allocated based on Tai Chi-related experiences and thus failed to meet the requirement of random allocation. For the studies without adopting intervention protocols, criterions such as similar at baseline (SB) and therapist blinded (TB) were not applicable to the studies (<italic>N</italic> = 5). Details of quality assessment are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Quality assessment of reviewed studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SAB</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SB</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TB</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AB</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DR</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ITA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OSQ</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tao et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tao et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wei et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wei et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fong et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yin et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zheng et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hawkes et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>EC, eligibility criteria; RA, random allocation; CA, concealed allocation; SAB, similar at baseline; SB, subject blinded; TB, therapist blinded; AB, assessor blinded; DR, drop-out rate; ITA, intention-to-treat analysis; BC, between-group comparison; PM, points measures; OSQ, overall study quality; CD, cannot determine; NA, not applicable</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Summary of evidence</title><p>Summary of the studies involved with four categories of interest regarding the impacts of Tai Chi on brain structures, functional connectivity, neural activity, and electric activity. Details of the summarized evidence are displayed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Brain structures</title><p>One study examined the differences in the brain structures between experienced Tai Chi practitioners and people lacking routine exercise. MRI image identified thicker cortex in the left and right hemisphere of long-term Tai Chi practitioners in comparison to the cortical regions of people with a sedentary lifestyle. The study suggested that cortex thickness in the left medial occipitotemporal sulcus and lingual sulcus is subject to the intensity of Tai Chi practice (Wei et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Functional connectivity</title><p>Tai Chi-induced benefits in cognitive function were observed after elderly participants receiving a 6-week multimodal intervention, which consisted of Tai Chi exercise, group counseling, and cognitive training. Changes in functional connectivity included enhanced rsFC between the medial prefrontal cortex and the medial temporal lobe (Li et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Given the fact that Tai Chi was the only form of physical activity in the intervention program, it is reasonable to assume that, to a certain extent, Tai Chi exercise contributed to the enhanced functional connectivity in correlation to improved cognitive performance.</p><p>Tao and colleagues examined correlates of mental control and functional connectivity (Tao et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Participants who completed Tai Chi or a similar exercise (Baduanjin) over the 12-week intervention achieved a significant improvement in mental control and memory function. fMRI identified a significant decrease in the resting state functional connectivity (rsFC) between bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) and putamen, suggesting a negative relationship between mental control improvement and rsFC DLPFC-putamen connectivity (Tao et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Superior memory function was found in alignment with increased rsFC between bilateral hippocampus and medial prefrontal cortex (Tao et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Both studies substantiated the association between cognitive function and functional connectivity in prefrontal areas.</p></sec><sec><title>Brain neural activity</title><p>Regional homogeneity (ReHo) and amplitude of low-frequency fluctuations (ALFF) in BOLD signal of fMRI revealed spontaneous neuronal activity (Zang et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Fox and Raichle, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). The previous study found that ALFF declines with aging (Zuo and Xing, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). A multimodal intervention including Tai Chi, cognitive training, and group counseling benefited the intervention group in which strengthened ALFF in the middle frontal gyrus, superior frontal gyrus, and anterior cerebellum lobe was observed (Yin et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Another study following similar protocols identified reorganized ReHo in the superior and middle temporal gyri, and the posterior lobe of the cerebellum (Zheng et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Enhanced intrinsic brain activity is the evidence of Tai Chi-induced benefits in promoting cognitive functions.</p></sec><sec><title>Brain electric activity</title><p>EEG detects brain electric activity, which is subject to physical activity. Participants showed better performance in math computation after Tai Chi and yoga practice (Field et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Increased theta activity indicated immediate relaxation during exercise. The study suggested that Tai Chi and yoga exerted an immediate impact on brain activity. Brain plasticity was partially evident in that brain activity was adaptive to specific task.</p><p>Liu et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) investigated spontaneous brain activity of Tai Chi experts and novices during practice. Experts indicated a significantly higher alpha-wave amplitude than novices in eye-close resting and recovery period, suggesting that the experts could quickly and effectively reach a psychological relaxation. Also, the experts exhibited a higher beta-wave amplitude than novices, implying that experts tend to be more physiologically excited than novices throughout the practice. Experts indicated well-developed mind concentration capacity, which was evident in the alpha shift tendency from occipital lobe to central or frontal regions.</p><p>Cognitive function was assessed by event-related potential (ERP) while subjects conducting a task-switch test under homogeneous and heterogeneous conditions (Fong et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). P3 amplitude exhibited no difference between young adults and older adults with either regular endurance training or Tai Chi exercise. However, all three groups indicated significantly larger P3 amplitude than that indicated in the group of sedentary older adults. Similar P3 patterns between young and older adults participating in long-term exercise provided evidence regarding the benefits of endurance training and Tai Chi exercise on cognitive function. Another study examining P3b amplitude of subjects conducting task-switch test confirmed the benefits of long-term Tai Chi practice in the neural substrates of executive function (Hawkes et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The included studies reported positive outcomes of Tai Chi practice in older adults. Specifically, Tai Chi-induced benefits involved with superior capacities in respect to mental control (Tao et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), memory (Tao et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), fitness (Liu et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Wei et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), cognition (Fong et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Li et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Wei et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Yin et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), and executive function (Field et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Hawkes et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zheng et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Findings as to physiological and psychological improvement substantiated the significant role of Tai Chi practice in counteracting age-related decline in motor and cognitive function. More importantly, neural imaging techniques applied to the included studies provided evidence on the connection between improved performance and changes in the neural system. Aging brain still retains some plasticity, which may contribute to delaying or reversing neurological deterioration in the aging process (Kramer et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Gabbard, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Wei et al. (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) identified effects of Tai Chi intervention on reshaping brain structures. The finding is consistent with previous studies, which observed greater cortical thickness in older adults after memory training (Engvig et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), meditation practice (Lazar et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), and aerobic exercise (Colcombe et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Functional change is associated with the development of new neurons and synapses in the brain (Honey et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Cai et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In alignment with other forms of exercise, Tai Chi exercise mitigates brain structural and functional deficits (Seidler et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Older adults maintaining an active lifestyle by routinely practicing Tai Chi indicated enhanced neural plasticity (Liu et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Field et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Fong et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Hawkes et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The included studies provided evidence-based explanation on the neural mechanisms underlying the exercise-induced improvement in motor and cognitive performance.</p><p>The reviewed studies only adopted tasks related to cognition, working memory, and executive function. Motor tasks, however, have yet been incorporated into EEG, fMRI, or MRI scan. In comparison to the EEG detection, which allows moderate physical activity, fMRI and MRI require subjects to maintain a resting state. Even small head motions may produce noise in brain scans (Power et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Satterthwaite et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Van Dijk et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), which proposed a challenge of integrate neuroimaging techniques into motor tasks. Researchers have designed a few tasks, which require a small range of motion such as finger tapping (Stoodley et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Gardini et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), reaching and grasping (Culham et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), and lower limb joint motions (Kapreli et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). To expand knowledge on neural correlates of motor performance, feasible motor tasks should be developed to fit the setting of research employing the neuroimaging techniques.</p><p>Older adults experience reduced hemispheric asymmetry due to age-related deficits in neural connectivity (Cabeza, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Evidence from fMRI scan indicated symmetric brain activations when older adults were performing cognitive tasks (Grady, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). A recent study involved with older adults also identified reduced asymmetry in movement patterns between dominant and non-dominant hand, suggesting a potential connection to the reduced hemispheric asymmetry (Przybyla et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). However, the theory remains to be an assumption without direct evidence from a study, which applies fMRI to motor tasks. By investigating the change in motor performance, whether it is associated with age-related degeneration or Tai Chi-incurred improvement, researchers can better understand neural mechanisms underlying the aging process.</p><p>The lack of robust empirical research on Tai Chi-incurred changes for older adults is a limitation of the review. The inherent risk of bias in the study design, paired with the limited literature, suggests the necessity of an increasing number of RCTs in this field. Only two of the included studies reported effect size, which makes it difficult to compare the effectiveness between studies. Future research should report the effect size so that critical conclusion can be reached based on statistical evidence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The literature review summarized 11 studies, which employed neuroimaging techniques and EEG to investigate effects of Tai Chi on hemispheric reorganization. The reviewed articles provide evidence that there may be cognitive improvement associated with modified brain activity, functional connectivity, and brain structures in older adults through Tai Chi exercise. Future studies should account for the potential connection between changed motor functions and corresponding neural mechanisms underlying the aging process. RCTs are needed to provide powerful evidence on the effect of Tai Chi intervention. In contrast to previous research focusing on performance, future studies should analyze the effects of intervention from the neurological standpoint. Applying neuroimaging techniques and EEG to Tai Chi intervention is worth investigating, which allows researchers to explore the neural mechanisms related to the effectiveness of Tai Chi exercise on counteracting the aging process.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>ZP and XS contributed to the conception and design of the review. ZP, XS, and QF applied the search strategy. All authors applied the selection criteria. All authors completed assessment of risk of bias. All authors analyzed the data and interpreted data. XS, QF, and ZP wrote this manuscript. LH, YL, CC, JL, and M-LK critically edited the manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This research was supported by a combination of institutions as stated below: National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC31401018); The National Research Foundation of Korea Grant funded by the Korean Government (MOE) (NRF 2017S1A2A2039405); Mississippi State University College of Education Undergraduate Student Research Grant.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boychuk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Remple</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleim</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Motor training induces experience-specific patterns of plasticity across motor cortex and spinal cord</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>1776</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1782</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00515.2006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16959909?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16959909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabeza</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Hemispheric asymmetry reduction in older adults: the HAROLD model</article-title>. <source>Psychol. Aging</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0882-7974.17.1.85</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11931290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11931290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Brain plasticity and motor practice in cognitive aging</article-title>. <source>Front. Aging Neurosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2014.00031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24653695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24653695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colcombe</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>K. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalf</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Aerobic exercise training increases brain volume in aging humans</article-title>. <source>J. Gerontol. Ser. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>1166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1170</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/61.11.1166</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17167157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colcombe</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>K. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalf</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Cardiovascular fitness, cortical plasticity, and aging</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>3316</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3321</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0400266101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14978288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14978288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Culham</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danckert</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gati</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodale</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Visually guided grasping produces fMRI activation in dorsal but not ventral stream brain areas</article-title>. <source>Exp. Brain Res.</source>
<volume>153</volume>, <fpage>180</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>189</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-003-1591-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12961051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engvig</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fjell</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westlye</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moberget</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundseth</surname><given-names>&#x000d8;.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Effects of memory training on cortical thickness in the elderly</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>1667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1676</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.05.041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20580844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20580844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>K. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colcombe</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadhwa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bherer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalf</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Training-induced plasticity in older adults: effects of training on hemispheric asymmetry</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol. Aging</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2005.12.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16480789?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16480789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>K. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gildengers</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butters</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Physical activity and brain plasticity in late adulthood</article-title>. <source>Dialogues Clin. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>108</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 23576893?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23576893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diego</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Reif</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Tai chi/yoga effects on anxiety, heartrate, EEG and math computations</article-title>. <source>Complement. Ther. Clin. Pract.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctcp.2010.05.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20920810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20920810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The benefits of endurance exercise and Tai Chi Chuan for the task-switching aspect of executive function in older adults: an ERP study</article-title>. <source>Front. Aging Neurosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2014.00295</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25389403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25389403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raichle</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Spontaneous fluctuations in brain activity observed with functional magnetic resonance imaging</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>700</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>711</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2201</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17704812?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17704812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>A. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Intrinsic fluctuations within cortical systems account for intertrial variability in human behavior</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2007.08.023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17920023?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17920023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabbard</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Lifelong Motor Development.</source>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Higher Ed.</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venneri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGeown</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toraci</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nocetti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Porro</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Brain activation patterns characterizing different phases of motor action: execution, choice and ideation</article-title>. <source>Brain Topogr.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>692</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10548-016-0491-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27072014?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27072014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giedd</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raznahan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander-Bloch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gogtay</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Child psychiatry branch of the National Institute of Mental Health longitudinal structural magnetic resonance imaging study of human brain development</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2014.236</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25195638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25195638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Functional brain imaging and age-related changes in cognition</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychol.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0301-0511(00)00059-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11035226?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11035226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishihira</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamijo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effects of habitual moderate exercise on response processing and cognitive processing in older adults</article-title>. <source>Jpn. J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2170/jjphysiol.R2068</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15796787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15796787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manselle</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woollacott</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Tai Chi and meditation-plus-exercise benefit neural substrates of executive function: a cross-sectional, controlled study</article-title>. <source>J. Complement. Integr. Med.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jcim-2013-0031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25294719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25294719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffstaedter</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grefkes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roski</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caspers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilles</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eickhoff</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Age-related decrease of functional connectivity additional to gray matter atrophy in a network for movement initiation</article-title>. <source>Brain Struct. Funct.</source>
<volume>220</volume>, <fpage>999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1012</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-013-0696-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24399178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24399178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honey</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporns</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammoun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gigandet</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiran</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meuli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Predicting human resting-state functional connectivity from structural connectivity</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>2035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2040</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0811168106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19188601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanzo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerpa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The effect of Tai Chi on functional lower extremity mobility and strength, ankle proprioception, and postural adaptation in older adults</article-title>. <source>American J. Med. Med. Sci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5923/j.ajmms.20170706.01</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapreli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanasopoulos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papathanasiou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Hecke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strimpakos</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouliamos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Lateralization of brain activity during lower limb joints movement. An fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1721</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.05.043</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16859927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16859927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bherer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colcombe</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenough</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Environmental influences on cognitive and brain plasticity during aging</article-title>. <source>J. Gerontol. Ser. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>M940</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>M957</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/59.9.M940</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15472160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15472160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>V. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Interim follow-up of a randomized controlled trial comparing Chinese style mind body (Tai Chi) and stretching exercises on cognitive function in subjects at risk of progressive cognitive decline</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Geriatr. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>740</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.2602</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21495078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21495078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Meditation experience is associated with increased cortical thickness</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1893</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.wnr.0000186598.66243.19</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16272874?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Multimodal intervention in older adults improves resting-state functional connectivity between the medial prefrontal cortex and medial temporal lobe</article-title>. <source>Front. Aging Neurosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2014.00039</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24653698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24653698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikuda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Physiological benefits of 24-style Taijiquan exercise in middle-aged women</article-title>. <source>J. Physiol. Anthropol. Appl. Human Sci.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2114/jpa.22.219</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14519910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14519910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balachandran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harriell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Comparative impacts of tai chi, balance training, and a specially-designed yoga program on balance in older fallers</article-title>. <source>Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.</source>
<volume>95</volume>, <fpage>1620.e30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1628.e30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apmr.2014.04.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24835753?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24835753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Par&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Immediate neural plasticity shapes motor performance</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>RC52</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-01-j0005.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10627629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10627629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petzinger</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vukovic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akopian</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meshul</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Enhancing neuroplasticity in the basal ganglia: the role of exercise in Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source>Mov. Disord.</source>
<volume>25</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>), <fpage>S141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S145</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.22782</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20187247?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20187247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>A. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaggar</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Spurious but systematic correlations in functional connectivity MRI networks arise from subject motion</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>2142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2154</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.10.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22019881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22019881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Przybyla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaland</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagesteiro</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Motor asymmetry reduction in older adults</article-title>. <source>Neurosci. Lett.</source>
<volume>489</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2010.11.074</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21144883?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21144883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Changes in leg muscle strength and power after Tai Chi exercise in patients with symptomatic knee osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr. Cartil.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>S430</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2016.01.776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satterthwaite</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loughead</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruparel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakonarson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Impact of in-scanner head motion on multiple measures of functional connectivity: relevance for studies of neurodevelopment in youth</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>632</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.12.063</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22233733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22233733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seidler</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burutolu</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fling</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwin</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Motor control and aging: links to age-related brain structural, functional, and biochemical effects</article-title>. <source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>733</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2009.10.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19850077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19850077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoodley</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valera</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmahmann</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Functional topography of the cerebellum for motor and cognitive tasks: an fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>1560</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1570</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.08.065</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21907811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21907811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egorova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Tai Chi Chuan and Baduanjin practice modulates functional connectivity of the cognitive control network in older adults</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>41581</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep41581</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28169310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28169310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egorova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Increased hippocampus&#x02013;medial prefrontal cortex resting-state functional connectivity and memory function after tai chi chuan practice in elder adults</article-title>. <source>Front. Aging Neurosci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2016.00025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26909038?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26909038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomasi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Aging and functional brain networks</article-title>. <source>Mol. Psychiatry</source> 17, <volume>471</volume>, <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>558</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2012.27</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tousignant</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corriveau</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Efficacy of supervised Tai Chi exercises versus conventional physical therapy exercises in fall prevention for frail older adults: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Disabil. Rehabil.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1435</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09638288.2012.737084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23167499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23167499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabuncu</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckner</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The influence of head motion on intrinsic functional connectivity MRI</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.07.044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21810475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhagen</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vet</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bie</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessels</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boers</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouter</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The Delphi list: a criteria list for quality assessment of randomized clinical trials for conducting systematic reviews developed by Delphi consensus</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Epidemiol.</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0895-4356(98)00131-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10086815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10086815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>K. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaddock</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Neurobiological markers of exercise-related brain plasticity in older adults</article-title>. <source>Brain Behav. Immun.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2012.10.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23123199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23123199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor-Piliae</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>K. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effect of Tai Chi on cognitive performance in older adults: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.12611</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24383523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24383523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>G. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>X. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Tai Chi Chuan optimizes the functional organization of the intrinsic human brain architecture in older adults</article-title>. <source>Front. Aging Neurosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2014.00074</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24860494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24860494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>G.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>F.-M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Can Taichi reshape the brain? A brain morphometry study</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e61038</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061038</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23585869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23585869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Coordination exercise and postural stability in elderly people: effect of Tai Chi Chuan</article-title>. <source>Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>608</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>612</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/apmr.2001.22615</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11346836?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11346836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Intervention-induced enhancement in intrinsic brain activity in healthy older adults</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>7309</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep07309</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25472002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25472002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Regional homogeneity approach to fMRI data analysis</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2003.12.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15110032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Combined cognitive-psychological-physical intervention induces reorganization of intrinsic functional brain architecture in older adults</article-title>. <source>Neural Plast.</source>
<volume>2015</volume>:<fpage>713104</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/713104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25810927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25810927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>X. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>X. X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Test-retest reliabilities of resting-state FMRI measurements in human brain functional connectomics: a systems neuroscience perspective</article-title>. <source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2014.05.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24875392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24875392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>