<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front Aging NeurosciFront Aging NeurosciFront. Aging Neurosci.Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience1663-4365Frontiers Media S.A.591596310.3389/fnagi.2018.00110NeuroscienceSystematic ReviewThe Effects of Tai Chi Intervention on Healthy Elderly by Means of Neuroimaging and EEG: A Systematic ReviewPanZhujun1*SuXiwen2FangQun1HouLijuan2LeeYounghan1ChenChih C.1LamberthJohn1KimMi-Lyang31Department of Kinesiology, Mississippi State University, Starkville, MS, United States2Exercise Physiology Laboratory, College of Physical Education and Sports, Beijing Normal University, Beijing, China3Department of Sports, Leisure and Recreation, Soonchunhyang University, Asan, South KoreaEdited by: Sarah A. Schoen, STAR Institute for Sensory Processing Disorder, United StatesReviewed by: Xu Lei, Southwest University, China; Deep R. Sharma, SUNY Downstate Medical Center, United States*Correspondence: Zhujun Pan zp147@msstate.edu184201820181011009120180342018Copyright © 2018 Pan, Su, Fang, Hou, Lee, Chen, Lamberth and Kim.2018Pan, Su, Fang, Hou, Lee, Chen, Lamberth and KimThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Aging is a process associated with a decline in cognitive and motor functions, which can be attributed to neurological changes in the brain. Tai Chi, a multimodal mind-body exercise, can be practiced by people across all ages. Previous research identified effects of Tai Chi practice on delaying cognitive and motor degeneration. Benefits in behavioral performance included improved fine and gross motor skills, postural control, muscle strength, and so forth. Neural plasticity remained in the aging brain implies that Tai Chi-associated benefits may not be limited to the behavioral level. Instead, neurological changes in the human brain play a significant role in corresponding to the behavioral improvement. However, previous studies mainly focused on the effects of behavioral performance, leaving neurological changes largely unknown. This systematic review summarized extant studies that used brain imaging techniques and EEG to examine the effects of Tai Chi on older adults. Eleven articles were eligible for the final review. Three neuroimaging techniques including fMRI (N = 6), EEG (N = 4), and MRI (N = 1), were employed for different study interests. Significant changes were reported on subjects' cortical thickness, functional connectivity and homogeneity of the brain, and executive network neural function after Tai Chi intervention. The findings suggested that Tai Chi intervention give rise to beneficial neurological changes in the human brain. Future research should develop valid and convincing study design by applying neuroimaging techniques to detect effects of Tai Chi intervention on the central nervous system of older adults. By integrating neuroimaging techniques into randomized controlled trials involved with Tai Chi intervention, researchers can extend the current research focus from behavioral domain to neurological level.Tai ChiagingneuroimagingEEGneural plasticityNational Natural Science Foundation of China10.13039/501100001809NSFC31401018Ministry of Education10.13039/501100002701NRF-2017S1A2A2039405<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Literature search</title><p>Five electronic databases (Google scholar, PubMed, Cochrane Library, Scopus, and Web of science) were searched for relevant studies published since 1990. The following terms were entered in multiple combinations, including older adults, elderly, seniors, aging, Tai Chi Chuan, Tai chi, Taichi, and Tai Ji. Terms for neuroimaging techniques include brain imaging, electroencephalography (EEG), event-related potentials (ERP) diffuse optical tomography (DOT), diffuse optical imaging (DOI), event-related optical signal (EROS), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) arterial spin labeling (ASL), magnetoencephalography (MEG), computed tomography (CT), positron emission tomography (PET), and single-photon emission computerized tomography (SPECT). Manual search was conducted for known articles in the area by titles instead of keywords search.</p></sec><sec><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>Studies were eligible for inclusion if the following criteria were met: (1) subjects were healthy older adults or middle-aged adults (average age of Tai Chi group must be over 50); (2) Tai Chi was applied to exercise intervention; (3) brain imaging methods including MRI, fMRI, EEG, ERP etc. were used to assess variables of interest. The screening process consisted of two phases. First, two reviewers (XS &amp; ZP) independently examined title, keywords, and abstracts of retrieved articles. In the second phase, a third author (QF) was responsible to deal with any disagreement between the reviewers.</p><p>Studies that failed to conform to one of the specified criteria were considered ineligible. To gain a comprehensive understanding of Tai Chi-related changes in the central nervous system of older adults, there were no restrictions on the types of studies. However, conference abstracts, review articles, monograph, and videos were excluded.</p></sec><sec><title>Quality assessment</title><p>The methodological quality was assessed by Delphi list for quality assessment (Verhagen et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). To reduce the risk of bias in assessment, two reviewers (XS &amp; ZP) independently scored the quality of the included articles. Inconsistencies between the two reviewers were solved after discussing with a third author.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction</title><p>Study characteristics encompass basic information of the selected articles, including author(s) of study and year of publication, study design, place of study, sample size and attribution rate, intervention frequency and duration, age of subjects, and measures. Age of subjects refers to the average group age, which should be above 50. Measures applied to the studies must include neuroimaging (fMRI or MRI) or neuroelectric techniques (EEG). Rationale, findings, and practical implications were summarized according to the purpose, results, and conclusions of the retrieved studies.</p></sec></sec>Author contributionsZP and XS contributed to the conception and design of the review. ZP, XS, and QF applied the search strategy. All authors applied the selection criteria. All authors completed assessment of risk of bias. All authors analyzed the data and interpreted data. XS, QF, and ZP wrote this manuscript. LH, YL, CC, JL, and M-LK critically edited the manuscript.Conflict of interest statementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.Funding. This research was supported by a combination of institutions as stated below: National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC31401018); The National Research Foundation of Korea Grant funded by the Korean Government (MOE) (NRF 2017S1A2A2039405); Mississippi State University College of Education Undergraduate Student Research Grant.ReferencesAdkinsD. L.BoychukJ.RempleM. S.KleimJ. A. (2006). Motor training induces experience-specific patterns of plasticity across motor cortex and spinal cord. J. Appl. Physiol.
101, 1776–1782. 10.1152/japplphysiol.00515.200616959909CabezaR. (2002). Hemispheric asymmetry reduction in older adults: the HAROLD model. Psychol. Aging
17, 85–100. 10.1037/0882-7974.17.1.8511931290CaiL.ChanJ. S.YanJ. H.PengK. (2014). Brain plasticity and motor practice in cognitive aging. Front. Aging Neurosci.
6:31. 10.3389/fnagi.2014.0003124653695ColcombeS. J.EricksonK. I.ScalfP. E.KimJ. S.PrakashR.McAuleyE.. (2006). Aerobic exercise training increases brain volume in aging humans. J. Gerontol. Ser. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
61, 1166–1170. 10.1093/gerona/61.11.116617167157ColcombeS. J.KramerA. F.EricksonK. I.ScalfP.McAuleyE.CohenN. J.. (2004). Cardiovascular fitness, cortical plasticity, and aging. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
101, 3316–3321. 10.1073/pnas.040026610114978288CulhamJ. C.DanckertS. L.De SouzaJ. F.GatiJ. S.MenonR. S.GoodaleM. A. (2003). Visually guided grasping produces fMRI activation in dorsal but not ventral stream brain areas. Exp. Brain Res.
153, 180–189. 10.1007/s00221-003-1591-512961051EngvigA.FjellA. M.WestlyeL. T.MobergetT.SundsethØ.LarsenV. A.. (2010). Effects of memory training on cortical thickness in the elderly. Neuroimage
52, 1667–1676. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.05.04120580844EricksonK. I.ColcombeS. J.WadhwaR.BhererL.PetersonM. S.ScalfP. E.. (2007). Training-induced plasticity in older adults: effects of training on hemispheric asymmetry. Neurobiol. Aging
28, 272–283. 10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2005.12.01216480789EricksonK. I.GildengersA. G.ButtersM. A. (2013). Physical activity and brain plasticity in late adulthood. Dialogues Clin. Neurosci.
15, 99–108. 23576893FieldT.DiegoM.Hernandez-ReifM. (2010). Tai chi/yoga effects on anxiety, heartrate, EEG and math computations. Complement. Ther. Clin. Pract.
16, 235–238. 10.1016/j.ctcp.2010.05.01420920810FongD. Y.ChiL. K.LiF.ChangY. K. (2014). The benefits of endurance exercise and Tai Chi Chuan for the task-switching aspect of executive function in older adults: an ERP study. Front. Aging Neurosci.
6:295. 10.3389/fnagi.2014.0029525389403FoxM. D.RaichleM. E. (2007). Spontaneous fluctuations in brain activity observed with functional magnetic resonance imaging. Nat. Rev. Neurosci.
8, 700–711. 10.1038/nrn220117704812FoxM. D.SnyderA. Z.VincentJ. L.. (2007). Intrinsic fluctuations within cortical systems account for intertrial variability in human behavior. Neuron
56, 171–184. 10.1016/j.neuron.2007.08.02317920023GabbardC. P. (2011). Lifelong Motor Development.
San Francisco, CA: Pearson Higher Ed.GardiniS.VenneriA.McGeownW. J.ToraciC.NocettiL.PorroC. A.. (2016). Brain activation patterns characterizing different phases of motor action: execution, choice and ideation. Brain Topogr.
29, 679–692. 10.1007/s10548-016-0491-527072014GieddJ. N.RaznahanA.Alexander-BlochA.SchmittE.GogtayN.RapoportJ. L. (2015). Child psychiatry branch of the National Institute of Mental Health longitudinal structural magnetic resonance imaging study of human brain development. Neuropsychopharmacology
40, 43–49. 10.1038/npp.2014.23625195638GradyC. L. (2000). Functional brain imaging and age-related changes in cognition. Biol. Psychol.
54, 259–281. 10.1016/S0301-0511(00)00059-411035226HattaA.NishihiraY.KimS. R.KanedaT.KidaT.KamijoK.. (2005). Effects of habitual moderate exercise on response processing and cognitive processing in older adults. Jpn. J. Physiol.
55, 29–36. 10.2170/jjphysiol.R206815796787HawkesT. D.ManselleW.WoollacottM. H. (2014). Tai Chi and meditation-plus-exercise benefit neural substrates of executive function: a cross-sectional, controlled study. J. Complement. Integr. Med.
11, 279–288. 10.1515/jcim-2013-003125294719HoffstaedterF.GrefkesC.RoskiC.CaspersS.ZillesK.EickhoffS. B. (2015). Age-related decrease of functional connectivity additional to gray matter atrophy in a network for movement initiation. Brain Struct. Funct.
220, 999–1012. 10.1007/s00429-013-0696-224399178HoneyC. J.SpornsO.CammounL.GigandetX.ThiranJ. P.MeuliR.. (2009). Predicting human resting-state functional connectivity from structural connectivity. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
106, 2035–2040. 10.1073/pnas.081116810619188601JainA.TaylorJ.SanzoP.ZerpaC. (2017). The effect of Tai Chi on functional lower extremity mobility and strength, ankle proprioception, and postural adaptation in older adults. American J. Med. Med. Sci.
7, 229–237. 10.5923/j.ajmms.20170706.01KapreliE.AthanasopoulosS.PapathanasiouM.Van HeckeP.StrimpakosN.GouliamosA.. (2006). Lateralization of brain activity during lower limb joints movement. An fMRI study. Neuroimage
32, 1709–1721. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.05.04316859927KramerA. F.BhererL.ColcombeS. J.DongW.GreenoughW. T. (2004). Environmental influences on cognitive and brain plasticity during aging. J. Gerontol. Ser. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.
59, M940–M957. 10.1093/gerona/59.9.M94015472160LamL. C.ChauR. C.WongB. M.FungA. W.LuiV. W.TamC. C.. (2011). Interim follow-up of a randomized controlled trial comparing Chinese style mind body (Tai Chi) and stretching exercises on cognitive function in subjects at risk of progressive cognitive decline. Int. J. Geriatr. Psychiatry
26, 733–740. 10.1002/gps.260221495078LazarS. W.KerrC. E.WassermanR. H.. (2005). Meditation experience is associated with increased cortical thickness. Neuroreport
16:1893. 10.1097/01.wnr.0000186598.66243.1916272874LiR.ZhuX.YinS.NiuY.ZhengZ.HuangX.. (2014). Multimodal intervention in older adults improves resting-state functional connectivity between the medial prefrontal cortex and medial temporal lobe. Front. Aging Neurosci.
6:39. 10.3389/fnagi.2014.0003924653698LiuY.MimuraK.WangL.IkudaK. (2003). Physiological benefits of 24-style Taijiquan exercise in middle-aged women. J. Physiol. Anthropol. Appl. Human Sci.
22, 219–225. 10.2114/jpa.22.21914519910NiM.MooneyK.RichardsL.BalachandranA.SunM.HarriellK.. (2014). Comparative impacts of tai chi, balance training, and a specially-designed yoga program on balance in older fallers. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.
95, 1620.e30–1628.e30. 10.1016/j.apmr.2014.04.02224835753ParéM.MunozD. P. (2000). Immediate neural plasticity shapes motor performance. J. Neurosci.
20:RC52. 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-01-j0005.200010627629PetzingerG. M.FisherB. E.Van LeeuwenJ. E.VukovicM.AkopianG.MeshulC. K.. (2010). Enhancing neuroplasticity in the basal ganglia: the role of exercise in Parkinson's disease. Mov. Disord.
25(Suppl. 1), S141–S145. 10.1002/mds.2278220187247PowerJ. D.BarnesK. A.SnyderA. Z.SchlaggarB. L.PetersenS. E. (2012). Spurious but systematic correlations in functional connectivity MRI networks arise from subject motion. Neuroimage
59, 2142–2154. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.10.01822019881PrzybylaA.HaalandK. Y.BagesteiroL. B.. (2011). Motor asymmetry reduction in older adults. Neurosci. Lett.
489, 99–104. 10.1016/j.neulet.2010.11.07421144883ReidK.PriceL.HarveyW. (2016). Changes in leg muscle strength and power after Tai Chi exercise in patients with symptomatic knee osteoarthritis. Osteoarthr. Cartil.
24:S430
10.1016/j.joca.2016.01.776SatterthwaiteT. D.WolfD. H.LougheadJ.RuparelK.ElliottM. A.HakonarsonH.. (2012). Impact of in-scanner head motion on multiple measures of functional connectivity: relevance for studies of neurodevelopment in youth. Neuroimage
60, 623–632. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.12.06322233733SeidlerR. D.BernardJ. A.BurutoluT. B.FlingB. W.GordonM. T.GwinJ. T.. (2010). Motor control and aging: links to age-related brain structural, functional, and biochemical effects. Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
34, 721–733. 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2009.10.00519850077StoodleyC. J.ValeraE. M.SchmahmannJ. D. (2012). Functional topography of the cerebellum for motor and cognitive tasks: an fMRI study. Neuroimage
59, 1560–1570. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.08.06521907811TaoJ.ChenX.EgorovaN.LiuJ.XueX.WangQ.. (2017). Tai Chi Chuan and Baduanjin practice modulates functional connectivity of the cognitive control network in older adults. Sci. Rep.
7:41581. 10.1038/srep4158128169310TaoJ.LiuJ.EgorovaN.ChenX.SunS.XueX.. (2016). Increased hippocampus–medial prefrontal cortex resting-state functional connectivity and memory function after tai chi chuan practice in elder adults. Front. Aging Neurosci.
8:25. 10.3389/fnagi.2016.0002526909038TomasiD.VolkowN. D. (2012). Aging and functional brain networks. Mol. Psychiatry 17, 471, 549–558. 10.1038/mp.2012.27TousignantM.CorriveauH.RoyP. M.. (2013). Efficacy of supervised Tai Chi exercises versus conventional physical therapy exercises in fall prevention for frail older adults: a randomized controlled trial. Disabil. Rehabil.
35, 1429–1435. 10.3109/09638288.2012.73708423167499Van DijkK. R.SabuncuM. R.BucknerR. L. (2012). The influence of head motion on intrinsic functional connectivity MRI. Neuroimage
59, 431–438. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.07.04421810475VerhagenA. P.de VetH. C.de BieR. A.KesselsA. G.BoersM.BouterL. M.. (1998). The Delphi list: a criteria list for quality assessment of randomized clinical trials for conducting systematic reviews developed by Delphi consensus. J. Clin. Epidemiol.
51, 1235–1241. 10.1016/S0895-4356(98)00131-010086815VossM. W.EricksonK. I.PrakashR. S.ChaddockL.KimJ. S.AlvesH.. (2013). Neurobiological markers of exercise-related brain plasticity in older adults. Brain Behav. Immun.
28, 90–99. 10.1016/j.bbi.2012.10.02123123199WayneP. M.WalshJ. N.Taylor-PiliaeR. E.WellsR. E.PappK. V.DonovanN. J.. (2014). Effect of Tai Chi on cognitive performance in older adults: systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Am. Geriatr. Soc.
62, 25–39. 10.1111/jgs.1261124383523WeiG. X.DongH. M.YangZ.LuoJ.ZuoX. N. (2014). Tai Chi Chuan optimizes the functional organization of the intrinsic human brain architecture in older adults. Front. Aging Neurosci.
6:74. 10.3389/fnagi.2014.0007424860494WeiG.-X.XuT.FanF.-M.. (2013). Can Taichi reshape the brain? A brain morphometry study. PLoS ONE
8:e61038. 10.1371/journal.pone.006103823585869WongA. M.LinY. C.ChouS. W.TangF. T.WongP. Y. (2001). Coordination exercise and postural stability in elderly people: effect of Tai Chi Chuan. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil.
82, 608–612. 10.1053/apmr.2001.2261511346836YinS.ZhuX.LiR.NiuY.WangB.ZhengZ.. (2014). Intervention-induced enhancement in intrinsic brain activity in healthy older adults. Sci. Rep.
4:7309. 10.1038/srep0730925472002ZangY.JiangT.LuY.HeY.TianL. (2004). Regional homogeneity approach to fMRI data analysis. Neuroimage
22, 394–400. 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2003.12.03015110032ZhengZ.ZhuX.YinS.WangB.NiuY.HuangX.. (2015). Combined cognitive-psychological-physical intervention induces reorganization of intrinsic functional brain architecture in older adults. Neural Plast.
2015:713104. 10.1155/2015/71310425810927ZuoX. N.XingX. X. (2014). Test-retest reliabilities of resting-state FMRI measurements in human brain functional connectomics: a systems neuroscience perspective. Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.
45, 100–118. 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2014.05.00924875392
