<?xml version="1.0"?>
JBI Database System Rev Implement RepJBI Database System Rev Implement RepJBISRISJbi Database of Systematic Reviews and Implementation Reports2202-4433Wolters Kluwer5437711JBISRIR-2016-00322910.11124/JBISRIR-2016-003229Systematic ReviewsEffects of foot and ankle devices on balance, gait and falls in adults with sensory perception loss: a systematic reviewPatonJoanne1HattonAnna L.2RomeKeith3KentBridie451School of Health Professions, Plymouth University, Plymouth, Devon, United Kingdom2School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia3Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Sciences, Auckland University of Technology, Auckland 1010, New Zealand4The University of Plymouth Centre for Innovations in Health and Social Care: a Joanna Briggs Institute Centre of Excellence5School of Nursing and Midwifery, Plymouth University, Plymouth, Devon, United KingdomCorrespondence: Joanne Paton, joanne.paton@plymouth.ac.uk12201622220171412127162© 2016 THE JOANNA BRIGGS INSTITUTE2016EXECUTIVE SUMMARYObjectivesThe objective of the review was to evaluate the effectiveness of foot and ankle devices for the prevention of falls and the improvement of balance and gait in adults with sensory perception loss.Inclusion criteria Types of participantsParticipants were community-dwelling adults with bilateral pathological sensory perception loss.Types of intervention(s)/phenomena of interestThe current review evaluated any foot or ankle device, including but not restricted to, all types of footwear (therapeutic and retail), insoles (customized and prefabricated) and ankle-foot orthoses (AFOs).Types of studiesIn the absence of randomized controlled trials (RCT), the review considered experimental and epidemiological study designs, except case series, individual case reports and descriptive cross-sectional studies.OutcomesThe primary outcome was number of falls. Secondary outcome measures were clinical or laboratory measures of balance or gait.Search strategyA search for published and unpublished literature from inception to March 2015 written in the English language was conducted across a number of major electronic databases. A three-step search strategy was developed using MeSH terminology and keywords to ensure all that relevant materials are captured.Methodological qualityMethodological quality of included studies was assessed by two reviewers, who appraised each study independently, using standardized Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) critical appraisal tools.Data extractionQuantitative data were extracted from the studies that were identified as meeting the criteria for methodological quality using the standardized JBI data extraction tools.Data synthesisDue to the heterogeneity of populations, interventions and outcome measures, meta-analyses were not possible and results are presented in narrative form.KeywordsBalancefallsfootwearinsolesneuropathyBackgroundSensory perception loss in the lower limbs is commonly associated with a number of chronic conditions including diabetes, neurological and autoimmune diseases.1-4 Peripheral neuropathy associated with diabetes is the most common cause of sensory perception loss, affecting up to 50% of individuals with the condition.4 Altered somatosensory input can have major implications on postural control. At the feet, reduced information about the supporting surface or altered awareness of lower limb positioning can impair the ability to successfully respond to threats to balance. These sensory changes, commonly observed in aging populations, can be accelerated in adults with pathological loss of foot sensation,3,5 increasing their risk of falls and injury.6-8Falls are a major public health issue for adults with sensory perception loss. In people with diabetes, many of whom present with peripheral neuropathy, up to 39% of those aged over 65 years8 and 35% of those above 55 years9 are reported to fall annually. While pathological sensory loss cannot be reversed, one potential modifiable external fall risk factor is the interface between the foot or ankle and supporting surface. Foot and ankle devices including footwear, insoles and ankle-foot orthoses (AFOs) are all modalities that can be manipulated to alter this interface and potentially an individual's propensity to falling. Indeed, several studies show that wearing suboptimal footwear is an influential factor contributing to slips, trips and falls in older people.10 Notably, inappropriate footwear has been reported in up to 75% of people who experience a fall-related hip fracture.11Foot and ankle devices, including shoe insoles and AFOs have been shown to alter standing balance,12 gait kinetics and kinematics12-14 in healthy young,13 aging,12 rheumatoid arthritic15 and diabetic neuropathic14 populations. While their mechanism of action remains unclear, current theories suggest that footwear interventions may bring about their effects by way of providing mechanical support, shock attenuation and alterations in sensorimotor control, or a combination of all.16,17 Mechanoreceptors located in the plantar surface of the feet provide important sensory information about changes in the position of foot pressure, which is used to inform maintenance of upright body position. However, plantar sensory thresholds are reduced with increasing age18,19 and further compromised in those with pathological sensory perception loss.3,20 As such, a wide range of shoe insole devices have been developed with a view to enhancing residual sensory information at the lower limbs for improving balance control and gait in insensate populations.21-26 Insoles can be defined as any material construction positioned within a shoe, on which the foot rests. Insoles can be pre-fabricated or custom-made devices and include a variety of profiles ranging from form-fitting to flat insoles.To date, three systematic reviews have been conducted addressing the impact of insoles12,27 and footwear features10 on measures of balance and falls risk in aging populations, including those with peripheral nervous system disorders.27 However, despite the major clinical and functional implications of sensory perception loss, the role of footwear interventions in this patient group has not been addressed using systematic review methodology. The prescription of therapeutic footwear and insoles plays a pivotal role in the management of people with peripheral neuropathy, as a means to reduce areas of high plantar pressures and prevent the development of foot ulceration.28 While this preventative strategy aligns with recommendations from the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence guidelines29 and a Cochrane review of the data,30 the potential benefits (or otherwise) of such footwear interventions on balance, gait or falls risk remain unknown.Laboratory and clinical-based measures of balance and gait have been used to explore the effects of wearing footwear interventions on postural control mechanisms.12,31-33 During static balance tasks, such as standing quietly in a comfortable position (unperturbed), on a force platform, the magnitude and velocity of center of pressure (COP) movement in mediolateral and anterior-posterior axes have been extracted to quantify the effect of insoles and footwear.12 Notably, COP velocity is reported to be one of the most sensitive measures in detecting between-condition differences in balance control.34 Other traditional sway parameters, such as mean speed and amplitude of the COP, have been used in previous trials to predict falls.35 Clinical assessments of mobility and functional task performance enable clinicians to observe balance control during demanding postural challenges that simulate those encountered in daily life.36,37 Such balance tests include the functional reach and Berg Balance Scale, with the former reported to be a predictor of falls and sensitive to change following the introduction of an intervention.38,39 Further, modifications in walking patterns have been associated with falls in aging populations.40 Older fallers frequently adopt a more conservative gait pattern, showing marked reductions in velocity and step length, increased step width and variability.41,42 Therefore, spatiotemporal gait parameters commonly feature as primary outcome measures in studies evaluating the effect of an intervention on falls risk.12,43,44The aim of this review was three-fold. First, the review aimed to highlight balance and gait deficits and falls risk for consideration by healthcare professionals when prescribing foot and ankle devices to people with loss of foot sensation. Second, this review set out to establish the therapeutic benefits (or otherwise) of foot and ankle devices on laboratory and clinical measures of balance, mobility and falls, within clinical populations with sensory perception loss. Third, the results of this review will be used to identify any footwear interventions and design features that have the capacity to alter balance, gait and reduce falls. This knowledge will be used to guide the future prescription and development of foot and ankle devices for people with pathological sensory perception loss. This review was conducted according to an a priori published protocol.45ObjectivesThe primary and secondary objectives of this systematic review were to:Synthesize the best available evidence regarding the effects of foot and ankle devices on falls in adults with pathological, bilateral lower limb sensory perception loss.Evaluate the effect of foot and ankle devices on the surrogate secondary measures of falls risk, with regard to: (i) gait and (ii) balance in adults with pathological, bilateral lower limb sensory perception loss.Generate knowledge to inform the development of a new footwear device for people at increased risk of balance impairments and falls due to loss of foot sensation.More specifically, the review content provides a summary of current evidence regarding the effect of foot and ankle devices (including therapeutic and retail footwear, pre-fabricated and custom-made insoles and AFO) on fall frequency or incidence, and clinical or laboratory measures of balance and gait, in adults with sensory perception loss.Inclusion criteriaTypes of participantsThe current review considered studies that included participants who were community-dwelling adults over the age of 18 years with bilateral sensory perception loss, defined as being unable to feel a 10 g monofilament at one or more sites on the plantar surface of the foot.46Exclusion criteriaPeople with foot ulceration at the time of the study.People with unilateral sensory perception loss.People from hospitals or care homes.People with an upper motor neuron injury (e.g. stroke survivors).People with age-related loss of foot sensation that did not originate from pathology.Types of intervention(s)/phenomena of interestThe current review considered studies that evaluated the effect of any foot or ankle device on balance, gait or falls in adults with sensory perception loss. Foot or ankle devices were defined as any device placed in direct contact with the foot or ankle. This included therapeutic and non-therapeutic footwear, insoles designed to increase mechanical support or afferent sensory feedback, AFO and ankle braces used to restrict joint motion. In this review, studies were included if they presented one of the following comparisons: (i) foot or ankle device was compared to another foot or ankle device or (ii) foot or ankle device was compared to no intervention/control condition.Studies that included any of the following interventions were excluded from the review:Industrial safety footwear.AFO that extends to the level of, or beyond, the knee joint.Foot ulcer offloading devices.OutcomesStudies that reported any measure of falls frequency or incidence were eligible for inclusion in the review. This review also considered studies that included any standardized clinical measures (e.g. Berg Balance Scale,36 Functional Reach37) or laboratory-based assessment (e.g. COP movement34) of static or dynamic standing balance. Similarly, studies that measured gait by way of clinical tests (e.g. Timed Up and Go Test,47 Dynamic Gait Index48) or laboratory assessments (e.g. spatiotemporal gait parameters41) were included in the review.Types of studiesThe current review considered experimental and epidemiological study designs including randomized controlled trials, non-randomized controlled trials, quasi-experimental, before and after studies, prospective and retrospective cohort studies, case-control studies and analytical cross-sectional studies. Descriptive epidemiological study designs including case series, individual case reports and descriptive cross-sectional studies were excluded from the review.Search strategyThe search strategy aimed to find both published and unpublished studies. A three-step search strategy was utilized in this review. An initial limited search of MEDLINE and EMBASE (OVID) was undertaken followed by analysis of the text words contained in the title and abstract, and of the index terms used to describe the articles. A second search using all identified keywords and index terms was undertaken across all included databases. Third, the reference list of all identified reports and articles was searched for additional studies. Studies published in the English language and published from inception to March 2015 were considered for inclusion in this review.The sources to be searched includes:MEDLINE, Embase (OVID), CINAHL, AMED (EBSCO), The Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials and the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) Database of Systematic Reviews and Implementation Reports.The search for unpublished studies included:Google Scholar, a thesis database (http://www.thesis.com), BIOSIS, Zetoc (http://zetoc.jisc.ac.uk.plymouth.idm.oclc.org/wzgw?db=etoc) and EThOS.Initial MESH and key terms that were used were related to foot orthosis and insoles, footwear and shoes, ankle foot orthosis and ankle braces, postural balance and body sway, gait and walking pattern, stabilising and destabilising, accidental falls, older persons, nervous system disorders, diabetes and neuropathy.An example of a full search strategy used in a major database is provided in Appendix I.Method of the reviewAll studies selected for retrieval were assessed by two independent reviewers for methodological validity prior to inclusion in the review. A list of the full-text articles that were assessed for eligibility can be found in Appendix II. Each paper was assessed using standardized critical appraisal instruments from the Joanna Briggs Institute Meta-Analysis of Statistics Assessment and Review Instrument (JBI-MAStARI) (Appendix III). Where disagreements arose between the reviewers, these were resolved through discussion until agreement was reached. When it was unclear if study participants were assessed as having pathological sensory perception loss, the corresponding author of the article was contacted for clarification. In total, eight authors were contacted and six responded. When no response was received from an author, the corresponding article was excluded.Data extractionQuantitative data were extracted from papers included in the review using the standardized data extraction tool from JBI-MAStARI (Appendix IV). The data extracted included specific details about the interventions, populations, study methods and outcomes of significance to the review question and specific objectives.Data synthesisQuantitative data analysis by way of statistical pooling was not possible due to the wide and heterogeneous range of study methods and outcome measures used across the included studies. Therefore, the findings of this review are presented in narrative form, with general themes established in the discussion.Findings of the reviewThe studies included within this review were too heterogeneous to be combined for meta-analysis. Studies differed in terms of participant characteristics, intervention and outcome measures, therefore findings will be presented in a narrative form. A summary of the results, conclusions and characteristics of included studies can be found in Appendix VI.Comparison 1: insoles with vibrating component activated versus insoles with vibrating component immobilizedActivated vibrating insoles (turned on) were compared with immobilized vibrating insoles (turned off) for people with diabetes and neuropathy in two studies,21,22 including 32 people with diabetes and neuropathy and 27 healthy older adults. Both studies measured the effect of the insoles on postural sway. One study recorded mean and maximum stabilogram radius, area and range in the anterior-posterior and medial-lateral direction using a marker attached to the right shoulder, quiet standing with eyes closed only.21 While the other used force plate stabiliometry to record root mean square COP velocity in anterior-posterior and medial-lateral directions with eyes open, eyes closed and while performing a dual task.22Both studies reported increased sway in people with diabetes and neuropathy when compared to controls. One trial21 reported a significant reduction in all sway parameters measured with eyes closed in both groups with vibration activated, although absolute values or the size of the difference were not fully reported. The other trial22 found no difference between insole conditions with the exception of anterior-posterior sway in the group with diabetes and neuropathy. However, this difference was only evident when balance was challenged by simultaneously removing visual cues and diverting attention. Under these test conditions, the root mean square COP velocity in the anterior-posterior direction reduced from 24.3 to 20.4 mm/s when the vibration was activated.22 Both studies provide evidence that vibrating insoles may reduce sway in people with diabetes and neuropathy when other compensatory balance strategies are compromised.Comparison 3: regular footwear versus barefoot for people with diabetes and neuropathyA single study51 compared regular footwear with walking barefoot, in 12 people with diabetes and neuropathy and eight controls matched for age, sex and body mass index. The authors reported on nine different gait parameters recorded while participants walked over short (7 m) and long (20 m) distances. Participants were asked to bring the shoes they wore most often during activities of daily living. Most chose to wear either Oxford type footwear (approximately 40%) or New Balance type footwear (approximately 60%) (personal correspondence with the author). There was no difference in any of the gait parameters when regular footwear was worn over a short distance. Over the longer distance, the diabetic neuropathic group displayed a significantly greater double support time (20%) when compared to the elderly control group. The was no significant difference in any of the gait parameters when regular footwear was worn over a long distance with the exception of coefficient of variation of gait velocity. Over the longer distances, wearing shoes reduced the coefficient of variation of gait velocity in people with diabetes and neuropathy by 46% to a similar level to that seen in the controls when tested wearing shoes. There is limited evidence to suggest that wearing footwear over long distances increases the consistency of step-to-step velocity in people with diabetes and neuropathy to a level similar to that seen in elderly healthy people.Comparison 4: ankle-foot orthosis versus no intervention for people with sensory perception lossAnkle-foot orthosis was compared to no intervention in 65 people with peripheral neuropathy in three studies24,52,53 reported in four publications.24,52-54 Participants were diagnosed with a range of underlying long-term conditions; 49 were diagnosed with diabetes, nine suffered idiopathic sensory loss, three had connective tissue disease, two had neuropathy originating from the toxic effect of medication, one was diagnosed with hypothyroidism and one had a family history of neuropathy.One study52 compared a plastic semi-flexible sagittal plane AFO with no intervention in 11 people with sensory perception loss, seven of whom were diagnosed diabetic. The authors measured balance using the specifically designed dynamic postural system (EquiTest NeuroCom International Inc). The authors reported that the sensory organization scores calculated by the system significantly improved when the AFO was worn by 13% standing with eyes open, 35% standing with eyes closed, 39% standing on a rotating platform with eyes open and 59% standing on a rotating platform with eyes closed.In a second study,53 the same research team appeared to repeat their 2006 study with a group of 12 people with diabetes and neuropathy. The authors reported that the sensory organization scores calculated by the dynamic postural system improved significantly with eyes closed but not with eyes open. The improvement recorded when the AFO was worn when standing on a static platform with eyes closed was 2%. The improvement recorded when the AFO was worn when standing on the rotating platform with eyes closed was 80%.A third study24 compared a medial-lateral AFO with no intervention in 42 people with peripheral neuropathy, (30 with diabetes) while walking over irregular terrain under low-light conditions. The authors reported a significant reduction in step width range (-28.4 mm), step width variability (-3.8 mm) and step time variability of (0.024 s) when the AFO was worn. Standard deviation (SD) was used as a measure of variability. However, it is unclear if the calculation was based on the SD of the total group score or the range of SDs taken from individual scores.In a separate publication,54 the same research team presents secondary analysis from their previous 2004 study using a sub-sample of 20 females. The authors reported that step length, as a fraction of body height, increased in this sub-group by 0.007 (P &lt; 0.001) of 20 females when the AFO was worn. Comparisons of step length for the original total sample were not reported.There is limited evidence to suggest that static balance and perturbed balance of people with sensory perception loss improves when a semi-flexible plastic sagittal plane AFO is worn; this improvement was greater when visual cues were removed. Evidence to suggest that medial-lateral AFO reduces step-to-step variability and increases step length of people with sensory perception loss is very weak.Limitations of the reviewThe findings of this review were limited because of the small number of studies meeting the inclusion criteria, the poor methodological quality of those studies, the inability to be able to pool the results and the inadequate sample size meaning most studies were underpowered. Moreover, only studies reported in English were included. This may have resulted in the exclusion of studies that were relevant and thus important for this review. Qualitative studies were excluded from the review, and these studies may have been able to contribute to the feasibility aspects of wearing/using the foot and ankle devices.AcknowledgementsJP is funded by a National Institute for Health Research CAT Clinical Lectureship award (CAT/CL10/007). This article/paper/report presents independent research funded by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR).There is no conflict of interest in this project.Appendix I: Search strategyMEDLINE(Ovid)Search February 20151. foot orthosis/2. (insole$1 or inlay$1 or insert$1).kw,ti.3. (footwear or shoe$1).kw,ti.4. (ankle adj ortho∗).mp. or (ankle adj brace).kw,ti. [mp = title, abstract, original title, name of substance word, subject heading word, keyword heading word, protocol supplementary concept word, rare disease supplementary concept word, unique identifier]5. (foot adj ortho∗).mp. or (foot adj brace).kw,ti. [mp = title, abstract, original title, name of substance word, subject heading word, keyword heading word, protocol supplementary concept word, rare disease supplementary concept word, unique identifier]6. 1 or 2 or 3 or 4 or 57. postural balance/8. posture.kw,ti.9. ((body adj sway) or balance).kw,ti.10. “center of pressure”.kw,ti.11. (stabilising or destabilising).kw,ti.12. (gait or (walking adj pattern)).kw,ti.13. 7 or 8 or 9 or 10 or 11 or 1214. Accidental Falls/15. “fall∗”.kw,ti.16. 14 or 1517. 13 or 1618. exp nervous system disorders/19. (diabet∗ or neuropath∗ or “multiple sclerosis” or “parkinsons disease”).mp. [mp = title, abstract, original title, name of substance word, subject heading word, keyword heading word, protocol supplementary concept word, rare disease supplementary concept word, unique identifier]20. 18 or 1921. 6 and 17 and 20Appendix II: Studies selected for retrieval1. Citaker S, Gunduz AG, Guclu MB, Nazliel B, Irkec C, Kaya D. Relationship between foot sensation and standing balance in patients with multiple sclerosis. Gait Posture. 2011;34(2):275-278.2. Mold JW, Vesley SK, Keyl BA, Schenk JB, Roberts M. The prevalence, predictors, and consequences of peripheral sensory neuropathy in older patients. J Am Board Fam Pract. 2004;17(5):309-318.3. Vinik AI, Holland AT, Le Beau JM, Liuzzi FJ, Stansberry KB, Colen LB. Diabetic Neuropathies. Diabetic Care. 1992;15(12):1926-1975.4. Young MJ, Boulton AJM, Macleaod AF, Williams DDR, Sonkesn PH. A multicentre study of the prevalence of diabetic peripheral neuropathy in the United Kingdom hospital population. Diabetologia. 1993;36(2):150-154.5. Richardson JK, Hurvitz EA. Peripheral neuropathy: a true risk factor for falls. J Gerontol. 1995; 50A(4):M211-M5.6. Cavanagh P, Derr J, Ulbrecht S, Maser R, Orchard J. Problems with gait and posture in neuropathic patients with insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. Diabet Med. 1992;9(5):469-474).7. Ducic I, Short KW, Dellon AL. Relationship between loss of pedal sensibility, balance, and falls in patients with peripheral neuropathy. Ann Plast Surg. 2004;52(6):535-540.8. Tilling L, Darawil K, Britton M. Falls as a complication of diabetes mellitus in older people. J Diabetes Complications. 2006;20(3):158-162.9. Macgilchrist C, Paul L, Ellis BM, Howe TE, Kennon B, Godwin J. Lower-limb risk factors for falls in people with diabetes mellitus. Diab Med. 2010;27(2):162-168.10. Menant JC, Steele JR, Menz HB, Munro BJ, Lord SR. Optimizing footwear for older people at risk of falls. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2008;45(8):1167-1182.11. Sherrington CI, Menz HB. An evaluation of footwear worn at the time of fall-related hip fracture. Age Aging. 2003;32(3):310-314.12. Hatton AL, Rome K, Dixon J, Martin D, McKeon P. Footwear interventions: a critical review of their sensory and mechanical effects on balance performance and gait in older adults. J Am Podiatr Medical Assoc. 2013;103(6):516-533.13. Nester CJ, Hutchins S, Bowker P. Effect of foot orthoses on rearfoot complex kinematics during walking gait. Foot and Ankle Int. 2001;22(2):133-139.14. Paton J, Bruce G, Stenhouse E, Zahra D, Jones R. A comparison of customised and prefabricated insoles to reduce risk factors for neuropathic diabetic foot ulceration: a participant-blinded randomised controlled trial. J Foot and Ankle Res. 2012;5(1):31.15. Brenton-Rule A, D’Almeida S, Bassett S, Carroll M, Dalbeth N, Rome K. The effects of sandals on postural stability in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: an exploratory study. Clin Biomech. 2013;29(3):350-353.16. Mills K, Blanch P, Chapman AR, McPoil TG, Vicenzino B. Foot orthoses and gait: a systematic review and meta-analysis of literature pertaining to potential mechanisms. Br J Sports Med. 2010;44(14):1035-1046.17. Nigg BM, Nurse MA, Stefanyshyn DJ. Shoe inserts and orthotics for sport and physical activities. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 1999;31(7 suppl):S421-S428.18. Jeng C, Michelson J, Mizel M. Sensory thresholds of normal human feet. Foot Ankle Int. 2000;21(6):501-503.19. McCarthy KA. Peripheral neuropathy in the aging patient: common causes, assessment, and risks. Top Clin Chiropractic. 1999;6(4):56-61.20. Reid KS, Martin BD, Duerksen F, Nicolle LE, Garrett M, Simonsen JN, et al. Diabetic foot complications in a northern Canadian Aboriginal community. Foot Ankle Int. 2006;27(12):1065-1073.21. Priplata AA, Patritti BL, Niemi JB, Hughes R, Gravelle DC, Lipsitz LA, et al. Noise-enhanced balance control in patients with diabetes and patients with stroke. Ann Neurol. 2006;59(1):4-12.22. Hijmans JM, Geertzen JHB, Zijlstra W, Hof At L, Postema K. Effects of vibrating insoles on standing balance in diabetic neuropathy. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2008;45(9):1441-1450.23. Perry SD, Radtke A, McIlroy WE, Fernie GR, Maki BE. Efficacy and effectiveness of a balance-enhancing insole. J Gerontol Ser A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2008;63(6):595-602.24. Richardson JK, Thies SB, DeMott TK, Ashton-Miller JA. Interventions improve gait regularity in patients with peripheral neuropathy while walking on an irregular surface under low light. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2004;52(4):510-515.25. Son J, Ashton-Miller JA, Richardson JK. Do ankle orthoses improve ankle proprioceptive thresholds or unipedal balance in older persons with peripheral neuropathy? Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2010;89(5):369-375.26. Van Geffen JA, Dijkstra PU, Hof AL, Halbertsma JPK, Postema K. Effect of flat insoles with different Shore A values on posture stability in diabetic neuropathy. Prosthet Orthot Int. 2007;31(3):228-235.27. Hijmans M, Geertzen JHB, Dijkstra PU, Postema K. A systematic review of the effects of shoes and other ankle or foot appliances on balance in older people and people with peripheral nervous system disorders. Gait Posture. 2007; 25: 316-323.28. Paton J, Bruce G, Jones R, Stenhouse E. Effectiveness of insoles used for the prevention of ulceration in the neuropathic diabetic foot: a systematic review. J Diabetes Complications. 2011;25(1):52-62.29. 10 NCG. Prevention and management of foot problems in people with type 2 diabetes. NICE. [cited January 2016]. Available from: www.nice.org.uk/CG010NICEguideline., 2004.30. Spencer S. Pressure relieving interventions for preventing and treating diabetic foot ulcers. Cochrane Database Systematic Rev. 2000;(3):CD002302.31. de Morais Barbosa C, Barros Bértolo M, Marques Neto JF, Bellini Coimbra I, Davitt M, de Paiva Magalhães E. The effect of foot orthoses on balance, foot pain and disability in elderly women with osteoporosis: a randomized clinical trial. Rheumatology. 2013;52(3):515-522.32. Hartmann A, Murer K, de Bie RA, de Bruin ED. The effect of a training program combined with augmented afferent feedback from the feet using shoe insoles on gait performance and muscle power in older adults: a randomised controlled trial. Disabil Rehabil. 2010;32(9):755-764.33. Tencer AF, Koepsell TD, Wolf ME, Frankenfeld CL, Buchner DM, Kukull WA, et al. Biomechanical properties of shoes and risk of falls in older adults. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2004;52(11):1840-1846.34. Raymakers J, Samson M, Verhaar H. The assessment of body sway and the choice of the stability parameter(s). Gait Posture. 2005;21(1):48-58.35. Piirtola M, Era P. Force platform measurements as predictors of falls among older people – a review. Gerontology. 2006;52(1):1-16.36. Berg K, Wood-Dauphinėe S, Williams JI, Gayton D. Measuring balance in the elderly: preliminary development of an instrument. Physiother Can. 1989;41(6):304-311.37. Duncan PW, Weiner DK, Chandler J, Studenski S. Functional Reach: a new clinical measure. J Gerontol. 1990;45(6):M192-M197.38. Duncan PW, Studenski SA, Chandler J, Prescott B. Functional reach: predictive validity in a sample of elderly male veterans. J Gerontol. 1992;47(3):M93-M98.39. Weiner DK, Boniorni DR, Studenski SA, Buncan PW, Kochersberger GG. Does functional reach improve with rehabilitation?. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1993;74(8):796-800.40. Lord S, Sherrington C, Menz H, Close J. Falls in older people: risk factors and strategies for prevention. New York: Cambridge University Press; 2007.41. Hausdorff JM, Rios DA, Edelberg HK. Gait variability and fall risk in community-living older adults: a 1-year prospective study. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2001;82(8):1050-1056.42. Menz HB, Lord SR, Fitzpatrick RC. Age-related differences in walking stability. Age Ageing. 2003;32(2):137-142.43. Galica AM, Kang HG, Priplata AA, D’Andrea SE, Starobinets OV, Sorond FA, et al. Subsensory vibrations to the feet reduce gait variability in elderly fallers. Gait Posture. 2009;30(3):383-387.44. Perry SD, Radtke A, McIlroy WE, Fernie GR, Maki BE. Efficacy and effectiveness of a balance-enhancing insole. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2008;63(6):595-602.45. Paton J, Collings R, Glasser S, Kent B. The effects of foot and ankle devices on balance, gait and falls in adults with sensory perception loss: a systematic review protocol. JBI Database Syst Rev Implement Rep. 2014;12(11):74-91.46. Boulton AJM, Armstrong DG, Albert SF, Frykberg RG, Hellman R, Kirkman MS, et al. Comprehensive foot examination and risk assessment: a report of the Task Force of the Foot Care Interest Group of the American Diabetes Association, with endorsement by the American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists. Diabetes Care. 2008;31(8):1679-1685.47. Chantanachai T, Pichaiyongwongdee S, Jalayondeja C. Fall prediction in thai elderly with timed up and go and tandem walk test: a cross-sectional study. J Med Assoc Thai. 2014;97(Suppl 7):S21-S25.48. Jonsdottir J, Cattaneo D. Reliability and validity of the dynamic gait index in persons with chronic stroke. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2007;88(11):1410-1415.49. Moher D, Liberati A, Tetzlaff J, Altman D. The PRISMA Group (2009). Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. BMJ (open access). 2009;339:b2535, doi: 10.1136/bmj.b2535.50. Kelleher K, Spence W, Solomonidis S, Apatsidis D. The effect of textured insoles on gait patterns of people with multiple sclerosis. Gait Posture. 2010;32(1):67-71.51. Najafi B, Khan T, Fleischer A, Wrobel J. The impact of footwear and walking distance on gait stability in diabetic patients with peripheral neuropathy. J Am Podiatr Med Assoc. 2013;103(3):165-173.52. Rao N, Aruin AS. Automatic postural responses in individuals with peripheral neuropathy and ankle-foot orthoses. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2006;74(1):48-56.53. Rao N, Aruin AS. Auxiliary sensory cues improve automatic postural responses in individuals with diabetic neuropathy. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2011;25(2):110-117.54. Richardson JK, Thies S, Ashton-Miller JA. An exploration of step time variability on smooth and irregular surfaces in older persons with neuropathy. Clin Biomech. 2008;23(3):349-356.55. Wrobel JS, Ammanath P, Le T, Luring C, Wensman J, Grewal GS, et al. A novel shear reduction insole effect on the thermal response to walking stress, balance, and gait. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2014;8(6):1151-1156.56. Wrobel J, Najafi B. Diabetic foot biomechanics and gait dysfunction. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2010;1(4):833-845.57. Grewal GS, Bharara M, Menzies R, Talal TK, Armstrong D, Najafi B. Diabetic peripheral neuropathy and gait: does footwear modify this association? J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2013;7(5):1138-1146.58. David T, Redmond A, Chapman G, Smith T, Hamilton D, Jones R, et al. Recommendations for the conduct of efficacy trials of treatment devices for osteoarthritis: a report from a working group of the Arthritis Research UK Osteoarthritis and Crystal Diseases Clinical Studies Group. Rheumatology. 2016 Feb; 55 (2); 320-326.59. Guillebastre B, Calmels P, Rougier P. Assessment of appropriate ankle-foot orthoses models for patients with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease. Orthotics. 2011(8):619-627.60. Kalron A, Pasitselsky D, Greenberg-Abrahami M, Achiron A. Do textured insoles affect postural control and spatiotemporal parameters of gait and plantar sensation in people with multiple sclerosis? PM&amp;R. 2015;7(1):17-25.61. McLoughlin J, Barr C, Sturnieks D, Lord S, Crotty M. Effect of wearing a dorsiflexion assist orthosis on mobility, perceived fatigue and exertion during the six-minute walk test in people with multiple sclerosis: a randomised cross-over protocol. BMC Neuro. 2012; 12 (27).62. Priplata AA, Niemi JB, Harry JD, Lipsitz LA, Collins JJ. Vibrating insoles and balance control in elderly people. Lancet. 2003;362(9390):1123-1124.Appendix III: Appraisal instrumentsMAStARI appraisal instrumentAppendix IV: Data extraction instrumentMAStARI data extraction instrumentAppendix V: Excluded studies and reasons for exclusion1. Bregman D, De Groot V, Van Diggele P, Meulman H, Houdijk H, Harlaar J. Polypropylene ankle foot orthoses to overcome drop-foot gait in central neurological patients: a mechanical and functional evaluation.Reason for exclusion: Unable to contact author. Unclear if the three MS participants were neuropathic.2. Cattaneo D, Marazzini F, Crippa A, Cardini R. Do static or dynamic AFOs improve balance?Reason for exclusion: Unable to contact author. participants not obviously tested for neuropathy.3. Creylman V, Muraru L, Pallari J, Vertommen H, Peeraer L. Gait assessment during the initial fitting of customized selective laser sintering ankle foot orthoses in subjects with drop foot.Reason for exclusion: Pathology and therefore any neuropathy unilateral.4. Dixon J, Hatton A, Robinson J, Gamesby-Iyayi H, Hodgson D, Rome K, Warnett R, Martin D. Effect of textured insoles on balance and gait in people with multiple sclerosis: an exploratory trial.Reason for exclusion: Majority of participants were not neuropathic.5. Dufek J, Neumann E, Hawkins M, O’Toole B. Functional and dynamic response characteristics of a custom composite ankle foot orthosis for Charcot-Marie-Tooth patients.Reason for exclusion: Authors contacted: Did not check for sensory perception loss.6. Farmer S, Pearce G, Whittall J, Quinlivan R, Patrick J. The use of stock orthoses to assist gait in neuromuscular disorders: a pilot study.Reason for exclusion: Age range from 14 years. Not neuropathic.7. Grewal G, Bharara M, Talal R, Talal K, Armstrong D, Najafi B. Diabetic peripheral neuropathy and gait: does footwear modify this association?Reason for exclusion: Authors contacted: unable to differentiate data from participants with diabetic peripheral neuropathy wearing footwear and those in cast/offloading sandals. Excluded after critical appraisal as the allocation of the intervention group was unclear.8. Guillebastre B, Calmels P, Rougier P. Assessment of appropriate ankle-foot orthoses models for patients with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease.Reason for exclusion: No clear identification of pathological sensory loss. Not able to distinguish between neuropathic and non-neuropathic participants.9. Jenkins M, Almeida Q, Spaulding S, van Oostveen R, Holmes J, Johnson A, Perry S. Plantar cutaneous sensory stimulation improves single-limb support time, and EMG activation patterns among individuals with Parkinson's disease.Reason for exclusion: Exclusion criteria not neuropathic.10. Kalron A, Pasitselsky D, Greenberg-Abrahami M, Achiron. A. Do textured insoles affect postural control and spatiotemporal parameters of gait and plantar sensation in people with Multiple Sclerosis?Reason for exclusion: Inclusion criteria less than 5.07 monofilament thus not all participants meet neuropathic criteria.11. Maki B, Perry S, Norrie R, McIlroy W. Effect of facilitation of sensation from plantar foot-surface boundaries on postural stabilization in young and older adults.Reason for exclusion: No pathological sensory perception loss.12. McLoughlin J, Barr C, Sturnieks D, Lord S, Crotty M. Effect of wearing a dorsiflexion assist orthosis on mobility, perceived fatigue and exertion during the six-minute walk test in people with multiple sclerosis: a randomised cross-over protocol.Reason for exclusion: Protocol only. Author contacted; trial has now been completed and published but no measures of foot sensation were taken.13. McLoughlin J, Lord S, Barr C, Crotty C, Sturnieks D. Dorsiflexion assist orthosis reduces the physiological cost and mitigates deterioration in strength and balance associated with walking in people with multiple sclerosis.Reason for exclusion: Participants not tested for neuropathy.14. Perry S, Radtke A, McIlroy W, Fernie G, Maki B. Efficacy and effectiveness of a balance-enhancing insole.Reason for exclusion: Although vibration perception levels appear normal for elderly people. Not pathological sensory loss.15. Priplata A, Niemi J, Harry J, Lipsitz L, Collins J. Vibrating insoles and balance control in elderly people.Reason for exclusion: Not pathological sensation loss. Sensation loss within normal limits for elderly population.16. Qiu F, Cole M, Davids K, Hennig E, Silburn P, Netscher H, Kerr G. Effects of textured insoles on balance in people with Parkinson's disease.Reason for exclusion: Author contacted.; Participants not assessed for sensation loss.17. Ramdharry G, Marsden J, Day B, Thompson A. De-stabilizing and training effects of foot orthoses in multiple sclerosis.Reason for exclusion: Author contacted.; Participants not tested for neuropathy.18. Ramdharry G, Pollard A, Marsden J, Reilly M, Comparing gait performance of people with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease who do and do not wear ankle foot orthoses.Reason for exclusion: Unclear if pathological sensation loss: light touch score would suggest neuropathy vibration at hallux would suggest not.19. Sheffler L, Hennessey M, Knutson J, Naples G, Chae J. Functional effect of an ankle foot orthosis on gait in multiple sclerosis: a pilot study.Reason for exclusion: Subjects were excluded for absent sensation in the ipsilateral lower limb.20. Son J, Ashton-Miller J, Richardson J., Do ankle orthoses improve ankle proprioceptive thresholds or unipedal balance in older persons with peripheral neuropathy?Reason for exclusion: Poor quality: Both reviewers considered outcome measures as unreliable. This study was excluded after critical appraisal.21. Stevens V, Goodman K, Rough K, Kraft G. Gait impairment and optimizing mobility in multiple sclerosis.Reason for exclusion: Discussion of the literature.22. Wegener C, Wegener K, Smith R, Schott C, Burns J. Biomechanical effects of sensorimotor orthoses in adults with Charcot Marie Tooth disease.Reason for exclusion: Authors contacted not all participants neuropathic.23. de Morais Barbosa C, Barros Bertolo M, Marques Neto J, Bellini Coimbra I, Davitt M, de Paiva Magalhaes E. The effect of foot orthoses on balance, foot pain and disability in elderly women with osteoporosis: a randomized clinical trial.Reason for exclusion: Exclusion criteria were reduced tactile and thermal foot sensibility.Appendix VI: List of study findings/conclusions/characteristics of included studiesMAStARIAppendix VII: JBI levels of evidenceReferences1.CitakerSGunduzAGGucluMBNazlielBIrkecCKayaD
Relationship between foot sensation and standing balance in patients with multiple sclerosis. Gait Posture
2011; 34
2:275–278.216836002.MoldJWVesleySKKeylBASchenkJBRobertsM
The prevalence, predictors, and consequences of peripheral sensory neuropathy in older patients. J Am Board Fam Pract
2004; 17
5:309–318.153559433.VinikAIHollandMTLe BeauJMLiuzziFJStansberryKBColenLB
Diabetic neuropathies. Diabetes Care
1992; 15
12:1926–1975.14642464.YoungMJBoultonAJMMacleaodAFWilliamsDDRSonkesnPH
A multicentre study of the prevalence of diabetic peripheral neuropathy in the United Kingdom hospital population. Diabetologia
1993; 36
2:150–154.84585295.RichardsonJKHurvitzEA
Peripheral neuropathy: a true risk factor for falls. J Gerontol
1995; 50A
4:M211–M215.6.CavanaghPDerrJUlbrechtSMaserROrchardJ
Problems with gait and posture in neuropathic patients with insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. Diabet Med
1992; 9
5:469–474.16118367.DucicIShortKWDellonAL
Relationship between loss of pedal sensibility, balance, and falls in patients with peripheral neuropathy. Ann Plast Surg
2004; 52
6:535–540.151669718.TillingLDarawilKBrittonM
Falls as a complication of diabetes mellitus in older people. J Diabetes Complicat
2006; 20
3:158–162.166322359.MacgilchristCPaulLEllisBMHoweTEKennonBGodwinJ
Lower-limb risk factors for falls in people with diabetes mellitus. Diabet Med
2010; 27
2:162–168.2054625910.MenantJCSteeleJRMenzHBMunroBJLordSR
Optimizing footwear for older people at risk of falls. J Rehabil Res Dev
2008; 45
8:1167–1182.1923511811.SherringtonCIMenzHB
An evaluation of footwear worn at the time of fall-related hip fracture. Age Ageing
2003; 32
3:310–314.1272061812.HattonALRomeKDixonJMartinDMcKeonP
Footwear interventions: a critical review of their sensory and mechanical effects on balance performance and gait in older adults. J Am Podiatr Med Assoc
2013; 103
6:516–533.2429798813.NesterCJHutchinsSBowkerP
Effect of foot orthoses on rearfoot complex kinematics during walking gait. Foot Ankle Int
2001; 22
2:133–139.1124922314.PatonJBruceGStenhouseEZahraDJonesR
A comparison of customised and prefabricated insoles to reduce risk factors for neuropathic diabetic foot ulceration: a participant-blinded randomised controlled trial. J Foot Ankle Res
2012; 5
1:31.2321695915.Brenton-RuleAD’AlmeidaSBassettSCarrollMDalbethNRomeK
The effects of sandals on postural stability in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: An exploratory study. Clin Biomech
2014; 29
3:350–353.16.MillsKBlanchPChapmanARMcPoilTGVicenzinoB
Foot orthoses and gait: a systematic review and meta-analysis of literature pertaining to potential mechanisms. Br J Sports Med
2010; 44
14:1035–1046.1999633017.NiggBMNurseMAStefanyshynDJ
Shoe inserts and orthotics for sport and physical activities. Med Sci Sports Exerc
1999; 31
(7 suppl):S421–S428.1041654318.JengCMichelsonJMizelM
Sensory thresholds of normal human feet. Foot Ankle Int
2000; 21
6:501–503.1088411019.McCarthyKA
Peripheral neuropathy in the aging patient: common causes, assessment, and risks. Top Clin Chiro
1999; 6
4:56–61.20.ReidKSMartinBDDuerksenFNicolleLEGarrettMSimonsenJN
Diabetic foot complications in a northern Canadian Aboriginal community. Foot Ankle Int
2006; 27
12:1065–1073.1720743421.PriplataAAPatrittiBLNiemiJBHughesRGravelleDCLipsitzLA
Noise-enhanced balance control in patients with diabetes and patients with stroke. Ann Neurol
2006; 59
1:4–12.1628707922.HijmansJMGeertzenJHBZijlstraWHof AtLPostemaK
Effects of vibrating insoles on standing balance in diabetic neuropathy. J Rehabil Res Dev
2008; 45
9:1441–1450.1931976623.PerrySDRadtkeAMcIlroyWEFernieGRMakiBE
Efficacy and effectiveness of a balance-enhancing insole. J Gerontol A Bio Sci Med Sci
2008; 63
6:595–602.1855963424.RichardsonJKThiesSBDeMottTKAshton-MillerJA
Interventions improve gait regularity in patients with peripheral neuropathy while walking on an irregular surface under low light. J Am Geriatric Soc
2004; 52
4:510–515.25.SonJAshton-MillerJARichardsonJK
Do ankle orthoses improve ankle proprioceptive thresholds or unipedal balance in older persons with peripheral neuropathy?
Am J Phys Med Rehabil
2010; 89
5:369–375.2040730226.Van GeffenJADijkstraPUHofALHalbertsmaJPKPostemaK
Effect of flat insoles with different Shore A values on posture stability in diabetic neuropathy. Prosthet Orthot Int
2007; 31
3:228–235.1797900927.HijmansMGeertzenJHBDijkstraPUPostemaK
A systematic review of the effects of shoes and other ankle or foot appliances on balance in older people and people with peripheral nervous system disorders. Gait Posture
2007; 25
2:316–323.1668724828.PatonJBruceGJonesRStenhouseE
Effectiveness of insoles used for the prevention of ulceration in the neuropathic diabetic foot: a systematic review. J Diabetes Complicat
2011; 25
1:52–62.1985407529.10 NCGPrevention and management of foot problems in people with type 2 diabetes. 2004; Available from: www.nice.org.uk/CG010NICEguideline. [cited January 1, 2016].30.SpencerS
Pressure relieving interventions for preventing and treating diabetic foot ulcers. Cochrane Database Syst Rev
2000; 3:CD002302.1090855031.de Morais BarbosaCBarros BértoloMMarques NetoJFBellini CoimbraIDavittMde Paiva MagalhãesE
The effect of foot orthoses on balance, foot pain and disability in elderly women with osteoporosis: a randomized clinical trial. Rheumatology
2013; 52
3:515–522.2319290532.HartmannAMurerKde BieRAde BruinED
The effect of a training program combined with augmented afferent feedback from the feet using shoe insoles on gait performance and muscle power in older adults: a randomised controlled trial. Disabil Rehabil
2010; 32
9:755–764.2049115233.TencerAFKoepsellTDWolfMEFrankenfeldCLBuchnerDMKukullWA
Biomechanical properties of shoes and risk of falls in older adults. J Am Geriatr Soc
2004; 52
11:1840–1846.1550706034.RaymakersJSamsonMVerhaarH
The assessment of body sway and the choice of the stability parameter(s). Gait Posture
2005; 21
1:48–58.1553603335.PiirtolaMEraP
Force platform measurements as predictors of falls among older people – a review. Gerontology
2006; 52
1:1–16.1643981936.BergKWood-DauphinėeSWilliamsJIGaytonD
Measuring balance in the elderly: preliminary development of an instrument. Physiother Can
1989; 41
6:304–311.37.DuncanPWWeinerDKChandlerJStudenskiS
Functional Reach: a new clinical measure. J Gerontol
1990; 45
6:M192–M197.222994138.DuncanPWStudenskiSAChandlerJPrescottB
Functional reach: predictive validity in a sample of elderly male veterans. J Gerontol
1992; 47
3:M93–M98.157319039.WeinerDKBoniorniDRStudenskiSABuncanPWKochersbergerGG
Does functional reach improve with rehabilitation?
Arch Phys Med Rehabil
1993; 74
8:796–800.834706340.LordSSherringtonCMenzHCloseJ
Falls in older people: risk factors and strategies for prevention. New York, NY:Cambridge University Press; 2007.41.HausdorffJMRiosDAEdelbergHK
Gait variability and fall risk in community-living older adults: a 1-year prospective study. Arch Phys Med Rehabil
2001; 82
8:1050–1056.1149418442.MenzHBLordSRFitzpatrickRC
Age-related differences in walking stability. Age Ageing
2003; 32
2:137–142.1261555543.GalicaAMKangHGPriplataAAD’AndreaSEStarobinetsOVSorondFA
Subsensory vibrations to the feet reduce gait variability in elderly fallers. Gait Posture
2009; 30
3:383–387.1963284544.PerrySDRadtkeAMcIlroyWEFernieGRMakiBE
Efficacy and effectiveness of a balance-enhancing insole. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci
2008; 63
6:595–602.1855963445.PatonJCollingsRGlasserSKentB
The effects of foot and ankle devices on balance, gait and falls in adults with sensory perception loss: a systematic review protocol. JBI Database Syst Rev Implement Rep
2014; 12
11:74–91.46.BoultonAJMArmstrongDGAlbertSFFrykbergRGHellmanRKirkmanMS
Comprehensive foot examination and risk assessment: a report of the Task Force of the Foot Care Interest Group of the American Diabetes Association, with endorsement by the American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists. Diabetes Care
2008; 31
8:1679–1685.1866323247.ChantanachaiTPichaiyongwongdeeSJalayondejaC
Fall prediction in Thai elderly with timed up and go and tandem walk test: a cross-sectional study. J Med Assoc Thai
2014; 97
(Suppl 7):S21–S25.2514152248.JonsdottirJCattaneoD
Reliability and validity of the dynamic gait index in persons with chronic stroke. Arch Phys Med Rehabil
2007; 88
11:1410–1415.1796488049.MoherDLiberatiATetzlaffJAltmanD
The PRISMA Group (2009)Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. BMJ (open access)
2009; 339
4:b2535.50.KelleherKSpenceWSolomonidisSApatsidisD
The effect of textured insoles on gait patterns of people with multiple sclerosis. Gait Posture
2010; 32
1:67–71.2040031251.NajafiBKhanTFleischerAWrobelJ
The impact of footwear and walking distance on gait stability in diabetic patients with peripheral neuropathy. J Am Podiatr Med Assoc
2013; 103
3:165–173.2369771952.RaoNAruinAS
Automatic postural responses in individuals with peripheral neuropathy and ankle-foot orthoses. Diabetes Res Clin Pract
2006; 74
1:48–56.1663127353.RaoNAruinAS
Auxiliary sensory cues improve automatic postural responses in individuals with diabetic neuropathy. Neurorehabil Neural Repair
2011; 25
2:110–117.2082941254.RichardsonJKThiesSAshton-MillerJA
An exploration of step time variability on smooth and irregular surfaces in older persons with neuropathy. Clin Biomech
2008; 23
3:349–356.55.WrobelJSAmmanathPLeTLuringCWensmanJGrewalGS
A novel shear reduction insole effect on the thermal response to walking stress, balance, and gait. J Diabetes SciTechnol
2014; 8
6:1151–1156.56.WrobelJNajafiB
Diabetic foot biomechanics and gait dysfunction. J Diabetes Sci Technol
2010; 1
4:833–845.57.GrewalGSBhararaMMenziesRTalalTKArmstrongDNajafiB
Diabetic peripheral neuropathy and gait: does footwear modify this association?
J Diabetes SciTechnol
2013; 7
5:1138–1146.58.DavidTRedmondAChapmanGSmithTHamiltonDJonesR
Recommendations for the conduct of efficacy trials of treatment devices for osteoarthritis: a report from a working group of the Arthritis Research UK Osteoarthritis and Crystal Diseases Clinical Studies Group. Rheumatology
2016; 55
2:320–326.2636188259.GuillebastreBCalmelsPRougierP
Assessment of appropriate ankle-foot orthoses models for patients with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease. Orthotics
2011; 90
8:619–627.60.KalronAPasitselskyDGreenberg-AbrahamiMAchironA
Do textured insoles affect postural control and spatiotemporal parameters of gait and plantar sensation in people with multiple sclerosis?
PM&amp;R
2015; 7
1:17–25.2515344761.McLoughlinJBarrCSturnieksDLordSCrottyM
Effect of wearing a dorsiflexion assist orthosis on mobility, perceived fatigue and exertion during the six-minute walk test in people with multiple sclerosis: a randomised cross-over protocol. BMC Neuro
2012; 12
27:27.62.PriplataAANiemiJBHarryJDLipsitzLACollinsJJ
Vibrating insoles and balance control in elderly people. Lancet
2003; 362
9390:1123–1124.14550702Table 1Assessment of methodological qualityCitationQ1Q2Q3Q4Q5Q6Q7Q8Q9Comparable cohort/case control studiesHijmans et al.22YYYYYN/AN/AYYKelleher et al.50YYUUYN/AN/AYYNajafi et al.51YUYYYN/AN/AYYvan Geffen et al.26YUUYYN/AN/AYYPriplata et al.21YUUYYN/AN/AYY%100404080100N/AN/A100100Before and after studiesRao and Aruin52UYUYN/AN/AN/AYYRao and Aruin53UYYYYN/AN/ANNRichardson et al.54UYYYUN/AN/AYYRichardson et al.24UYYYYN/AN/AYYWrobel et al.55YYUYYUN/AYY%2010060100750N/A8080Detail of the questions included in the JBI-MAStARI critical appraisal checklists can be found in Appendix III.
