<?xml version="1.0"?>
Obes SurgObes SurgObesity Surgery0960-89231708-0428Springer USNew York470937026530712194510.1007/s11695-015-1945-7Review ArticleMechanism Underlying the Weight Loss and Complications of Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass. ReviewAbdeenGGhaliana@gmail.comle RouxCWInvestigative Science, Imperial College London, London, UK Diabetes Complications Research Centre, Conway Institute, University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland Gastrosurgical Laboratory, University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, Sweden 31120153112015201626410421© The Author(s) 2015Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.Various bariatric surgical procedures are effective at improving health in patients with obesity associated co-morbidities, but the aim of this review is to specifically describe the mechanisms through which Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB) surgery enables weight loss for obese patients using observations from both human and animal studies. Perhaps most but not all clinicians would agree that the beneficial effects outweigh the harm of RYGB; however, the mechanisms for both the beneficial and deleterious (for example postprandial hypoglycaemia, vitamin deficiency and bone loss) effects are ill understood. The exaggerated release of the satiety gut hormones, such as GLP-1 and PYY, with their central and peripheral effects on food intake has given new insight into the physiological changes that happen after surgery. The initial enthusiasm after the discovery of the role of the gut hormones following RYGB may need to be tempered as the magnitude of the effects of these hormonal responses on weight loss may have been overestimated. The physiological changes after RYGB are unlikely to be due to a single hormone, or single mechanism, but most likely involve complex gut-brain signalling. Understanding the mechanisms involved with the beneficial and deleterious effects of RYGB will speed up the development of effective, cheaper and safer surgical and non-surgical treatments for obesity.KeywordsRYGBMechanismWeight lossComplicationsFood preferencesissue-copyright-statement© Springer Science+Business Media New York 2016Food IntakeResearch StudiesHunger and FullnessLifestyle changes with a lower calorie diet can be effective at initiating weight loss; however, most of the results from randomised controlled trials (RCT) are disappointing regarding long-term weight loss maintenance [17, 18]. Approximately 70–80 % of patients fail to maintain their initial lifestyle-induced weight loss thought to be due to physiologically compensatory responses that defend the previous weight ‘set point’ [19]. Whilst on a long-term low-calorie diet, patients usually report an increase in hunger, a decrease in satiety and pre-occupation with energy-dense fatty and sweet food [20, 21]. This may be part of a normal physiological response and not due to lack of motivation.Reduced calorie intake after RYGB is usually a consequence of significantly smaller meal sizes, and reduced calorie content of food eaten [22] compensated only partially by increased meal frequency [23]. Enhanced satiety is the dominant contributing factor [24]. A dramatic decrease in daily energy intake, 600–700 kcal [22, 25], during the first month post-surgery increases to 1000–1800 kcal during the first year [22, 26–32]. An average reduction of 1800 kcal per day from pre-operative intake can be sustained for several years [32, 33]. Protein intake during the first year after surgery is often lower than recommended at 0.5 g/kg, rather than the recommendation of at least 1.5 g/kg/day [27, 34]. The mechanisms are unclear, but may be due to temporary intolerance of higher protein diet and dairy foods [22, 25, 27, 35–37]. Relative intake of fat and carbohydrates decrease during the first year post-surgery, but return to the baseline after 1 year [22], although the contribution of high and low glycaemic index carbohydrates may change. Many patients reduce their intake of high glycaemic index carbohydrates and increase their intake of lower glycaemic index carbohydrates. Changes in behaviour associated with eating after RYGB were reported in the 1970s using structured interviews that suggested that patients reached satiety more quickly, with the most common reason given as a ‘lack of desire’ for food [38].Potential MediatorsIncreased Transit of Food into the Midgut Through the Gastric PouchWhether the size of the gastric pouch and stoma in RYGB surgery affects food intake and body weight is contested. It remains controversial in both the human and animal literature whether a larger gastric pouch and stoma causes less weight loss [39–43]. The stoma becomes more ‘compliant’ with time, allowing food to transit more easily from the pouch into the alimentary limb, but may also result in food being ‘stored’ in the pouch and not emptying rapidly enough. Thus, the initial diameter of the anastomosis may not affect weight loss in the long term [44]. To study a RYGB technique that created a very small pouch, a high-pressure manometer was used, but a large stoma demonstrated that the pressure in the pouch (immediately proximal to the gastroenteral anastomosis) was lower than in the alimentary limb [45]. This suggests there was no restriction at the level of the stoma because of the absence of a high-pressure zone proximal to the pouch. Insertion of a gastric balloon into the alimentary limb and inflation of the balloon to a pressure of 20 cm water demonstrated that patients with the highest pressure generated by the alimentary limb had the smallest meal volume during an ad libitum meal. In contrast, those with the lowest pressure in the alimentary limb took longer to terminate their meal. Mechanoreceptors within the alimentary limb may be important determinants of meal size if food rapidly transits through the pouch to reach the alimentary limb in a less digested state than usual. The component that determines caloric intake may be the alimentary limb and not the pouch size or stoma diameter.HormonalRYGB alters endogenous gut hormone responses to a meal. Glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1), peptide YY (PYY) and ghrelin have been the best studied candidates in the context of reduced food intake and sustained weight loss after RYGB. GLP-1 and PYY responses to mixed meals or oral glucose have been at the centre of interest of several studies investigating patients 6 weeks to 10 years after RYGB [46–51]. Significantly elevated responses are seen in GLP-1 and PYY as early as 2 days after RYGB [52] and may remain elevated for more than a decade after RYGB [53]. Patients who lost the most weight after RYGB also had the highest levels of these postprandial satiety gut hormones [54, 55]. Blocking the release of these hormones in humans and rats with octreotide increased food intake after RYGB, but not after adjustable gastric banding (AGB) surgery in humans [51] or sham operations in rats [56].Mechanistic studies in rodents have suggested the physiological significance of PYY because weight loss in PYY-knockout mice after a RYGB variant was lower than in wild-type mice [57]. Exogenous PYY specific antibodies also increased food intake in rats after bypass type procedures [51]. Physiologically, PYY has been shown to delay gut transit time, but probably does not increase energy expenditure in human [58]. GLP-1 responses are very similar to those of PYY after RYGB, but have additionally been linked with increases in insulin secretion [59, 60]. Postprandial responses of GLP-1 before surgery do not correlate with change in weight loss after surgery, suggesting that pre-operative gut hormone responses are not prognostic [61]. Enhanced GLP-1 signalling on its own is also not sufficient to reduce body weight after RYGB, suggesting that it is multiple gut hormone responses that mediate the increased satiation after a meal [62].Reduced ghrelin was the first proposed hormonal mechanism to explain weight loss after RYGB. At first, ghrelin levels were thought to be lower compared to diet-induced weight loss which increased ghrelin in a control group of subjects [63]. It was postulated that this decrease was partially responsible for reduced hunger after RYGB. Subsequent studies in patients after RYGB were more controversial reporting a reduction in fasting and postprandial ghrelin levels [50, 64–70], no alteration in fasting and postprandial levels [51, 52, 71–79] and a rise in fasting ghrelin levels [80–84]. Considering all the data and variability, it is likely that RYGB results in a comparative ghrelin deficiency considering that ghrelin normally increases after diet-induced weight loss, but the magnitude of this contribution is unclear [85, 86].NeuralThe vagal afferent fibres in the gastric and proximal small bowel mucosa are known to be sensitive to mechanical stretch in order to detect the volume of ingested food [87]. The vagus nerve with both the ventral and dorsal gastric branches on the large gastric remnant is transected during the formation of the gastric pouch. The vagal fibres to the gastric pouch are thus intact, and these could mediate satiety as food passes through the pouch. The vagal denervation more distally may attenuate signalling. Taken together, this may play a role in satiation [88]. Visceral sensory information from the gut is communicated centrally using the afferent (sensory) vagus nerve signalling to the nucleus of the tractus solitarius (NTS). Here, visceral sensory information and hormonal and metabolic inputs are integrated together with neuronal inputs from other brainstem areas [89] and may well be the most important way in which RYGB signals to the brain. Transmission of these signals involving the gut hormones such as ghrelin may be impaired after vagotomy [90]. RYGB appears to have the potential to alter neural responses [91] to reduce hedonic behaviour associated with eating highly palatable and calorie-dense foods. These changes in reward value of food may alter the amount of food consumed [38, 92–94].Change in Bile AcidsBile acids are agonists for the cell-membrane G protein-coupled receptors, TGR5, which in turn enhances the release of GLP-1 and PYY. Bile acids also bind the farnesoid X receptor (FXR) [95]. The anatomical changes after RYGB result in bile progressing down the biliopancreatic limb to the distal L cells without mixing with food. As a result, the availability of undiluted bile acids in the distal intestine may enhance stimulation of TGR5 receptors on L cells [96]. Serum bile acid concentration is raised after RYGB [97] and is associated with increased energy expenditure possibly through signalling via the cyclic adenosine monophosphate cAMP-dependent thyroid hormone triggering enzyme type 2 iodothyronine deiodinase [98]. Fibroblast growth factor (FGF) 19 is increased and binds to fibroblast growth factor receptor (FGFR4) activating fibroblast growth factor receptor c-kit (FGRR1c) in the presence of co-receptor β Klotho [99]. The result is increased protein synthesis in the liver [100]. FGF19 also plays a role in enhanced mitochondria activity [100]. Activation of the FXR receptor may facilitate the effects of bile acids on energy homeostasis through FGF19 that is released from ileal enterocytes which can lead to increases in metabolic rate and decreases in adiposity [101, 102].Bile acids, after a mixed test meal in human subjects, was positively correlated with circulating GLP-1 and PYY, but negatively correlated with ghrelin [103]. Pournaras et al. have demonstrated that total plasma bile acids are elevated after RYGB [104] and suggested that they may be partly responsible for the intestinal hypertrophy, anorexigenic hormone secretion and alterations in gut microbiota [105].Change in Gut MicrobiotaObesity is associated with low-grade inflammation, increased Firmicutes and decreased Bacteroidetes in animals [106] and humans [107–109]. Intestinal microbiota has also been shown to utilise energy from food and thus increase the host’s energy-harvesting capacity [110]. Proteobacteria (gammaproteobacteria) has been shown to increase after RYGB in humans [111] with the major contributor being Enterobacter hormaechei. The significant improvement of weight, inflammation and metabolic status after surgery was associated with increased bacterial variety. An association was observed between adipose tissue gene expression and bacterial genes at baseline with a 10-fold increase 3 months after surgery, and this may suggest a restored crosstalk between both the gut microbiota and the host [112].After RYGB, acidity was reduced in the alimentary limb leading to a decrease of hydrochloric acid flux in the gut, while bile acids were increased in the biliopancreatic limb. Bacteroidetes growth was attenuated at lower pH, whereas Escherichia coli increased at a higher pH. Gut microbiota quickly adapt in a ‘starvation-like state’ created by RYGB and rapidly and sustainably increase. Changes in microbiota in mice after RYGB were independent of weight alteration and caloric restriction [113]. Transfer of the gut microbiota from RYGB-treated mice to non-operated, germ-free mice resulted in weight loss and reduced fat mass in the recipient animals. The altered microbial production of short-chain fatty acids that increases may partly be an explanation [113]. Although RYGB did not change gut microbiota from the ‘obese state’ to the ‘lean state’, it did create a ‘third state’ which on balance appear to be associated with many of the beneficial characteristics of RYGB.Food PreferencesObservationsWeight gain has been linked to a preference for both sweet and/or high-fat foods [114, 115], which may partly explain why obese people regain body weight frequently after ‘dieting’ [116, 117]. The common view summarised earlier by Pangborn and Simone is: “In the mind of a normal person, sugar and sweets are ‘fattening’ and most overweight people have a ‘sweet tooth’” [118]. Hedonism associated with palatable foods is considered a significant factor which increases the prevalence of obesity. A motivational factor that is referred to as ‘hedonic hunger’ [119] may be a trigger for overeating [120].Patients after RYGB tend to increase the intake of fruit and vegetables as well as low-fat food [121, 122]. The dumping syndrome was thought to induce these changes in food preference [123], as initially it was considered as a useful characteristic of the RYGB to ‘teach’ patients to avoid calorie-dense foods and thus consume fewer calories [124]. However, patients after RYGB appear to make healthier food choices and adopt a more balanced diet (even when they do not experience dumping) [121, 125] and have considerable reduction in energy intake (EI) and energy density. A comparison on food groups was done for a group of patients after RYGB and total number of servings from fat, grains and sweetened beverages was reduced and remained reduced in the longer term. However, meats, dairy products, fruits and sweets were reduced in the short term, but then returned to baseline by 12 months [22]. When energy intake was reduced to 1300 kcal, 60 and 25 % of patients ,respectively, were consuming less than one serving per day from both fruits and vegetables. Whole grains intake increased from 25 to 40 % within the first 3 months, but then returned to baseline at 12 months [22]. The association between reduced diet energy density and weight loss is controversial as some studies describe no association [126], while others show that shifts in food preferences are partially responsible for the decreased calorie intake and weight loss after RYGB [127].RYGB in humans appears to alter taste through unconditional and conditional mechanisms [24, 128–130] leading to the concept of ‘behaviour surgery’ [123]. In 1987, Sugerman et al. reported that ‘sweet-eaters’ did particularly well after RYGB [131, 132]. Some of the initial findings were confounded by intolerance to sweets related to symptoms of the dumping syndrome [38, 131–133]. Conditioned taste aversion may thus be a factor in some patients. These initial assumptions resulted in many clinicians thinking that the RYGB works by ‘punishing’ the ‘poor behaviours’ of obese patients. The notion that RYGB becomes an external enforcer that goes against the free will of the patient has led to some authors questioning the morality of RYGB as a tool that changes patients’ behaviour against patients’ natural wishes [134]. This misconception may have reduced the wider acceptance of RYGB as a valid physiological treatment for the pathology that results in obesity. Classical conditioned food aversion is, however, an unlikely explanation as most patients with severe dumping still report that they like the taste of sweet foods, but that they have learned to consume only small quantities that do not cause negative visceral symptoms or consume sweets at night before bedtime, suggesting a conditioned food avoidance to be a more likely explanation. Distinguishing between the terms is important because avoidance implies that the palatability of sweet or fat did not change when small quantities are consumed, but that the subject ‘learns’ to stop consuming the food sooner (earlier avoidance) because large quantities may have negative visceral consequences [135–137].MediatorsRYGB could be exerting its effects on food selection and preference through any one of the taste function domains important in normal physiology such as sensory-discriminative (stimulus identification), hedonic (ingestive motivation) and physiological (digestive preparation) [138, 139]. Affective responses to taste stimuli, which can be considered an example of ingestive motivation, can be both conditioned and unconditioned. It remains controversial which of these three domains are involved and what their interactions are to determine food preferences after RYGB surgery. For example, RYGB could have effects directly on the central gustatory pathways related with feeding and reward through gut hormonal mediators. Alternatively, changes in the sensory signals could alter the intensity or the quality of tastants, but also lead to an unconditioned change in palatability. If RYGB causes visceral malaise after ingestion of fat, then it is possible that the palatability of fat could alter through a process of learning (conditioned response) [140].Although there are suggestions in animal models that the hedonic properties of sweet and fat stimuli may change after RYGB [23, 140–144], less work has been done in humans. Miras et al. using the progressive ratio task showed that RYGB resulted in the selective decrease of the reward value of a sweet and fat tastant, but not vegetables [145]. Further support comes from studies of brain reward cognitive systems linked to eating behaviour as studied by functional MRI (fMRI), where brain hedonic responses to calorie-dense food are lower after RYGB compared to patients who have lost similar amounts of weight after adjustable gastric banding [128].Energy ExpenditureAccording to the laws of thermodynamics, energy that enters a system (energy intake) must either be stored (body energy gain) or be used (activity, heat or faecal energy loss). Energy expenditure (EE) is usually decreased during food restriction, a phenomenon known as the ‘starvation response’ [146]. Weight loss in rodent models of RYGB is associated with preservation of lean body mass and increased EE [146]. Humans have decreased basal metabolic rate, but increased meal-induced thermogenesis after RYGB [32, 122, 147–153]. Evidence is now also emerging to suggest that the metabolic rate of the small bowel is increased after RYGB with more carbohydrate consumption which may explain the changes observed in respiratory quotient after these operations [154]. Reduced resting energy expenditure (REE) or basal metabolic rate after RYGB [122, 147, 155–157] may be attenuated due to relative lean mass preservation. Patients who regain the weight they lost 2 years after RYGB have lower REE [149], suggesting that elevating REE after RYGB may enhance weight loss. Physical activity may further help increase activity-related EE and also preserve lean mass, and therefore REE, after RYGB [158].Calorie MalabsorptionSeveral bariatric operations were designed to result in malabsorption of calories [159]. The exclusion of the approximately 10 % of the bowel (50 cm of BPL) after RYGB is unlikely to result in calorie malabsorption usually during other small bowel resections. Moreover, the exaggerated gut hormone responses which reduce gut transit have a net result of RYGB not altering oro-caecal transit time or functional enterocyte mass [16]. RYGB may, however, impair pancreatic exocrine function which could contribute to a small amount of fat malabsorption, the magnitude of which is probably too small to contribute substantially to weight loss [160–162].Mechanisms of ComplicationsThe rise in the number of RYGB procedures [163] has also increased the absolute number of complications associated with this procedure even though the percentage of patients with complications has reduced due to better surgical experience [164].Postprandial hypoglycaemia, even in patients who never had type 2 diabetes, can occur several hours after a meal and is distinct from early dumping syndrome which occurs within minutes after eating [165, 166]. Early dumping is an outcome of rapid emptying of food into the jejunum due to the lack of a pylorus presumably causing neural activation in the proximal alimentary limb [167]. Late dumping, or ‘postprandial hypoglycaemia’, happens 1–3 h after ingesting a meal and is a result of the exaggerated insulin response to high glycaemic index carbohydrates in the meal. The proposed mechanisms involve increased β-cell mass and improved β-cell function and non-β-cell mechanisms, which may include a lack of ghrelin (a counter-regulatory measure to hypoglycaemia) [63, 168]. In addition, the sustained weight loss can reduce insulin resistance which renders the previous insulin responses needed pre-surgery to suddenly become excessive. The aetiology of hypoglycaemia is likely to be different for individual patients and is also probably a mixture of the anatomic, hormonal and metabolic changes after RYGB [169]. Although treatment of this complication can be difficult, pancreatectomies are no longer advised [170], but rather a multimodal medical approach is favoured [171].Unexplained Abdominal PainUp to 10 % of the patients complain of unexplained chronic abdominal pain which can be difficult for both the treating clinician and patient to acknowledge [172, 173]. Mild abdominal pain is reported by up to 95 % of patients at some point after RYGB [172, 174–176]. Symptom severity fluctuates between vague discomfort and severe colicky pain [177]. Vomiting and nausea, especially if prolonged, are symptoms of pathology and are not part of the normal postoperative course after RYGB; nonetheless, up to 80 % of patients report the symptoms at some point after surgery [172, 174]. Abdominal pain may be recurrent, and it should be remembered that internal hernias may spontaneously reduce causing intermittent pain. Early investigation when acute symptoms of abdominal pain first presents is mandatory due to the risk of obstruction, volvulus and ischaemia of the herniated bowel [172, 178]. Cross-sectional imaging is often unhelpful and the use of laparoscopy is frequently required for diagnosis. Management protocols for chronic unexplained abdominal pain are not clearly defined, but the jejunal-jejunal anastomosis is currently receiving more attention as a possible cause for these chronic problems.Anastomotic StenosisWith the circular stapler technique, this can be a common complication with a reported incidence of up to 27 % and a recurrence rate of up to 33 % [179]. Usually dysphagia occurs within 6 months after surgery. Endoscopy can often be used both as a diagnostic but also an intervention tool.Vitamin Deficiencies: Iron, Vitamin B12, Folic Acid, Vitamin D and CalciumIron deficiency occurs in up to 49 % of patients after RYGB [180]. Reduced acid production in the small stomach pouch decreases iron absorption [181]. For iron to be absorbed, the ferric iron in foods has to be reduced to the ferrous state, but because hydrochloric acid is lower after RYGB, this process is attenuated [182]. Reduced intake of iron-rich foods after RYGB such as red meat may also contribute [183, 184].In the stomach, both pepsin and hydrochloric acid are required for absorption of vitamin B12. Deficiencies of vitamin B12 occur in up to 70 % of patients after RYGB [184–186] because achlorhydria prevents vitamin B12 separation from foods due to reduced ingestion of meat and insufficient secretion of intrinsic factor after surgery [182].Folic acid deficiency affects up to 35 % of patients after RYGB. Folate absorption is enabled by hydrochloric acid with absorption in the proximal third of the small bowel most important [186]. Vitamin B12 also acts as a coenzyme in converting methyltetrahydrofolate to tetrahydrofolate. Thus, folate deficiency might result from achlorhydria, bypassing of the proximal small bowel, vitamin B12 deficiency and/or decreased folate ingestion [184–187].Hypocalcaemia occurs in up to 10 % and low serum 25-hydroxy vitamin D levels in up to half of RYGB patients [188]. Nevertheless, most obese patients had significantly lower basal 25-hydroxyl vitamin D concentrations and higher parathyroid hormone concentrations as compared to age-matched lean controls [189]. Deficiencies may occur because calcium is typically absorbed in the proximal small bowel which is bypassed after RYGB. Intolerances can develop to calcium-rich sources such as milk especially if the fat content is high. Calcium can be released from bone as evident from the increased bone turnover and subsequent reduced bone mass after RYGB [190, 191]. The higher bone turnover in the RYGB patients could be partly due to the weight loss in these patients [192], but animal studies suggest that bone loss exceeds what would be expected from weight loss alone [193].Loss of Bone DensityMany patients with obesity have very healthy bone density before surgery due to long-term excessive weight bearing. This may be protective and partly explains the controversy of why the loss of bone density after RYGB does not cause more bone fractures [194, 195] even if the risk for fracturing may be increased. Multiple mechanisms may contribute to RYGB reducing bone density, including physiologically reduced mechanical load related to weight loss after surgery, hyperparathyroidism due to insufficient calcium consumption or reduced intestinal calcium and vitamin D absorption. Humoral factors from adipose tissue (oestradiol, leptin, adiponectin), pancreas (e.g. insulin, amylin) or the gut (ghrelin, glucagon-like peptide-2, glucose-dependent insulinotropic peptide) may also play a role [196, 197] by connecting a web of consistent regulatory pathways [196].Kidney StonesHyperoxaluria is common after RYGB, but the incidence of renal calculi is much lower than after jejunal-ileal bypass (JIB) [198–200]. Comparison with the JIB is important because the incidence as well as the potential mechanisms may be different after RYGB. The lithogenic effects after RYGB may stem from reduced calcium binding to oxalate in the intestinal lumen. The excess oxalate is then cleared by the kidneys resulting in hyperoxaluria and calcium oxalate nephrolithiasis. Almost 21 % of patients after JIB, which causes significant malabsorption, developed kidney stones 5 years after surgery [201], but the incidence of kidney stones after RYGB appears to depend on a combination of other factors such as hydration status and urine volume [200]. Patients in high stone-forming areas of the world have increased number of stones while those in low stone-forming countries may have an incidence similar to the background population [202]. Thus, RYGB alone is not enough to cause kidney stones, but it does potentiate other predisposing factors.Reference1.RubinoFSchauerPRKaplanLMCummingsDEMetabolic surgery to treat type 2 diabetes: clinical outcomes and mechanisms of actionAnnu Rev Med20106139341110.1146/annurev.med.051308.105148200593452.PoriesWJBariatric surgery: risks and rewardsJ Clin Endocrinol Metab200893s89s9610.1210/jc.2008-1641189872753.LaureniusALarssonIBueterMChanges in eating behaviour and meal pattern following Roux-en-Y gastric bypassInt J Obes20123634835510.1038/ijo.2011.2174.NoraMGuimarãesMAlmeidaRMetabolic laparoscopic gastric bypass for obese patients with type 2 diabetesObes Surg2011211643164910.1007/s11695-011-0418-x215128185.McCartyTMArnoldDTLamontJPFisherTLKuhnJAOptimizing outcomes in bariatric surgery: outpatient laparoscopic gastric bypassAnn Surg2005242494161928096.SjostromLLindroosAKPeltonenMLifestyle, diabetes, and cardiovascular risk factors 10 years after bariatric surgeryN Engl J Med20043512683269310.1056/NEJMoa035622156162037.FrancoJRuizPPalermoMGagnerMA review of studies comparing three laparoscopic procedures in bariatric surgery: sleeve gastrectomy, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and adjustable gastric bandingOBES SURG2011211458146810.1007/s11695-011-0390-5214558338.WingRRPhelanSLong-term weight loss maintenanceAm J Clin Nutr200582222S225S160028259.CooperZDollHAHawkerDMTesting a new cognitive behavioural treatment for obesity: a randomized controlled trial with three-year follow-upBehav Res Ther20104870671310.1016/j.brat.2010.03.0082069132810.OlbersTGronowitzEWerlingMTwo-year outcome of laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass in adolescents with severe obesity: results from a Swedish Nationwide Study (AMOS)Int J Obes2012361388139510.1038/ijo.2012.16011.BozaCGamboaCAwruchDPerezGEscalonaAIbañezLLaparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass versus laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding: five years of follow-upSurg Obes Relat Dis2010647047510.1016/j.soard.2010.02.0452070214612.WongSKKongAPMuiWLLaparoscopic bariatric surgery: a five-year reviewHong Kong Med J20091521001091934273513.KimTHDaudAUdeAOEarly U.S. outcomes of laparoscopic gastric bypass versus laparoscopic adjustable silicone gastric banding for morbid obesitySurg Endosc20062020220910.1007/s00464-005-0243-11634156914.LakdawalaMBhaskerAMulchandaniDGoelSJainSComparison between the results of laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy and laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass in the Indian population: a retrospective 1-year studyObes Surg2010201610.1007/s11695-009-9981-91980264615.WeberMMüllerMKBucherTLaparoscopic gastric bypass is superior to laparoscopic gastric banding for treatment of morbid obesityAnn Surg200424097598210.1097/01.sla.0000145924.64932.8f1557020316.PournarasDJOsborneAHawkinsSCRemission of type 2 diabetes after gastric bypass and banding: mechanisms and 2 year outcomesAnn Surg201025296697110.1097/SLA.0b013e3181efc49a2110710617.SorensenTIAWeight loss causes increased mortality: prosObes Rev200343710.1046/j.1467-789X.2003.00090.x1260852218.GersteinHCDo lifestyle changes reduce serious outcomes in diabetes?N Engl J Med201336918919010.1056/NEJMe13069872379613219.MacleanPSBergouignanACornierMAJackmanMRBiology’s response to dieting: the impetus for weight regainAm J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol2011301R581R60010.1152/ajpregu.00755.20102167727220.SumithranPPrendergastLADelbridgeELong-term persistence of hormonal adaptations to weight lossN Engl J Med20113651597160410.1056/NEJMoa11058162202998121.HofmannWvan KoningsbruggenGMStroebeWRamanathanSAartsHAs pleasure unfolds. Hedonic responses to tempting foodPsychol Sci2010211863187010.1177/09567976103891862110688522.MillerGDNorrisAFernandezAChanges in nutrients and food groups intake following laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB)Obes Surg201424111926193210.1007/s11695-014-1259-12474847423.ZhengHShinACLenardNRMeal patterns, satiety, and food choice in a rat model of Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgeryAm J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol2009297R1273R128210.1152/ajpregu.00343.20091972671424.MirasADLe RouxCWMechanisms underlying weight loss after bariatric surgeryNat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol20131057558410.1038/nrgastro.2013.1192383548825.XanthakosSANutritional deficiencies in obesity and after bariatric surgeryPediatr Clin N Am2009561105112110.1016/j.pcl.2009.07.00226.LindroosAKLissnerLSjostromLWeight change in relation to intake of sugar and sweet foods before and after weight reducing gastric surgeryInt J Obes Relat Metab Dis J Int Assoc Study Obes19962063464327.MoizeVGeliebterAGluckMEObese patients have inadequate protein intake related to protein intolerance up to 1 year following Roux-en-Y gastric bypassObes Surg200313232810.1381/0960892033211365481263060928.Bobbioni-HarschEHuberOMorelPHFactors influencing energy intake and body weight loss after gastric bypassEur J Clin Nutr20025655155610.1038/sj.ejcn.16013571203265629.BrolinRLRobertsonLBKenlerHACodyRPWeight loss and dietary intake after vertical banded gastroplasty and Roux-en-Y gastric bypassAnn Surg199422078210.1097/00000658-199412000-00012798614630.NaslundIJarnmarkIAnderssonHDietary intake before and after gastric bypass and gastroplasty for morbid obesity in womenInt J Obes198712503513306976731.CoughlinKBellRMBivinsBAWrobelSGriffenWOPreoperative and postoperative assessment of nutrient intakes in patients who have undergone gastric bypass surgeryArch Surg198311881381610.1001/archsurg.1983.01390070025006686012932.FlancbaumLChobanPBradleyLRBURGEJCChanges in measured resting energy expenditure after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass for clinically severe obesitySurgery199712294394910.1016/S0039-6060(97)90336-6936989533.Warde-KamarJRogersMFlancbaumLLaferrèreBCalorie intake and meal patterns up to 4 years after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgeryObes Surg2004141070107910.1381/09608920419756681547959634.BavarescoMPaganiniSLimaTPNutritional course of patients submitted to bariatric surgeryObes Surg20102071672110.1007/s11695-008-9721-61893188435.SchinkelERPettineSMAdamsEHarrisMImpact of varying levels of protein intake on protein status indicators after gastric bypass in patients with multiple complications requiring nutritional supportObes Surg200616243010.1381/0960892067752221681641775336.Westerterp-PlantengaMSNieuwenhuizenATomeDSoenenSWesterterpKRDietary protein, weight loss, and weight maintenanceAnnu Rev Nutr200929214110.1146/annurev-nutr-080508-1410561940075037.HeberDGreenwayFLKaplanLMLivingstonESalvadorJStillCEndocrine and nutritional management of the post-bariatric surgery patient: an Endocrine Society Clinical Practice GuidelineJ Clin Endocrinol Metabol2010954823484310.1210/jc.2009-212838.HalmiKAMasonEFalkJRStunkardAAppetitive behavior after gastric bypass for obesityInt J Obes19815457464730933039.HeneghanHMYimcharoenPBrethauerSAKrohMChandBInfluence of pouch and stoma size on weight loss after gastric bypassSurg Obes Relat Dis2012840841510.1016/j.soard.2011.09.0102205539040.BueterMLöwensteinCAshrafianHVagal sparing surgical technique but not stoma size affects body weight loss in rodent model of gastric bypassObes Surg20102061662210.1007/s11695-010-0075-52011973541.CamposGMRablCMulliganKFactors associated with weight loss after gastric bypassArch Surg200814387788410.1001/archsurg.143.9.8771879442642.TopartPBecouarnGRitzPPouch size after gastric bypass does not correlate with weight loss outcomeObes Surg2011211350135410.1007/s11695-011-0460-82166064143.MadanATichanskyDPhillipsJDoes pouch size matter?Obes Surg20071731732010.1007/s11695-007-9058-61754683844.GouldJGarrenMBollVStarlingJThe impact of circular stapler diameter on the incidence of gastrojejunostomy stenosis and weight loss following laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypassSurg Endosc2006201017102010.1007/s00464-005-0207-51676392845.Fandriks L. The role of the smaller stomach. 31-8-2011. Postgraduate course B, XVI World Congress of the International Federation for the Surgery of Obesity and Metabolic Disorders, Hamburg, Germany. Ref Type: Report46.LaferrereBHeshkaSWangKIncretin levels and effect are markedly enhanced 1 month after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery in obese patients with type 2 diabetesDiabetes Care2007301709171610.2337/dc06-15491741679647.LaferrereBTeixeiraJMcGintyJEffect of weight loss by gastric bypass surgery versus hypocaloric diet on glucose and incretin levels in patients with type 2 diabetesJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2008932479248510.1210/jc.2007-28511843077848.MorinigoRMoizeVMusriMGlucagon-like peptide-1, peptide YY, hunger, and satiety after gastric bypass surgery in morbidly obese subjectsJ Clin Endocrinol Metabol2006911735174010.1210/jc.2005-090449.KornerJInabnetWConwellIMDifferential effects of gastric bypass and banding on circulating gut hormone and leptin levelsObesity (Silver Spring)2006141553156110.1038/oby.2006.1791703096650.RodieuxFGiustiVD'AlessioDASuterMTappyLEffects of gastric bypass and gastric banding on glucose kinetics and gut hormone releaseObesity (Silver Spring)20081629830510.1038/oby.2007.831823963651.le RouxCWAylwinSJBatterhamRLGut hormone profiles following bariatric surgery favor an anorectic state, facilitate weight loss, and improve metabolic parametersAnn Surg200624310811410.1097/01.sla.0000183349.16877.841637174452.Le RouxCWWelbournRWerlingMGut hormones as mediators of appetite and weight loss after Roux-en-Y gastric bypassAnn Surg200724678078510.1097/SLA.0b013e3180caa3e31796816953.DarMSChapmanWHIIIPenderJRGLP-1 response to a mixed meal: what happens 10 years after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB)?Obes Surg2012221077108310.1007/s11695-012-0624-12241910854.MeguidMMGladeMJMiddletonFAWeight regain after Roux-en-Y: a significant 20 % complication related to PYYNutrition20082483284210.1016/j.nut.2008.06.0271872508055.DirksenCJorgensenNBBojsen-MollerKNGut hormones, early dumping and resting energy expenditure in patients with good and poor weight loss response after Roux-en-Y gastric bypassInt J Obes201337111452145910.1038/ijo.2013.1556.BatterhamRLCohenMAEllisSMInhibition of food intake in obese subjects by peptide YY3-36N Engl J Med200334994194810.1056/NEJMoa0302041295474257.ChandaranaKGelegenCKarraEDiet and gastrointestinal bypass-induced weight loss: the roles of ghrelin and peptide YYDiabetes20116081081810.2337/db10-05662129287058.SlothBHolstJJFlintAGregersenNTAstrupAEffects of PYY1-36 and PYY3-36 on appetite, energy intake, energy expenditure, glucose and fat metabolism in obese and lean subjectsAm J Physiol Endocrinol Metabol2007292E1062E106810.1152/ajpendo.00450.200659.TroySSotyMRibeiroLIntestinal gluconeogenesis is a key factor for early metabolic changes after gastric bypass but not after gastric lap-band in miceCell Metab2008820121110.1016/j.cmet.2008.08.0081876202160.Peterli R, Wolnerhanssen B, Peters T, et al. Improvement in glucose metabolism after bariatric surgery: comparison of laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy: a prospective randomized trial. Ann Surg. 2009;250.61.ReinehrTRothCLSchernthanerGHKoppHPKriwanekSSchernthanerGPeptide YY and glucagon-like peptide-1 in morbidly obese patients before and after surgically induced weight lossObes Surg2007171571157710.1007/s11695-007-9323-81804661362.Ye J., Hao Z., Mumphrey M.B. et al. GLP-1 receptor signaling is not required for reduced body weight after RYGB in rodents. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol 201463.CummingsDEWeigleDSFrayoRSPlasma ghrelin levels after diet-induced weight loss or gastric bypass surgeryN Engl J Med20023461623163010.1056/NEJMoa0129081202399464.FoschiDCorsiFColomboFDifferent effects of vertical banded gastroplasty and Roux-en-Y gastric bypass on meal inhibition of ghrelin secretion in morbidly obese patientsJ Invest Surg200821778110.1080/089419307018836241834062465.FruhbeckGRotellarFHernández-LizoainJLFasting plasma ghrelin concentrations 6 months after gastric bypass are not determined by weight loss or changes in insulinemiaObes Surg2004141208121510.1381/09608920423869041552763666.GelonezeBTambasciaMAPillaVFGelonezeSRRepettoEMParejaJCGhrelin: a gut-brain hormone: effect of gastric bypass surgeryObes Surg200313172210.1381/0960892033211365391263060867.LeonettiFSilecchiaGIacobellisGDifferent plasma ghrelin levels after laparoscopic gastric bypass and adjustable gastric banding in morbid obese subjectsJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2003884227423110.1210/jc.2003-0301331297029168.LinEGletsuNFugateKThe effects of gastric surgery on systemic ghrelin levels in the morbidly obeseArch Surg200413978078410.1001/archsurg.139.7.7801524941369.MorinigoRCasamitjanaRMoizeVShort-term effects of gastric bypass surgery on circulating ghrelin levelsObes Res2004121108111610.1038/oby.2004.1391529247570.TritosNAMunEBertkauAGraysonRMaratos-FlierEGoldfineASerum ghrelin levels in response to glucose load in obese subjects post-gastric bypass surgeryObes Res20031191992410.1038/oby.2003.1261291749471.CouceMCottamDEsplenJSchauerPBurgueraBIs ghrelin the culprit for weight loss after gastric bypass surgery? A negative answerObes Surg20061687087810.1381/0960892067778221511683948572.FarajMHavelPJPhélisSBlankDSnidermanADCianfloneKPlasma acylation-stimulating protein, adiponectin, leptin, and ghrelin before and after weight loss induced by gastric bypass surgery in morbidly obese subjectsJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2003881594160210.1210/jc.2002-0213091267944473.KaramanakosSNVagenasKKalfarentzosFAlexandridesTKWeight loss, appetite suppression, and changes in fasting and postprandial ghrelin and peptide-YY levels after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and sleeve gastrectomy: a prospective, double blind studyAnn Surg200824740140710.1097/SLA.0b013e318156f0121837618174.KornerJBesslerMCiriloLJEffects of Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery on fasting and postprandial concentrations of plasma ghrelin, peptide YY, and insulinJ Clin Endocrinol Metab20059035936510.1210/jc.2004-10761548308875.KornerJInabnetWFebresGProspective study of gut hormone and metabolic changes after adjustable gastric banding and Roux-en-Y gastric bypassInt J Obes (Lond)20093378679510.1038/ijo.2009.791941777376.LiouJMLinJTLeeWJThe serial changes of ghrelin and leptin levels and their relations to weight loss after laparoscopic minigastric bypass surgeryObes Surg200818848910.1007/s11695-007-9305-x1808072477.OlivanBTeixeiraJBoseMEffect of weight loss by diet or gastric bypass surgery on peptide YY3-36 levelsAnn Surg200924994895310.1097/SLA.0b013e3181a6cdb01947468578.StoeckliRChandaRLangerIKellerUChanges of body weight and plasma ghrelin levels after gastric banding and gastric bypassObes Res20041234635010.1038/oby.2004.431498122879.WhitsonBALeslieDBKelloggTAEntero-endocrine changes after gastric bypass in diabetic and nondiabetic patients: a preliminary studyJ Surg Res2007141313910.1016/j.jss.2007.02.0221757403680.Garcia-FuentesEGarrido-SanchezLGarcia-AlmeidaJMDifferent effect of laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and open biliopancreatic diversion of Scopinaro on serum PYY and ghrelin levelsObes Surg2008181424142910.1007/s11695-008-9560-51854284981.HoldstockCEngströmBEOhrvallMLindLSundbomMKarlssonFAGhrelin and adipose tissue regulatory peptides: effect of gastric bypass surgery in obese humansJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2003883177318310.1210/jc.2002-0217341284316282.SundbomMHoldstockCEngströmBEKarlssonFAEarly changes in ghrelin following Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: influence of vagal nerve functionality?Obes Surg20071730431010.1007/s11695-007-9056-81754683683.VendrellJBrochMVilarrasaNResistin, adiponectin, ghrelin, leptin, and proinflammatory cytokines: relationships in obesityObes Res20041296297110.1038/oby.2004.1181522933684.YbarraJBobbioni-HarschEChassotGPersistent correlation of ghrelin plasma levels with body mass index both in stable weight conditions and during gastric-bypass-induced weight lossObes Surg20091932733110.1007/s11695-008-9748-81897503885.PournarasDJle RouxCWGhrelin and metabolic surgeryInt J Pept2010201073374310.1155/2010/21726786.BerthoudHRShinACZhengHObesity surgery and gut-brain communicationPhysiol Behav201110510611910.1016/j.physbeh.2011.01.0232131509587.BerthoudHRVagal and hormonal gut-brain communication: from satiation to satisfactionNeurogastroenterol Motil200820Suppl 1647210.1111/j.1365-2982.2008.01104.x1840264388.BerthoudHRThe vagus nerve, food intake and obesityRegul Pept2008149152510.1016/j.regpep.2007.08.0241848277689.SchwartzMWWoodsSCPorteDSeeleyRJBaskinDGCentral nervous system control of food intakeNature20004046616711076625390.le RouxCWNearyNMHalseyTJGhrelin does not stimulate food intake in patients with surgical procedures involving vagotomyJ ClinEndocrinol Metabol2005904521452410.1210/jc.2004-253791.OchnerCNKwokYConceicaoESelective reduction in neural responses to high calorie foods following gastric bypass surgeryAnn Surg201125350250710.1097/SLA.0b013e318203a2892116980992.FormanEMHoffmanKLMcGrathKBHerbertJDBrandsmaLLLoweMRA comparison of acceptance- and control-based strategies for coping with food cravings: an analog studyBehav Res Ther2007452372238610.1016/j.brat.2007.04.0041754436193.LoweMRvan SteenburghJOchnerCNIndividual differences in brain activation in relation to ingestive behavior and obesityPhysiol Behav2009556157110.1016/j.physbeh.2009.04.0011936153594.LoweMRButrynMLDidieERThe Power of Food Scale. A new measure of the psychological influence of the food environmentAppetite20095311411810.1016/j.appet.2009.05.0161950062395.KreymannBGhateiMAWilliamsGBloomSRGlucagon-like peptide-1 7–36: a physiological incretin in manLancet19873301300130410.1016/S0140-6736(87)91194-9289090396.KatsumaSHirasawaATsujimotoGBile acids promote glucagon-like peptide-1 secretion through TGR5 in a murine enteroendocrine cell line STC-1Biochem Biophys Res Commun200532938639010.1016/j.bbrc.2005.01.1391572131897.PattiMEHoutenSMBiancoACSerum bile acids are higher in humans with prior gastric bypass: potential contribution to improved glucose and lipid metabolismObesity2009171671167710.1038/oby.2009.1021936000698.WatanabeMHoutenSMMatakiCBile acids induce energy expenditure by promoting intracellular thyroid hormone activationNature200643948448910.1038/nature043301640032999.GeHBaribaultHVonderfechtSCharacterization of a FGF19 variant with altered receptor specificity revealed a central role for FGFR1c in the regulation of glucose metabolismPLoS One20127e3360310.1371/journal.pone.003360322457778100.Morton G.J., Kaiyala K.J., Foster-Schubert K.E., Cummings D.E., Schwartz M.W. Carbohydrate feeding dissociates the postprandial FGF19 response from circulating bile acid levels in humans. The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism 2013101.HoltJALuoGBillinANDefinition of a novel growth factor-dependent signal cascade for the suppression of bile acid biosynthesisGenes Dev2003171581159110.1101/gad.108350312815072102.InagakiTChoiMMoschettaAFibroblast growth factor 15 functions as an enterohepatic signal to regulate bile acid homeostasisCell Metab2005221722510.1016/j.cmet.2005.09.00116213224103.RobertsREGlicksmanCAlaghband-ZadehJSherwoodRAAkujiNle RouxCWThe relationship between postprandial bile acid concentration, GLP-1, PYY and ghrelinClin Endocrinol (Oxf)201174677210.1111/j.1365-2265.2010.03886.x21039722104.PournarasDJGlicksmanCVincentRPThe role of bile after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass in promoting weight loss and improving glycaemic controlEndocrinology20121533613361910.1210/en.2011-214522673227105.FuretJPKongLCTapJDifferential adaptation of human gut microbiota to bariatric surgery-induced weight loss: links with metabolic and low-grade inflammation markersDiabetes2010593049305710.2337/db10-025320876719106.ClarkeSFMurphyEFNilaweeraKThe gut microbiota and its relationship to diet and obesity: new insightsGut Microbes2012318620210.4161/gmic.2016822572830107.ArmougomFHenryMVialettesBRaccahDRaoultDMonitoring bacterial community of human gut microbiota reveals an increase in Lactobacillus in obese patients and methanogens in anorexic patientsPLoS One20094e712510.1371/journal.pone.000712519774074108.LeyRETurnbaughPJKleinSGordonJIMicrobial ecology: human gut microbes associated with obesityNature20064441022102310.1038/4441022a17183309109.TurnbaughPJHamadyMYatsunenkoTA core gut microbiome in obese and lean twinsNature200945748048410.1038/nature0754019043404110.TurnbaughPJLeyREMahowaldMAMagriniVMardisERGordonJIAn obesity-associated gut microbiome with increased capacity for energy harvestNature20064441027113110.1038/nature0541417183312111.ZhangHDiBaiseJKZuccoloAHuman gut microbiota in obesity and after gastric bypassProc Natl Acad Sci20091062365237010.1073/pnas.081260010619164560112.Aron-Wisnewsky J, Clement K. Gut microbiota in obesity and type-2 diabetes: links with diet and weight loss intervention. Intestin Microbiota Health Dis Mod Concepts. 2014;307.113.Liou A.P., Paziuk M., Luevano J.M., Machineni S., Turnbaugh P.J., Kaplan L.M. Conserved shifts in the gut microbiota due to gastric bypass reduce host weight and adiposity. Sci Transl Med 2013; 5:178ra41.114.Wurtman JudithJThe involvement of brain serotonin in excessive carbohydrate snacking by obese carbohydrate craversJ Am Diet Assoc1984849100410076381575115.SpitzerLRodinJHuman eating behavior: a critical review of studies in normal weight and overweight individualsAppetite1981229332910.1016/S0195-6663(81)80018-9116.DrewnowskiABrunzellJDSandeKIveriusPHGreenwoodMRCSweet tooth reconsidered: taste responsiveness in human obesityPhysiol Behav19853561762210.1016/0031-9384(85)90150-74070436117.RodinJRadke-SharpeNRebuffé-ScriveMGreenwoodMRWeight cycling and fat distributionInt J Obes1990143033102361807118.PangbornRSimonMBody size and sweetness preferenceJ Am Diet Assoc1958349924813575095119.LoweMRButrynMLHedonic hunger: a new dimension of appetite?Physiol Behav20079143243910.1016/j.physbeh.2007.04.00617531274120.SchultesBErnstBWilmsBThurnheerMHallschmidMHedonic hunger is increased in severely obese patients and is reduced after gastric bypass surgeryAm J Clin Nutr20109227728310.3945/ajcn.2009.2900720519559121.ErnstBThurnheerMWilmsBSchultesBDifferential changes in dietary habits after gastric bypass versus gastric banding operationsObes Surg20091927428010.1007/s11695-008-9769-319034589122.OlbersTBjorkmanSLindroosABody composition, dietary intake, and energy expenditure after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and laparoscopic vertical banded gastroplasty: a randomized clinical trialAnn Surg200624471572210.1097/01.sla.0000218085.25902.f817060764123.MirasADLe RouxCWBariatric surgery and taste: novel mechanisms of weight lossCurr Opin Gastroenterol201026214014510.1097/MOG.0b013e328333e94a19901832124.DeitelMThe change in the dumping syndrome conceptObes Surg2008181622162410.1007/s11695-008-9756-818941845125.ThomasJRGizisFMarcusEFood selections of Roux-en-Y gastric bypass patients up to 2.5 years postsurgeryJ Am Diet Assoc201011060861210.1016/j.jada.2009.12.01720338287126.LaureniusALarssonIMelansonKJDecreased energy density and changes in food selection following Roux-en-Y gastric bypassEur J Clin Nutr20136716817310.1038/ejcn.2012.20823299713127.KenlerHABrolinRECodyRPChanges in eating behavior after horizontal gastroplasty and Roux-en-Y gastric bypassAm J Clin Nutr19905287922360554128.Scholtz S., Miras A.D., Chhina N. et al. Obese patients after gastric bypass surgery have lower brain-hedonic responses to food than after gastric banding. Gut, gutjnl-2013 2013.129.TamCSBerthoudHRBueterMCould the mechanisms of bariatric surgery hold the key for novel therapies?: report from a Pennington Scientific SymposiumObes Rev20111298499410.1111/j.1467-789X.2011.00902.x21729236130.MeillonSMirasADRouxCWGastric bypass surgery alters food preferences through changes in the perception of tasteClinical Practice20131047147910.2217/cpr.13.32131.SugermanHJLondreyGLKellumJMWeight loss with vertical banded gastroplasty and Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: selective vs. random assignmentAm J Surg19895457464132.SugermanHJStarkeyJVBirkenhauerRA randomized prospective trial of gastric bypass versus vertical banded gastroplasty for morbid obesity and their effects on sweets versus non-sweets eatersAnn Surg198720561362410.1097/00000658-198706000-000023296971133.LinnerJHComparative effectiveness of gastric bypass and gastroplasty: a clinical studyArch Surg198211769570010.1001/archsurg.1982.013802901410257073492134.HofmannBHjelmesaethJSovikTTMoral challenges with surgical treatment of type 2 diabetesJ Diabetes Complicat20132759760310.1016/j.jdiacomp.2013.07.00624028746135.Schafe G.E., Bernstein I.L. Taste aversion learning. 1996136.GarciaJKoellingRARelation of cue to consequence in avoidance learningPsychon Sci1966412312410.3758/BF03342209137.BirchLLDevelopment of food preferencesAnnu Rev Nutr199919416210.1146/annurev.nutr.19.1.4110448516138.SpectorACGlendinningJILinking peripheral taste processes to behaviorCurr Opin Neurobiol20091937037710.1016/j.conb.2009.07.01419674892139.SpectorACLinking gustatory neurobiology to behavior in vertebratesNeurosci Biobehav Rev20002439141610.1016/S0149-7634(00)00013-010817842140.Le RouxCWBueterMTheisNGastric bypass reduces fat intake and preferenceAm J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol20113014R1057R106610.1152/ajpregu.00139.201121734019141.BueterMMirasADChichgerHAlterations of sucrose preference after Roux-en-Y gastric bypassPhysiol Behav201110470972110.1016/j.physbeh.2011.07.02521827777142.HajnalAKovacsPAhmedTMeirellesKLynchCJCooneyRNGastric bypass surgery alters behavioral and neural taste functions for sweet taste in obese ratsAm J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol2010299G967G97910.1152/ajpgi.00070.201020634436143.ShinACZhengHPistellPJBerthoudHRRoux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery changes food reward in ratsInt J Obes20113564265110.1038/ijo.2010.174144.TichanskyDRebeccaGAMadanAHarperJTokitaKBoughterJDecrease in sweet taste in rats after gastric bypass surgerySurg Endosc2011251176118110.1007/s00464-010-1335-020844896145.MirasADJacksonRNGoldstoneAPOlbersTHackenbergTSpectorACle RouxCWGastric bypass surgery for obesity decreases the reward value of a sweet-fat stimulus as assessed in a progressive ratio taskAm J Clin Nutr201296346747310.3945/ajcn.112.03692122836034146.NestoridiEKvasSKucharczykJStylopoulosNResting energy expenditure and energetic cost of feeding are augmented after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass in obese miceEndocrinology20121532234224410.1210/en.2011-204122416083147.CarrascoFPapapietroKCsendesAChanges in resting energy expenditure and body composition after weight loss following Roux-en-Y gastric bypassObes Surg20071760861610.1007/s11695-007-9117-z17658019148.FlancbaumLVerducciJChobanPChanges in measured resting energy expenditure after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass for clinically severe obesity are not related to bypass limb-lengthObes Surg1998843744310.1381/0960892987655543319731680149.FariaSKellyEFariaOEnergy expenditure and weight regain in patients submitted to Roux-en-Y gastric bypassObes Surg20091985685910.1007/s11695-009-9842-619399563150.CarrascoFRojasPRuzMEnergy expenditure and body composition in severe and morbid obese women after gastric bypass]Revista m_Ñdica de Chile2008136570151.AdamiGFCampostanoABessarioneDResting energy expenditure in long-term postobese subjects after weight normalization by dieting or biliopancreatic diversionObes Surg1993339739910.1381/09608929376555910610757952152.CastroCMLimaMMRaseraIJrOliveiraAJrGomesGPAparecidaCGEffects of Roux-en-Y gastric bypass on resting energy expenditure in womenObes Surg2008181376138010.1007/s11695-008-9460-818320289153.AdamiGFCampostanoAGandolfoPMarinariGBessarioneDScopinaroNBody composition and energy expenditure in obese patients prior to and following biliopancreatic diversion for obesityEur Surg Res19962829529810.1159/0001294698813654154.SaeidiNMeoliLNestoridiEReprogramming of intestinal glucose metabolism and glycemic control in rats after gastric bypassScience201334140641010.1126/science.123510323888041155.Bobbioni-HarschEMorelPHuberOEnergy economy hampers body weight loss after gastric bypassJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2000854695470010.1210/jcem.85.12.708311134130156.CareyDPliegoGRaymondRBody composition and metabolic changes following bariatric surgery: effects on fat mass, lean mass and basal metabolic rate: six months to one-year follow-upObes Surg2006161602160810.1381/09608920677931934717217636157.DasSKRobertsSBKehayiasJJBody composition assessment in extreme obesity and after massive weight loss induced by gastric bypass surgeryAm J Physiol Endocrinol Metab2003284E1080E108810.1152/ajpendo.00185.200212604503158.MetcalfBRabkinRRabkinJMetcalfLLehman-BeckerLWeight loss composition: the effects of exercise following obesity surgery as measured by bioelectrical impedance analysisObes Surg20051518318610.1381/096089205326838115802058159.O'BrienPEBariatric surgery: mechanisms, indications and outcomesJ Gastroenterol Hepatol2010251358136510.1111/j.1440-1746.2010.06391.x20659224160.KumarRLieskeJCCollazo-ClavellMLFat malabsorption and increased intestinal oxalate absorption are common after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgerySurgery201114965466110.1016/j.surg.2010.11.01521295813161.OdstrcilEAMartinezJGSanta AnaCAThe contribution of malabsorption to the reduction in net energy absorption after long-limb Roux-en-Y gastric bypassAm J Clin Nutr20109270471310.3945/ajcn.2010.2987020739420162.CarswellKAVincentRPBelgaumkarAPThe effect of bariatric surgery on intestinal absorption and transit timeObes Surg20141–10579680510.1007/s11695-013-1166-x163.SantryHPGillenDLLauderdaleDSTrends in bariatric surgical proceduresJAMA20052941909191710.1001/jama.294.15.190916234497164.National Bariatric Surgery Registry, First Registry Report to march 2010. 2010. Ref Type: Report165.TackJArtsJCaenepeelPDe WulfDBisschopsRPathophysiology, diagnosis and management of postoperative dumping syndromeNat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol2009658359010.1038/nrgastro.2009.14819724252166.UklejaADumping syndrome: pathophysiology and treatmentNutr Clin Pract20052051752510.1177/011542650502000551716207692167.MathewsDHChange in effective circulating volume during experimental dumping syndromeSurgery196048118519414422271168.CummingsDEFoster-SchubertKEOverduinJGhrelin and energy balance: focus on current controversiesCurr Drug Targets2005615316910.2174/138945005317456915777186169.KapoorRRJamesCHussainKAdvances in the diagnosis and management of hyperinsulinemic hypoglycemiaNat Clin Pract End Met2009510111210.1038/ncpendmet1046170.ServiceGJThompsonGBServiceFJAndrewsJCCollazo-ClavellMLLloydRVHyperinsulinemic hypoglycemia with nesidioblastosis after gastric-bypass surgeryN Engl J Med200535324925410.1056/NEJMoa04369016034010171.PattiMEGoldfineABHypoglycemia after gastric bypass: the dark side of GLP-1Gastroenterology201414660560810.1053/j.gastro.2014.01.03824468184172.ComeauEGagnerMInabnetWBHerronDMQuinnTMPompASymptomatic internal hernias after laparoscopic bariatric surgerySurg Endosc200519343910.1007/s00464-003-8515-015529196173.HusainSAhmedARJohnsonJBossTO'MalleyWSmall-bowel obstruction after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: etiology, diagnosis, and managementArch Surg200714298810.1001/archsurg.142.10.98817938313174.GarzaEJrKuhnJArnoldDNicholsonWReddySMcCartyTInternal hernias after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypassAm J Surg200418879680010.1016/j.amjsurg.2004.08.04915619502175.ChoMCarrodeguasLPintoDDiagnosis and management of partial small bowel obstruction after laparoscopic antecolic antegastric Roux-en-Y gastric bypass for morbid obesityJ Am Coll Surg200620226226810.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2005.10.01816427551176.FilipJEMattarSGBowersSPSmithCDInternal hernia formation after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass for morbid obesityAm Surg20026864064312132750177.MartinLCMerkleEMThompsonWMReview of internal hernias: radiographic and clinical findingsAm J Roentgenol200618670371710.2214/AJR.05.064416498098178.ReddySAYangCMcGinnisLASeggermanREGarzaEFordKLIIIDiagnosis of transmesocolic internal hernia as a complication of retrocolic gastric bypass: CT imaging criteriaAm J Roentgenol2007189525510.2214/AJR.06.089817579151179.Swartz D.E., Gonzalez V., Felix E.L. Anastomotic stenosis after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: a rational approach to treatment. Surgery for Obesity and Related Diseases2:632–636180.HalversonJDMicronutrient deficiencies after gastric bypass for morbid obesityAm Surg198652115945983777703181.SmithCDHerkesSBBehrnsKEGastric acid secretion and vitamin B12 absorption after vertical Roux-gastric-Y bypass for morbid obesityAnn Surg1993218919610.1097/00000658-199307000-000148328834182.DeckerGASwainJMCrowellMDScolapioJSGastrointestinal and nutritional complications after bariatric surgeryAm J Gastroenterol20071022571258010.1111/j.1572-0241.2007.01421.x17640325183.Balsiger, Bruno M., Kennedy, Frank P., Abu-Lebdeh, Haitham S., Collazo-Clavell, Maria, Jensen, Michael D., O'Brien, Timothy, Hensrud, Donald D., Dinneen, Sean F., Thompson, Geoffrey B., and Que, Florencia G. Prospective evaluation of Roux-en-Y gastric bypass as primary operation for medically complicated obesity. Mayo Clinic Proceedings 75[7], 673–680. 2000. Elsevier. Ref Type: Conference Proceeding184.AvinoahEOvnatACharuziINutritional status seven years after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgerySurgery19921111371421736382185.RhodeBMArseneauPCooperBAKatzMGilfixBMMacLeanLDVitamin B-12 deficiency after gastric surgery for obesityAm J Clin Nutr1996631031098604656186.BrolinREGormanJHPetschenikAJBradleyLJKenlerHACodyRPAre vitamin B12 and folate deficiency clinically important after roux-en-Y gastric bypass?J Gastrointest Surg1998243644210.1016/S1091-255X(98)80034-69843603187.UpdegraffTANeufeldNJProtein, iron, and folate status of patients prior to and following surgery for morbid obesityJ Am Diet Assoc1981781357217567188.BrolinRELaMarcaLBKenlerHACodyRPMalabsorptive gastric bypass in patients with superobesityJ Gastrointest Surg2002619520510.1016/S1091-255X(01)00022-111992805189.WortsmanJMatsuokaLYChenTCLuZHolickMFDecreased bioavailability of vitamin D in obesityAm J Clin Nutr20007269069310966885190.CoatesPSFernstromJDFernstromMHSchauerPRGreenspanSLGastric bypass surgery for morbid obesity leads to an increase in bone turnover and a decrease in bone massJ Clin Endocrinol Metabol2004891061106510.1210/jc.2003-031756191.von MachMAStoeckliRBilzSKraenzlinMLangerIKellerUChanges in bone mineral content after surgical treatment of morbid obesityMetabolism20045391892110.1016/j.metabol.2004.01.01515254887192.ShahMSimhaVGargALong-term impact of bariatric surgery on body weight, comorbidities, and nutritional statusJ Clin Endocrinol Metabol2006914223423110.1210/jc.2006-0557193.AbeggKGehringNWagnerCARoux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery reduces bone mineral density and induces metabolic acidosis in ratsAm J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol2013305R999R100910.1152/ajpregu.00038.201324026074194.Lalmohamed A, de Vries F, Bazelier MT, et al. Risk of fracture after bariatric surgery in the United Kingdom: population based, retrospective cohort study. BMJ: Br Med J . 2012;345.195.LangloisJAMussolinoMEVisserMLookerACHarrisTMadansJWeight loss from maximum body weight among middle-age and older white women and the risk of hip fracture: the NHANES I epidemiologic follow-up studyOsteoporos Int20111276376810.1007/s00198017005311605743196.ReidIRRelationships between fat and boneOsteoporos Int20081959560610.1007/s00198-007-0492-z17965817197.Reid IR. Relationships among body mass, its components, and bone. IBMS BoneKEy. 2002.198.AsplinJRCoeFLHyperoxaluria in kidney stone formers treated with modern bariatric surgeryJ Urol200717756556910.1016/j.juro.2006.09.03317222634199.DuffeyBGPedroRNMakhloufARoux-en-Y gastric bypass is associated with early increased risk factors for development of calcium oxalate nephrolithiasisJ Am Coll Surg20082061145115310.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2008.01.01518501812200.SinhaMKCollazo-ClavellMLRuleAHyperoxaluric nephrolithiasis is a complication of Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgeryKidney Int20077210010710.1038/sj.ki.500219417377509201.MoleDRTomsonCRVMortensenNWinearlsCGRenal complications of jejuno-ileal bypass for obesityQJM200194697710.1093/qjmed/94.2.6911181982202.MatlagaBRShoreADMagnusonTClarkJMJohnsRMakaryMAEffect of gastric bypass surgery on kidney stone diseaseJ Urol20091812573257710.1016/j.juro.2009.02.02919375090203.PinkneyJConsensus at last? The International Diabetes Federation statement on bariatric surgery in the treatment of obese type 2 diabetesDiabet Med20112888488510.1111/j.1464-5491.2011.03354.x21668496204.Cummings D.E. Endocrine mechanisms mediating remission of diabetes after gastric bypass surgery. Int J Obes 0 AD; 33:S33-S40.205.Fruhbeck G. Bariatric and metabolic surgery: a shift in eligibility and success criteria. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2015.206.ShinACZhengHBerthoudHRVagal innervation of the hepatic portal vein and liver is not necessary for Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery-induced hypophagia, weight loss, and hypermetabolismAnn Surg201225529430110.1097/SLA.0b013e31823e71b722202582
