<?xml version="1.0"?>
Biol Mood Anxiety DisordBiol Mood Anxiety DisordBiology of Mood &amp; Anxiety Disorders2045-5380BioMed Central40296082045-5380-3-202451738810.1186/2045-5380-3-20ResearchEmotion regulation in social anxiety disorder: behavioral and neural responses to three socio-emotional tasksZivMichal1ziv.michal@gmail.comGoldinPhilippe R1pgoldin@stanford.eduJazaieriHooria1hooria@stanford.eduHahnKevin S1kshahn@stanford.eduGrossJames J1gross@stanford.edu1Department of Psychology, Stanford University, Jordan Hall, Bldg. 420, 94305-2130 Stanford, CA, USA2013411201332020275201323102013Copyright © 2013 Ziv et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.2013Ziv et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.BackgroundSocial anxiety disorder (SAD) is thought to involve deficits in emotion regulation, and more specifically, deficits in cognitive reappraisal. However, evidence for such deficits is mixed.MethodsUsing functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) of blood oxygen-level dependent (BOLD) signal, we examined reappraisal-related behavioral and neural responses in 27 participants with generalized SAD and 27 healthy controls (HC) during three socio-emotional tasks: (1) looming harsh faces (Faces); (2) videotaped actors delivering social criticism (Criticism); and (3) written autobiographical negative self-beliefs (Beliefs).ResultsBehaviorally, compared to HC, participants with SAD had lesser reappraisal-related reduction in negative emotion in the Beliefs task. Neurally, compared to HC, participants with SAD had lesser BOLD responses in reappraisal-related brain regions when reappraising faces, in visual and attention related regions when reappraising criticism, and in the left superior temporal gyrus when reappraising beliefs. Examination of the temporal dynamics of BOLD responses revealed late reappraisal-related increased responses in HC, compared to SAD. In addition, the dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (DMPFC), which showed reappraisal-related increased activity in both groups, had similar temporal dynamics in SAD and HC during the Faces and Criticism tasks, but greater late response increases in HC, compared to SAD, during the Beliefs task. Reappraisal-related greater late DMPFC responses were associated with greater percent reduction in negative emotion ratings in SAD patients.ConclusionsThese results suggest a dysfunction of cognitive reappraisal in SAD patients, with overall reduced late brain responses in prefrontal regions, particularly when reappraising faces. Decreased late activity in the DMPFC might be associated with deficient reappraisal and greater negative reactivity.Trial registrationClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT00380731Social anxietyEmotion regulationReappraisalfMRIDMPFCTemporal dynamicsBackgroundSocial anxiety disorder (SAD) is characterized by heightened anxiety in a wide array of social situations [1]. It has been suggested that these elevated levels of anxiety may be due to ineffective emotion regulation [2]. Specifically, it has been suggested that patients with SAD use adaptive emotion regulation strategies, such as cognitive reappraisal, less frequently than non-anxious healthy adults [3]. In healthy individuals, cognitive reappraisal, which involves changing the meaning of a stimulus that gives rise to an emotion, can modify emotional reactions to anxiety-provoking situations, leading to greater psychological flexibility and emotional well being [4]. In SAD, deficits in cognitive reappraisal are thought to be related to difficulty in modifying the negative thoughts that arise before, during, and after social evaluative situations [5].Neuroimaging findingsOne source of evidence regarding reappraisal in SAD comes from neuroimaging studies. To date, three studies have investigated the neural correlates of cognitive reappraisal in SAD. In the first study, Goldin and colleagues examined cognitive reappraisal of social (harsh facial expressions) and physical (violent scenes) threat in SAD patients and healthy controls. Regulation during social threat, but not physical threat, was associated with diminished recruitment of brain systems implicated in cognitive reappraisal (dorsomedial and dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (PFC)), and attention modulation (medial cuneus, posterior cingulate cortex, and parietal cortex) in SAD, compared to healthy controls [5].In a second study by this group, using negative self-beliefs, the temporal dynamics of the BOLD response, in addition to its signal magnitude, were analyzed [3]. Findings revealed greater early activity in healthy controls during reappraisal of negative self-beliefs in brain networks implicated in reappraisal (dorsomedial, dorsolateral, and ventrolateral PFC), language (left inferior frontal gyrus), and visual (precuneus, inferior parietal) processing, while SAD patients had greater late responses in dorsomedial and ventrolateral PFC, insula, and visual processing regions. Taken together, these two studies suggest a failure to recruit reappraisal-related prefrontal regions in SAD. This differential activity of prefrontal regulatory regions in SAD has been observed in other neuroimaging studies [6-10].The third study that explicitly addressed the neural correlates of emotion regulation in SAD, by Bruhl and colleagues [11], reported results that are discrepant with the two studies reported above. In this study, patients were instructed either to perform ‘reality checking’ or to simply anticipate and then look at negative, positive, and neutral pictures. Thus, in contrast to the first two studies, which compared patients to healthy controls, this study compared patients applying cognitive control with patients not using cognitive control. The authors found regulation-related reduced activity in emotion reactivity regions (amygdala, insula, thalamus), and in the dorsolateral PFC and cingulated cortex, with no regions with increased activity due to cognitive control.Explaining mixed findingsOne possible explanation for the mixed findings may be the different contexts that were examined. Each of these studies focused on only one emotional probe: faces, beliefs, or non-socially specific affective pictures. However, in the SAD literature, it has been shown that the choice of emotional probes and experimental paradigms has a much larger effect on the results of fMRI investigations than is typically thought [12].In addition to using different stimuli, another source of variability in the imaging literature is the different data analytic approaches used in each study. The majority of studies in SAD so far have used BOLD signal magnitude analyses that usually collapse across time. Only a handful of studies examined the temporal dynamics of the BOLD responses [3,13-15]. Of these studies, only one [3] has specifically focused on emotion regulation processes. Analysis of BOLD signal temporal dynamics can reveal information that might be hidden when averaging across time. It can also reveal between-group differences in brain regions that have the same averaged response among two groups, such as a pattern of early brain responses in one group, or delayed responses in the other group. Indeed, the one study examining temporal dynamics of emotion regulation processes in SAD found delayed BOLD signal onset in the dorsomedial and ventrolateral PFC regions in patients, relatively to healthy controls [3].The present studyThe goal of the present study was to examine behavioral and fMRI BOLD responses in patients with SAD compared to healthy controls (HC) when reappraising socio-emotional stimuli. To test whether emotion dysregulation in SAD is related to a specific socio-emotional stimulus, or whether this is a more general core deficit, three contexts were compared: (1) looming harsh faces (Faces); (2) dynamic video clips of actors delivering social criticism (Criticism); and (3) written autobiographical social anxiety-related negative self-beliefs (Beliefs). To our knowledge, no study has directly tested reappraisal-related BOLD responses in patients with SAD across several distinct socio-emotional tasks that vary in both content and form.Behaviorally, we hypothesized that, compared to HC, patients with SAD would be less successful in down regulating negative emotional reactivity when implementing cognitive reappraisal in each of the three tasks. Neurally, we hypothesized that, compared to HC, patients with SAD would have: (1) lesser BOLD responses in reappraisal-related PFC regions; and (2) delayed (that is, late) BOLD responses in reappraisal-related PFC regions. In addition to analyzing the differential and common BOLD responses separately for each task, we examined BOLD signal temporal dynamics in regions showing similar reappraisal-related increased activity in SAD and HC across all three tasks. The purpose of this analysis was to see whether there are cognitive reappraisal-related brain responses that are stimulus-independent, and whether more refined timing differences in patients and HC could be revealed using analyses of the BOLD signal temporal dynamics.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>This study was part of a randomized controlled trial (RCT) of cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) for SAD, and data from participants in this RCT have been published in other baseline brain papers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Participants included 27 (12 women) unmedicated (minimum of three months since stopping pharmacotherapy) adults who met <italic>DSM-IV-TR</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] criteria for primary generalized SAD and 27 (13 women) HC with no lifetime history of psychiatric disorders (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). As reported in Ziv et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], patients were recruited through clinician referrals and advertisements on community and online bulletin boards. Two PhD-level clinical psychologists assessed each potential participant using the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for <italic>DSM-IV-TR Lifetime version (ADIS-IV-L</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]<italic>.</italic> Only patients who met clinical diagnostic criteria for a principal diagnosis of current generalized SAD (defined as greater than moderate anxiety/fear for five or more distinct social situations) or HC with no current or past history of DSM-IV disorders were eligible for participation.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and clinical variables</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>SAD</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>HC</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>t</italic>
</bold><bold>-value</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Partial eta</bold><sup>
<bold>2</bold>
</sup><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left"> </th><th align="left"><bold><italic>n</italic></bold> <bold>= 27</bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>n</italic></bold> <bold>= 27</bold></th><th align="left"> </th><th align="left"> </th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Women (<italic>n</italic>)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Age (mean years ± SD)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">31.1 ± 7.6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">32.6 ± 9.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Education (mean years ± SD)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">16.3 ± 2.3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">17.5 ± 1.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" valign="bottom">Ethnicity<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  - Caucasian<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">17<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  - Asian<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  - Latino<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  - Native American<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  - Native Hawaiian<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  - Filipino<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  - African American<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">LSAS-SR (Mean ± SD)</td><td align="left">99.3 ± 11.8</td><td align="left">15.3 ± 9.1</td><td align="left">29.2<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left">0.94</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt;0.0001.</p><p>LSAS-SR = Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale - Self-Report.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Patients and HC did not differ significantly in age or years of education (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). All participants were right-handed as assessed by the Edinburgh Handedness Inventory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Potential patients were excluded if they reported current pharmacotherapy or psychotherapy, history of neurological disorders, and current psychiatric disorders (other than SAD, generalized anxiety disorder, agoraphobia without a history of panic attacks, dysthymia, or specific phobia). HC were not permitted to meet criteria for any current or past psychiatric disorders.</p><p>Among patients, current Axis-I co-morbidity included two with panic attacks, two with generalized anxiety disorder, two with dysthymia, and two with specific phobia. Past Axis-I co-morbidity included six with major depression, one with post-traumatic stress disorder, four with substance abuse, and one with eating disorder. Thirteen patients reported past (that is, ended &gt;1 year ago) non-cognitive-behavioral psychotherapy, and seven reported past pharmacotherapy. The study was approved by the Stanford Medical Research Institutional Review Board (Protocol ID #79403). All participants provided informed consent in accordance with Stanford University Human Subjects Committee rules.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical assessment</title><p>To assess social anxiety symptom severity, participants completed the Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale-Self-Report (LSAS-SR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. This questionnaire assesses both fear and behavioral avoidance of social situations, and is widely used in the research of SAD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>To provide greater sensitivity, from 67 patients who were eligible for the study, we selected a subgroup of 27 SAD patients with the highest social anxiety symptom severity (range of LSAS-SR scores for the whole group: 66–102; and for the subgroup: 85–102). We compared this SAD subgroup to a group of 27 healthy controls.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental tasks</title><p>The three fMRI tasks have been described previously by Ziv et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The tasks were composed of ‘React’ and ‘Reappraise’ conditions. Prior to scanning, participants were trained in how to react and to reappraise with stimuli not used in the MR scanner tasks. The instructions for the ‘React’ condition were to react normally without any attempt to control, modify, or regulate any reactions. During the ‘Reappraise’ condition, participants were instructed to try and down regulate negative emotion reactions by actively reinterpreting the meaning of the emotion inducing stimulus. We used reappraisal methods developed by Ochsner et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>].</p><p>After each trial, participants provided a negative emotion rating using a button response pad positioned in the participant’s right hand inside the magnet by responding to ‘How negative do you feel?’ (1 = not at all to 5 = very much). All tasks were programmed in Eprime (Psychology Software Tools, Inc.).</p><sec><title>Faces task</title><p>This task consisted of 24 trials during which the participants viewed color photos of faces displaying Ekman facial action coded anger and contempt facial expressions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Each trial consisted of a cue (Look or Reframe) lasting 1.5 s, a single harsh facial stimulus presented in color and appearing to move closer to the participant to simulate looming (every 3 s over a total of 9 s), and a negative emotion rating after the face stimulus terminated (3 s) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>a). The length of the entire task was 516 TRs, which is 12 min and 54 s (774 s). Participants were trained prior to the baseline scan to either react to the faces by engaging in the picture (‘Just let yourself feel’) and thinking: ‘This person is upset with me; angry with me’, or to reappraise their emotion, for example by thinking: ‘Maybe this person just had a bad day’.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>The three socio-emotional tasks. (a)</bold> Looming harsh faces (Faces); <bold>(b)</bold> Social criticism (Criticism); <bold>(c)</bold> Negative self-beliefs (Beliefs). Each task was composed of ‘React’ and ‘Reappraise’ trials, which consisted of: (1) a 1.5-s ‘Cue’; (2) a socio-emotional stimulus (a looming harsh face/ a video-clip of an actor delivering social criticism/ an autobiographical sentence + negative self-beliefs); and (3) a negative emotion rating scale. Participants were instructed to either react normally to the stimuli without any attempt to control, modify, or regulate their reactions (‘React’), or to try and down regulate negative emotion reactions by actively reinterpreting the meaning of the emotion inducing stimulus (‘Reappraise’).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="2045-5380-3-20-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Criticism task</title><p>The task consisted of videotaped actors delivering social criticism and social praise and harsh or happy evaluation-congruent facial expressions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>b). The stimuli were delivered by five male and five female actors (seven Anglo-Americans and three Asian-Americans), with an age range of 23 to 50 years. In each trial the participants were asked to either ‘Just Watch’ or ‘Reframe’ their reaction (1.5 s) during the social evaluation video clip (12 s). Each video clip had a 4.5-s waiting period during which the actor silently maintained a neutral facial expression followed by a 7.5-s evaluation period in which the actor delivered a social criticism or praise statement while displaying a harsh or positive facial expression. For the current study, only the 7.5-s evaluation period of the social criticism trials were included in the analysis. After each video clip, participants were cued to rate their current negative emotion (3 s). Each condition consisted of 16 trials delivered across two runs of 342 TRs, 8 min 35 s each (513 s). Participants were trained on the instructions prior to scanning. Participants were told to react to the social criticism by reflecting on how the statement represents something true about themselves, or to reappraise their emotion, for example by thinking: ‘this is not always true’, or ‘this is only a thought, not a fact’.</p></sec><sec><title>Beliefs task</title><p>This task consisted of five situations. The first was an experimenter-composed neutral situation that was used to obtain baseline emotion ratings for reading neutral statements. The neutral situation was followed by four participant-generated autobiographical social anxiety situations that were characterized by social anxiety, humiliation, and/or embarrassment. Prior to scanning session, participants composed a single paragraph describing the events, thoughts, and feelings for each situation, and provided situation-specific negative self-beliefs (NSBs). At the scanner, the participants were asked to either React to the negative self-beliefs, or to Reframe their reaction.</p><p>Three situations were presented in a first run lasting 374 TRs, 9 min 21 s (561 s), followed by two situations in a second run of 256 TRs, 6 min 24 s (534 s). Each situation consisted of an instruction to react/reframe (1.5 s), 16 sentences (3 s each,) in white font against a black background describing the situation, 10 NSBs (9 s each) embedded in the unfolding story in uppercase letters that flashed nine times (850 ms on + 150 ms off), and a negative emotion rating after each NSB (3 s) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>c). Participants were trained prior to scanning to react to the NSBs by reflecting on how the NSB represents something that is true about themselves, or to reappraise their reaction by thinking of a positive coping statement that directly challenges the thoughts (‘try to re-interpret the statement so it is less negative and toxic for you’).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Image acquisition</title><p>Information about the fMRI image acquisition and data preprocessing have been described previously by Ziv et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. We used a General Electric 3-T Signa magnet with a T2*-weighted gradient echo spiral-in/out pulse sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] and a custom-built quadrature ‘dome’ elliptical bird cage head-coil (GE Healthcare, Milwaukee, WI, USA). Head movements were minimized using a bite-bar and foam padding. Functional volumes (516 for faces, 684 for criticism, 630 for belief tasks) were obtained from 22 sequential axial slices (repetition time = 1500 ms, echo time = 30 ms, flip angle = 60°, field of view = 22 cm, matrix = 64 × 64, single-shot, resolution = 3.438 mm<sup>2</sup> × 4.5 mm). Three-dimensional high-resolution anatomical scans were acquired using a fast spin-echo spoiled gradient recall (resolution = 0.8594 mm<sup>2</sup> × 1.5 mm; field of view = 22 cm, frequency encoding = 256).</p></sec><sec><title>FMRI data preprocessing</title><p>We used Analysis of Functional Neuroimages (AFNI) software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] for preprocessing and statistical analysis. Preprocessing included an analysis of potential outliers, volume registration to a base image, motion correction, 4 mm<sup>3</sup> isotropic Gaussian spatial smoothing, high-pass filtering (0.011 Hz), linear detrending, and conversion into BOLD signal percentage change in each voxel. In addition, the first four images of each functional run were excluded, to allow for T2* equilibration effects. For the Criticism and Belief tasks, the two functional runs were concatenated prior to statistical analysis. No volumes demonstrated motion in the x, y, or z directions in excess of ±1 mm. There was no evidence of stimulus-correlated motion, as assessed by correlations between condition-specific reference functions and x, y, z motion correction parameters.</p></sec><sec><title>fMRI statistical analysis</title><p>Multiple-regression implemented with AFNI 3dDeconvolve included baseline parameters to remove mean, linear, and quadratic trends, and motion-related variance in the BOLD signal. Regressors for the React and Reappraise conditions were convolved with the Cohen’s gamma variate model of the hemodynamic response function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Functional MRI BOLD signal intensity was computed as percentage of signal change, an effect size measure [(MR signal per voxel per time point/mean MR signal in that voxel for the entire functional run) × 100].</p><p>Individual brain maps were converted to Talairach atlas space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] and second-level group statistical parametric maps were produced according to a random-effects model. To correct for multiple comparisons, AlphaSim, a Monte Carlo simulation bootstrapping program in the AFNI library, was used to protect against false positives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. This method uses a voxel-wise and cluster volume joint-probability threshold to establish a cluster-wise false-positive cluster detection level. The cluster statistical threshold for the between-group analyses consisted of a voxel-wise <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.005 and cluster volume &gt;244 mm<sup>3</sup> (6 voxels × 3.438 mm<sup>3</sup>) to protect against false-positive cluster detection at <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01.</p><p>To examine differential responses in BOLD signal magnitude, we conducted a whole-brain 2 Group (SAD, HC) between-group t-test of Reappraise <italic>versus</italic> React in SAD <italic>versus</italic> HC. To identify common responses, we ran a one-sample t-test of Reappraise <italic>versus</italic> React in SAD, and separately in HC.</p><p>To further examine the between-group differences in the BOLD responses during reappraisal, we ran between-group t-tests for early (first three time points, 0 to 4.5 s) and late (last two/three time points, 4.5 to 7.5 s or 4.5 to 9 s) BOLD responses for the contrast of Reappraise <italic>versus</italic> React. This analysis was conducted in each of the brain regions showing a between-group difference, and had several sub-steps: (1) creating masks from each of the clusters surviving the threshold of the between-group t-test, separately for each task; (2) extracting the percent signal change from each of these regions, at the individual subject level, for the Reappraise condition and for the React condition; (3) calculating the percent signal change for Reappraise minus React; (4) averaging (for each subject) the percent signal change for the first three time points, and for the last three time points; and (5) running between-group t-tests (SAD <italic>versus</italic> HC) separately for the early and late averaged responses, for each task.</p><p>In a secondary analysis, we examined brain regions showing BOLD responses common to SAD and HC across the three tasks, and ran between-group t-tests on the contrast of Reappraise <italic>versus</italic> React, for early and late responses, separately, for each task.</p></sec></sec>EndnoteaThe increased reappraisal-related activity during criticism was found in two clusters identified as the left fusiform gyrus (1. x,y,z = -24, -68, -12, voxel size = 16; 2. x,y,z = -45, -65, -16, voxel size = 6) and in three clusters identified as the right cerebellum (1. x,y,z = 3, -68, -9, voxel size = 12; 2. x,y,z = 24, -51, -16, voxel size = 7; 3. x,y,z = 17, -58, -12, voxel size = 7). All demonstrated similar pattern of temporal dynamics. For simplicity, we report here only the effects of the biggest cluster in each region (16 voxels for the left fusiform, 12 voxels for the right cerebellum).Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsMZ participated in the study’s design and coordination, contributed to data acquisition, conducted the fMRI sessions, conducted the data analyses, and took the lead on writing the manuscript. PRG helped conceive of the design of the study, participated in the study’s design and coordination, contributed to data acquisition, conducted the fMRI sessions, consulted on data analyses, and contributed to writing the manuscript. HJ participated in the study’s design and coordination, contributed to data acquisition, conducted the fMRI sessions, consulted on data analyses, and contributed to writing the manuscript. KSH consulted on data analyses, and contributed to writing the manuscript. JJG helped conceive of the design of the study, consulted on data analyses, and contributed to writing the manuscript. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.AcknowledgementsWe wish to thank Gary Glover, Ph.D. for his technical assistance with magnetic resonance imaging. This research was supported by an NIMH Grant R01 MH076074, awarded to James Gross. Michal Ziv had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.SteinMBSteinDJSocial anxiety disorderLancet200831115112510.1016/S0140-6736(08)60488-218374843HofmannSGCognitive mediation of treatment change in social phobiaJ Consult Clin Psychol2004339339915279523GoldinPRManber-BallTWernerKHeimbergRGrossJJNeural mechanisms of cognitive reappraisal of negative self-beliefs in social anxiety disorderBiol Psychiatry200931091109910.1016/j.biopsych.2009.07.01419717138GrossJJHandbook of emotion regulation2007New York, NY: Guilford PressGoldinPRManberTHakimiSCanliTGrossJJNeural bases of social anxiety disorder: emotional reactivity and cognitive regulation during social and physical threatArch Gen Psychiatry2009317018010.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2008.52519188539LorberbaumJPKoseSJohnsonMRAranaGWSullivanLKHamnerMBBallengerJCLydiardRBBrodrickPSBohningDEGeorgeMSNeural correlates of speech anticipatory anxiety in generalized social phobiaNeuroreport200432701270515597038BlairKGeraciMDevidoJMcCaffreyDChenGVythilingamMNgPHollonNJonesMBlairRJPineDSNeural response to self- and other referential praise and criticism in generalized social phobiaArch Gen Psychiatry200831176118410.1001/archpsyc.65.10.117618838634GuyerAELauJYMcClure-ToneEBParrishJShiffrinNDReynoldsRCChenGBlairRJLeibenluftEFoxNAAmygdala and ventrolateral prefrontal cortex function during anticipated peer evaluation in pediatric social anxietyArch Gen Psychiatry200831303131210.1001/archpsyc.65.11.130318981342SripadaCSAngstadtMBanksSNathanPJLiberzonIPhanKLFunctional neuroimaging of mentalizing during the trust game in social anxiety disorderNeuroreport2009398498910.1097/WNR.0b013e32832d0a6719521264ZivMGoldinPRJazaieriHHahnKSGrossJJIs there less to social anxiety than meets the eye? Behavioral and neural responses to three socio-emotional tasksBiol Mood Anxiety Disord20133510.1186/2045-5380-3-523448192BruhlABHerwigUDelsignoreAJanckeLRuferMGeneral emotion processing in social anxiety disorder: neural issues of cognitive controlPsychiatry Res2013310811510.1016/j.pscychresns.2012.05.00623146247Freitas-FerrariMCHallakJETrzesniakCFilhoASMachado-de-SousaJPChagasMHNardiAECrippaJANeuroimaging in social anxiety disorder: a systematic review of the literatureProg Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry2010356558010.1016/j.pnpbp.2010.02.02820206659GoldinPRGrossJJEffects of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) on emotion regulation in social anxiety disorderEmotion20103839120141305GoldinPZivMJazaieriHGrossJJRandomized controlled trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction versus aerobic exercise: effects on the self-referential brain network in social anxiety disorderFront Hum Neurosci2012329523133411CampbellDWSareenJPaulusMPGoldinPRSteinMBReissJPTime-varying amygdala response to emotional faces in generalized social phobiaBiol Psychiatry2007345546310.1016/j.biopsych.2006.09.01717188251DSM-IV-TRDiagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders19944Washington, DC: American Psychiatric Association2000DiNardoPABrownTABarlowDHAnxiety disorders interview schedule for DSM-IV: lifetime version (ADIS-IV-L)1994Albany, NY: Graywind Publications, IncOldfieldRCThe assessment and analysis of handedness: the Edinburgh inventoryNeuropsychologia197139711310.1016/0028-3932(71)90067-45146491LiebowitzMRSocial phobiaMod Probl Pharmacopsychiatry198731411732885745FrescoDMColesMEHeimbergRGLiebowitzMRHamiSSteinMBGoetzDThe Liebowitz social anxiety scale: a comparison of the psychometric properties of self-report and clinician-administered formatsPsychol Med200131025103511513370OchsnerKNRayRDCooperJCRobertsonERChopraSGabrieliJDGrossJJFor better or for worse: neural systems supporting the cognitive down-and up-regulation of negative emotionNeuroimage2004348349910.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.06.03015488398EkmanPFriesenWFacial action coding system: a technique for the measurment of facial movement1978Palo Alto, CA: Consulting Psychologists PressGloverGHLawCSSpiral-in/out BOLD fMRI for increased SNR and reduced susceptibility artifactsMagn Reson Med2001351552210.1002/mrm.122211550244CoxRWAFNI: software for analysis and visualization of functional magnetic resonance neuroimagesComput Biomed Res1996316217310.1006/cbmr.1996.00148812068CohenMSParametric analysis of fMRI data using linear systems methodsNeuroimage199739310310.1006/nimg.1997.02789299383TalairachJTournouxPCo-planar stereotaxic atlas of the human brain1988New York, NY: ThiemeFormanSDCohenJDFitzgeraldMEddyWFMintunMANollDCImproved assessment of significant activation in functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI): use of a cluster-size thresholdMagn Reson Med1995363664710.1002/mrm.19103305087596267McclureEBPineDSCicchetti D, Cohen DJSocial anxiety and emotion regulation: A model for developmental psychopathology perspectives on anxiety disordersDevelopmental Psychopathology, Risk, Disorder, and Adaptation20062Hoboken, New Jersey: John Wiley &amp; Sons47050OchsnerKNSilversJABuhleJTFunctional imaging studies of emotion regulation: a synthetic review and evolving model of the cognitive control of emotionAnn N Y Acad Sci20123E1E2410.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06751.x23025352SteinMBGoldinPRSareenJZorrillaLTBrownGGIncreased amygdala activation to angry and contemptuous faces in generalized social phobiaArch Gen Psychiatry200231027103410.1001/archpsyc.59.11.102712418936SchultzLTHeimbergRGAttentional focus in social anxiety disorder: potential for interactive processesClin Psychol Rev200831206122110.1016/j.cpr.2008.04.00318555570LundhLGOstLGRecognition bias for critical faces in social phobicsBehav Res Ther1996378779410.1016/0005-7967(96)00035-68952121HorleyKWilliamsLMGonsalvezCGordonEFace to face: visual scanpath evidence for abnormal processing of facial expressions in social phobiaPsychiatry Res20043435310.1016/j.psychres.2004.02.01615261704O’DohertyJDayanPSchultzJDeichmannRFristonKDolanRJDissociable roles of ventral and dorsal striatum in instrumental conditioningScience2004345245410.1126/science.109428515087550VrtickaPSimioniSFornariESchluepMVuilleumierPSanderDNeural substrates of social emotion regulation: a FMRI study on imitation and expressive suppression to dynamic facial signalsFront Psychol201339523450458MuellerEMHofmannSGSantessoDLMeuretAEBitranSPizzagalliDAElectrophysiological evidence of attentional biases in social anxiety disorderPsychol Med200931141115210.1017/S003329170800482019079826McRaeKGrossJJWeberJRobertsonERSokol-HessnerPRayRDGabrieliJDOchsnerKNThe development of emotion regulation: an fMRI study of cognitive reappraisal in children, adolescents and young adultsSoc Cogn Affect Neurosci20123112210.1093/scan/nsr09322228751Van der MeerLCostafredaSAlemanADavidASSelf-reflection and the brain: a theoretical review and meta-analysis of neuroimaging studies with implications for schizophreniaNeurosci Biobehav Rev2010393594610.1016/j.neubiorev.2009.12.00420015455NorthoffGBermpohlFCortical midline structures and the selfTrends Cogn Sci2004310210710.1016/j.tics.2004.01.00415301749LemogneCDelaveauPFretonMGuionnetSFossatiPMedial prefrontal cortex and the self in major depressionJ Affect Disord20123e1e1110.1016/j.jad.2010.11.03421185083GoldinPRMcRaeKRamelWGrossJJThe neural bases of emotion regulation: reappraisal and suppression of negative emotionBiol Psychiatry2008357758610.1016/j.biopsych.2007.05.03117888411
