<?xml version="1.0"?>
Exp Ther MedExp Ther MedETMExperimental and Therapeutic Medicine1792-09811792-1015D.A. Spandidos378684810.3892/etm.2013.1210etm-06-03-0773ArticlesAcupuncture for the treatment of urinary incontinence: A review of randomized controlled trialsPAIKSUN-HOHANSU-RYUNKWONOH-JUNAHNYOUNG-MINLEEBYUNG-CHEOLAHNSE-YOUNGDepartment of Internal Medicine, College of Korean Medicine, Kyung Hee University, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul 130-702, Republic of KoreaCorrespondence to: Professor Se-Young Ahn, Hospital of Korean Medicine, Kyung Hee University Medical Center, Kyung Hee University, 1 Hoegi-Dong, Dongdaemun-Gu, Seoul 130-701, Republic of Korea, E-mail: thyroidsafe@naver.com92013097201309720136377378026320132762013Copyright © 2013, Spandidos Publications2013This is an open-access article licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License. The article may be redistributed, reproduced, and reused for non-commercial purposes, provided the original source is properly cited.The aim of this study was to examine the effects of acupuncture on urinary incontinence and to discuss why these acupoints were selected. Seven databases were searched for any randomized controlled trials (RCTs) that investigated the use of acupuncture or acupressure as a treatment for urinary incontinence, and the Cochrane risk of bias tool was utilized to evaluate the risk of bias in each study. Four RCTs met all the inclusion criteria. The results from the selected RCTs failed to demonstrate any statistically significant improvements in urinary incontinence, although acupuncture or acupressure did exhibit favorable effects on overactive bladder symptoms and quality of life, in comparison with other conventional therapies. There have been limited results supporting acupuncture or acupressure as an effective treatment method for urinary incontinence; therefore, further RCTs are required to confirm the effectiveness of acupuncture or acupressure in the treatment of urinary incontinence.acupunctureacupressureurinary incontinenceleakageIntroductionAcupuncture has been performed in Korea for thousands of years and is still actively practiced in clinics today. In particular, acupuncture is known to be useful due to its pain relieving effects; however, at present, it is also studied and used for the treatment of broader symptoms, such as urinary incontinence. Urinary incontinence is a common condition, affecting ~25% of premenopausal and 40% of postmenopausal women. While it may not be a critical problem, it reduces the quality of life; however, only approximately one in four women with urinary incontinence consult a doctor about their condition (1).Stress and urge incontinence are the two most common types of urinary incontinence, and mixed incontinence, which is a combination of the two, is also prevalent. Stress incontinence occurs when the bladder pressure exceeds urethral resistance as a result of an increased abdominal pressure, for example due to sneezing or coughing (2). Stress incontinence is defined as an involuntary leakage when the abdominal pressure increases, whereas urge incontinence occurs as a result of uncontrolled abnormal detrusor contractions that exceed the urethral pressure (2). The etiology of the urinary urgency that causes urge incontinence has not yet been fully elucidated, although some peripheral nerves, as well as the central nervous system, may be involved in muscle hypersensitivity and the reduced effectiveness of smooth muscle relaxation (3).Acupuncture was initially described as a successful treatment for certain overactive bladder symptoms in the 1980s (4,5), and, since then, a number of clinical trials on incontinence have been carried out (6–8). There have been numerous clinical trials and some randomized controlled trials (RCTs) on urinary incontinence due to bladder instability or stress incontinence; however, the results are limited and there have been no systematic reviews to date.The acupoints used in the studies were selected based on Korean Medicine theory, and their mechanism may be understood with reference to the autonomic and somatic nerve innervations to the bladder. Certain studies have indicated that acupuncture may influence the autonomic nerve system (9). There has not been sufficient consideration of the depth of the acupuncture insertion into the body in previous studies, and, therefore, this review aimed to provide information as to why insertion depth is necessary as a differential factor.In this review, we examined the efficacy of acupuncture with regard to urinary incontinence, and assessed the levels of the autonomic efferent and afferent pathways and the depth of the needle insertion in the acupuncture.There is a complex rationale behind the choice of acupuncture points for incontinence. The muscles controlling micturition are controlled by the autonomic and somatic nervous system. The detrusor muscle is relaxed by sympathetic stimulation that originates from the lumbar spinal cord T11-L2 region, and contracted by parasympathetic stimulation from the sacral spinal cord S2-4 region. The external urethral sphincter is under somatic control (10). Therefore, the coordination of the autonomic and somatic nerves to the bladder and urethra is important not only in micturition, but also in incontinence.The points that are most commonly used in acupuncture are BL31, BL32 and BL33, which are located above the first, second and third sacral foramina, which lie over the first, second and third sacral nerve roots, respectively. These points are frequently used, due to the fact that they correspond with the segmental innervation of the parasympathetic nerve supply to the bladder.The acupuncture points that are known to affect the micturition center and parasympathetic innervation to the urinary system include BL23, BL28 and several points on one of the eight extra meridians in the lower abdomen (11). BL23 is located at the L2 level, BL28 is located paravertebrally from the second sacral foramina and points three, four and six on the CV are located in between the pubic and the umbilical cord.In Korean Medicine, acupoints SP6, ST36 and KI3, located on the legs, are also considered to assist bladder function by invigorating energy. Furthermore, these acupoints on the legs correspond to the skin dermatomes from L4-S2 innervation, which means that stimulation of these points may influence bladder function. Similarly, points three, four and six on the CV correspond to the skin dermatomes from T11-L1.Since the afferent and efferent innervations of the bladder are affected by the sympathetic nerves originating at T11-L2, as well as the parasympathetic and somatic nerves originating at S2-4, these acupoints appear to be strongly organized segmentally.In the majority of the remaining studies on bladder dysfunction, the stimulation points (not restricted to acupuncture) were selected in accordance with the segmental innervation of the nerves. Electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) applied over the pubic area, which pertains to the sacral dermatome, has exhibited certain positive effects (12), while other animal studies have also demonstrated that stimulation on the perineal area affects the bladder and sphincter function (13).The locations of BL31, BL32 and BL33 correspond with the origin of the somatic fibers of the pudendal nerve, which provide excitatory innervation to the pelvic floor muscles and the sphincter so that they are able to remain in a contracted state. A previous study has described the beneficial effects of transcutaneous stimulation of the pupendal nerve on incontinence (14). The authors hypothesized that sacral nerve stimulation depended on the stimulation of afferent axons (which was by electrical stimulation in this particular study) in the spinal roots, and that this led to the modulation of the voiding and continence reflex pathways in the central nervous system (14).The acupoint ST36 is predominantly used in the treatment of gastrointestinal symptoms, although it may also be used for urinary disorders. In a study investigating the ST36 acupoint, functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) results indicated activation in the hypothalamus and bilateral prefrontal cortex, suggesting that acupoint ST36 activated the neural brainstem-thalamus-cortex reticular system and increased the neurotransmitter concentrations (15). It is for this reason that acupuncture has been proposed to affect micturition through the descending serotonergic system. At present, there are numerous experimental and clinical data supporting the theory that the serotonergic input facilitates glutamate-induced activation of the pudendal nerve, and thereby helps to maintain the external urethral sphincter in a closed state (8). However, there are also physiological similarities between muscle training and acupuncture, and there have been suggestions that acupuncture may be regarded as an artificial method of muscle training (16).With regard to the insertion depth of the acupuncture needles, it has been observed that the majority of the studies concerning acupuncture have focused on the efficacy of the acupoint itself. Although electroacupuncture is frequently studied, there has been little investigation surrounding the insertion depth or the thickness of the acupuncture needle. The area of acupuncture that is predominantly focused upon is its analgesic effect on pain, and therefore most of the studies or trials concerning the depth of acupuncture have been restricted to its pain relieving effects (17,18). However, even in consideration of these studies, an appropriate penetration depth of the acupuncture needle has not been suggested. In patients with lower back pain, it has been observed that deep insertion into the muscle produced greater efficacy than shallow insertion (19). Furthermore, it has been demonstrated that, with regard to analgesic effects, the insertion of acupuncture needles into the muscles affects the nociceptors, while insertion purely into the skin does not (20). Therefore, it has been indicated that acupuncture may have different effects, according to insertion depth; however, as of yet, there is no standard regarding the depth of insertion.While there have been relatively few clinical trials concerning incontinence that have considered the insertion depth of the acupuncture, those trials that have mentioned the depth of insertion lack consistency, as well as an explanation regarding the reason for changing the depth of insertion (8,21,22).For the purpose of skin dermatome stimulation, the acupuncture needle has to be inserted shallowly, so that it only penetrates the skin. With regard to urinary dysfunction, the acupoints on the limbs are associated with the skin dermatomes from the spinal innervation that influence bladder function, as are the acupoints on the lower abdomen (CV 3, 4 and 6). Therefore, when acupuncture is applied to these acupoints, in order to influence bladder function, it is necessary for the depth of insertion to be no deeper than the skin. However, if the purpose is to stimulate the muscle or nerve, a deeper insertion is required. Therefore, it is necessary for the needles at the acupoints on the spinal part of the BL meridian to be inserted deeper than those at other BL points. In addition, it is necessary that the application of acupuncture to strengthen the muscle that assists the act of urination has a penetration that is sufficiently deep for the muscle to be reached.Therefore, aside from the acupuncture point itself, there is a requirement for the insertion depth of the acupuncture needle to differ according to the intention of the stimulation.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Data sources</title><p>The following sources were researched up to August 2012: Korean electronic databases (which included KISS, JISTI, DBPIA and the Korean Traditional Knowledge Portal), MedLine, The Cochrane Library and the Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health Literature (CINAHL).</p><p>The key words used in the search for RCTs were ‘acupuncture’ AND ‘bladder’ OR ‘incontinence’ OR ‘overactive’ OR ‘urgency’ OR ‘urinary’. In Korean, Acupuncure AND (‘Urinary incontinence’ OR ‘Bladder’) were used. Each database was manually searched, independently.</p><sec><title>Study selection</title><sec><title>Types of studies</title><p>The review was restricted to RCTs on humans that compared acupuncture or acupressure with a control group and that included pharmacological treatment, nonpharmacological treatment, such as pelvic floor muscle exercises, sham acupuncture and placebo acupuncture (relaxation point acupuncture). Articles written in English or Korean were included with language restriction.</p></sec><sec><title>Types of participants</title><p>The review included participants of all ages who suffered from urinary incontinence. The exclusion criteria comprised individuals who had original underlying diseases or had a secondary illness, such as diabetic bladder dysfunction or a hysterectomy.</p></sec><sec><title>Types of intervention</title><p>Clinical trials evaluating acupuncture treatments, including acupressure, were included. The types of control interventions considered in this review included pharmacological treatment, nonpharmacological treatment, such as pelvic floor muscle exercises, sham acupuncture and placebo acupuncture (relaxation point acupuncture).</p></sec><sec><title>Types of outcome measure</title><p>The assessed outcomes were a reduction in the percentage of all daytime or urge accidents, in addition to changes in the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) symptom scores, self-reported severity of urine leakage and number of urine leakage episodes. The assessment of the treatments was performed using bladder diaries, the Medical Outcome Short-Form (MOS SF-36), the Incontinence Impact Questionnaire (IIQ), the Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI), symptom questionnaires, VAS, VAS side-effects, the Psychosocial Adjustment to Illness Scale (PAIS), urodynamic assessments, cystometric tests, perineometry, four-day frequency volume charts, four-day scales, pad tests and the Chinese version of the King’s Health Questionnaire (CKHQ). The secondary outcomes assessed were the occurrence of adverse events.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction and assessment of the risk of bias</title><p>The full texts of the selected articles were obtained and read in full by reviewers independently. The risk of bias was assessed using the Cochrane criteria, which comprised sequence generation, allocation sequence concealment, blinding of participants, blinding of assessors, incomplete outcome data and selective outcome reporting. The assessment was based on the statement from the authors of each article (<xref rid="tI-etm-06-03-0773" ref-type="table">Table I</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec></sec>AcknowledgementsThis study was supported by the Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF), funded by the Ministry of Education, Science, and Technology (grant no. 2005-0049404).References1NygaardIEHeitMStress urinary incontinenceObstet Gynecol1046076202004153397762AbramsPCadozoLFallMStandardisation Sub-committee of the International Continence SocietyThe standardisation of terminology of lower urinary tract dysfunction: report from the Standardisation Sub-committee of the International Continence SocietyNeurourol Urodyn211671782002118576713RobinsonDPatholophysiology of female lower urinary tract dysfunctionObstet Gynecol Clin North Am25747756199899215544PhilipTShahPJWorthPHAcupuncture in the treatment of bladder instabilityBr J Urol61490493198834016575ChangPLUrodynamic studies in acupuncture in women with frequency, urgency, and dysuriaJ Urol140563566198834116756BergströmKCarlssonCLindholmCWidengrenRImprovement of urge- and mixed-type incontinence after acupuncture treatment among elderly women - a pilot studyJ Auton Nerv Syst791731802000106996497HonjoHKitakojiHKawakitaKAcupuncture for urinary incontinence in patients with chronic spinal cord injuryNippon Hinyokika Gakkai Zasshi896656691998(In Japanese)97395888KelleherCFilshieJKhullarVCardozoLAcupuncture and the treatment of irritative bladder symptomsAcupunct Med1291219949KnardahlSElamMOlaussonBWallinBGSympathetic nerve activity after acupuncture in humansPain7519251998953967010RajaofetraNPassagiaJGMarlierLSerotoninergic, noradrenergic, and peptidergic innervation of Onuf’s nucleus of normal and transected spinal cords of baboons (Papio papio)J Comp Neurol3181171992137476311MinniBCapozzaNCretiGDe GennaroMCaionePBischkoJBladder instability and enuresis treated by acupuncture and electro-therapeutics: early urodynamic observationsAcupunct Electrother Res1519251990197357712NakamuraMSakuraiTTsujimotoYTadaYBladder inhibition by electrical stimulation of the perianal skinUrol Int4162631986348584913SatoASatoYShimadaFTorigataYChanges in vesical function produced by cutaneous stimulation in ratsBrain Res944654741975115685514Chartier-KastlerEJRuud BoschJLPerrigotMLong-term results of sacral nerve stimulation (S3) for the treatment of neurogenic refractory urge incontinence related to detrusor hyperreflexiaJ Urol1641476148020001102568615JiangHWangPJZengHWZhaoXHCentral mechanism of electric-acupuncture at Zusanli (ST36) for gastric mucous membrane protection with FMRIZhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi901458146220102097321516AndersonSLundebergTAcupuncture - from empiricism to science: functional background to acupuncture effects in pain and diseaseMed Hypotheses452712811995856955117ItohKMinakawaYKitakojiHEffect of acupuncture depth on muscle painChin Med62420012169660318SilcaMLSilvaJRPradoWAThe antinociceptive effect of electroacupuncture at different depths of acupoints and under the needling surfaceChin Med7320122236926619ItohKKatsumiYKitakojiHTrigger point acupuncture treatment of chronic low back pain in elderly patients - a blinded RCTAcupunct Med2217017720041562877420ItohKOkadaKKawakitaKA proposed experimental model of myofascial trigger points in human muscle after slow eccectric exerciseAcupunct Med2221220041507793221EngbergSCohenSSereikaSMThe efficacy of acupuncture in treating urge and mixed incontinence in women: a pilot studyJ Wound Ostomy Continence Nurs3666167020091992074922EmmonsSLOttoLAcupuncture for overactive bladder: a randomized controlled trialObstet Gynecol10613814320051599462923ChangKKWongTKWongTHLeungAWChungJWEffect of acupressure in treating urodynamic stress incontinence: a randomized controlled trialAm J Chin Med391139115920112208398724de AzevedoRFCbiariBMOkadaDMOnishiETImpact of acupuncture on otoacoustic emissions in patients with tinnitusBraz J Otorhinolaryngol7359960720071809480025OkadaDMOnishiETChamiFIBorinACassolaNGuerreiroVMAcupuncture for tinnitus immediate reliefBraz J Otorhinolaryngol7218218620061695185026HansenPEHansenJHBentzenOAcupuncture treatment of chronic unilateral tinnitus - a double-blind cross-over trialClin Otolaryngol Allied Sci73253291982675670927VilholmOJMøllerKJørgensenKEffect of traditional Chinese acupuncture on severe tinnitus: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, clinical investigation with open therapeutic controlBr J Audiol321972041998971033728JeonSWKimKSNamHJLong-term effect of acupuncture for treatment of tinnitus: a randomized, patient- and assessor-blind, sham-acupuncture-controlled, pilot trialJ Alter Complement Med18693699201229WangKBuggeJBuggeSA randomised, placebo-controlled trial of manual and electrical acupuncture for the treatment of tinnitusComplement Ther Med1824925520102113036130MarksNJEmeryPOnisiphorouCA controlled trial of acupuncture in tinnitusJ Laryngol Otol98110311091984638701831EzzoJBermanBHadhazyVAJadadARLaoLSinghBBIs acupuncture effective for the treatment of chronic pain? A systemic reviewPain8621722520001081225132ZaslawskiCJCobbinDLidumsEPetoczPThe impact of site specificity and needle manipulation on changes to pain pressure threshold following manual acupuncture: a controlled studyComplement Ther Med11112120031266797033LokeYKDerrySAronsonJKA comparison of three different sources of data in assessing the frequencies of adverse reactions to amiodaroneBr J Clin Pharmacol5761662120041508981534LokeYKDerrySReporting of adverse drug reactions in randomised controlled trials - a systematic surveyBMC Clin Pharmacol13200111591227Figure 1Flow chart of trial selection process. CCT, controlled clinical trial; RCT, randomized controlled trial.Table ISummary of acupuncture treatment administered in each trial.First author (yr) [country] (ref)Experience of acupuncturistDe-qiBody posture of patientsAcupuncture pointTreatment frequencyF/UType of needleStimulation methodEngberg (2009) [USA] (20)Not mentioned (licensed by the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania)ConsideredLay prone or sat in massage chairKI3, SP6, BL23, BL31, BL32, BL33Twice a week6 weeks, treatment; 4 weeks laterExtremity points: 32 gauge, 3 cm long disposable needles Paraspinal points: 32 gauge, 4 cm long disposable needlesExtremity points: Inserted to a depth of 20–30 mm Paraspinal points: Inserted to a depth of 30–40 mm. Needles remained in place for 25 minKelleher (1994) [England] (8)ExperiencedNot mentionedNot mentionedSP6, ST36, CV3 or 4, BL23, BL28. 2 paravertebral, lumbar, segmental points, 4 sacral, segmental pointsWeekly treatments6 weeks, treatment; 3 months later36 gauge, 3 cm long, disposable needlesMinimal stimulation technique: Needles were merely flicked into the skin, left in situ a few millimetres below the skin without further stimulation for 10 minEmmons (2005) [USA] (21)Not mentioned (obstetrician- gynecologist)ConsideredNot mentionedSP6, BL39, BL28, CV4Weekly treatments4 weeks, treatment; 2–4 weeks laterNot mentionedNeedles were placed and rotated clockwise until the patient reported the sensation of de-qi, then were retained without further stimulation for 20 minChang (2011) [Hong Kong] (22)One-month training and practice for the trialConsideredNot mentionedCV3, CV4, CV6, ST36, SP6, L23, BL28, BL323 weekly treatments10 weeks treatment, no f/uyr, year of publication; ref, reference number; F/U, follow-up.Table IIResults of assessing the risk of bias.First author (yr) [country] (ref)Sequence generationAllocation sequence concealmentBlinding of participantsBlinding of assessorIncomplete outcome dataSelective outcome reportingEngberg (2009) [USA] (20)YUYYNYKelleher (1994) [England] (8)YUNUUYEmmons (2005) [USA] (21)YYYYNYChang (2011) [Hongkong] (22)YUYNYNyr, year of publication; ref, reference number; Y, yes; U, unclear; N, no.Table IIISummary of randomized controlled trials of acupuncture for the treatment of urinary incontinence.First author (yr) [country] (ref)N (T/C)Population age range (mean), yearsDesign/blindingType of controlInterventionResultsAssessment of the treatmentAdverse events (AE)Engberg (2009) [USA] (20)9 (4/5)44–66 (54.8)Parallel/SBSham acupunctureAcupuncturePercentage reduction of all daytime accidentat 1 week: 63.30% vs. 18.88% NSat 4 week: 67.47% vs. 16.67% NSUrge accidentsat 1 week: 74.61 vs. 16.67 NSat 4 week: 75.2 vs. 24.92 NS7-day bladder diary (MOS SF-36)IIQ and UDINo serious AEDrowsy (P=0.05)Minor bleeding site (P=0.05)Kelleher (1994) [England] (8)39 (20/19)24–72 (51.2)Parallel/openOxybutynin 5 mg twice dailyAcupunctureChange in symptom visual analogue scores: Urge incontinence: NSBladder diarySymptom questionnaireVAS, PAISUrodynamic assessmentLight headacheDiscomfort due to insertion of needlesEmmons (2005) [USA] (21)74 (38/36)22–82 (53)Parallel/SBPlacebo acupuncture (relaxation points)AcupuncturePercentage change in incontinence: 59% vs. 40% NSIIQ and UDI3-day voiding diaryCystometric testNo significant AE.23% bleeding, bruising.25% minor discomfort with needle placementChang (2011) [Hong Kong] (22)81 (27/27/27)18–60 (49.57)Parallel/SBSham group: Sham acupressure + pelvic floor muscle trainingControl group: Pelvic floor of muscle trainingAcupressureSelf-reported severity of urine leakage and number of urine leakage episodes: between 3 groups: NSSelf-reported severity urine leakage: intervention vs. control group: statistically significant difference (U=−2.06, P=0.04)Self-reported severity of urine leakage: intervention vs. sham group: statistically significant difference (U=−2.48, p=0.01)Number of urine leakages: NSPerineometry4-day frequency volume chart, 4-point scalePad test, CKHQNo serious AEyr, year of publication; ref, reference number; N, number of participants; T, number of treatment group participants; C, number of control group participants; SB, single blind; NS, not significant; MOS SF-36, medical outcomes short-form; IIQ and UDI, incontinence impact questionnaire and urogenital distress inventory; VAS, visual analog scale; PAIS, psychosocial adjustment to illness scale; CKHQ, Chinese version of the King’s health questionnaire.
