<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://www.biomedcentral.com/xml/article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Musculoskelet Disord</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Musculoskelet Disord</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2474</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3441769</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2474-13-68</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22574814</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-13-68</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Principles of brain plasticity in improving sensorimotor function of the knee and leg in patients with anterior cruciate ligament injury: a double-blind randomized exploratory trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>eva.ageberg@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>Anders</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>anders.bjorkman@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>Birgitta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>birgitta.rosen@med.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>Ewa M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>eroos@health.sdu.dk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Orthopedics, Clinical Sciences Lund, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Health Sciences, Lund University, PO Box 157,, SE-221 00, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Hand Surgery, Clinical Sciences Malm&#x000f6;, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Research Unit for Musculoskeletal Function and Physiotherapy, Institute of Sports Science and Clinical Biomechanics, University of Southern Denmark, Odense, Denmark</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2012 Ageberg et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ageberg et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2474/13/68"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Severe traumatic knee injury, including injury to the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL), leads to impaired sensorimotor function. Although improvements are achieved by training, impairment often persists. Because good sensorimotor function is associated with better patient-reported function and a potential lower risk of future joint problems, more effective treatment is warranted. Temporary cutaneous anesthesia of adjacent body parts was successfully used on the hand and foot to improve sensorimotor function. The aim of this study was to test whether this principle of brain plasticity could be used on the knee. The hypothesis was that temporary anesthesia of the skin area above and below the knee would improve sensorimotor function of the ipsilateral knee and leg in subjects with ACL injury.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>In this double-blind exploratory study, 39 subjects with ACL injury (mean age 24&#x02009;years, SD 5.2, 49% women, mean 52&#x02009;weeks after injury or reconstruction) and self-reported functional limitations and lack of trust in the knee were randomized to temporary local cutaneous application of anesthetic (EMLA&#x000ae;) (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20) or placebo cream (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19). Fifty grams of EMLA&#x000ae;, or placebo, was applied on the leg 10&#x02009;cm above and 10&#x02009;cm below the center of patella, leaving the area around the knee without cream. Measures of sensory function (perception of touch, vibration sense, knee kinesthesia) and motor function (knee muscle strength, hop test) were assessed before and after 90 minutes of treatment with EMLA&#x000ae; or placebo. The paired t-test was used for comparisons within groups and analysis of variance between groups, except for ordinal data where the Wilcoxon signed rank test, or Mann&#x02013;Whitney test, was used. The number of subjects needed was determined by an a priori sample size calculation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>No statistically significant or clinically relevant differences were seen over time (before vs. after) in the measures of sensory or motor functions in the EMLA&#x000ae; group or in the placebo group. There were no differences between the groups due to treatment effect (EMLA&#x000ae; vs. placebo).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Temporary cutaneous anesthesia of adjacent body parts had no effect in improving sensorimotor function of the knee and leg in subjects with severe traumatic knee ligament injury.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Severe traumatic knee injury, including injury to the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL), leads to impaired sensorimotor function. This is observed as, for example, proprioceptive deficiency, and reduced muscle strength and functional performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Although improvements are achieved by training interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], impairment often persists despite such treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Also, the achieved improvements are evident in measures of motor function (muscle strength, functional performance), but the possible influence of training on sensory function (proprioceptive acuity) remains uncertain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The importance of sensorimotor function is reflected by its association with the patient&#x02019;s perceived knee-related function and quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], and its potential protective role for detrimental long-term consequences, such as osteoarthritis (OA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. From this perspective, treatment resulting in improved sensorimotor function would be of value for patients with knee injury and OA in the short and long term.</p><p>The primary motor (M1) and sensory (S1) cortex is organized somatotopically, where different body parts project to different parts of the M1 and S1. The somatotopic map does not represent the body in its actual proportions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Instead, larger cortical areas are being assigned to sensitive parts or parts with complex motor demands such as the hands and face [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. It is well known from animal and human experiments that temporary cutaneous anesthesia of one body part leads to cortical re-organization resulting in a corresponding silent area in the sensory cortex. This allows adjacent nearby body parts in the primary somatosensory cortex to rapidly expand at the expense of the silent cortical area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. This phenomenon, i.e., the manner in which the nervous system can modify its organization and ultimately its function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], is often referred to as brain plasticity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>The ability of the central nervous systems (CNS) to change can also be used for therapeutic purposes, i.e., targeted plasticity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] where weakened or lost functions can be strengthened. In healthy persons as well as in patients with median or ulnar nerve injuries, cutaneous anesthesia of the forearm has been shown to rapidly improve sensory function in the hand. The principle of temporary cutaneous anesthesia of adjacent body parts in combination with training was more effective in improving sensory function of the hand than training only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The rapid improvement of sensory function and the enhanced effects 4&#x02009;weeks after the last local anesthesia treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], indicates that this intervention is clinically useful and relevant. Hypothetically, this principle could also be used to improve sensorimotor function of the knee. The ACL-injured knee may constitute a suitable model for this approach, because this peripheral musculoskeletal injury may also be regarded as a neurophysiological dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. An advantage is that the selective cutaneous anesthesia does not affect motor function of the leg, which means that the individual can use the leg during training while the skin is anesthetized.</p><p>In this study, we hypothesized that temporary anesthesia of the skin area above and below the knee would improve sensorimotor function of the ipsilateral knee and leg in subjects with severe traumatic knee ligament injury and self-reported functional limitations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Subjects and randomization</title><p>Thirty-nine (19 women) subjects with ACL injury were included in this exploratory double-blind RCT. Inclusion criteria were: i) 18 to 35&#x02009;years, ii) ongoing post-injury/post-surgery training, iii)&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;10&#x02009;weeks after ACL injury, or&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;16&#x02009;weeks after ACL reconstruction, iv) ability to perform a single-limb hop, v) self-reported functional limitations. Functional limitations were determined as knee-related problems in physical function and/or quality of life in at least 2 of 4 questions in the Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) as follows: 1) at least moderate difficulty in jumping (subscale sport and recreation function, question 3); 2) at least moderate difficulty in twisting/pivoting on the injured knee (subscale sport and recreation function, question 4); 3) at least moderate trouble with lack of confidence in the knee (subscale quality of life, question 3); 4) at least moderate difficulty with the knee in general (subscale quality of life, question 4). Exclusion criteria were a history of other major orthopedic lesions, such as previous knee injury or fracture, and allergic reactions to anesthetic agents. The patients were enrolled at a sports physical therapy clinic by the test leader. They all had neuromuscular training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], supervised by either of eight physical therapists at this clinic. Subject characteristics, including activity level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] and self-reported outcomes assessed by the Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], are given in Table&#x02009;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th colspan="2" align="left"><bold>Characteristic</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>EMLA group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Placebo group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Age (y)*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">25 (5.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">23 (4.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Women (n)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">BMI*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">23.7 (3.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">24.3 (2.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">ACL injury (ACL reconstruction) (n)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6 (14)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9 (10)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Time after ACL injury or ACL reconstruction (weeks)<sup>&#x02021;</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">54 (17&#x02013;315)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">48 (10&#x02013;243)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Previous contralateral ACL injury/reconstruction (n)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Tegner activity level<sup>&#x02020;</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2 (2&#x02013;4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4 (2&#x02013;6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">KOOS subscales*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02002;Pain<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">82 (10.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">78 (12.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02002;Symptoms<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">74 (12.0)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">72 (14.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02002;ADL<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">90 (8.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">90 (10.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02002;Sport/Rec<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">47 (20.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">47 (24.7)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02002;QOL</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">41 (12.4)</td><td align="center">40 (10.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* Mean (SD), &#x02020; median (quartiles), <sup>&#x02021;</sup> mean (range), BMI; body mass index.</p><p>ACL reconstruction: hamstring tendons graft, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;23, patellar tendon graft, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.</p><p>The Tegner Activity Scale, ranges from 0 to 10, least to hardest strenuous activity for the knee. A Tegner activity level of 2 is equal to recreational sports such as golf, cycling and swimming, an activity level of 4 is equal to recreational sports such as jogging, aerobics, or cross-country skiing and a Tegner activity level of 6 is equal to recreational sports such as tennis or badminton and competitive sports such as orienteering.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The subjects were randomly allocated, using a random number generator, to temporary anesthesia using a local anesthetic cream, EMLA&#x000ae;, (EMLA&#x000ae; group) or a placebo cream (oil and water emulsion) (placebo group). To ensure an equal number of men and women in each group two computer-generated randomization lists, one for women and one for men, were drawn up by a biostatistician and given to the assessor. The assessor allocated the next available number on entry into the trial, assigning the subjects to treatment/placebo. The Research Ethics committee of Lund University approved the study (LU 107/2007), and all subjects gave their written informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Protocol and masking</title><p>Twenty subjects received a local anesthetic cream containing 2.5% lidocaine and 2.5% prilocaine (EMLA&#x000ae;, AstraZeneca, S&#x000f6;dert&#x000e4;lje, Sweden) and 19 subjects received a placebo cream of an oil and water emulsion (DAX, Opus Health Care Inc., Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden). The two creams were identical in color, consistency and packaging. A staff member, not participating as an assessor or subject in the study, distributed the packages with cream to the assessor. Fifty grams of EMLA&#x000ae;, or placebo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], was applied circumferentially on the leg 10&#x02009;cm above and 10&#x02009;cm below the center of patella, leaving the area around the knee without cream (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The skin areas where the EMLA&#x000ae;/placebo was applied were covered with film wrap and a Tubigrip&#x000ae; stocking (MEDLOCK Medical, Oldham, UK). After 90 minutes, during which time the subject was seated, the EMLA&#x000ae;/placebo was carefully washed off. The test leader and the subjects were blinded to group allocation, and the subjects were told not to reveal any possible anesthetic sensation. Therefore, the presence or absence of anesthesia in the area where the EMLA&#x000ae;/placebo was applied was not verified by the assessor or the subject. The success of blinding related to cream was not evaluated.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1 </label><caption><p><bold>Application of local anesthetic or placebo cream.</bold> EMLA, or placebo, applied on the leg 10&#x02009;cm above and 10&#x02009;cm below the center of patella, leaving the area around the knee without cream.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2474-13-68-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Outcome measures</title><p>Measures of sensory and motor functions were assessed before and after 90 minutes of treatment with EMLA&#x000ae; or placebo according to the protocol of our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The tests were performed in the order that they are described below. EMLA&#x000ae;/placebo was applied and all tests were performed on the injured leg only (in those four with a previous contralateral knee injury, the recently injured leg was tested). An experienced assessor, who received explicit guidelines and thorough training and pilot-testing prior to study start, performed the measurements.</p><sec><title>Measures of sensory function</title><p>Three measures of sensory function were used; perception of touch, vibration sense and knee kinesthesia. Lower values in these tests indicate better sensory function.</p><sec><title>Perception of touch</title><p>Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments (SWM) were used for assessing perception of touch at the most prominent point of the medial and lateral femoral condyles, just proximal of the joint space (areas where no cream was applied). In our previous study, one site (the medial femoral condyle) was assessed only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Because a ceiling effect was found in that study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], two sites were included in the current study. Prior to the test, the SWM (nr 4.31, 2.0&#x02009;g) was demonstrated on the patient&#x02019;s styloid process of the hand, so that the subjects could familiarize themselves with the test. Thereafter, the subjects lay in a supine position and were asked to close their eyes, concentrate on their knee and respond when they felt any sensation of touch. The assessment was performed according to a standardized procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Each monofilament, starting with the thinnest and continuing with thicker until response to sensation, was applied perpendicular to the skin for 1.5 seconds and lifted for 1.5 seconds. The filament was applied 3 times to the same spot and was bent each time to exert the specific pressure. Feeling the monofilament was recorded when at least one out of three applications was identified by the patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Vibratory perception threshold</title><p>Vibratory perception threshold (VPT) was assessed by a biothesiometer (Bio-Medical Instrument, Newbury, OH, USA), as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Prior to the test, the Biothesiometer was demonstrated on the patient&#x02019;s ulna styloid process, so that the subjects could familiarize themselves with the test. Thereafter, the subjects lay in a supine position and were asked to close their eyes, concentrate on their foot/knee and respond when they felt any sensation of vibration. The biothesiometer tip was held with uniform pressure at two sites: the most prominent point of the medial malleolus and the medial femoral condyle (same location as that for testing perception of touch). Three consecutive measurements were taken on each site, and the amplitude was replaced to zero between each measurement without moving the biothesiometer tip from the location. The amplitude was increased by 1 Volt per second until the subjects responded to a sensation of vibration. This was noted as the VPT. The first measurement was regarded a trial test, and was, thus, excluded from the analysis. If the difference between the second and third measurement was more than 20%, 2 additional tests were taken. The mean of the second and third, or fourth and fifth, measurements was used in the analysis. High reliability has been reported for the biothesiometer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Vibration data for the patients and controls was reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Knee kinesthesia</title><p>Kinesthesia was measured in a specifically designed apparatus, which has been used and described in detail in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. The subjects lay in a lateral decubitus position, were asked to close their eyes, concentrate on their knee and respond when they felt any sensation of movement in their knee. Measurements of the threshold for detection of passive motion (TDPM) were performed towards knee extension (TE) and knee flexion (TF) from the starting position of 20&#x000b0; knee joint flexion, giving the variables TE20 and TF20. The median values of three consecutive measurements of these two variables were determined. The variables from the 20&#x000b0; starting position (TE20 and TF20) have been found to be reliable in uninjured subjects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. The sum of TE20 and TF20, giving an index value, was used for statistical analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Measures of motor function</title><p>Two measures of motor function were used; the one-leg hop test for distance and knee extensor muscle power. Higher values in these tests indicate better motor function.</p><sec><title>One-leg hop test for distance</title><p>The one-leg hop test for distance with the arms free, aiming at a more functional execution of the hop, was used. The one-leg hop test is widely used for predicting functional knee stability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Muscle strength, balance and confidence in the knee are contributing factors to the performance of this test. The subjects were told to hop as far as possible, taking off and landing on the same foot, maintaining their balance for about 2&#x02013;3 seconds. The test was performed three times, the hop distance being measured (in cm) from toe in the starting position to heel in the landing position. If the subject improved more than 10&#x02009;cm between the second and third hop, additional hops were performed until an increase of less than 10&#x02009;cm was measured. A trial one-leg hop preceded the measurements. The subjects wore shoes, e.g., sneakers. The mean value of the three best hops was used in the analysis. The reliability of this test is high in subjects with ACL injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Knee extension power</title><p>The muscle strength test was performed as described, with standardized verbal instructions and encouragement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The subject was seated, using an individual seating position, in a knee extension weight training machine (Precor, Icarian, Bor&#x000e5;s, Sweden). The test was performed with the injured leg, and the other leg was fixed in place using a strap. Before the strength test, the subjects completed ten repetitions at a sub-maximum weight, followed by five repetitions using a somewhat higher sub-maximum weight. The subject then performed a single repetition, of approximately 90% of their maximum, to select the appropriate starting weight.</p><p>On a given signal, the subject was asked to extend his/her knee as quickly and forcefully as possible from approximately 110<sup>o</sup> of knee flexion to full knee extension (0<sup>o</sup> of flexion). The distance the weight stack was lifted and the time it took to fully extend the knee was measured with a linear encoder connected to the weight stack of the machine. In all, the subjects performed five maximum trials at five weight levels, until a decrease in power was seen. The weight was increased by 5&#x02009;kg for each trial. The rest period between trials was 30&#x02009;s, which was considered to be sufficient for full recovery. The average power was calculated by Muscle Lab, a computerised muscle function measuring system (Ergotest Technology, Oslo, Norway). If a subject reported pain in the knee during a test, which occurred in a few cases, this particular test was cancelled and the measurement was repeated. Data was missing for 2 patients (1 patient did not perform the test because of knee pain, and too few accurate values to calculate average power for 1 patient). Average power (W) was used in the analysis.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The number of subjects needed was determined by an a priori sample size calculation from our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. No primary outcome measure was determined, since the study has an exploratory character. We expected to find an improvement in more than one of the variables to interpret the results as an effect from treatment. For knee kinesthesia, sample size calculations revealed that at least 12 subjects were needed to detect an improvement by treatment of 30% within groups (SD<sub>diff</sub> 0.49), with 80% power at the 5% significance level. For vibration sense, 13 subjects were needed to detect an improvement of 20% (SD<sub>diff</sub> 3.3) within groups. For the one-leg hop test, and knee extension power, less than 10 subjects were needed to detect an improvement by treatment of 10% within groups, with 80% power at the 5% significance level. Based on these sample-size calculations, we included 40 subjects. The paired t-test was used for comparisons within groups and analysis of variance, adjusting the variables for activity level, between groups. All variables had Shapiro-Wilk statistic of &#x0003e;0.90, except knee kinesthesia and VPT at the medial malleolus. Because some variables were not normally distributed, the results were confirmed using non-parametric statistics. Wilcoxon signed rank test, or Mann&#x02013;Whitney test, was used for ordinal data (perception of touch). Effect size was calculated by taking the difference between the means before and after EMLA&#x000ae;/placebo and dividing it by the SD of the same measure before EMLA&#x000ae;/placebo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. An effect size of &#x0003c;0.50 was considered small, 0.50 to 0.79 moderate, and &#x02265;0.80 large [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. A level of <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 was chosen to indicate statistical significance. Group allocation was concealed to the person analyzing the data, until the results were completed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>There were no differences between the groups due to treatment effect (EMLA&#x000ae; vs. placebo) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). No statistically significant or clinically relevant differences were seen over time (before vs. after) in the measures of sensory or motor functions in the EMLA&#x000ae; group or in the placebo group.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Results for outcomes of sensory and motor functions in the EMLA and placebo groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>EMLA group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Placebo group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19)</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>EMLA vs. placebo</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Before</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>After</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Before</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>After</bold><hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center"><bold>Mean (SE)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Mean (SE)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Mean diff (95% CI)</bold>(after minus before)</th><th align="center"><bold>Mean (SE)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Mean (SE)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Mean diff (95% CI)</bold>(after minus before)</th><th align="center"><bold>Mean diff (95% CI)</bold>(EMLA minus placebo)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Sensory function</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">SWM med fem cond (grams)&#x02020;*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.02 (0.008:0.02)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.008 (0.008:0.02)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.430<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.008 (0.008:0.02)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.008 (0.008:0.04)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.134<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.276<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">SWM lat fem cond (grams)&#x02020;*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.008 (0.008:0.02)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.008 (0.008:0.02)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.442<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.008 (0.008:0.04)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.008 (0.008:0.03)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.505<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.951<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">VPT med mall (Volt)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9.2(0.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10.3(0.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1.1(0.4:1.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9.7(0.60)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10.2(0.68)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.5(&#x02212;0.1:1.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.6(&#x02212;0.4:1.5)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">VPT med fem cond (Volt)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15.5(1.27)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15.1(1.51)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x02212;0.4(&#x02212;1.9:1.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">16.0(1.20)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15.5(1.22)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x02212;0.6(&#x02212;2.4:1.3)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.0(&#x02212;2.4:2.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">TDPM (degrees)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.69(0.33)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.52(0.27)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x02212;0.16(&#x02212;0.73:0.41)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.74(0.37)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.84(0.54)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.11(&#x02212;1.0:1.27)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x02212;0.28(&#x02212;1.57:1.01)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Motor function</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">One-leg hop (cm)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">79.2(12.4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">83.3(7.61)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4.0(&#x02212;0.1:8.2)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">90.6(9.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">100.0(9.7)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9.5(3.6:15.3)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x02212;6.4(&#x02212;13.4:0.6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Knee ext power (W)*</td><td align="center">130.0(12.4)</td><td align="center">139.5(14.0)</td><td align="center">9.5(1.4:17.7)</td><td align="center">156.9(15.4)</td><td align="center">158.3(15.5)</td><td align="center">1.5(&#x02212;8.1:11.0)</td><td align="center">6.9(&#x02212;5.5:19.4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SWM</italic> Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments, <italic>VPT</italic> vibration perception threshold, <italic>Med mall</italic> medial malleolus, <italic>Med fem cond</italic> medial femoral condyle, <italic>Lat fem cond</italic> lateral femoral condyle, <italic>TDPM</italic> threshold for detection of passive motion, <italic>ext</italic> extension.</p><p>&#x02020; median (quartiles).</p><p>* Missing data 1 patient for SWM (placebo group) and 2 patients for knee ext power (1 patient in each group).</p><p>Mean and standard error (SE) and mean difference (95% CI) (after minus before) for the tests of sensory function (perception of touch, vibration sense, kinesthesia) and motor function (one-leg hop test, knee extension power) before and after treatment with EMLA/placebo, and mean difference (95% CI) (EMLA minus placebo) between the EMLA and placebo groups (t-test). Median (quartiles) and p-value (Wilcoxon singed rank test, Mann&#x02013;Whitney test) given for perception of touch (ordinal data).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title><bold>Sensory function before and after treatment with EMLA</bold>&#x000ae; <bold>or placebo</bold></title><p>There were no differences between the groups in effects of treatment for the measures of sensory function (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The effect sizes were generally small in the EMLA&#x000ae; group (between 0.08 and 0.44) and in the placebo group (between 0.07 and 0.19, except for perception of touch at the medial femoral condyle; effect size 0.78). No differences were found before vs. after treatment for perception of touch, vibration sense at the medial femoral condyle, or TDPM in the EMLA&#x000ae; group. A higher VPT at the medial malleolus, indicating poorer vibration sense, was found after compared with before treatment. No differences were found between assessments (before vs. after) for perception of touch, vibration sense, or kinesthesia in the placebo group (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Motor function before and after treatment with EMLA&#x000ae; or placebo</title><p>There were no differences between the groups in effects of treatment for the measures of motor function (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The effect sizes were small in the EMLA&#x000ae; group (one-leg hop test 0.11, knee extension power 0.18) and in the placebo group (one-leg hop test 0.22, knee extension power 0.02). The patients in the EMLA&#x000ae; group had higher knee extension power, and the patients in the placebo group jumped a longer distance, after compared with before treatment (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The hypothesis of this exploratory RCT on principles of brain plasticity in improving sensorimotor function of the knee in subjects with severe traumatic knee ligament injury was not confirmed. No effect was found of temporary cutaneous anesthesia of the skin area above and below the knee on sensorimotor function of the ipsilateral knee and leg in these subjects.</p><p>The forearm is located next to the hand in the somatotopic map [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and by anaesthetizing the forearm, the cortical hand area can expand over the forearm area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Thus, more nerve cells can be available for the hand, resulting in improved hand function. This principle has been successfully used in subjects with or without hand nerve injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], and was recently also efficiently applied to the foot in subjects with or without diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><p>Diminished activation in several sensorimotor cortical areas has been observed in subjects with ACL injury compared with controls, indicating that the injury causes re-organization of the central nervous system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Conversely, it may be assumed that cortical re-organization can be achieved by an efficient intervention. By assessing sensory function in the knee, we indirectly assessed a possible cortical re-organization. An improved sensory function, as found in the hands following forearm anesthesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], would indicate a cortical re-organization with an expanded cortical knee area in subjects with anesthetized leg areas. Although no such changes were seen, this does not completely rule out cortical changes following treatment. However, if cortical changes did occur they were likely very subtle. This, in combination with the fact that the knee normally has a very small representation in the somatosensory cortex, makes is difficult or perhaps even impossible in this case to detect changes in the cortical knee area using neuroimaging methods such as fMRI. With this in mind, and because no effects were found in the sensorimotor function tests in the present study or in a previous study in healthy subjects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], we decided not to perform fMRI because the likelihood of finding an cortical expansion-difference would be small.</p><p>Neurophysiologic mechanisms in the lower extremity may also differ from those in the upper extremity. Large overlaps in the sensorimotor activation have been shown following movement of the knee, ankle and toes as opposed to the fingers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. However, the same plasticity mechanisms likely occur in both the upper and lower extremity, thus making it possible to manipulate plasticity mechanisms also in the lower extremity in order to improve sensorimotor function, such as that reported for the foot [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><p>Because this was an RCT with a blinded design, that is, both the assessor and the subject were blinded to group allocation, numbness in the area where the EMLA&#x000ae;/placebo was applied (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) was not verified. However, the amount of EMLA&#x000ae; used (50&#x02009;g) is a dosage of active substance per cm<sup>2</sup> well within the recommendations to achieve cutaneous anesthesia.</p><p>The placing of the cream (above and below the knee) is most likely adequate in order to expect an increased cortical knee representation. Because the cortical area devoted to the lower extremity is small compared to the hand, we expected that a larger deafferented skin area was needed (compared to the upper extremity) in order to allow the knee to expand in the primary somatosensory and motor cortex. Therefore, the EMLA&#x000ae; or placebo was applied circumferentially on the skin both above and below the knee.</p><p>The effect sizes were generally small for all outcome measures, indicating that the magnitude of change by treatment was small. In previous studies on the hand and foot, focus was on assessing improvements of temporary anesthesia in sensory function (perception of touch, vibration sense) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], as these measures are relevant to the patient&#x02019;s daily activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Because we applied this concept to the knee, these sensory measures were included also in the present study. The perception of touch of the knee is not as delicate, discriminative or vital as in the hand or the foot sole. Therefore, the relevance of this measure for patients with knee injury, as used in the present study, may be questioned. The first study evaluating vibration sense in patients with ACL injury was recently reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Vibration perception threshold was not impaired in these patients compared with matched controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Perhaps a ceiling effect was present, limiting the chance of improving perception of touch and/or vibration sense in these patients by intervention using temporary anesthesia.</p><p>Several studies have shown a deficiency in proprioceptive acuity (kinesthesia, joint position sense) in patients with ACL injury; recently reported in a review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. While measures of motor function (muscle strength, functional performance) appear relevant for patients with knee injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], the association between sensory function (proprioceptive acuity) and patient-reported and motor functions is generally low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. For this reason, the development of more accurate and precise methods for assessing sensory function was proposed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. Possibly, measures of motor function may be more essential for activities of daily life and more demanding activities than measures of sensory function for subjects with knee injury. However, the possibilities of affecting motor outcomes by temporary anesthesia may be more difficult to achieve than for sensory outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><p>The major strength of the current and previous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] studies is the design; the subjects were randomized to anesthetic or placebo cream, the test leader was blinded to group allocation, and group allocation was concealed to the person analyzing the data until the results were completed. However, from the results of the present and previous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] studies, temporary cutaneous anesthesia was not a successful intervention to improve sensorimotor function for patients with severe traumatic knee ligament injury. The need for development and evaluation of methods to improve the effects of treatment on sensorimotor function after knee injury and knee OA remains.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The principle of temporary cutaneous anesthesia of adjacent body parts had no effect in improving sensorimotor function of the knee and leg in subjects with severe traumatic knee ligament injury.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>EA contributed to the design of the study, was responsible for acquisition, analysis and interpretation of data, and drafted the manuscript. AB and BR contributed to the design of the study and critically revised the manuscript. ER contributed to the design of the study, participated in analysis and interpretation of data, and critically revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final version.</p></sec><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2474/13/68/prepub">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2474/13/68/prepub</ext-link></p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the physical therapists at &#x0201c;Idrottsh&#x000e4;lsan&#x0201d; in Lund, Sweden, for providing the patients for this study. Grant supporters: The Swedish Research Council, and the Faculty of Medicine, Lund University.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Consequences of a ligament injury on neuromuscular function and relevance to rehabilitation-using the anterior cruciate ligament-injured knee as model</article-title><source>J Electromyogr Kinesiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1050-6411(02)00022-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12086815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12086815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Risberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Myklebust</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Engebretsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Neuromuscular training versus strength training during first 6&#x02009;months after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Phys Ther</source><year>2007</year><volume>87</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2522/ptj.20060041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17442840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zech</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Banzer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Neuromuscular training for rehabilitation of sports injuries: a systematic review</article-title><source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source><year>2009</year><volume>41</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1831</fpage><lpage>1841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0b013e3181a3cf0d</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19727032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19727032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Risberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>The long-term effect of 2 postoperative rehabilitation programs after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a randomized controlled clinical trial with 2&#x02009;years of follow-up</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1958</fpage><lpage>1966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546509335196</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19556470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19556470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Neeter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Silbernagel</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><article-title>Muscle strength and functional performance in patients with anterior cruciate ligament injury treated with training and surgical reconstruction or training only: a two to five-year followup</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1773</fpage><lpage>1779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.24066</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19035430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19035430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beynnon</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Naud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brattbakk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><article-title>Accelerated versus nonaccelerated rehabilitation after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a prospective, randomized, double-blind investigation evaluating knee joint laxity using roentgen stereophotogrammetric analysis</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2536</fpage><lpage>2548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546511422349</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21952714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21952714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Silbernagel</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><article-title>Knee extension and flexion muscle power after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction with patellar tendon graft or hamstring tendons graft: a cross-sectional comparison 3&#x02009;years post surgery</article-title><source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source><year>2009</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00167-008-0645-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18982311?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18982311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trulsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garwicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Relationships between postural orientation and self reported function, hop performance and muscle power in subjects with anterior cruciate ligament injury</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>143</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-11-143</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20594339?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20594339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eitzen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Risberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Preoperative quadriceps strength is a significant predictor of knee function two years after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction</article-title><source>Br J Sports Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsm.2008.057059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19224907?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19224907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><article-title>Joint injury causes knee osteoarthritis in young adults</article-title><source>Curr Opin Rheumatol</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.bor.0000151406.64393.00</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15711235?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15711235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pinczewski</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Linklater</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>A 10-year comparison of anterior cruciate ligament reconstructions with hamstring tendon and patellar tendon autograft: a controlled, prospective trial</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546506296042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17261567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17261567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennell</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><article-title>Muscle weakness, afferent sensory dysfunction and exercise in knee osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Rheumatol</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrrheum.2010.195</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21119605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21119605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Boldrey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Somatic motor and sensory representations in the cerebral cortex of man as studied by electrical stimulation</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>1937</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/60.4.389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><source>The Cerebral Cortex of Man: A Clinical Study of Localization of Function</source><year>1950</year><publisher-name>Macmillan, New York</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maldjian</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Detre</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsop</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><article-title>The sensory somatotopic map of the human hand demonstrated at 4 Tesla</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.1999.0448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10385581?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10385581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stippich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapfer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Somatotopic mapping of the human primary somatosensory cortex by fully automated tactile stimulation using functional magnetic resonance imaging</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>277</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(99)00835-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10643889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10643889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Nervous system reorganization following injury</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2002</year><volume>111</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(02)00025-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12031403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12031403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><article-title>Human brain plasticity: an emerging view of the multiple substrates and mechanisms that cause cortical changes and related sensory dysfunctions after injuries of sensory inputs from the body</article-title><source>Brain Res Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>39</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12423766?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12423766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaas</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><article-title>Plasticity of sensory and motor maps in adult mammals</article-title><source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source><year>1991</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ne.14.030191.001033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2031570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2031570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Bloedel J, Ebner T, Wise S</person-group><article-title>Motor cortical substrates and mechanisms for learning</article-title><source>Acquisition of Motor Behaviour in Vertebrates</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>MIT, Cambridge</publisher-name><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>386</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><source>Principles of Neural Science. 4th edition. New York: McGraw-Hill</source><year>2000</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Purves</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>La Mantia</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name><name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Sinauer Associates Inc, Sunderland</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duffau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Brain plasticity: from pathophysiological mechanisms to therapeutic applications</article-title><source>J Clin Neurosci</source><year>2006</year><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocn.2005.11.045</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17049865?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17049865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Improved sensory relearning after nerve repair induced by selective temporary anaesthesia - a new concept in hand rehabilitation</article-title><source>J Hand Surg [Br]</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsb.2005.10.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hassan-Zadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lajevardi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Esfahani</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Improvement of hand sensibility after selective temporary anaesthesia in combination with sensory re-education</article-title><source>NeuroRehabilitation</source><year>2009</year><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19597277?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Enhanced sensory relearning after nerve repair by using repeated forearm anaesthesia: aspects on time dynamics of treatment</article-title><source>Acta Neurochir Suppl</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-211-72958-8_26</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17985560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17985560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kapreli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanasopoulos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Papathanasiou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Hecke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Keleki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Strimpakos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunaert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Lower limb sensorimotor network: issues of somatotopy and overlap</article-title><source>Cortex</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0010-9452(08)70477-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17405668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17405668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kapreli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanasopoulos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gliatis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Papathanasiou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Strimpakos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Hecke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouliamos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunaert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Anterior cruciate ligament deficiency causes brain plasticity: a functional MRI study</article-title><source>Am J Sports Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2419</fpage><lpage>2426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546509343201</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19940314?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19940314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Z&#x000e4;tterstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Frid&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>Early rehabilitation of acute anterior cruciate ligament injury-a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Scand J Med Sci Sports</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9659676?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9659676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tegner</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lysholm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Rating systems in the evaluation of knee ligament injuries</article-title><source>Clin Orthop</source><year>1985</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><?supplied-pmid 4028566?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4028566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekdahl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><article-title>Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)&#x02013;validation of a Swedish version</article-title><source>Scand J Med Sci Sports</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9863983?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9863983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekdahl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Beynnon</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><article-title>Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)&#x02013;development of a self-administered outcome measure</article-title><source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source><year>1998</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9699158?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9699158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weibull</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Improved sensibility of the foot after temporary cutaneous anesthesia of the lower leg</article-title><source>Neuroreport</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WNR.0b013e32831b4486</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19033877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><article-title>Principles of brain plasticity in improving sensorimotor function of the knee and leg in healthy subjects: a double-blind randomized exploratory trial</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-10-99</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19656355?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19656355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><source>(ASHT) ASoHT</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.asht.org">www.asht.org</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frenette</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mergler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferraris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Measurement precision of a portable instrument to assess vibrotactile perception threshold</article-title><source>Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>61</volume><issue>5&#x02013;6</issue><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2079057?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2079057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shakoor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><article-title>Reduced lower extremity vibratory perception in osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.23241</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18163397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18163397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thorlund</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakoor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandal</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><article-title>Vibratory perception threshold in young and middle-aged patients at high risk of knee osteoarthritis compared to controls.</article-title><source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source><year>2011</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21905255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frid&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Z&#x000e4;tterstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>Proprioception in the nearly extended knee. Measurements of position and movement in healthy individuals and in symptomatic anterior cruciate ligament injured patients</article-title><source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source><year>1996</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01567966</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9046506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9046506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Frid&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stomberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>Bilateral proprioceptive defects in patients with a unilateral anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a comparison between patients and healthy individuals</article-title><source>J Orthop Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.1100180408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11052492?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11052492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Flenhagen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Test-retest reliability of knee kinesthesia in healthy adults</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>57</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-8-57</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17608920?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17608920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Risberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder-Mackler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>A systematic review of evidence for anterior cruciate ligament rehabilitation: how much and what type?</article-title><source>Physical Therapy in Sport</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ptsp.2004.02.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paterno</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberger</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><article-title>The test-retest reliability of a one legged hop for distance in young adults with and without ACL reconstruction</article-title><source>Isokin Ex Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neeter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Development of a strength test battery for evaluating leg muscle power after anterior cruciate ligament injury and reconstruction</article-title><source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source><year>2006</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00167-006-0040-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16477472?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16477472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kazis</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meenan</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><article-title>Effect sizes for interpreting changes in health status</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>1989</year><volume>27</volume><issue>3 Suppl</issue><fpage>S178</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2646488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2646488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weibull</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Rapid cortical reorganisation and improved sensitivity of the hand following cutaneous anaesthesia of the forearm</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2009.06629.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19250441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19250441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Acute improvement of hand sensibility after selective ipsilateral cutaneous forearm anaesthesia</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2733</fpage><lpage>2736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2004.03742.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15548216?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15548216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lundborg</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlin</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><article-title>Cutaneous anaesthesia of the lower leg can improve sensibility in the diabetic foot. A double-blind, randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>Diabet Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1464-5491.2010.03014.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20636964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20636964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gokeler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjaminse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewett</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lephart</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Engebretsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ageberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Postema</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Otten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Proprioceptive deficits after ACL injury: are they clinically relevant?</article-title><source>Br J Sports Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21511738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21511738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>