<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC Musculoskelet DisordBMC Musculoskelet DisordBMC Musculoskeletal Disorders1471-2474BioMed Central34417691471-2474-13-682257481410.1186/1471-2474-13-68Research ArticlePrinciples of brain plasticity in improving sensorimotor function of the knee and leg in patients with anterior cruciate ligament injury: a double-blind randomized exploratory trialAgebergEva12eva.ageberg@med.lu.seBjörkmanAnders3anders.bjorkman@med.lu.seRosénBirgitta3birgitta.rosen@med.lu.seRoosEwa M4eroos@health.sdu.dk1Department of Orthopedics, Clinical Sciences Lund, Lund University, Lund, Sweden2Department of Health Sciences, Lund University, PO Box 157,, SE-221 00, Lund, Sweden3Department of Hand Surgery, Clinical Sciences Malmö, Lund University, Lund, Sweden4Research Unit for Musculoskeletal Function and Physiotherapy, Institute of Sports Science and Clinical Biomechanics, University of Southern Denmark, Odense, Denmark20121052012136868131020111332012Copyright © 2012 Ageberg et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.2012Ageberg et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.BackgroundSevere traumatic knee injury, including injury to the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL), leads to impaired sensorimotor function. Although improvements are achieved by training, impairment often persists. Because good sensorimotor function is associated with better patient-reported function and a potential lower risk of future joint problems, more effective treatment is warranted. Temporary cutaneous anesthesia of adjacent body parts was successfully used on the hand and foot to improve sensorimotor function. The aim of this study was to test whether this principle of brain plasticity could be used on the knee. The hypothesis was that temporary anesthesia of the skin area above and below the knee would improve sensorimotor function of the ipsilateral knee and leg in subjects with ACL injury.MethodsIn this double-blind exploratory study, 39 subjects with ACL injury (mean age 24 years, SD 5.2, 49% women, mean 52 weeks after injury or reconstruction) and self-reported functional limitations and lack of trust in the knee were randomized to temporary local cutaneous application of anesthetic (EMLA®) (n = 20) or placebo cream (n = 19). Fifty grams of EMLA®, or placebo, was applied on the leg 10 cm above and 10 cm below the center of patella, leaving the area around the knee without cream. Measures of sensory function (perception of touch, vibration sense, knee kinesthesia) and motor function (knee muscle strength, hop test) were assessed before and after 90 minutes of treatment with EMLA® or placebo. The paired t-test was used for comparisons within groups and analysis of variance between groups, except for ordinal data where the Wilcoxon signed rank test, or Mann–Whitney test, was used. The number of subjects needed was determined by an a priori sample size calculation.ResultsNo statistically significant or clinically relevant differences were seen over time (before vs. after) in the measures of sensory or motor functions in the EMLA® group or in the placebo group. There were no differences between the groups due to treatment effect (EMLA® vs. placebo).ConclusionsTemporary cutaneous anesthesia of adjacent body parts had no effect in improving sensorimotor function of the knee and leg in subjects with severe traumatic knee ligament injury.BackgroundSevere traumatic knee injury, including injury to the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL), leads to impaired sensorimotor function. This is observed as, for example, proprioceptive deficiency, and reduced muscle strength and functional performance [1]. Although improvements are achieved by training interventions [2-4], impairment often persists despite such treatment [5]. Also, the achieved improvements are evident in measures of motor function (muscle strength, functional performance), but the possible influence of training on sensory function (proprioceptive acuity) remains uncertain [3,4,6]. The importance of sensorimotor function is reflected by its association with the patient’s perceived knee-related function and quality of life [7-9], and its potential protective role for detrimental long-term consequences, such as osteoarthritis (OA) [10-12]. From this perspective, treatment resulting in improved sensorimotor function would be of value for patients with knee injury and OA in the short and long term.The primary motor (M1) and sensory (S1) cortex is organized somatotopically, where different body parts project to different parts of the M1 and S1. The somatotopic map does not represent the body in its actual proportions [13,14]. Instead, larger cortical areas are being assigned to sensitive parts or parts with complex motor demands such as the hands and face [15,16]. It is well known from animal and human experiments that temporary cutaneous anesthesia of one body part leads to cortical re-organization resulting in a corresponding silent area in the sensory cortex. This allows adjacent nearby body parts in the primary somatosensory cortex to rapidly expand at the expense of the silent cortical area [17,18]. This phenomenon, i.e., the manner in which the nervous system can modify its organization and ultimately its function [19,20], is often referred to as brain plasticity [21,22].The ability of the central nervous systems (CNS) to change can also be used for therapeutic purposes, i.e., targeted plasticity [23] where weakened or lost functions can be strengthened. In healthy persons as well as in patients with median or ulnar nerve injuries, cutaneous anesthesia of the forearm has been shown to rapidly improve sensory function in the hand. The principle of temporary cutaneous anesthesia of adjacent body parts in combination with training was more effective in improving sensory function of the hand than training only [24,25]. The rapid improvement of sensory function and the enhanced effects 4 weeks after the last local anesthesia treatment [24,26], indicates that this intervention is clinically useful and relevant. Hypothetically, this principle could also be used to improve sensorimotor function of the knee. The ACL-injured knee may constitute a suitable model for this approach, because this peripheral musculoskeletal injury may also be regarded as a neurophysiological dysfunction [27,28]. An advantage is that the selective cutaneous anesthesia does not affect motor function of the leg, which means that the individual can use the leg during training while the skin is anesthetized.In this study, we hypothesized that temporary anesthesia of the skin area above and below the knee would improve sensorimotor function of the ipsilateral knee and leg in subjects with severe traumatic knee ligament injury and self-reported functional limitations.<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Subjects and randomization</title><p>Thirty-nine (19 women) subjects with ACL injury were included in this exploratory double-blind RCT. Inclusion criteria were: i) 18 to 35 years, ii) ongoing post-injury/post-surgery training, iii) ≥ 10 weeks after ACL injury, or ≥ 16 weeks after ACL reconstruction, iv) ability to perform a single-limb hop, v) self-reported functional limitations. Functional limitations were determined as knee-related problems in physical function and/or quality of life in at least 2 of 4 questions in the Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) as follows: 1) at least moderate difficulty in jumping (subscale sport and recreation function, question 3); 2) at least moderate difficulty in twisting/pivoting on the injured knee (subscale sport and recreation function, question 4); 3) at least moderate trouble with lack of confidence in the knee (subscale quality of life, question 3); 4) at least moderate difficulty with the knee in general (subscale quality of life, question 4). Exclusion criteria were a history of other major orthopedic lesions, such as previous knee injury or fracture, and allergic reactions to anesthetic agents. The patients were enrolled at a sports physical therapy clinic by the test leader. They all had neuromuscular training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], supervised by either of eight physical therapists at this clinic. Subject characteristics, including activity level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] and self-reported outcomes assessed by the Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th colspan="2" align="left"><bold>Characteristic</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>EMLA group (n = 20)</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Placebo group (n = 19)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Age (y)*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">25 (5.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">23 (4.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Women (n)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">BMI*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">23.7 (3.1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">24.3 (2.9)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">ACL injury (ACL reconstruction) (n)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">6 (14)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9 (10)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Time after ACL injury or ACL reconstruction (weeks)<sup>‡</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">54 (17–315)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">48 (10–243)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Previous contralateral ACL injury/reconstruction (n)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Tegner activity level<sup>†</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2 (2–4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4 (2–6)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">KOOS subscales*<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  Pain<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">82 (10.8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">78 (12.2)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  Symptoms<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">74 (12.0)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">72 (14.3)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  ADL<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">90 (8.6)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">90 (10.4)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">  Sport/Rec<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"> <hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">47 (20.9)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">47 (24.7)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">  QOL</td><td align="left"> </td><td align="center">41 (12.4)</td><td align="center">40 (10.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* Mean (SD), † median (quartiles), <sup>‡</sup> mean (range), BMI; body mass index.</p><p>ACL reconstruction: hamstring tendons graft, n = 23, patellar tendon graft, n = 1.</p><p>The Tegner Activity Scale, ranges from 0 to 10, least to hardest strenuous activity for the knee. A Tegner activity level of 2 is equal to recreational sports such as golf, cycling and swimming, an activity level of 4 is equal to recreational sports such as jogging, aerobics, or cross-country skiing and a Tegner activity level of 6 is equal to recreational sports such as tennis or badminton and competitive sports such as orienteering.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The subjects were randomly allocated, using a random number generator, to temporary anesthesia using a local anesthetic cream, EMLA®, (EMLA® group) or a placebo cream (oil and water emulsion) (placebo group). To ensure an equal number of men and women in each group two computer-generated randomization lists, one for women and one for men, were drawn up by a biostatistician and given to the assessor. The assessor allocated the next available number on entry into the trial, assigning the subjects to treatment/placebo. The Research Ethics committee of Lund University approved the study (LU 107/2007), and all subjects gave their written informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Protocol and masking</title><p>Twenty subjects received a local anesthetic cream containing 2.5% lidocaine and 2.5% prilocaine (EMLA®, AstraZeneca, Södertälje, Sweden) and 19 subjects received a placebo cream of an oil and water emulsion (DAX, Opus Health Care Inc., Malmö, Sweden). The two creams were identical in color, consistency and packaging. A staff member, not participating as an assessor or subject in the study, distributed the packages with cream to the assessor. Fifty grams of EMLA®, or placebo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], was applied circumferentially on the leg 10 cm above and 10 cm below the center of patella, leaving the area around the knee without cream (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The skin areas where the EMLA®/placebo was applied were covered with film wrap and a Tubigrip® stocking (MEDLOCK Medical, Oldham, UK). After 90 minutes, during which time the subject was seated, the EMLA®/placebo was carefully washed off. The test leader and the subjects were blinded to group allocation, and the subjects were told not to reveal any possible anesthetic sensation. Therefore, the presence or absence of anesthesia in the area where the EMLA®/placebo was applied was not verified by the assessor or the subject. The success of blinding related to cream was not evaluated.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1 </label><caption><p><bold>Application of local anesthetic or placebo cream.</bold> EMLA, or placebo, applied on the leg 10 cm above and 10 cm below the center of patella, leaving the area around the knee without cream.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2474-13-68-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Outcome measures</title><p>Measures of sensory and motor functions were assessed before and after 90 minutes of treatment with EMLA® or placebo according to the protocol of our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The tests were performed in the order that they are described below. EMLA®/placebo was applied and all tests were performed on the injured leg only (in those four with a previous contralateral knee injury, the recently injured leg was tested). An experienced assessor, who received explicit guidelines and thorough training and pilot-testing prior to study start, performed the measurements.</p><sec><title>Measures of sensory function</title><p>Three measures of sensory function were used; perception of touch, vibration sense and knee kinesthesia. Lower values in these tests indicate better sensory function.</p><sec><title>Perception of touch</title><p>Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments (SWM) were used for assessing perception of touch at the most prominent point of the medial and lateral femoral condyles, just proximal of the joint space (areas where no cream was applied). In our previous study, one site (the medial femoral condyle) was assessed only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Because a ceiling effect was found in that study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], two sites were included in the current study. Prior to the test, the SWM (nr 4.31, 2.0 g) was demonstrated on the patient’s styloid process of the hand, so that the subjects could familiarize themselves with the test. Thereafter, the subjects lay in a supine position and were asked to close their eyes, concentrate on their knee and respond when they felt any sensation of touch. The assessment was performed according to a standardized procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Each monofilament, starting with the thinnest and continuing with thicker until response to sensation, was applied perpendicular to the skin for 1.5 seconds and lifted for 1.5 seconds. The filament was applied 3 times to the same spot and was bent each time to exert the specific pressure. Feeling the monofilament was recorded when at least one out of three applications was identified by the patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Vibratory perception threshold</title><p>Vibratory perception threshold (VPT) was assessed by a biothesiometer (Bio-Medical Instrument, Newbury, OH, USA), as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Prior to the test, the Biothesiometer was demonstrated on the patient’s ulna styloid process, so that the subjects could familiarize themselves with the test. Thereafter, the subjects lay in a supine position and were asked to close their eyes, concentrate on their foot/knee and respond when they felt any sensation of vibration. The biothesiometer tip was held with uniform pressure at two sites: the most prominent point of the medial malleolus and the medial femoral condyle (same location as that for testing perception of touch). Three consecutive measurements were taken on each site, and the amplitude was replaced to zero between each measurement without moving the biothesiometer tip from the location. The amplitude was increased by 1 Volt per second until the subjects responded to a sensation of vibration. This was noted as the VPT. The first measurement was regarded a trial test, and was, thus, excluded from the analysis. If the difference between the second and third measurement was more than 20%, 2 additional tests were taken. The mean of the second and third, or fourth and fifth, measurements was used in the analysis. High reliability has been reported for the biothesiometer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Vibration data for the patients and controls was reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Knee kinesthesia</title><p>Kinesthesia was measured in a specifically designed apparatus, which has been used and described in detail in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. The subjects lay in a lateral decubitus position, were asked to close their eyes, concentrate on their knee and respond when they felt any sensation of movement in their knee. Measurements of the threshold for detection of passive motion (TDPM) were performed towards knee extension (TE) and knee flexion (TF) from the starting position of 20° knee joint flexion, giving the variables TE20 and TF20. The median values of three consecutive measurements of these two variables were determined. The variables from the 20° starting position (TE20 and TF20) have been found to be reliable in uninjured subjects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. The sum of TE20 and TF20, giving an index value, was used for statistical analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Measures of motor function</title><p>Two measures of motor function were used; the one-leg hop test for distance and knee extensor muscle power. Higher values in these tests indicate better motor function.</p><sec><title>One-leg hop test for distance</title><p>The one-leg hop test for distance with the arms free, aiming at a more functional execution of the hop, was used. The one-leg hop test is widely used for predicting functional knee stability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Muscle strength, balance and confidence in the knee are contributing factors to the performance of this test. The subjects were told to hop as far as possible, taking off and landing on the same foot, maintaining their balance for about 2–3 seconds. The test was performed three times, the hop distance being measured (in cm) from toe in the starting position to heel in the landing position. If the subject improved more than 10 cm between the second and third hop, additional hops were performed until an increase of less than 10 cm was measured. A trial one-leg hop preceded the measurements. The subjects wore shoes, e.g., sneakers. The mean value of the three best hops was used in the analysis. The reliability of this test is high in subjects with ACL injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Knee extension power</title><p>The muscle strength test was performed as described, with standardized verbal instructions and encouragement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The subject was seated, using an individual seating position, in a knee extension weight training machine (Precor, Icarian, Borås, Sweden). The test was performed with the injured leg, and the other leg was fixed in place using a strap. Before the strength test, the subjects completed ten repetitions at a sub-maximum weight, followed by five repetitions using a somewhat higher sub-maximum weight. The subject then performed a single repetition, of approximately 90% of their maximum, to select the appropriate starting weight.</p><p>On a given signal, the subject was asked to extend his/her knee as quickly and forcefully as possible from approximately 110<sup>o</sup> of knee flexion to full knee extension (0<sup>o</sup> of flexion). The distance the weight stack was lifted and the time it took to fully extend the knee was measured with a linear encoder connected to the weight stack of the machine. In all, the subjects performed five maximum trials at five weight levels, until a decrease in power was seen. The weight was increased by 5 kg for each trial. The rest period between trials was 30 s, which was considered to be sufficient for full recovery. The average power was calculated by Muscle Lab, a computerised muscle function measuring system (Ergotest Technology, Oslo, Norway). If a subject reported pain in the knee during a test, which occurred in a few cases, this particular test was cancelled and the measurement was repeated. Data was missing for 2 patients (1 patient did not perform the test because of knee pain, and too few accurate values to calculate average power for 1 patient). Average power (W) was used in the analysis.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The number of subjects needed was determined by an a priori sample size calculation from our previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. No primary outcome measure was determined, since the study has an exploratory character. We expected to find an improvement in more than one of the variables to interpret the results as an effect from treatment. For knee kinesthesia, sample size calculations revealed that at least 12 subjects were needed to detect an improvement by treatment of 30% within groups (SD<sub>diff</sub> 0.49), with 80% power at the 5% significance level. For vibration sense, 13 subjects were needed to detect an improvement of 20% (SD<sub>diff</sub> 3.3) within groups. For the one-leg hop test, and knee extension power, less than 10 subjects were needed to detect an improvement by treatment of 10% within groups, with 80% power at the 5% significance level. Based on these sample-size calculations, we included 40 subjects. The paired t-test was used for comparisons within groups and analysis of variance, adjusting the variables for activity level, between groups. All variables had Shapiro-Wilk statistic of &gt;0.90, except knee kinesthesia and VPT at the medial malleolus. Because some variables were not normally distributed, the results were confirmed using non-parametric statistics. Wilcoxon signed rank test, or Mann–Whitney test, was used for ordinal data (perception of touch). Effect size was calculated by taking the difference between the means before and after EMLA®/placebo and dividing it by the SD of the same measure before EMLA®/placebo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. An effect size of &lt;0.50 was considered small, 0.50 to 0.79 moderate, and ≥0.80 large [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. A level of <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05 was chosen to indicate statistical significance. Group allocation was concealed to the person analyzing the data, until the results were completed.</p></sec></sec>Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsEA contributed to the design of the study, was responsible for acquisition, analysis and interpretation of data, and drafted the manuscript. AB and BR contributed to the design of the study and critically revised the manuscript. ER contributed to the design of the study, participated in analysis and interpretation of data, and critically revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final version.Pre-publication historyThe pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2474/13/68/prepubAcknowledgementsWe thank the physical therapists at “Idrottshälsan” in Lund, Sweden, for providing the patients for this study. Grant supporters: The Swedish Research Council, and the Faculty of Medicine, Lund University.AgebergEConsequences of a ligament injury on neuromuscular function and relevance to rehabilitation-using the anterior cruciate ligament-injured knee as modelJ Electromyogr Kinesiol200212320521210.1016/S1050-6411(02)00022-612086815RisbergMAHolmIMyklebustGEngebretsenLNeuromuscular training versus strength training during first 6 months after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a randomized clinical trialPhys Ther200787673775010.2522/ptj.2006004117442840ZechAHubscherMVogtLBanzerWHanselFPfeiferKNeuromuscular training for rehabilitation of sports injuries: a systematic reviewMed Sci Sports Exerc200941101831184110.1249/MSS.0b013e3181a3cf0d19727032RisbergMAHolmIThe long-term effect of 2 postoperative rehabilitation programs after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a randomized controlled clinical trial with 2 years of follow-upAm J Sports Med200937101958196610.1177/036354650933519619556470AgebergEThomeeRNeeterCSilbernagelKGRoosEMMuscle strength and functional performance in patients with anterior cruciate ligament injury treated with training and surgical reconstruction or training only: a two to five-year followupArthritis Rheum200859121773177910.1002/art.2406619035430BeynnonBDJohnsonRJNaudSFlemingBCAbateJABrattbakkBNicholsCEAccelerated versus nonaccelerated rehabilitation after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a prospective, randomized, double-blind investigation evaluating knee joint laxity using roentgen stereophotogrammetric analysisAm J Sports Med201139122536254810.1177/036354651142234921952714AgebergERoosHPSilbernagelKGThomeeRRoosEMKnee extension and flexion muscle power after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction with patellar tendon graft or hamstring tendons graft: a cross-sectional comparison 3 years post surgeryKnee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc200917216216910.1007/s00167-008-0645-418982311TrulssonARoosEMAgebergEGarwiczMRelationships between postural orientation and self reported function, hop performance and muscle power in subjects with anterior cruciate ligament injuryBMC Musculoskelet Disord201011114310.1186/1471-2474-11-14320594339EitzenIHolmIRisbergMAPreoperative quadriceps strength is a significant predictor of knee function two years after anterior cruciate ligament reconstructionBr J Sports Med200943537137610.1136/bjsm.2008.05705919224907RoosEMJoint injury causes knee osteoarthritis in young adultsCurr Opin Rheumatol200517219520010.1097/01.bor.0000151406.64393.0015711235PinczewskiLALymanJSalmonLJRussellVJRoeJLinklaterJA 10-year comparison of anterior cruciate ligament reconstructions with hamstring tendon and patellar tendon autograft: a controlled, prospective trialAm J Sports Med200735456457410.1177/036354650629604217261567RoosEMHerzogWBlockJABennellKLMuscle weakness, afferent sensory dysfunction and exercise in knee osteoarthritisNat Rev Rheumatol201171576310.1038/nrrheum.2010.19521119605PenfieldWBoldreyESomatic motor and sensory representations in the cerebral cortex of man as studied by electrical stimulationBrain19376038944310.1093/brain/60.4.389PenfieldWRasmussenTThe Cerebral Cortex of Man: A Clinical Study of Localization of Function1950Macmillan, New YorkMaldjianJAGottschalkAPatelRSDetreJAAlsopDCThe sensory somatotopic map of the human hand demonstrated at 4 TeslaNeuroImage1999101556210.1006/nimg.1999.044810385581StippichCHofmannRKapferDHempelEHeilandSJansenOSartorKSomatotopic mapping of the human primary somatosensory cortex by fully automated tactile stimulation using functional magnetic resonance imagingNeurosci Lett19992771252810.1016/S0304-3940(99)00835-610643889ChenRCohenLGHallettMNervous system reorganization following injuryNeuroscience2002111476177310.1016/S0306-4522(02)00025-812031403WallJTXuJWangXHuman brain plasticity: an emerging view of the multiple substrates and mechanisms that cause cortical changes and related sensory dysfunctions after injuries of sensory inputs from the bodyBrain Res Rev2002392–318121512423766KaasJHPlasticity of sensory and motor maps in adult mammalsAnnu Rev Neurosci19911413716710.1146/annurev.ne.14.030191.0010332031570DonoghueJHessGSanesJBloedel J, Ebner T, Wise SMotor cortical substrates and mechanisms for learningAcquisition of Motor Behaviour in Vertebrates1996MIT, Cambridge363386KandelESchwartzJJesselTPrinciples of Neural Science. 4th edition. New York: McGraw-Hill2000PurvesDAugustineGFitzpatrickDHallWLa MantiaA-SMcNamaraJWilliamsSNeuroscience2004Sinauer Associates Inc, SunderlandDuffauHBrain plasticity: from pathophysiological mechanisms to therapeutic applicationsJ Clin Neurosci200613988589710.1016/j.jocn.2005.11.04517049865RosénBBjörkmanALundborgGImproved sensory relearning after nerve repair induced by selective temporary anaesthesia - a new concept in hand rehabilitationJ Hand Surg [Br]200631212613210.1016/j.jhsb.2005.10.017Hassan-ZadehRLajevardiLEsfahaniARKamaliMImprovement of hand sensibility after selective temporary anaesthesia in combination with sensory re-educationNeuroRehabilitation200924438338619597277LundborgGBjörkmanARosénBEnhanced sensory relearning after nerve repair by using repeated forearm anaesthesia: aspects on time dynamics of treatmentActa Neurochir Suppl200710012112610.1007/978-3-211-72958-8_2617985560KapreliEAthanasopoulosSPapathanasiouMVan HeckePKelekiDPeetersRStrimpakosNSunaertSLower limb sensorimotor network: issues of somatotopy and overlapCortex200743221923210.1016/S0010-9452(08)70477-517405668KapreliEAthanasopoulosSGliatisJPapathanasiouMPeetersRStrimpakosNVan HeckePGouliamosASunaertSAnterior cruciate ligament deficiency causes brain plasticity: a functional MRI studyAm J Sports Med200937122419242610.1177/036354650934320119940314ZätterströmRFridénTLindstrandAMoritzUEarly rehabilitation of acute anterior cruciate ligament injury-a randomized clinical trialScand J Med Sci Sports1998831541599659676TegnerYLysholmJRating systems in the evaluation of knee ligament injuriesClin Orthop198519843494028566RoosEMRoosHPEkdahlCLohmanderLSKnee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)–validation of a Swedish versionScand J Med Sci Sports1998864394489863983RoosEMRoosHPLohmanderLSEkdahlCBeynnonBDKnee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)–development of a self-administered outcome measureJ Orthop Sports Phys Ther199828288969699158RosénBBjörkmanAWeibullASvenssonJLundborgGImproved sensibility of the foot after temporary cutaneous anesthesia of the lower legNeuroreport2009201374110.1097/WNR.0b013e32831b448619033877AgebergEBjörkmanARosénBLundborgGRoosEMPrinciples of brain plasticity in improving sensorimotor function of the knee and leg in healthy subjects: a double-blind randomized exploratory trialBMC Musculoskelet Disord2009109910.1186/1471-2474-10-9919656355(ASHT) ASoHTwww.asht.orgFrenetteBMerglerDFerrarisJMeasurement precision of a portable instrument to assess vibrotactile perception thresholdEur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol1990615–63863912079057ShakoorNAgrawalABlockJAReduced lower extremity vibratory perception in osteoarthritis of the kneeArthritis Rheum200859111712110.1002/art.2324118163397ThorlundJBShakoorNAgebergESandalLFBlockJARoosEMVibratory perception threshold in young and middle-aged patients at high risk of knee osteoarthritis compared to controls.Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)201164114414821905255FridénTRobertsDZätterströmRLindstrandAMoritzUProprioception in the nearly extended knee. Measurements of position and movement in healthy individuals and in symptomatic anterior cruciate ligament injured patientsKnee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc19964421722410.1007/BF015679669046506RobertsDFridénTStombergALindstrandAMoritzUBilateral proprioceptive defects in patients with a unilateral anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a comparison between patients and healthy individualsJ Orthop Res200018456557110.1002/jor.110018040811052492AgebergEFlenhagenJLjungJTest-retest reliability of knee kinesthesia in healthy adultsBMC Musculoskelet Disord200785710.1186/1471-2474-8-5717608920RisbergMLewekMSnyder-MacklerLA systematic review of evidence for anterior cruciate ligament rehabilitation: how much and what type?Physical Therapy in Sport2004512514510.1016/j.ptsp.2004.02.003PaternoMVGreenbergerHBThe test-retest reliability of a one legged hop for distance in young adults with and without ACL reconstructionIsokin Ex Sci1996616NeeterCGustavssonAThomeePAugustssonJThomeeRKarlssonJDevelopment of a strength test battery for evaluating leg muscle power after anterior cruciate ligament injury and reconstructionKnee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc20061457158010.1007/s00167-006-0040-y16477472KazisLEAndersonJJMeenanRFEffect sizes for interpreting changes in health statusMed Care1989273 SupplS1781892646488BjörkmanAWeibullARosénBSvenssonJLundborgGRapid cortical reorganisation and improved sensitivity of the hand following cutaneous anaesthesia of the forearmEur J Neurosci200929483784410.1111/j.1460-9568.2009.06629.x19250441BjörkmanARosénBLundborgGAcute improvement of hand sensibility after selective ipsilateral cutaneous forearm anaesthesiaEur J Neurosci200420102733273610.1111/j.1460-9568.2004.03742.x15548216LundborgGNBjörkmanACRosénBNNilssonJADahlinLBCutaneous anaesthesia of the lower leg can improve sensibility in the diabetic foot. A double-blind, randomized clinical trialDiabet Med201027782382910.1111/j.1464-5491.2010.03014.x20636964GokelerABenjaminseAHewettTELephartSMEngebretsenLAgebergEEngelhardtMArnoldMPPostemaKOttenEProprioceptive deficits after ACL injury: are they clinically relevant?Br J Sports Med201146318019221511738
