<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front NeuroengFront NeuroengFront. Neuroeng.Frontiers in Neuroengineering1662-6443Frontiers Media S.A.411418510.3389/fneng.2014.00030NeuroscienceOriginal Research ArticleBrain-computer interface-based robotic end effector system for wrist and hand rehabilitation: results of a three-armed randomized controlled trial for chronic strokeAngKai Keng1*GuanCuntai1PhuaKok Soon1WangChuanchu1ZhouLongjiang1TangKa Yin1Ephraim JosephGopal J.2KuahChristopher Wee Keong2ChuaKaren Sui Geok21Institute for Infocomm Research, Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR)Singapore2Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Tan Tock Seng HospitalSingaporeEdited by: Christoph Guger, Guger Technologies OEG, AustriaReviewed by: Robert Leeb, Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland; Surjo R. Soekadar, University Hospital of Tübingen, Germany*Correspondence: Kai Keng Ang, Institute for Infocomm Research, Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), 1 Fusionopolis Way, #21-01, Connexis (South Tower), Singapore 138632, Singapore e-mail: kkang@i2r.a-star.edu.sgThis article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Neuroengineering.2972014201473015420140872014Copyright © 2014 Ang, Guan, Phua, Wang, Zhou, Tang, Ephraim Joseph, Kuah and Chua.2014This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.The objective of this study was to investigate the efficacy of an Electroencephalography (EEG)-based Motor Imagery (MI) Brain-Computer Interface (BCI) coupled with a Haptic Knob (HK) robot for arm rehabilitation in stroke patients. In this three-arm, single-blind, randomized controlled trial; 21 chronic hemiplegic stroke patients (Fugl-Meyer Motor Assessment (FMMA) score 10–50), recruited after pre-screening for MI BCI ability, were randomly allocated to BCI-HK, HK or Standard Arm Therapy (SAT) groups. All groups received 18 sessions of intervention over 6 weeks, 3 sessions per week, 90 min per session. The BCI-HK group received 1 h of BCI coupled with HK intervention, and the HK group received 1 h of HK intervention per session. Both BCI-HK and HK groups received 120 trials of robot-assisted hand grasping and knob manipulation followed by 30 min of therapist-assisted arm mobilization. The SAT group received 1.5 h of therapist-assisted arm mobilization and forearm pronation-supination movements incorporating wrist control and grasp-release functions. In all, 14 males, 7 females, mean age 54.2 years, mean stroke duration 385.1 days, with baseline FMMA score 27.0 were recruited. The primary outcome measure was upper extremity FMMA scores measured mid-intervention at week 3, end-intervention at week 6, and follow-up at weeks 12 and 24. Seven, 8 and 7 subjects underwent BCI-HK, HK and SAT interventions respectively. FMMA score improved in all groups, but no intergroup differences were found at any time points. Significantly larger motor gains were observed in the BCI-HK group compared to the SAT group at weeks 3, 12, and 24, but motor gains in the HK group did not differ from the SAT group at any time point. In conclusion, BCI-HK is effective, safe, and may have the potential for enhancing motor recovery in chronic stroke when combined with therapist-assisted arm mobilization.electroencephalographymotor imagerybrain-computer interfacestroke rehabilitationrobotic<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Ethics Committee approval was obtained from the Institution's Domain Specific Review Board, National Healthcare Group, Singapore. The trial was registered in ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT01287975). Informed consent was obtained prior to study enrollment.</p></sec><sec><title>Study design</title><p>The randomized controlled trial was conducted over ~2.5 year period from 1 January 2011 to 31 June 2013 at an outpatient rehabilitation facility, involving subjects who had completed inpatient rehabilitation at the Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows a flow chart of the trial (refer Supplementary Material for CONSORT checklist).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>CONSORT Diagram: a flow from recruitment through follow-up and analysis</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneng-07-00030-g0001"/></fig><p>Inclusion criteria included first-ever clinical stroke confirmed on neuroimaging, ages 21–80 years of age, duration &gt;4 months post stroke, moderate to severe impairment of upper extremity function assessed by FMMA (Fugl-Meyer et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>) score 10–50; motor power assessed by Medical Research Council (MRC) (Compston, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) grades &gt;2/5 in shoulder abductors, and &gt;2/5 in the elbow flexors, and 1–3 in wrist dorsiflexors and finger flexors and ability to understand simple instructions.</p><p>Subjects were excluded if they had medical instability such as unresolved sepsis; postural hypotension; end stage renal failure terminal illness; severe aphasia, inattention; hemi spatial neglect; severe visual impairment; epilepsy; severe depression; psychiatric disorder; recurrent stroke; skull defects compromising EEG cap fit; severe spasticity assessed [modified Ashworth scale (MAS) (Bohannon and Smith, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>) &gt;2 in any shoulder, elbow or wrist/finger muscles]; pain assessed by visual analog scale (VAS) (Price et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) &gt;4/10; fixed joint contractures; skin conditions such as infections or eczema which could be worsened by robotic exoskeletal or EEG cap contact.</p></sec><sec><title>EEG data acquisition</title><p>In this study, EEG data from 27 channels were collected using the Nuamps EEG acquisition hardware<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn0001"><sup>1</sup></xref> with unipolar Ag/AgCl electrodes channels, digitally sampled at 250 Hz with a resolution of 22 bits for voltage ranges of ±130 mV. EEG recordings from all channels were bandpass filtered from 0.05 to 40 Hz by the acquisition hardware.</p></sec><sec><title>Haptic knob robot</title><p>The haptic knob (HK) robot is a two-degree-of-freedom robotic hand interface for hand grasping and knob manipulation PP (Lambercy et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The hand interface was designed using two parallelogram structures that supported an exchangeable handle in order to adapt to various hand sizes, finger orientations, and subjects with right or left stroke-impaired hand. The HK robot-assisted hand grasping PP involved finger flexion and extension exercises performed using the linear degree-of-freedom (DOF) of the HK, while the rotational DOF was held in a static position. The HK robot-assisted knob manipulation PP involved wrist pronation or supination, and hand coordination exercises performed using the rotational DOF of the HK, while the linear DOF was held in a static position.</p><p>During training with the HK, subjects were seated comfortably in a padded, height adjustable chair with 2-point chest strapping without arm rests to reduce compensatory trunk movements. For each subject, the stroke-impaired forearm was placed on a padded support and the subject was instructed to grasp the end effector of the HK. The height of the chair was adjusted until a comfortable level, the subject's shoulder abducted at about 40° and the elbow flexed at about 90°. The digits of the subject stroke-impaired hand were then strapped to the HK's end effector with Velcro bands to prevent them from slipping.</p><p>Instructions and feedbacks were provided on a computer screen for the progress of the HK robot-assisted PP in a form of a picture manipulation task using a solid frame to represent the current position, and a dotted frame to represent the target position. For the HK robot-assisted hand grasping PP, an outward-pointing arrow was shown to instruct the subject to perform hand opening (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Once the target outer limit was reached, an inward-pointing arrow was shown to instruct the subject to perform hand closing (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). This open-and-close action formed a single trial. Subsequently, a different picture was used for the next trial. For the HK robot-assisted knob manipulation PP, a right-curved arrow was shown to instruct the subject to perform a clockwise wrist rotation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). Once the target limit is reached, a left-curved arrow was shown to instruct the subject to perform counter-clockwise wrist rotation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). This wrist pronation-and- supination action formed a single trial. Similarly, a different picture was used for the next trial. For both the hand grasping and knob manipulation PP, HK robot-assisted movement was initiated if no movement from the subject was detected after an interval of 2 s.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Cues used in BCI-HK and HK interventions</bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> Hand opening; <bold>(B)</bold> hand closing; <bold>(C)</bold> wrist pronation; and <bold>(D)</bold> wrist supination.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneng-07-00030-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>EEG-based MI-BCI screening</title><p>A study on 99 healthy subjects had shown that ~7% of the subjects achieved below 60% classification accuracies (Guger et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Subsequently, a study on 54 stroke patients had shown that ~13% of the patients achieved classification accuracies below chance level (Ang et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Hence there is a small minority of subjects who cannot operate EEG-based MI-BCI. Thus, in this study, eligible subjects were first screened for their ability to operate EEG-based MI-BCI.</p><p>The screening session comprised 4 runs of EEG data collection. The first 2 runs collected EEG from subjects who performed kinesthetic MI (Stinear et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) of the stroke-impaired hand while strapped to the HK, and idle condition. The subjects were seated comfortably and instructed to imagine moving their stroke-impaired hand in an open-and-close action, and voluntary movements were restrained by static resistance from the HK robot. Subjects were also instructed to minimize voluntary head and body movements. Electromyography (EMG) were recorded from the stroke-impaired hand to check for attempted movements while performing motor imagery (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In the subsequent 2 runs, the subjects were instructed to relax while passive movement (PM) of the stroke-impaired hand was performed using the HK robot for the hand grasping action. The entire screening session consisted of 4 runs of 80 trials each for a total of 320 trials, and an inter-run break of at least 2 min was provided. Each run comprised 40 trials of MI or PM, and 40 trials of idle condition. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref> shows the timing for a single-trial from the screening section. Each trial lasted ~12 s and each run lasted ~8 min. The screening session lasted ~1 h inclusive of EEG setup time. The EEG from the first 2 runs were used to compute the 10×10-fold cross-validation accuracy of classifying MI of the stroke-impaired hand vs. the idle condition using the filter bank common spatial pattern (FBCSP) algorithm (Ang et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Setup of BCI-HK and HK intervention for stroke rehabilitation at a local hospital</bold>. The setup comprised Electroencephalography (EEG) cap, Electromyography (EMG) electrodes, EEG amplifier, and Haptic Knob (HK) robot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneng-07-00030-g0003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Acquisition of EEG for BCI-HK intervention</bold>. <bold>(A)</bold> Timing of performing kinesthetic MI of the stroke-impaired hand and idle condition for the calibration session; <bold>(B)</bold> timing of performing kinesthetic MI of the stroke-impaired coupled with HK robot-assisted PP for the rehabilitation session.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneng-07-00030-g0004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Randomization and blinding</title><p>Subjects who passed BCI screening were randomly assigned to receive either one of 3 interventions:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>BCI-HK which concomitantly comprised EEG-based MI-BCI coupled with HK robot-assisted PP therapy (60 min) followed by therapist-assisted arm mobilization (30 min).</p></list-item><list-item><p>HK which comprised HK robot-assisted PP therapy (60 min) followed by therapist-assisted arm mobilization (30 min).</p></list-item><list-item><p>SAT which comprised distal arm training of forearm pronation-supination movements incorporating wrist control and grasp-release of various objects (60 min) and overall therapist-assisted arm mobilization (30 min) conducted by a trained occupational therapist.</p></list-item></list><p>The randomization block size was 3 and the allocation sequence was 1:1:1 generated using STATA software version 10.2 (Stata Corp, College Station, TX, USA). Enrollment and assignment of participants was provided by KSGC. As subject blinding was not feasible, all outcome assessments for this study were performed by occupational therapist DXD who was blinded to allocation. There were no protocol deviations.</p><p>All groups received 18 sessions of supervised interventions for a total of 27 h over 6 weeks, 3 times per week, 90 min per session, by occupational therapist GJEJ and engineer KSP. This included 15 min for set up and breaks for short rests. Adverse events via questionnaire were monitored after each intervention session. Discontinuation criteria included new neurological or serious adverse events; increase in arm pain or spasticity of greater than 30% from baseline; or severe fatigue resulted from the interventions.</p><sec><title>BCI-HK intervention</title><p>The BCI-HK intervention consisted of a calibration session and 18 therapy sessions of MI-BCI coupled with HK robot-assisted PP therapy. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> shows the setup for the BCI-HK intervention.</p><p>The calibration session comprised 4 runs of EEG data collection that was similar to the screening session whereby subjects performed MI in the first 2 runs and PM in the subsequent 2 runs. The EEG from the first 2 runs were used to compute a subject-specific calibration model using the FBCSP algorithm (Ang et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) to classify MI vs. the idle condition in the subsequent therapy sessions. The EEG data collected from performing PM were not analyzed in this study.</p><p>Each therapy session comprised 4 runs of 30 concomitant MI and PP trials each, for a total of 120 trials. An inter-run break of 3–5 min was provided after each run. Allowable pain-free ranges of motion for the hand grasping and knob manipulation PP were first individually pre-determined by GJEJ. This HK calibration involved calibrating six positions: closing, opening, and static position for hand grasping; clockwise, counter clockwise and static position for knob manipulation. For the first 2 runs, the subjects are instructed to perform kinesthetic MI of the stroke-impaired hand for the hand grasping action. Subjects were also instructed to minimize voluntary head and body movements. EMG from the stroke-impaired hand was checked to ensure that there was no attempted movement during MI. If MI-related brain signals was successfully detected by the FBCSP algorithm (Ang et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) using the subject-specific calibration model, then the HK robot-assisted hand grasping PP would be initiated. For the subsequent 2 runs, the subjects are instructed to perform kinesthetic MI of the stroke-impaired hand for the knob manipulation action. If MI was successfully detected, then the HK robot-assisted knob manipulation PP would be initiated. If MI was not detected in 2 consecutive trials, then the HK robot-assisted PP would be automatically initiated. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> shows the timing for a single-trial from the therapy session. Each trial lasted ~17 to 23 s and each run lasted ~12 min. Each therapy session lasted ~1.5 h inclusive of breaks and setup time.</p></sec><sec><title>HK intervention</title><p>The HK intervention comprised 18 therapy sessions of HK robot-assisted hand grasping, and knob manipulation PP. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> shows the setup for the HK intervention, which is the same as the BCI-HK intervention. EEG data was also collected for the HK intervention but was not analyzed in this report.</p><p>Each therapy session comprised 4 runs of 30 PP trials each for a total of 120 trials. An inter-run break of 3–5 min was provided after each run. Similar to the BCI-HK intervention, allowable pain-free ranges of motion were pre-determined, and HK calibration was performed by GJEJ prior to the start of the therapy session. For the first 2 runs, the subjects performed HK robot-assisted hand grasping PP. For the subsequent 2 runs, the subjects performed HK robot-assisted knob manipulation PP. If no movements from the subject were detected, the HK would initiate fully assisted PP after 2 s. Each trial lasted ~9 to 15 s and each run lasted ~8 min. Each therapy session lasted ~ 1 h inclusive of breaks and setup time.</p></sec><sec><title>SAT intervention</title><p>The SAT intervention comprised 18 therapist-assisted sessions. Each session comprised 60 min of repetitive task training (Langhorne et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) focusing on forearm pronation-supination movements incorporating wrist control and grasp-release of various objects.</p></sec><sec><title>Therapist-assisted arm mobilization</title><p>All 3 groups received 30 min of therapist-assisted arm mobilization following the principles of the professionally recognized Neuro-developmental Treatment Approach for stroke rehabilitation (Howle, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>), which included tone management and facilitation toward normal arm movement patterns via various closed-chain functional reach activities.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Sample size statistical analysis</title><p>The sample size was estimated with an assumption of a 4 point gains in total FMMA score for the BCI-HK and HK groups compared to the SAT group, and a standard deviation of 6.3 points based on the gains of the robot-assisted intervention in the previous study (Ang et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The expected number in each group was found to be 20 subjects to achieve statistical power of 80%. Sample size calculation was performed in MATLAB.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical methods</title><p>Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to examine the demographic and baseline group differences. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) was used to examine the group differences at each measurement point between the three groups after adjusting for baseline differences. Two-sided <italic>t</italic>-tests were performed to analyze for significant difference at each measurement point from baseline in each group. One-sided <italic>t</italic>-tests were then performed to analyze if the BCI-HK and HK interventions were better than the SAT intervention. Data analysis was performed using MATLAB and the level of significance was set at 5%.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome was the total FMMA score (range, 0–66) for the stroke-impaired upper extremity. Outcomes were measured at 5 time points during the study: at baseline (week 0), at mid-intervention (week 3), at completion of intervention (week 6), 6 weeks follow-up (week 12), and 18 weeks follow-up (week 24). There were no protocol deviations.</p></sec></sec>We thank the study participants and their caregivers for their participation in this trial. We acknowledge Mr. Donald Xu Dong, Senior Occupational Therapist, who performed the independent clinical outcome assessments. We also acknowledge the financial support from the Science and Engineering Research Council of the Agency for Science, Technology and Research, Singapore (Grant number: 092 148 0066)1Neuroscan Nuamps EEG Amplifier. Compumedics USA, Compumedics Neuroscan and Compumedics DWL, 6605 West W.T. Harris Blvd, Suite F, Charlotte, NC 28269, USA.ReferencesAngK. K.ChinZ. Y.WangC.GuanC.ZhangH. (2012). Filter bank common spatial pattern algorithm on BCI competition IV datasets 2a and 2b. Front. Neurosci. 6:39
10.3389/fnins.2012.0003922479236AngK. K.ChuaK. S. G.PhuaK. S.WangC.ChinZ. Y.KuahC. W. K. (2014). A randomized controlled trial of EEG-based motor imagery brain-computer interface robotic rehabilitation for stroke. Clin. EEG Neurosci. [Epub ahead of print]. 10.1177/155005941452222924756025AngK. K.GuanC. (2013). Brain-computer interface in stroke rehabilitation. J. Comput. Sci. Eng. 7, 139–146
10.5626/JCSE.2013.7.2.139AngK. K.GuanC.ChuaK. S. G.AngB. T.KuahC. W. K.WangC. (2011). A large clinical study on the ability of stroke patients to use EEG-based motor imagery brain-computer interface. Clin. EEG Neurosci. 42, 253–258
10.1177/15500594110420041122208123BirbaumerN.MurguialdayA. R.CohenL. (2008). Brain-computer interface in paralysis. Curr. Opin. Neurol. 21, 634–638
10.1097/WCO.0b013e328315ee2d18989104BlankertzB.TomiokaR.LemmS.KawanabeM.MullerK.-R. (2008). Optimizing spatial filters for robust EEG single-trial analysis. IEEE Signal Process Mag. 25, 41–56
10.1109/MSP.2008.4408441BohannonR. W.SmithM. B. (1987). Interrater reliability of a modified ashworth scale of muscle spasticity. Phys. Ther. 67, 206–207
3809245BraunS. M.BeurskensA. J.BormP. J.SchackT.WadeD. T. (2006). The effects of mental practice in stroke rehabilitation: a systematic review. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil. 87, 842–852
10.1016/j.apmr.2006.02.03416731221BuchE.WeberC.CohenL. G.BraunC.DimyanM. A.ArdT. (2008). Think to move: a neuromagnetic brain-computer interface (BCI) system for chronic stroke. Stroke
39, 910–917
10.1161/STROKEAHA.107.50531318258825CompstonA. (2010). Aids to the Investigation of Peripheral Nerve Injuries. Medical Research Council: Nerve Injuries Research Committee. His Majesty's Stationery Office: 1942; pp. 48 (iii) and 74 figures and 7 diagrams; with Aids to the Examination of the Peripheral Nervous System. By Michael O'Brien for the Guarantors of Brain. Saunders Elsevier: 2010; pp. [8] 64 and 94 Figures. Brain
133, 2838–2844
10.1093/brain/awq27020928945DimyanM. A.CohenL. G. (2011). Neuroplasticity in the context of motor rehabilitation after stroke. Nat. Rev. Neurol. 7, 76–85
10.1038/nrneurol.2010.20021243015DobkinB. H. (2007). Brain-computer interface technology as a tool to augment plasticity and outcomes for neurological rehabilitation. J. Physiol. 579, 637–642
10.1113/jphysiol.2006.12306717095557FritzS. L.LightK. E.PattersonT. S.BehrmanA. L.DavisS. B. (2005). Active finger extension predicts outcomes after constraint-induced movement therapy for individuals with hemiparesis after stroke. Stroke
36, 1172–1177
10.1161/01.STR.0000165922.96430.d015890987Fugl-MeyerA. R.JääsköL.LeymanI.OlssonS.SteglindS. (1975). The post-stroke hemiplegic patient. 1. a method for evaluation of physical performance. Scand. J. Rehabil. Med. 7, 13–31
1135616GladstoneD. J.DanellsC. J.BlackS. E. (2002). The fugl-meyer assessment of motor recovery after stroke: a critical review of its measurement properties. Neurorehabil. Neural Repair
16, 232–240
10.1177/15459680240110517112234086GugerC.EdlingerG.HarkamW.NiedermayerI.PfurtschellerG. (2003). How many people are able to operate an EEG-based brain-computer interface (BCI)?
IEEE Trans. Neural Syst. Rehabil. Eng. 11, 145–147
10.1109/TNSRE.2003.81448112899258HankeyG. J. (2013). The global and regional burden of stroke. Lancet Glob. Health
1, e239–e240
10.1016/S2214-109X(13)70095-0HowleJ. M. (2002). Neuro-developmental Treatment Approach: Theoretical Foundations &amp; Principles. Laguna Beach, CA: NDTAIetswaartM.JohnstonM.DijkermanH. C.JoiceS.ScottC. L.MacwalterR. S. (2011). Mental practice with motor imagery in stroke recovery: randomized controlled trial of efficacy. Brain
134, 1373–1386
10.1093/brain/awr07721515905KasashimaY.FujiwaraT.MatsushikaY.TsujiT.HaseK.UshiyamaJ. (2012). Modulation of event-related desynchronization during motor imagery with transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) in patients with chronic hemiparetic stroke. Exp. Brain Res. 221, 263–268
10.1007/s00221-012-3166-922791228LambercyO.DovatL.GassertR.BurdetE.Chee LeongT.MilnerT. (2007). A haptic knob for rehabilitation of hand function. IEEE Trans. Neural Syst. Rehabil. Eng. 15, 356–366
10.1109/TNSRE.2007.90391317894268LambercyO.DovatL.YunH.WeeS. K.KuahC.ChuaK. (2011). Effects of a robot-assisted training of grasp and pronation/supination in chronic stroke: a pilot study. J. Neuroeng. Rehabil. 8:63
10.1186/1743-0003-8-6322087842LanghorneP.BernhardtJ.KwakkelG. (2011). Stroke rehabilitation. Lancet
377, 1693–1702
10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60325-521571152LoA. C.GuarinoP. D.RichardsL. G.HaselkornJ. K.WittenbergG. F.FedermanD. G. (2010). Robot-assisted therapy for long-term upper-limb impairment after stroke. N. Engl. J. Med. 362, 1772–1783
10.1056/NEJMoa091134120400552MalouinF.JacksonP. L.RichardsC. L. (2013). Towards the integration of mental practice in rehabilitation programs. A critical review. Front. Hum. Neurosci. 7:576
10.3389/fnhum.2013.0057624065903MiharaM.HattoriN.HatakenakaM.YaguraH.KawanoT.HinoT. (2013). Near-infrared spectroscopy-mediated neurofeedback enhances efficacy of motor imagery-based training in poststroke victims: a pilot study. Stroke
44, 1091–1098
10.1161/STROKEAHA.111.67450723404723NilsenD. M.GillenG.GordonA. M. (2010). Use of mental practice to improve upper-limb recovery after stroke: a systematic review. Am. J. Occup. Ther. 64, 695–708
10.5014/ajot.2010.0903421073100PfurtschellerG.Lopes Da SilvaF. H. (1999). Event-related EEG/MEG synchronization and desynchronization: basic principles. Clin. Neurophysiol. 110, 1842–1857
10.1016/S1388-2457(99)00141-810576479PriceC. I. M.CurlessR. H.RodgersH. (1999). Can stroke patients use visual analogue scales?
Stroke
30, 1357–1361
10.1161/01.STR.30.7.135710390307Ramos-MurguialdayA.BroetzD.ReaM.LäerL.YilmazÖ.BrasilF. L. (2013). Brain-machine interface in chronic stroke rehabilitation: a controlled study. Ann. Neurol. 74, 100–108
10.1002/ana.2387923494615SharmaN.SimmonsL. H.JonesP. S.DayD. J.CarpenterT. A.PomeroyV. M. (2009). Motor imagery after subcortical stroke: a functional magnetic resonance imaging study. Stroke
40, 1315–1324
10.1161/STROKEAHA.108.52576619182071ShihJ. J.KrusienskiD. J.WolpawJ. R. (2012). Brain-computer interfaces in medicine. Mayo Clin. Proc. 87, 268–279
10.1016/j.mayocp.2011.12.00822325364StinearC.ByblowW.SteyversM.LevinO.SwinnenS. (2006). Kinesthetic, but not visual, motor imagery modulates corticomotor excitability. Exp. Brain Res. 168, 157–164
10.1007/s00221-005-0078-y16078024VarkutiB.GuanC.PanY.PhuaK. S.AngK. K.KuahC. W. K. (2013). Resting state changes in functional connectivity correlate with movement recovery for BCI and robot-assisted upper-extremity training after stroke. Neurorehabil. Neural Repair
27, 53–62
10.1177/154596831244591022645108WolpawJ. R.BirbaumerN.McfarlandD. J.PfurtschellerG.VaughanT. M. (2002). Brain-computer interfaces for communication and control. Clin. Neurophysiol. 113, 767–791
10.1016/S1388-2457(02)00057-312048038
