<?xml version="1.0"?>
Dialogues Clin NeurosciDialogues Clin NeurosciDialogues Clin NeurosciDialogues in Clinical Neuroscience1294-83221958-5969Les Laboratoires ServierFrance4140516Clinical ResearchPatient-reported outcomes in obsessive-compulsive disorderResultados percibidos por el paciente en el trastorno obsesivo compulsivoRésultats rapportés par les patients dans les troubles obsessionnels compulsifsSubramaniamMythilyMHSM*Research Division, Institute of Mental Health, SingaporeSohPaulineBAResearch Division, Institute of Mental Health, SingaporeOngClarissaBAResearch Division, Institute of Mental Health, SingaporeEsmond SeowLee SengBAResearch Division, Institute of Mental Health, SingaporePiccoLouisaMPHResearch Division, Institute of Mental Health, SingaporeVaingankarJanhavi AjitMScResearch Division, Institute of Mental Health, SingaporeChongSiow AnnMMedResearch Division, Institute of Mental Health, Singapore*E-mail: mythily@itnh.com.sg6201462014162239254Copyright: © 2014 Institut la Conférence Hippocrate - Servier Research Group2014This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The purpose of the article was to provide an overview of patient-reported outcomes (PROs) and related measures that have been examined in the context of obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD). The current review focused on patient-reported outcome measures (PROMs) that evaluated three broad outcome domains: functioning, health-related quality of life (HRQoL), and OCD-related symptoms. The present review ultimately included a total of 155 unique articles and 22 PROMs. An examination of the PROs revealed that OCD patients tend to suffer from significant functional disability, and report lower HRQoL than controls. OCD patients report greater symptom severity than patients with other mental disorders and evidence indicates that PROMs are sensitive to change and may be even better than clinician-rated measures at predicting treatment outcomes. Nonetheless, it should be noted that the measures reviewed lacked patient input in their development. Future research on PROMs must involve patient perspectives and include rigorous psychometric evaluation of these measures.El propósito de este artículo fue proporcionar una panorámíca de los resultados percíbidos por el paciente (PROs) y las mediciones relacionadas que se han efectuado en el trastorno obsesivo compulsivo (TOC). La revisión se centró en las mediciones de los resultados percíbidos por el paciente (PROMs) que evaluaron tres grandes áreas de resultados: funcíonamiento, calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CdVRS) y síntomas relacionados con el TOC. La presente revisión incluyó un total de 155 artículos indíviduales y 22 PROMs. Un análísis de los PROs reveló que los pacientes con TOC tienden a sufrir de una marcada incapacidad funcional y refieren una CdVRS menor que los controles. Los pacientes con TOC muestran una mayor gravedad sintomática que los pacientes con otros trastornos mentales y la evidencia indica que las PROMs son sensibles a los cambios y en la predicción de los resultados terapéuticos pueden ser incluso mejores que las mediciones realizadas por los clínicos. Sin embargo, hay que tener en cuenta que las medíciones revisadas carecían del aporte del paciente en su desarrollo. A futuro la investigación de las PROMs debe incluír las perspectivas del paciente e íncorporar rigurosas evaluacíones psícométrícas de estas mediciones.Cet article étudie les résultats rapportés par les patients (PRO, patient-reported outcome) et leurs mesures, analysés dans le contexte des TOC (troubles obsessionnels compulsifs). Les mesures des résultats rapportés par les patients (PROM, patient-reported outcome measures) évaluent ici trois grands domaines: le fonctionnement, la qualité de vie liée à la santé (QdVLS) et les symptômes liés aux TOC. La revue actuelle a finalement inclus un total de 155 articles originaux et 22 PROM. L'analyse des PRO montre que les patients atteints de TOC souffrent d'incapacité fonctionnelle significative et rapportent une moins bonne QdVLS que les témoins. Leurs symptômes rapportés sont plus sévères que ceux des patients atteints d'autres troubles mentaux et des données montrent que les PROM sont sensibles au changement et peuvent même mieux prédire les résultats thérapeutiques que les mesures faites par les médecins. Notons cependant que les mesures analysées ne disposent pas, dans leur évolution, de la contribution des patients. La recherche future sur les PROM doit fate intervenir le point de vue des patients et inclure une évaluation psychométrique rigoureuse de ces mesures.patient-reported outcomeobsessive-compulsive disorderfunctioninghealth-related quality of lifesymptom<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="methods"><title>Methodology</title><p>Index terms for PROs differ between the major bibliographic databases. It has been suggested that review authors should not rely on a single index or subheading search term to identify studies addressing PROs.<sup><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Multiple search terms are usually necessary. Furthermore, the search needs to combine index terms and free-text terms, and is likely to require several iterations.<sup><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> The present review was guided by the PRISMA statement and conducted in two phases. In the first phase, the authors (MS, CO, PS, and ES) identified various PROMs that were used in patients with OCD. They then conducted a systematic review using a search strategy using two keywords: (i) obsessive-compulsive disorder; AND (ii) specific instrument, and limited the search to abstract, title, and keywords. The databases used for the systematic review were PubMed, Science Direct, Medline, and Psyclnfo. In addition, reference lists of all included studies were hand searched. To ensure recency of articles, the search was restricted to the period between and inclusive of January 1995 to October 2013. Potentially relevant papers were examined by at least two authors who worked independently, with discrepancies of opinion resolved by meeting together as a group. Inclusion criteria included: (i) the study cohort comprised OCD patients where OCD was the primary diagnosis, diagnosed clinically or using <italic>DSM</italic> criteria; (ii) the study described outcomes among OCD patients using PROMs; (iii) the study was among adult populations; and (iv) the study focused on at least one of the three broad groups of outcomes—symptoms primarily related to OCD, functioning, and health-related quality of life (HRQoL). Exclusion criteria included studies not reported in English, studies in the general population (ie, not a patient population), case reports, case series, studies conducted only for validation purposes and studies that did not report on outcomes per se.</p></sec>REFERENCES1FoaEB.KozakMJ.GoodmanWK.HollanderE.JenikeMA.RasmussenSA.DSM-IV field trial: obsessive-compulsive disorder.Am J Psychiatry.1995152909678021272American Psychiatric Association.Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders. 5th ed. Arlington, VA: American Psychiatric Publishing.20133RuscioAM.SteinDJ.ChiuWT.KesslerRC.The epidemiology of obsessive-compulsive disorder in the National Comorbidity Survey Replication.Mol Psychiatry.2010155363187259124McEvoyPM.GroveR.SladeT.Epidemiology of anxiety disorders in the Australian general population: findings of the 2007 Australian National Survey of Mental Health and Wellbeing.Aust N Z J Psychiatry.201145957967220441735SubramaniamM.AbdinE.VaingankarJA.ChongSA.Obsessivecompulsive disorder: prevalence, correlates, help-seeking and quality of life in a multiracial Asian population.Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol.20124720352043225268256KohnR.SaxenaS.LevavI.SaracenoB.The treatment gap in mental health care.Bull World Health Organ.200482858866156409227VosT.FlaxmanAD.NaghaviM.et alYears lived with disability (YLDs) for 1160 sequelae of 289 diseases and injuries 1990-2010: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010.Lancet.201238021632196232456078UstunTB.Ayuso-MateosJL.ChatterjiS.Global burden of depressive disorders in the year 2000.Br J Psychiatry.2004184386392151235019U.S Food and Drug Administration. Guidance for Industry. Patientreported outcome measures: Use in medical product development to support labelling claims.Federal Register.200974651326513310WareJE.SherbourneCD.The MOS 36-item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36): I. Conceptual framework and item selection.Med Care.199230473483159391411The WHOQOL Group. The World Health Organization Quality of Life Assessment (WHOQOL): development and general psychometric properties.SocSciMed.1998461569158512FoaEB.HuppertJD.LeibergS.et alThe Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory: development and validation of a short version.Psychol Assess.200214485961250157413The Cochrane Collaboration Patient reported outcomes. In: Higgins JPT, Green S.Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions. Version 5.1.0. Chichester, UK: Wiley.201114StorchEA.AbramowitzJS.KeeleyM.Correlates and mediators of functional disability in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Depress Anxiety.2009268068131917010615SheehanDV.Harnett-SheehanK.RajBA.The measurement of disability,int Clin Psychopharmacol.1996(suppl 3)8995892311616WeissmanMM.BothwellS.Assessment of social adjustment by patient self-report.Arch Gen Psychiatry.1976331111111596249417MarksI.Behavioural Psychotherapy. Bristol, UK: John Wright; London, UK: Institute of Psychiatry198618DidieER.WaltersMM.PintoA.MenardW.EisenJL.ManceboM.RasmussenSA.PhillipsKA.A comparison of quality of life and psychosocial functioning in obsessive-compulsive disorder and body dysmorphic disorder.Ann Clin Psychiatry.2007191811861772902019RosaAC.DinizJB.FossaluzaV.TorresAR.FontenelleLF.De MathisAS.da Conceicäo RosarioM.MiguelEC.ShavittRG.Clinical correlates of social adjustment in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Psychiatr Res.201246128612922280071320KennedyBL.LinY.SchwabJJ.Work, social, and family disabilities of subjects with anxiety and depression.South Med J.200295142414271259731121LochnerC.MogotsiM.du ToitPL.KaminerD.NiehausDJ.SteinDJ.Quality of life in anxiety disorders: a comparison of obsessive-compulsive disorder, social anxiety disorder, and panic disorder.Psychopathology.2003362552621457105522StarcevicV.BerleD.BrakouliasV.SammutP.MosesK.MilicevicD.HannanA.Obsessive-compulsive personality disorder co-occurring with obsessive-compulsive disorder: Conceptual and clinical implications.Aust N Z J Psychiatry.20134765732268933523HuppertJD.SimpsonHB.NissensonKJ.LiebowitzMR.FoaEB.Quality of life and functional impairment in obsessive-compulsive disorder: a comparison of patients with and without comorbidity, patients in remission, and healthy controls.Depress Anxiety.20092639451880036824HollanderE.SteinDJ.FinebergNA.MarteauF.LegaultM.Quality of life outcomes in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder: relationship to treatment response and symptom relapse.J Clin Psychiatry.2010717847922049284525DiefenbachGJ.AbramowitzJS.NorbergMM.TolinDF.Changes in quality of life following cognitive-behavioral therapy for obsessive-compulsive disorder.Behav Res Ther.200745306030681755980326TükelR.BozkurtO.PolatA.GençA.AtliH.Clinical predictors of response to pharmacotherapy with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Psychiatry Clin Neurosci.2006604044091688443927FarrisSG.McLeanCP.Van MeterPE.SimpsonHB.FoaEB.Treatment response, symptom remission, and wellness in obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Clin Psychiatry.2013746856902394544528FontenelleJM.HarrisonBJ.SantanaL.et alCorrelates of insight into different symptom dimensions in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Ann Clin Psychiatry.20132511162337686529ReidJM.StorchEA.MurphyTK.Clinical correlates and treatment response of the Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale auxiliary items.Cogn Ther Res.20113540441330ManceboMC.GreenbergB.GrantJE.et alCorrelates of occupational disability in a clinical sample of obsessive-compulsive disorder.Compr Psychiatry.20084943501806304031ChamblessDL.SteketeeG.Expressed emotion and behavior therapy outcome: a prospective study with obsessive-compulsive and agoraphobic outpatients.J Consult Clin Psychol.1999676586651053523232FontenelleLF.BarbosaIG.LunaJV.RochaNP.Silva MirandaA.TeixeiraAL.Neurotrophic factors in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Psychiatry Res.20121991952002249470233BrakouliasV.StarcevicV.BerleD.et alThe use of psychotropic agents for the symptoms of obsessive-compulsive disorder.Australas Psychiatry.2013211171212342609734SantanaL.FontenelleJM.YücelM.FontenelleLF.Rates and correlates of nonadherence to treatment in obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Psychiatr Pract.20131942532333467835MontgomerySA.KasperS.SteinDJ.Bang HedegaardK.LemmingOM.Citalopram 20 rng, 40 mg and 60 mg are all effective and well tolerated compared with placebo in obsessive-compulsive disorder,Int Clin Psychopharmacol.20011675861123607236GerardA.LiardF.CrochardA.GoniS.MilletB.Disability in patients consulting for anxiety or mood disorders in primary care: response to antidepressant treatment.Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat.201286056142327191037Van NoppenB.SteketeeG.McCorkleBH.PatoM.Group and multifamily behavioral treatment for obsessive compulsive disorder: a pilot study.J Anxiety Disord.199711431446927678638WoottonBM.TitovN.DearBF.et alAn Internet administered treatment program for obsessive-compulsive disorder: a feasibility study.J Anxiety Disord.201125110211072189998339GreistJH.MarksIM.BaerL.KobakKA.WenzelKW.HirschMJ.et alBehavior therapy for obsessive-compulsive disorder guided by a computer or by a clinician compared with relaxation as a control.J Clin Psychiatry.2002631381451187421540KenwrightM.MarksI.GrahamC.FransesA.Mataix-ColsD.Brief scheduled phone support from a clinician to enhance computer-aided self-help for obsessive-compulsive disorder: randomized controlled trial.J Clin Psychol.200561149915081617308441StewartSE.YenCH.StackDE.JenikeMA.Outcome predictors for severe obsessive-compulsive patients in intensive residential treatment.J Psychiatr Res.2006405115191622985742BullingerM.AnderssonR.CellaD.AaronssonN.Developing and evaluating cross-cultural instruments from minimum requirements to optimal models.Qual Life Res.19932451459816197943BowlingA.Health-related quality of life: A discussion of the concept, its use and measurement background: The'Quality of Life' Presented to the Adapting to Change Core Course, September 1999. Available at: http://info.worldbank.org/etools/docs/library/48475/m2s5bowling.pdf last accessed on 16th Dec 2013.44EndicottJ.KneeJ.HarrisonW.BlumenthalR.Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire: a new measure.Psychopharmacol Bull.199329321326829068145FrischM.CornellJ.VillanuevaM.RetzlaffPJ.Clinical validation of the Quality of Life Inventory. A measure of life satisfaction for use in treatment planning and outcome assessment.Psychol Assess.199249210146DevinsGM.BinikYM.HutchinsonTA.HollombyDJ.BarrePE.GuttmannRD.The emotional impact of end-stage renal disease: Importance of patients' perceptions of intrusiveness and control.Int J Psychiatry Med.198313327343667186347FlanaganJC.A research approach to improving our quality of life. AmPsychologist.19783313814748OliverJPJ.The Social Care Directive: development of a quality of life profile for use in community services for the mentally ill.Soc Work Soc Sci Rev.1991354549EisenJL.ManceboMA.PintoA.et alImpact of obsessive compulsive disorder on quality of life.Compr Psychiatry.2006472702751676930150RapaportMH.ClaryC.FayyadR.EndicottJ.Quality-of-life impairment in depressive and anxiety disorders.Am J Psychiatry.2005162117111781593006651FontenelleIS.FontenelleLF.BorgesMC.et alQuality of life and symptom dimensions of patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Psychiatry Res.20101791982032048348452AlbertU.MainaG.BogettoF.et alClinical predictors of health related quality of life in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Compr Psychiatry.2010511932002015230253Rodriguez-SalgadoB.Dolengevich-SegalH.Arrojo-RomeroM.et alPerceived quality of life in obsessive-compulsive disorder: related factors.BMC Psychiatry.20066201668434654MoritzS.RuferM.FrickeS.et alQuality of life in obsessive-compulsive disorder before and after treatment.Compr Psychiatry.2005464534591627521355BobesJ.GonzálezMP.Bascara'nMT.ArangoC.SáizPA.BousoñoM.Quality of life and disability in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Eur Psychiatry.2001162392451141827556SrivastavaS.BhatiaMS.ThawaniR.JhanjeeA.Quality of life in patients with obsessive compulsive disorder: a longitudinal study from India.Asian J Psychiatr.201141781822305111457Stengler-WenzkeK.KrollM.MatschingerH.AngermeyerMC.Subjective quality of life of patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol.2006416626681672150258KumarA.SharmaMP.KandavelT.Janardhan ReddyYC.Cognitive appraisals and quality of life in patients with obsessive compulsive disorder.J Obsessive Compuls Relat Disord.2012130130559KoranLM.ThienemannML.DavenportR.Quality of life for patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Am J Psychiatry.1996153783788863369060AkdedeBBK.AlptekinK.AkvardarY.KitisA.Quality of life in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder: relations with cognitive functions and clinical symptoms.Turk J Psychiatry.200516131961OomsP.MantioneM.FigeeM.SchuurmanPR.van den MunckhofP.DenysD.Deep brain stimulation for obsessive-compulsive disorders: longterm analysis of quality of life.J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry.2014851531582371591262NorbergMM.CalamariJE.CohenRJ.RiemannBC.Quality of life in obsessive-compulsive disorder: an evaluation of impairment and a preliminary analysis of the ameliorating effects of treatment.Depress Anxiety.2008252482591735237763GezginçK.UguzF.KaratayliS.et alThe impact of obsessive-compulsive disorder in pregnancy on quality of life.Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract.2008121341372491662464KoranLM.BrombergD.HornfeldtCS.ShepskiJC.WangS.HollanderE.Extended-release fluvoxamine and improvements in quality of life in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Compr Psychiatry.2010513733792057951065HouSY.YenCF.HuangMF.WangPW.YehYC.Quality of life and its correlates in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Kaohsiung J Med Sci.2010263974072070525066HertensteinE.ThielN.HerbstN.et alQuality of life changes following inpatient and outpatient treatment in obsessive-compulsive disorder: a study with 12 months follow-up. AnnGen Psychiatry.201312467VikasA.AvasthiA.SharanP.Psychological impact of obsessive compulsive disorder on patients and their caregivers: a comparative study with depressive disorder.Int J Soc Psychiatry.20115745562125235568KuglerBB.LewinAB.PharesV.GeffkenGR.MurphyTK.StorchEA.Quality of life in obsessive-compulsive disorder: the role of mediating variables.Psychiatry Res.201320643492312255869SolankiRK.SinghP.MidhaA.et alDisability and quality of life in schizophrenia and obsessive compulsive disorder: a cross-sectional comparative study.East Asian Arch Psychiatry.2010207132235180570GururajGP.MathSB.ReddyJ.ChandrashekarCR.Family burden, quality of life and disability in obsessive compulsive disorder: an Indian perspective.J Postgrad Med.20085491971848052371FarooqiYN.RasulF.Gender differences in perceived quality of life of patients suffering from obsessive-compulsive disorder.Pak J Psychol Res.20112672CassinSE.RichterMA.ZhangKA.RectorNA.Quality of life in treatment-seeking patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder with and without major depressive disorder.Can J Psychiatry.2009544604671966016873MasellisM.RectorNA.RichterMA.Quality of life in OCD: differential impact of obsessions, compulsions, and depression comorbidity.Can J Psychiatry.20034872771265590374Stengler-WenzkeK.KrollM.Riedel-HellerS.MatschingerH.AngermeyerMC.Quality of life in obsessive-compulsive disorder: the different impact of obsessions and compulsions.Psychopathology.2007402822891762270775BesirogluL.UguzF.SaglamM.AgargunMY.CilliAS.Factors associated with major depressive disorder occurring after the onset of obsessivecompulsive disorder.J Affect Disord.200710273791722245876GrantJE.ManceboMC.PintoA.EisenJL.RasmussenSA.Impulse control disorders in adults with obsessive compulsive disorder.J Psychiatr Res.2006404945011643092277BeşiroğluL.CllliAS.AşkinR.The predictors of health care seeking behavior in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Compr Psychiatry.200445991081499966078TenneyNH.DenysDA.van MegenHJ.et alEffect of a pharmacological intervention on quality of life in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Int Clin Psychopharmacol.20031829331249077279DoughertyDD.JamesonM.DeckersbachT.et alOpen-label study of high (30 mg) and moderate (20 mg) dose escitalopram for the treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder.Int Clin Psychopharmacol.2009243063111973038880BeşiroğluL.UğuzF.YilmazE.AğargünMY.AşkinR.AydinA.Psychopharmacological treatment and quality of life in obsessive compulsive disorder.Turk Psikiyatri Derg .20081938451833074281CordioliAV.HeldtE.BochiDB.et alCognitive-behavioral group therapy in obsessive-compulsive disorder: a randomized clinical trial.PsychotherPsychosom.20037221121682AnderssonE.Ljo'tssonB.HedmanE.et alInternet-based cognitive behavior therapy for obsessive compulsive disorder: a pilot study.BMC Psychiatry.2011111252181299183SimpsonHB.FoaEB.LiebowitzMR.et alA randomized, controlled trial of cognitive-behavioral therapy for augmenting pharmacotherapy in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Am J Psychiatry.20081656216301831642284TwohigMP.HayesSC.et alA randomized clinical trial of acceptance and commitment therapy versus progressive relaxation training for obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Consult Clin Psychol.2010787057162087390585DehlinJP.MorrisonKL.TwohigMP.Acceptance and commitment therapy as a treatment for scrupulosity in obsessive compulsive disorder.BehavModif.20133740943086BrownRA.AbrantesAM.StrongDR.et alA pilot study of moderateintensity aerobic exercise for obsessive compulsive disorder.J Nerv Ment Dis.20071955145201756830087McKayD.AbramowitzJS.CalamariJE.et alA critical evaluation of obsessive-compulsive disorder subtypes: symptoms versus mechanisms.Clin Psychol Rev.2004242833131524583388ClarkDA.BeckAT.Manual for the Clark-Beck Obsessive Compulsive Inventory. San Antonio, TX: The Psychological Corporation.200289AbramowitzJS.DeaconB.OlatunjiB.et alAssessment of obsessivecompulsive symptom dimensions: Development and evaluation of the dimensional obsessive-compulsive scale.Psychol Assess.2010221801982023016490KlepschR.ZaworkaW.HandI.LunenschlossK.JauernigG.Derivation and validation of the Hamburg Obsession/ Compulsion Inventory-Short Form (HOCI-S): first results.Psychol Assess.1991319620191CooperJ.The Leyton Obsessional Inventory.Psychol Med.197014864552611392HodgsonRJ.RachmanS.Obsessional-compulsive complaints.Behav Res Ther.19971538939561233993Obsessive Compulsive Cognitions Working Group. Psychometric validation of the obsessive belief questionnaire and interpretation of intrusions inventory-Part 2: Factor analyses and testing of a brief version.Behav Res Ther.200543152715421629989494Van OppenP.HoekstraRJ.EmmelkampPM.The structure of obsessive-compulsive symptoms.Behav Res Ther.1995331523787293395Dell'OssoL.RucciP.CassanoGB.et alMeasuring social anxiety and obsessive-compulsive spectra: comparison of interviews and self-report instruments.Compr Psychiatry.20024381871189398496DerogatisL.SCL-90-R: Administration, Scoring and Procedures Manual-1 for the Revised Version. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press.197797ThordarsonDS.RadomskyAS.RachmanS.ShafranR.SawchukN.HakstianAR.The Vancouver Obsessional Compulsive Inventory (VOCI).Behav Res Ther.200442128913141538143998BaerL.GettingControl. Overcoming Your Obsessions and Compulsions. New York, NY: Penguin Books.199199ChikHM.CalamariJE.RectorNA.RiemannBC.What do low-dysfunctional beliefs obsessive-compulsive disorder subgroups believe?J Anxiety Disord.20102483784620621440100KyriosM.lobMA.Automatic and strategic processing in obsessivecompulsive disorder: Attentional bias, cognitive avoidance or more complex phenomena?J Anxiety Disord.1998122712929699114101ScarrabelottiMB.DuckJM.DickersonMM.Individual differences in obsessive-compulsive behavior: The role of the eysenckian dimensions and appraisals of responsibility.Pers Individ Dif.199518413421102DastgiriSS.NateghianS.Investigating the overlap of Padua inventory and worry among patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder, generalized anxiety disorder and normal people.Iran J Psychiatry.2008110113103FullanaMA.Mataix-ColsD.TrujilloJL.et alPersonality characteristics in obsessive-compulsive disorder and individuals with subclinical obsessive-compulsive problems.Br J Clin Psychol.200443(Pt 4)38739815530209104AmtzA.VonckenM.GoosenACA.Responsibility and obsessive-compulsive disorder: An experimental test.Behav Res Ther.20074542543516697349105ExnerC.MartinV.RiefW.Self- focused ruminations and memory deficits in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Cogn Ther Res.200933163174106OlantunjiBO.CiesielskiBG.ZaidDH.A selective impairment in attentional disengagement from erotica in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry.2011351977198221801779107López-SolàC.GutiérrezF.AlonsoP.et alSpanish version of the Dimensional Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (DOCS): Psychometric properties and relation to obsessive beliefs.Compr Psychiatry.20145520621424209609108EmmelkampPMG.KraaijkampHJM.van Den HoutMA.Assessment of obsessive-compulsive disorder.BehavModif.199923269279109MüllerN.PutzA.KathmannN.LehleR.GüntherW.StraubeA.Characteristics of obsessive-compulsive symptoms in Tourette's syndrome, obsessive-compulsive disorder, and Parkinson's disease.Psychiatry Res.1975701051149194204110JonesMK.MenziesRG.Danger ideation reduction therapy (DIRT) for obsessive-compulsive washers. A controlled trial.Behav Res Ther.1998369599709714946111ShinMS.KimMS.HaTH.KwonJS.Deficits of organizational strategy and visual memory in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Neuropsychology.20041866567215506834112MurayamaK.NakaoT.SanematsuH.et alDifferential neural network of checking versus washing symptoms in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry.20134016016622996045113OkadaK.OtaT.LidaJ.KishimotoN.KishimotoT.Lower prefrontal activity in adults with obsessive-compulsive disorder as measured by near-infrared spectroscopy. Prog NeuropsychopharmacolBiol Psychiatry.201343713114TumkayaS.KaradagF.MuellerST.et alSituation awareness in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Psychiatry Res.201320957958823537845115RubensteinCS.Symptom overlap between OCD and bulimia nervosa.J Anxiety Disord.1995919116ClarkDA.AntonyMM.BeckAT.SwinsonRP.SteerRA.Screening for obsessive and compulsive symptoms: validation of the Clark-Beck Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory.Psychol Assess.20051713214316029101117MoritzS.KempkeS.LuytenP.RandjbarS.JelinekL.Was Freud partly right on obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD)? Investigation of latent aggression in OCD.Psychiatry Res.201118718018420950865118BellochA.RonceroM.Garcia-SorianoM.CarrioC.CabedoE.Fernandez-AlvarezH.The Spanish version of the obsessive-compulsive inventory-revised (OCI-R): reliability, validity, diagnostic accuracy and sensitivity to treatment effects in clinical samples.J Obsessive Compuls Relat Disord.20132249256119EinsteinDA.MenziesRG.Magical thinking in obsessive-compulsive disorder, panic disorder and the general community.Behav Cogn Psychother.2006351357120HermansD.MartensK.De CortK.PietersG.EelenP.Reality monitoring and metacognitive beliefs related to cognitive confidence in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Behav Res Ther.20034138340112643963121SalkovskisPM.WroeAL.GeldhillA.et alResponsibility attitudes and interpretations are characteristic of obsessive compulsive disorder.Behav Res Ther.20003834737210761280122PengZW.XuT.MiaoGD.et alNeurological soft signs in obsessivecompulsive disorder: the effect of co-morbid psychosis and evidence for familiality.Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry.20123920020522735396123SouzaFP.FoaEB.MeyerE.NiederauerKG.CordioliAV.Psychometric properties of the Brazilian Portuguese version of the Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory - Revised (OCI-R).Rev Bras Psiquiatr.20113313714321829906124WooCW.KwonSM.LimYJ.ShinMS.The Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory-Revised (OCI-R): psychometric properties of the Korean version and the order, gender, and cultural effects.J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry.20104122022720163784125HuppertJD.MoserJS.GershunyBS.et alThe relationship between obsessive-compulsive and posttraumatic stress symptoms in clinical and non-clinical samples.J Anxiety Disord.20051912713615488372126AnholtGE.CathDC.EmmelkampPM.van OppenP.SmitJH.van BalkomAJ.Do obsessional beliefs discriminate OCD without tic patients from OCD with tic and Tourette's syndrome patients?Behav Res Ther.2006441537154316480944127AlonsoP.OrbegozoA.PujolJ.et alNeural correlates of obsessivecompulsive related dysfunctional beliefs.Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry.201347253223911440128RadomskyAS.AshbaughAR.GelfandLA.Relationships between anger, symptoms, and cognitive factors in OCD checkers.Behav Res Ther.2007452712272517723225129NiemeyerH.MoritzS.PietrowskyR.Responsibility, in eta cog nit ion and unrealistic pessimism in obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Obsessive Compuls Relat Disord.20132119129130WahlK.SchönfeldS.HissbachJ.et alDifferences and similarities between obsessive and ruminative thoughts in obsessive-compulsive and depressed patients: a comparative study.J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry.20114245446121596010131FilomenskyTZ.AlmeidaKM.Castro NogueiraMC.et alNeither bipolar nor obsessive-compulsive disorder: compulsive buyers are impulsive acquirers.Compr Psychiatry.20125355456122099581132Jimenez-MurciaS.Fernández-ArandaF.RaichRM.et alObsessivecompulsive and eating disorders: comparison of clinical and personality features.Psychiatry Clin Neurosci.20076138539117610663133FontenelleLF.MendlowiczMV.de MenezesGB.et alComparison of symptom profiles of obese binge eaters, obese non-binge eaters, and patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Nerv Ment Dis.200219064364612357101134SteinDJ.MullenL.IslamMN.CohenL.DeCariaCM.HollanderE.Compulsive and impulsive symptomatology in trichotillomania.Psychopathology.1995282082137480576135DoyleM.ChorcorainAN.GriffithE.TrimbleT.O'CallaghanE.Obsessive compulsive symptoms in patients with schizophrenia on clozapine and with obsessive compulsive disorder: a comparison study.Compr Psychiatry.20145513013624209980136MassR.WeigelS.SchneiderS.KlepschR.Schizophrenia-specific basic symptoms. A successful replication.Psychopathology.1998311131199636940137FontenelleLF.DominguesAM.SouzaWF.et alHistory of trauma and dissociative symptoms among patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder and social anxiety disorder.Psychiatr Q.2007782415017453345138TolinDF.WorhunskyP.BradyRE.MaltbyN.The relationship between obsessive beliefs and thought-control strategies in a clinical sample.Cogn Ther Res.200731307318139AnholtGE.EmmelkampPM.CathDC.van OppenP.NelissenH.SmitJH.Do patients with OCD and pathological gambling have similar dysfunctional cognitions?Behav Res Ther.20044252953715033499140WellenD.SamuelsJ.et alUtility of the Leyton Obsessional Inventory to distinguish OCD and OCPD.Depress Anxiety.20072430130617099877141BaptistaMN.MagnaLA.McKayD.Del-PortoJA.Assessment of obsessive beliefs: comparing individuals with obsessive-compulsive disorder to a medical sample.J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry.2011421521073999142RectorNA.CassinSE.RichterMA.BurroughsE.Obsessive beliefs in first-degree relatives of patients with OCD: a test of the cognitive vulnerability model.J Anxiety Disord.20092314514918619770143VulinkNCC.DenysD.BusL.WestenbergHGM.Female hormones affect symptom severity in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Int Clin Psychopharmacol.20062117117516528139144TynesLL.WinsteadDK.Subtyping obsessive compulsive patients by depressive symptoms: a retrospective pilot study.Psychiatr Q.19997053619924732145TaylorS.AbramowitzJS.KcKayD.Are there interactions among dysfunctional beliefs in obsessive compulsive disorder.Cogn Behav Ther.200534899815986785146DeBerardisD.CampanellaD.GambiF.et alInsight and alexithymia in adult outpatients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci.200525535035815711867147EinsteinDA.MenziesRG.The presence of magical thinking in obsessive compulsive disorder.Behav Res Ther.20044253954915033500148BrakouliasV.StarcevicV.BerleD.et alFurther support for five dimensions of obsessive-compulsive symptoms.J Nerv Ment Dis.201320145242923686154149EtteltS.RuhrmannS.BarnowS.et alImpulsiveness in obsessivecompulsive disorder: results from a family study.Acta Psychiatr Scand.2007115414717201865150TolinDF.BradyRE.HannanS.Obsessional beliefs and symptoms of obsessive-compulsive disorder in a clinical sample.J Psychopathol Behav Assess.2008303142151CalamariJE.CohenRJ.RectorNA.et alDysfunctional belief-based obsessive-compulsive disorder subgroups.Behav Res Ther.2006441347136016337605152WheatonMG.AbramowitzJS.BerrnanNC.RiemannBC.HaleLR.The relationship between obsessive beliefs and symptom dimensions in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Behav Res Ther.20104894995420800750153JulienD.O'ConnorKP.AardemaF.TodorovC.The specificity of belief domains in obsessive-compulsive symptom subtypes.Personal Individual Diff.20064112051216154RuferM.FrickeS.HeldD.CremerJ.HandI.Dissociation and symptom dimensions of obsessive-compulsive disorder. A replication study.Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci.200625614615016267636155GrabeHJ.GoldschmidtF.LehmkuhlL.GänsickeM.SpitzerC.FreybergerHJ.Dissociative symptoms in obsessive-compulsive dimensions.Psychopathology.19993231932410575330156FontenelleLF.SoaresID.MieleF.et alEmpathy and symptoms dimensions of patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Psychiatr Res.20094345546318614180157AksarayG.YelkenB.KaptanoğluC.OfluS.OzaltinM.Sexuality in women with obsessive compulsive disorder.J Sex Marital Ther.20012727327711354932158GrabeHJ.ThielA.FreybergerHJ.Symptoms of eating disorders in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Acta Psychiatr Scand.200010244945311142435159YapK.MoganC.KyriosM.Obsessive-compulsive disorder and comorbid depression: the role of OCD-related and non-specific factors.J Anxiety Disord.20122656557322495108160CareauY.O'ConnorKP.TurgeonL.FreestonMH.Childhood experiences and adult beliefs in obsessive-compulsive disorder: evaluating a specific etiological model.J Cogn Psychother.201226236256161AardemaF.O'ConnorKP.EmmelkampPM.Inferential confusion and obsessive beliefs in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Cogn Behav Ther.20063513814716952897162HashimotoN.NakaakiS.OmoriIM.et alDistinct neuropsychological profiles of three major symptom dimensions in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Psychiatry Res.201118716617320817310163KaradagF.OguzhanogluN.OzdelO.AtesciFC.AmukT.Memory function in patients with obsessive compulsive disorder and the problem of confidence in their memories: a clinical study.Croat Med J.20054628228715849851164EnrightSJ.BeechAR.ClaridgeGS.A further investigation of cognitive inhibition in obsessive-compulsive disorder and other anxiety disorders.Person Individ Diff.199519535542165Sizino da VictoriaM.NascimentoAL.FontenelleLF.Symptom-specific attentional bias to threatening stimuli in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Compr Psychiatry.20125378378822300902166ChoiJS.KimHS.YooSY.et alMorphometric alterations of anterior superior temporal cortex in obsessive-compulsive disorder.Depress Anxiety.20062329020616688740167NakamaeT.NarumotoJ.SakaiY.NishidaS.YamadaK.FukuiK.The neural basis of dysfunctional beliefs in non-medicated patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry.201237222522172533168FontenelleLF.BarbosaIG.LunaJV.de SousaLP.AbreuMN.TeixeiraAL.A cytokine study of adult patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.Compr Psychiatry.20125379780422300901169AlonsoP.López-SolàC.GratacósM.et alThe interaction between COMT and BDNF variants influences obsessive-compulsive-related dysfunctional beliefs.J Anxiety Disord.201327321723602946170EinstenDA.MenziesRG.Does magical thinking improve across treatment for obsessive-compulsive disorder?Behav Change.200825149155171O'ConnorKP.AardemaF.BouthillierD.et alEvaluation of an inference-based approach to treating obsessive-compulsive disorder.Cogn Behav Ther.20053414816316195054172AbramowitzJS.TolinDF.DiefenbachGJ.Measuring change in OCD: sensitivity of the obsessive-compulsive inventory-revised.J Psychopathology Behav Assess.200527317324173SolemS.HălandAT.VogelPA.HansenB.WellsA.Change in metacognitions predicts outcome in obsessive-compulsive disorder patients undergoing treatment with exposure and response prevention.Behav Res Ther.20094730130719203749174AnholtGA.van OppenP.CathDC.EmmelkampPM.SmitJH.van BalkomAJ.Sensitivity to change of the Obsessive Beliefs Questionnaire.Clin Psychol Psychother.20101715415919658124175Van NoppenBL.PatoMT.MarslandR.RasmussenSA.A time limited behavioral group for treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Psychother Pract Res.199872722809752638176KearnsC.ToneY.RushG.LuceyJV.Effectiveness of group-based cognitive-behavioural therapy in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder.The Psychiatrist Online.20103469177BortoncelloCF.BragaDT.GomesJB.SouzaFP.CordioliAV.Psychometric properties of the Brazilian version of the Obsessive Beliefs Questionnaire (OBQ-44).J Anxiety Disord.20122643043422306130178KrochmalikA.JonesMK.MenziesRG.Danger Ideation Reduction Therapy (DIRT) for treatment-resistant compulsive washing.Behav Res Ther.20013989791211480831179FritzlerBK.HeckerJE.LoseeMC.Self-directed treatment with minimal therapist contact: preliminary findings for obsessive-compulsive disorder.Behav Res Ther.1997356276319193126180GreistJH.JeffersonJW.KobakKA.et alA 1 year double-blind placebo-controlled fixed dose study of sertraline in the treatment of obsessivecompulsive disorder.Int Clin Psychopharmacol.19951057657673657181SelviY.AtliA.BeşiroğluL.AydinA.GulecM.The impact of obsessive beliefs on pharmacological treatment response in patients with obsessivecompulsive disorder.Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract.20111520921322121931182OverbeekT.SchruersK.VermettenE.GriezE.Comorbidity of obsessive-compulsive disorder and depression: prevalence, symptom severity, and treatment effect.J Clin Psychiatry.2002631106111212523869183KeijsersGPJ.HoogduinCAL.SchaapCPDR.de JongT.de KoningThe immediate effects of exposure versus response prevention in the treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder.Behav Cogn Psychother.1995233544184LiX.MayRS.TolbertLC.JacksonWT.FlournoyJM.BaxterLR.Risperidone and haloperidol augmentation of serotonin reuptake inhibitors in refractory obsessive-compulsive disorder: a crossover study.J Clin Psychiatry.20056673674315960567185AltemusM.GreenbergBD.KeulerD.JacobsonKR.MurphyDL.Open trial of flutamide for treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Clin Psychiatry.19996044244510453797186van BalkomAJ.de HaanE.van OppenP.SpinhovenP.HoogduinKA.van DyckR.Cognitive and behavioral therapies alone versus in combination with fluvoxamine in the treatment of obsessive compulsive disorder.J Nerv Ment Dis.19981864924999717867187MantovaniA.RossiS.BassiBD.SimpsonHB.FallonBA.LisanbySH.Modulation of motor cortex excitability in obsessive-compulsive disorder: An exploratory study on the relations of neurophysiology measures with clinical outcome.Psychiatry Res.20132101026103224064461188ThielA.ZugerM.JacobyGE.SchusslerG.Thirty-month outcome in patients with anorexia or bulimia nervosa and concomitant obsessive-compulsive disorder.Am J Psychiatry.19981552442499464205189KirkbyKC.BerriosGE.DanielsBA.MenziesRG.ClarkA.RomanoA.Process-outcome analysis in computer-aided treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder.Compr Psychiatry.20004125926510929793190AnholtGE.van OppenP.EmmelkampPM.et alMeasuring obsessivecompulsive symptoms: Padua Inventory-Revised vs. Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale.J Anxiety Disord.20092383083519443176191van OppenP.EmmelkampPMG.van BalkomAJLM.The sensitivity to change of measures for obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Anxiety Disord.19959241248192KennedyBL.MorrisRL.PedleyLL.SchwabJJ.The ability of the Symptom Checklist SCL-90 to differentiate various anxiety and depressive disorders.Psychiatr Q.20017227728811467161193HunterEE.PenickEC.PowellBJ.OthmerE.NickelEJ.DesouzaC.Development of scales to screen for eight common psychiatric disorders.J Nerv Ment Dis.200519313113515684916194BlackDW.MonahanP.GableJ.BlumN.ClancyG.BakerP.Hoarding and treatment response in 38 nondepressed subjects with obsessive-compulsive disorder.J Clin Psychiatry.1998594204259721822List of Abbreviations used in Table IIaBDDBody dysmorphic disorderBDNFBrain-derived neurotrophic factorGADGeneralized anxiety disorderGBTGroup behavior therapyHCHealthy controlIRTIntensive residential treatmentMDDMajor depressive disorderMFBTMulti-family behavior therapyOCObsessive-compulsiveOCDObsessive-compulsive disorderOCPDObsessive-compulsive personality disorderPDPanic disorderPDAPanic disorder with agoraphobiaPTSDPost-traumatic stress disorderRCTRandomised controlled trialSADSocial anxiety disorderSAS-SRSocial Adjustment Scale-Self ReportSDSSheehan Disability ScaleSSRISelective serotonin reuptake inhibitorWSASWork and Social Adjustment ScaleY-BOCSYale-Brown Obsessive-Compulsive ScaleList of Abbreviations used in Table IIbACTAcceptance and Commitment TherapyBDDBody dysmorphic disorderERPExposure and Response PreventionIIRSIllness Intrusiveness Rating ScaleMDDMajor Depressive DisorderMOS-36Medical Outcomes Study SF-36 Health SurveyOCDObsessive-compulsive disorderPDPanic DisorderPTSDPost-traumatic stress disorderQ-LES-QQuality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction QuestionnaireQOLQuality of lifeQOLIQuality of Life InventoryQOLS Quality of Life ScaleRCTRandomised controlled trialSF-36Short Form (36) Health SurveySPSocial phobiaSRIsSerotonin reuptake inhibitorsWHOQOL-BREFThe World Health Organization Quality of Life-BREFWHOQOL-BREF-TRWHO Quality of Life-BREF-Turkish VersionList of Abbreviations used in Table IIcBDBipolar disorderBDNFBrain derived neurotropic factorCAMCognitive Appraisal ModelBISBarratt Impulsiveness ScaleCBCompulsive buyersCBGTCognitive behavioral group therapyCBTCognitive behavioral therapyCOMTCatechol-O-methyltransferaseDASDysfunctional attitude scaleDIRTDanger Ideation Reduction TherapyDOCSDimensional Obsessive Compulsive ScaleEDEating disorderERPExposure and Response PreventionfMRIFunctional magnetic resonance imagingGADGeneralised anxiety disorderGDNFGlial cell-derived neurotrophic factorHZI/HOCIHamburg Obsessive Compulsive DisorderIBAInterference-Based ApproachLOILeyton Obsessional InventoryMADRASMontgomery Åsberg Depression Rating ScaleMDDMajor Depressive DisorderMIMagical ideationMOCIMaudsley Obsessive Compulsive InventoryMOCQMaudsley Obsessive Compulsive QuestionnaireNGFNerve growth factorOADOther anxiety disorderOBQObsessional Beliefs QuestionnaireOCDObsessive-compulsive disorderOCPDObsessive compulsive personality disorderOCI-RObsessive Compulsive Inventory-RevisedOCI-SVObsessive Compulsive Inventory-Short VersionPI-RPadua Inventory-RevisedPI-WSURPi-Washington State University revised form)PGPathological gamblingPTSDPost-traumatic stress disorderRASResponsibility Attitude ScaleRIQResponsibility Interpretations QuestionnaireROCFRey-Osterrieth Complex FigureSADSocial anxiety disorderSCL-90-RSymptom Checklist-90-RevisedSCWCStroop Color Word Task
