<?xml version="1.0"?>
Curr Behav Neurosci RepCurr Behav Neurosci RepCurrent Behavioral Neuroscience Reports2196-2979Springer International PublishingCham585755914410.1007/s40473-018-0144-yPersonality and Impulse Control Disorders (R Lee, Section Editor)Developmental Aspects of Schizotypy and Suspiciousness: a ReviewWongKeri K.+44(0)1223-34581kkyw3@cam.ac.uk12RaineAdrianaraine@sas.upenn.edu310000000121885934grid.5335.0Department of Psychology, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK 2Cambridge, Cambridgeshire UK 30000 0004 1936 8972grid.25879.31Departments of Criminology, Psychiatry, and Psychology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA USA 92201892201820185194101© The Author(s) 2018Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.Purpose of the ReviewThis review identifies the early developmental processes that contribute to schizotypy and suspiciousness in adolescence and adulthood. It includes the most recent literature on these phenomena in childhood.Recent FindingsThe early developmental processes that affect schizotypy and paranoia in later life are complex. In contrast to existing studies of psychiatric patients and clinical/nonclinical adult populations, the study of schizotypy and suspiciousness in young children and adolescents is possible due to new child-appropriate dimensional assessments. New assessments and the advancement of technology (e.g., virtual reality in mental health) as well as statistical modeling (e.g., mediation and latent-class analyses) in large data have helped identified the developmental aspects (e.g., psychosocial, neurocognitive and brain factors, nutrition, and childhood correlates) that predict schizotypy and suspiciousness in later life.SummaryProspective longitudinal designs in community youths can enhance our understanding of the etiology of schizophrenia-spectrum disorders and, in the future, the development of preventive interventions by extending adult theories and interventions to younger populations.KeywordsSchizotypal personality disorderSchizophreniaParanoiaSuspiciousnessDimensionalDevelopmentalUniversity of Cambridgeissue-copyright-statement© Springer International Publishing AG, part of Springer Nature 2018IntroductionSchizophrenia is a disabling, multidimensional disorder affecting roughly 1% of the general population. Studies of patients with persecutory delusions and schizotypal personality disorder (SPD) have helped advance our understanding of schizophrenia over the years, but its causes are still complex and its treatments are limited. Prospective longitudinal studies have recognized that schizotypy and suspiciousness reflect liability for later schizophrenia; hence, the continued research and clinical interest in these phenomena and its attenuated forms may shed light on the causes of schizophrenia. The presence of schizotypy and suspiciousness at both the clinical and community levels are profoundly distressing and associated with negative psychosocial functioning; hence, studying the developmental aspects of schizotypy and suspiciousness are again of significant clinical and research importance.Like schizophrenia, schizotypal personality disorder is a multidimensional disorder commonly reported to have a three-factor structure: cognitive-perceptual deficits (ideas of reference, odd beliefs, perceptual disturbances, and paranoia/suspiciousness), interpersonal deficits (lack of close friends, social anxiety, paranoia/suspiciousness), and disorganization (odd speech/thought, blunted affect, odd behavior). Schizotypy research informs our understanding of the etiology of schizophrenia in several ways: schizotypy allows researchers to study the prodrome and at-risk states of schizophrenia and related disorders taking a developmental approach. This approach allows the identification of developmental causes along the schizotypy continuum of severity. Schizotypy’s multidimensional framework, which includes paranoia/suspiciousness, enhances our understanding of the heterogeneous etiologies of schizophrenia-spectrum disorders, by allowing differential relationships to be examined across the dimensions. For example, recent findings have recognized that cognitive-perceptual and disorganized features of schizotypy provide high sensitivity and moderate discriminate validity in the SPD diagnosis compared to other personality disorders in the DSM-IV [1].Paranoia, or excess suspiciousness, is the unfounded belief that others purposely intend to cause harm [2•]. It is a subcomponent of schizotypy and the most commonly reported subtype of delusion in schizophrenic patients. While these subtypes are often interrelated, factor analytic studies have demonstrated that paranoia is a separate type of psychotic experience and therefore merits study in its own right [3]. While studies of suspiciousness have focused primarily on adult patient samples, studies in the last two decades have replicated findings from patient studies in young adults in the general population [4•]. More recent studies have even been extended to young children and adolescent populations in the general population, recognizing that attenuated symptoms of suspiciousness in the form of social mistrust exist early in development and are heritable and also associated with childhood psychopathology ([5••]; Zhou, (Wong KK, Raine A, &amp; Venables P (under review). Being left home alone at age three years is associated with increased schizotypy and antisocial behavior at ages 17 and 23 years.)). A short-term longitudinal study replicated this finding in help-seeking adolescents, identifying that paranoia persistence is predicted by a host of cognitive, affective, and social factors. Thus, studying delusions developmentally in the general population may help understand the clinical condition and develop preventive interventions.Both schizotypy and suspiciousness exist on a dimension; that is, schizotypy lies on a continuum of severity with schizophrenia and persecutory delusions lies on a continuum with paranoia [5••, 6•, 7•, 8]. Clinical symptoms of schizophrenia extend to milder symptoms of schizotypy and suspiciousness in the general population [2•, 9]. In schizotypy, studies have continuously demonstrated that subclinical psychosis closely resembles symptoms that have been identified in schizophrenia, indicating a continuum between the subclinical and clinical phenotypes [10, 11]. Similarly, in the paranoia literature, a review of 14 studies found that 10 to 15% of non-clinical young adults frequently report paranoid thoughts, of which 3% report clinical levels of paranoid thoughts that go undiagnosed [4•]. A recent meta-analysis of 35 unique participant cohorts has documented a strong support for a psychosis continuum in the population, with a median prevalence rate of approximately 5% and an incident rate of 3% [11]. The authors suggest that 75–90% of developmental psychotic experiences are fleeting and disappear over time; however, there is evidence that some of these developmental psychotic experiences may become more persistent and disabling given an individual’s level of exposure to subsequent environmental risks throughout life. Thus, understanding these developmental risks is of utmost importance in identifying those in need.Overall, the study of schizotypy and paranoia is well established with a number of independent reviews on schizotypy and suspiciousness [1, 2•, 6•, 9, 12, 13]. However, a few review the developmental aspects of the two conditions simultaneously. The current review fills this gap by presenting the developmental aspects that shape later schizotypy and suspiciousness in adulthood and the initial evidence of these phenomena in children and adolescents. We argue that a developmental perspective can extend our understanding of the etiology of schizophrenia and improve the identification of windows of opportunity for preventative or therapeutic interventions. This review includes both published and works under review on childhood schizotypy and suspiciousness that examine the assessments, developmental causal factors, treatments, and interventions before concluding with an overview of the future directions.AssessmentsClinical Interviews, Questionnaires, and Virtual RealitySchizotypal personality disorder and paranoia are commonly assessed by both categorical and dimensional approaches. Taking into account an individual’s personal and medical history, a clinician or mental health profession will administer the SCAN 2.1 (Schedules for Clinical Assessment in Neuropsychiatry by the WHO) or the SCID-5 (Structured Clinical Interview for the DSM-5). Both are semi-structured interviews to systematically determine the extent to which an individual qualifies for a mental disorder. The SCID-5 provides a current and lifetime assessment for schizophrenia and psychotic disorders, often administered in conjunction with self-report questionnaires.Complementing the categorical approach, self-report questionnaires measure dimensional aspects of schizotypy. The Schizotypal Personality Questionnaire (SPQ; [14]) is one of the most widely used measures of schizotypy. It is modeled on the DSM-III-R clinical diagnosis of schizotypy, capturing a well-replicated stable 3-factor structure using 74 yes/no items [15]. The SPQ has high internal consistency (α = 0.91), test-retest reliability (r = .82), convergent validity (r = .59 to .81), discriminant validity, criterion validity with the SCID-II (r = .63 and .68) [16]. A shorter 22-item version is also available (SPQ-B; [17]) and recently confirmed to be psychometrically robust and valid across 14 international samples of 16 to 68 year olds (n = 10,711, omega coefficient = 0.86 to 0.92) [18••]. As both the SPQ and SPQ-B are intended for adults, an equivalent reliable 22-item version SPQ-C with minor modifications is available for children (α = 0.91; [19•]). The three-factor structure of schizotypy is found to be stable across time and instrument for the SPQ [15] and SPQ-B [20], international populations of psychiatric patients [21–24], community adults [25–27], and adolescents [19•, 28] and is invariant across gender, religion, ethnicity, and social backgrounds [26, 29]. The SPQ and its subsequent brief versions are psychometrically robust, where a higher score often reflects greater neurobiological and genetic vulnerabilities [30, 31], thus offering researchers a tool to assess the etiology of schizotypy across development.Commonly used adult measures of paranoia range from 18- to 40-item Likert-scale self-reports and interview schedules assessing the frequency, persistence, levels of conviction and distress, and the severity of the persecutory delusions, where a higher score reflects greater distress on the dimension. A notable feature of these adult instruments is reference to time-span (e.g., “over the past year…,” “in the last week…”), which is often difficult for children to comprehend. Newer childhood measures of suspiciousness have dropped such references to time span. In one of the first child-appropriate dimensional measure of childhood suspiciousness—the Social Mistrust Scale (SMS: [5••])—the suspicion is referenced with school and home environments to assist in children’s recall and the questions kept brief. Validity studies of the SMS are growing in number and have thus far demonstrated good psychometric properties across ages (8 to 18 years alpha = 0.65 to 0.83), cultures (China, Hong Kong, and the UK), and instruments (i.e., convergence with the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale, r = .29 to .32).Complementing both interviews and questionnaires is virtual reality (VR) technology, which has received much research and clinical attention in psychiatry as it is seen as an effective experimental tool for symptom verification and treating mental health conditions in adult patients [32•]. In particular, VR has been applied as an assessment and treatment tool for patients with persecutory delusions. To date, there have been 44 VR studies on schizophrenia, of which 15 concern the assessment of paranoia, while six use VR as a treatment [33]. In the latest intervention study, Freeman et al.’ [34••] found large effects (d = 1.3) for VR cognitive therapy compared to VR exposure therapy in reducing delusions and distress in real-world situations. However, the sample was small (n = 30 patients) and researchers were not blind to participant’s treatment assignment.While virtual reality technology is used alongside traditional measures of paranoia (i.e., questionnaires and clinical interviews) to triangulate findings, VR by itself has several advantages. One prevailing challenge for paranoia research, which VR is able to overcome, is whether or not an individual’s delusion is genuine or unfounded. VR has clear advantages in providing live moment-to-moment assessments of paranoia by engaging the individual with a socially controlled computer-rendered environment with computer characters (e.g., London tube ride). By asking what the individual perceives of the avatars in the simulation, the researcher can gauge the extent to which a response or reaction to a benign avatar is hostile or neutral. A further advantage of the controlled VR environment lies in intervention. VR studies on adult patients with paranoia support the use of VR cognitive therapy in treating persecutory delusions. Through VR, researchers are able to repeatedly test and identify the environmental factors that trigger suspicions, in order to gradually modify the environment to help an individual change and better manage their hostile interpretations over time [34••]. Whether or not virtual therapy is effective in symptom identification and treatment in community population and youths is yet to be investigated.In summary, the technological advancement in VR and the development of new child-appropriate assessments add to the field by refining existing assessments through the triangulation of different sources of data. Though it remains to be seen whether virtual assessments and therapies may be helpful for assessing attenuated symptoms in younger populations, these advancements open up new developmental research possibilities for researchers to assess large groups of young people in normative samples. These efforts together help identify windows of opportunity for preventative and therapeutic interventions early in child development.CausesThe causes of schizotypal personality disorder and suspiciousness are complex. Empirical evidence suggests that there is no single factor responsible but that a multitude of interacting biological, social, and psychological factors are important considerations. We discuss these in turn below.Psychosocial Influences and Environmental AdversityAccording to evidence from cross-sectional and prospective studies using both self-report and official records, persons high in schizotypy and individuals with psychotic-like symptoms are more likely to report a history of child abuse, poor parental bonding and attachment, and trauma (including bullying and post-traumatic disorder) compared with controls [35–40]. A recent systematic review of cross-sectional, prospective, and retrospective studies (n = 25) has documented a strong association between early childhood trauma and later schizotypy and suspiciousness (odds ratio range = 2.01 to 4.15), adjusting for basic demographics [41]. There is some evidence for emotional abuse, neglect, and stressful childhood events including bullying being especially strong predictors of schizotypy; however, on the whole, differential effects of trauma were not found. The ALSPAC prospective cohort study (n = 6437) found that 8- and 10-year-olds identified as victims of bullying reported significantly more psychotic symptoms at age 12 years (odds ratio = 1.94) and with even stronger associations when victimization experience was chronic and severe (odds ratio = 4.6). This finding was independent of prior psychopathology, cognitive functioning, and family adversity.Prospective studies of attachment converge on the finding that poor parental bonding determined by a child showing great emotional distress (anxious attachment) or little distress avoidant attachment) in the absence of an attachment figure has been differentially linked with positive schizotypy and both positive and negative schizotypy, respectively [42]. In a systematic review of 22 studies of attachment and schizophrenia, Gumley et al. [43] found small to moderate effects between attachment insecurity and an increase in positive and negative symptoms of schizophrenia. However, there is a general consensus that study methodologies are heterogeneous with small samples and more longitudinal studies tracking the development beyond the early years of development are needed to establish long-term effects into adulthood.In the maltreatment literature, neglect appears to be central in the development of schizotypy. In particular, victims of physical neglect have a 4.9-fold increase in SPD [44]. In one of the few prospective longitudinal child health studies in Mauritius, children being left “home alone” at age 3 years (n = 34) were compared to children cared for by siblings/relatives (n = 222) and children cared for by their mothers (n = 1498). Children left home alone scored significantly higher levels of psychotic symptoms and conduct disorder at age 17 years and schizotypy and crime at age 23 years accounting for social adversity and ethnicity (Wong KK, Raine A, &amp; Venables P (under review). Being left home alone at age three years is associated with increased schizotypy and antisocial behavior at ages 17 and 23 years.)Why do psychosocial factors affect the development of schizotypal symptoms? There is some speculation that early abuse, neglect, and stress may result in structural and functional brain differences that give rise to schizotypal symptoms [45].Neurocognitive Functions and Brain AnatomyRecent studies have examined neurocognitive impairments in schizotypy and suspiciousness. A review of these studies reveals that schizotypal individuals have neurocognitive impairments in executive functions, sustained attention, working memory, verbal and spatial learning and memory, latent inhibition, negative priming, hemisphere asymmetry, verbal fluency, and motor skills [6•, 9].In paranoia, arguably the most well replicated finding is the stable characteristic of fast thinking (“jumping-to-conclusions”) and belief inflexibility where patients high in delusions make decisions based on limited information [46–48]. This abnormal reasoning bias is assessed using an established probabilistic reasoning task, the Beads Task [49], which has repeatedly distinguished patients with persecutory delusions from normal controls. However, the link between jumping-to-conclusions and suspicious young adults [50] and younger populations in the general population is weaker and less consistent [51, 52]. A comprehensive review of functional neuroimaging and neural network studies [53••], though predominantly cross-sectional in design, supports the jumping-to-conclusions cognitive deficit in patients with delusions and a presence of a reality distortion cluster of psychotic symptoms associated with various brain abnormalities (cerebral blood flow in the left lateral prefrontal cortex, ventral striatum, superior temporal gyrus, and parahippocampal region). There remains a gap in the literature as there is no longitudinal imaging study to date examining attributional bias or jumping-to-conclusion biases. A recent structural and functional brain imaging study of patients with persecutory delusions matched with controls found that patients showed brain abnormalities (reduced medial frontal/anterior cingulate cortex) in regions associated with the pathogenesis of delusions [54]. However, the study sample size was small (n = 22), patients with different subtypes of delusions were grouped together, and thus findings deserve to be replicated.Brain-imaging studies of SPD report increased prefrontal activation as measured by EEG and the performance of schizotypals tends to fall between the range of normal controls and schizophrenia patients [55], though more recent studies suggest that schizotypals are more similar to controls but outperforms the schizophrenic patient group [56]. However, a few studies using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) and near-infrared optical spectroscopy (NIRS) methods have also documented enhanced creativity and divergent thinking in individuals high in schizotypy compared with low schizotypy [57] and in schizotypals compared to schizophrenics and healthy controls [58], which has been attributed to increased right hemisphere functioning and right prefrontal activation. Schizotypals perform poorly on facial emotional recognition tasks, struggle to label positive emotions, fail to think in another person’s perspective as assessed using theory of mind tasks, and over-respond to hostile/threatening stimuli [59, 60]. In terms of brain structure, a review of 17 studies found that SPD patients have abnormalities paralleling those found in schizophrenia patients in the superior temporal gyrus, parahippocampus, corpus callosum, thalamus, and septum pellucidum, as well as in total cerebrospinal fluid volume [61]. However, unlike schizophrenic patients, SPD patients showed normal functioning in the medial temporal lobes. On balance, the imaging findings suggest that SPD represents a milder form of disease along the schizophrenia continuum.Molecular GeneticsThe identification of endophenotypes, the separation of behavioral symptoms into identifiable phenotypes with clear genetic connections, is a commonly used method to examine the underlying genetic causes of schizophrenia. A recent study investigated four candidate genes (DTNBP1, NRG1, DAOA/G32, and DAAO) common to schizophrenia and schizotypy and found DTNBP1, SNPs, rs2619522, and rs760761 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) to be associated with a decrease in positive and paranoid schizotypy scores [62•]. In particular, DAAO haplotype variability was noted on negative and disorganization schizotypy while DTNBP1 haplotype was associated with paranoid schizotypy.The genetic studies on paranoia are more sparse. Only recently has the heritability estimates of paranoia been estimated in a large sample of twin pairs (N = 5059) from England and Wales, finding that 50% of the variability in paranoia in the general population is due to genes [63••]. Another recent finding from a Chinese sample showed moderate heritability in 2000 younger twin pairs (25 to 39%) [64•]. While some progress has been made to investigate genetic influences on paranoia, identifying the exact gene has proved more challenging and has yet to be conducted.NutritionPoor prenatal nutrition has been associated with schizophrenia spectrum disorders, specifically with schizotypal traits, in the Netherlands and China. In a sample of Mauritian children, Venables and Raine [65] established that poor nutrition at age 3 years (defined as anemia and stunting) was related to schizotypal traits at age 23 years—a relationship that was mediated by cognitive functioning (e.g., Verbal IQ and performance IQ) at age 11 years.Childhood Correlates of Schizotypy and SuspiciousnessOnly a handful of studies to date have assessed schizotypy and suspiciousness in children and adolescents, and so childhood correlates are an underexplored area of research. In a large survey of the UK and Hong Kong schoolchildren (aged 8 to 14 years), children with high levels of suspiciousness reported significantly higher levels of anxiety, aggression, callous-unemotional traits, and lower levels of self-esteem compared with their non-suspicious peers, while self-reported suspicions were corroborated by peer ratings but not teacher or parent ratings, whether children’s suspicions are genuine or unfounded have yet to be tested [5••]. A short follow-up study on the same group of the suspicious and non-suspicious children found that self-reported persistent bullying experiences and hostile attributional biases predicted group membership (Wong, K. K. et al, unpublished data). A prospective study of paranoia in young children and adolescents: the role of hostile attributional bias and peer victimization.). Thematic analysis of the same sample confirmed that children with high levels of suspiciousness further identified children’s worries about their peers, which were corroborated by peer-rated suspiciousness (Wong KK (submitted). A qualitative study of childhood suspiciousness.).Treatment and InterventionsAs the causes of schizotypal personality disorder are unclear, its treatment has also been understudied. One line of research extending the literature on brain deficiencies using carefully designed stratified randomized controlled trial showed that early environmental enrichment consisting of physical exercise, cognitive stimulation, and nutritional enhancement at 3–5 years both improved brain functioning at 11 years and reduced schizotypy at ages 17 and 23 years [66•]. This suggests that omega-3 as a nutritional supplementation could be helpful in reducing schizotypal traits in the long-run.Recent published and ongoing randomized controlled (RCT) experiments on persecutory delusions targeting the cognitive causes of persecutory delusions have been promising. One of the first RCTs on persecutory delusions showed that six sessions of worry reduction cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) intervention plus standard care completed over 8 weeks was better than standard care alone at reducing baseline worries and persecutory delusions at 8 weeks and follow-up at 24 weeks [67]. In another RCT, 30 patients were randomized into virtual CBT versus treatment as usual (TAU) and found that virtual CBT was as successful in reducing paranoid delusions overtime. While this study has a small sample and researchers were not blinded to patients’ treatment group, other ongoing RCT randomizing 360 patients into TAU and SlowMo intervention (a digital therapy targeting inflexible thinking in paranoia) or TAU alone is currently being investigated [68••].Summary and Future DirectionsOur understanding of the etiology of schizotypy and suspiciousness has made significant progress over the years. Still, it is clear that more mediation analyses of prospective longitudinal studies and brain imaging studies (especially in delusions research), coupled with carefully designed randomized controlled trials, are needed to elucidate the etiology of schizotypy, suspiciousness, and ultimately schizophrenia. Though there have been some promising results from intervention studies, the evidence thus far stems largely from adult patients and so extending this line of work developmentally to younger populations may be effective in informing the development of early preventative interventions. More RCTs with longer follow-up may also be helpful in assessing the duration of intervention effects beyond the average follow-up period of an RCT. Finally, virtual reality as a non-invasive but immersive tool to assess and intervene on patients’ paranoid thoughts and other mental disorders holds great potential.This article is part of the Topical Collection on Personality and Impulse Control DisordersAcknowledgementsDr. Keri Wong is supported by the Cambridge Clare Hall Betty Behrens Research Fellowship.Compliance with Ethical StandardsConflict of InterestThe authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.Human and Animal Rights and Informed ConsentThis article does not contain any studies with human or animal subjects performed by any of the authors.ReferencesPapers of particular interest, published recently, have been highlighted as: • Of importance •• Of major importance1.RosellDRFuttermanSEMcMasterASieverLJSchizotypal personality disorder: a current reviewCurr Psychiatry Rep201416745210.1007/s11920-014-0452-1248282842.FreemanDGaretyPAComments on the content of persecutory delusions: does the definition need clarification?Br J Clin Psychol200039440741410.1348/014466500163400111074943.RonaldASieradzkaDCardnoAGHaworthCMMcGuirePFreemanDCharacterization of psychotic experiences in adolescence using the specific psychotic experiences questionnaire: findings from a study of 5000 16-year-old twinsSchizophr Bull201340486887710.1093/schbul/sbt106240625934.FreemanDDelusions in the nonclinical populationCurr Psychiatry Reports20068319120410.1007/s11920-006-0023-15.•• Wong, K. K., Freeman, D., &amp; Hughes, C. (2014). Suspicious young minds: paranoia and mistrust in 8-to 14-year-olds in the UK and Hong Kong. Br J Psychiatr, bjp-bp. The first large-scale study to develop a dimensional measure of suspiciousness in children and adolescents in the general population.6.Barrantes-VidalNGrantPKwapilTRThe role of schizotypy in the study of the etiology of schizophrenia spectrum disordersSchizophrenia Bull201541suppl_2S408S41610.1093/schbul/sbu1917.BebbingtonPEMcBrideOSteelCKuipersERadovanovičMBrughaTThe structure of paranoia in the general populationBr J Psychiatr2013202641942710.1192/bjp.bp.112.1190328.CombsDRPennDLFenigsteinAEthnic differences in sub-clinical paranoia: an expansion of norms for the paranoia scaleCult Divers Ethn Minor Psychol20028324825610.1037/1099-9809.8.3.2489.RaineASchizotypal personality: neurodevelopmental and psychosocial trajectoriesAnnu Rev Clin Psychol20062129132610.1146/annurev.clinpsy.2.022305.0953181771607210.MataIGilvarryCMJonesPBLewisSWMurrayRMShamPCSchizotypal personality traits in nonpsychotic relatives are associated with positive symptoms in psychotic probandsSchizophr Bull200329227328310.1093/oxfordjournals.schbul.a0070041455250311.Van OsJLinscottRJMyin-GermeysIDelespaulPKrabbendamLA systematic review and meta-analysis of the psychosis continuum: evidence for a psychosis proneness–persistence–impairment model of psychotic disorderPsychol Med200939217919510.1017/S00332917080038141860604712.DebbanéMBarrantes-VidalNSchizotypy from a developmental perspectiveSchizophrenia Bull201441suppl_2S386S39513.Kwapil TR, Barrantes-Vidal N. Schizotypal personality disorder: an integrative review. The Oxford handbook of personality disorders. 2012. p. 437–477.14.RaineAThe SPQ: a scale for the assessment of schizotypal personality based on DSM-III-R criteriaSchizophr Bull199117455556410.1093/schbul/17.4.555180534915.VenablesPHRaineAThe stability of schizotypy across time and instrumentsPsychiatry Res2015228358559010.1016/j.psychres.2015.05.0472609965916.Fonseca-Pedrero E, Debbané M, Ortuño-Sierra J, Chan RCK, Cicero DC, Zhang LC, et al. The structure of schizotypal personality traits: a cross-national study. Psychol Med. 2017:1–12.17.Raine A, Lencz T, Benishay DS. Schizotypal personality and skin conductance orienting. Schizotypal Pers. 1995:219–49. 10.1017/CBO9780511759031.011.18.•• Fonseca-Pedrero, E., Ortuño-Sierra, J., Lucas-Molina, B., Debbané, M., Chan, R. C., Cicero, D. C, ... &amp; Kwapil, T. (2017). Brief assessment of schizotypal traits: a multinational study. Schizophrenia Res.The largest study to date demonstrating measurement invariance and structural equivalence of the three-factor model of schizotypy.19.RaineAFungALCLamBYHPeer victimization partially mediates the schizotypy-aggression relationship in children and adolescentsSchizophr Bull201137593794510.1093/schbul/sbr0822179561320.Moreno-IzcoLSánchez-TorresAMLorente-OmeñacaRFañanásLRosaASalvatorePPeraltaVCuestaMJTen-year stability of self-reported schizotypal personality features in patients with psychosis and their healthy siblingsPsychiatry Res2015227228328910.1016/j.psychres.2015.02.0202588209921.AxelrodSRGriloCMSanislowCMcGlashanTHSchizotypal personality questionnaire-brief: factor structure and convergent validity in inpatient adolescentsJ Personal Disord200115216817910.1521/pedi.15.2.168.1921922.BattagliaMCavalliniMCMacciardiFBellodiLThe structure of DSM-III-R schizotypal personality disorder diagnosed by direct interviewsSchizophr Bull1997231839210.1093/schbul/23.1.83905011523.CalkinsMECurtisCEGroveWMIaconoWGMultiple dimensions of schizotypy in first degree biological relatives of schizophrenia patientsSchizophr Bull200430231732510.1093/oxfordjournals.schbul.a0070811527904924.VollemaMGHoijtinkHThe multidimensionality of self-report schizotypy in a psychiatric population: an analysis using multidimensional Rasch modelsSchizophr Bull200026356557510.1093/oxfordjournals.schbul.a0334781099339825.RaineAReynoldsCLenczTScerboATriphonNKimDCognitive-perceptual, interpersonal, and disorganized features of schizotypal personalitySchizophr Bull199420119120110.1093/schbul/20.1.191819741526.ReynoldsCARaineAMellingenKVenablesPHMednickSAThree-factor model of schizotypal personality: invariance across culture, gender, religious affiliation, family adversity, and psychopathologySchizophr Bull200026360361810.1093/oxfordjournals.schbul.a0334811099340127.RossiADaneluzzoESchizotypal dimensions in normals and schizophrenic patients: a comparison with other clinical samplesSchizophr Res2002541–2677510.1016/S0920-9964(01)00353-X1185398028.FossatiARaineACarrettaILeonardiBMaffeiCThe three-factor model of schizotypal personality: invariance across age and genderPersonal Individ Differ20033551007101910.1016/S0191-8869(02)00314-829.Ortuño-SierraJBadoudDKnechtFPainoMEliezSFonseca-PedreroEDebbanéMTesting measurement invariance of the Schizotypal Personality Questionnaire-Brief scores across Spanish and Swiss adolescentsPLoS One2013812e8204110.1371/journal.pone.00820412434918030.AvramopoulosDStefanisNCHantoumiISmyrnisNEvdokimidisIStefanisCNHigher scores of self reported schizotypy in healthy young males carrying the COMT high activity alleleMol Psychiatry20027770671110.1038/sj.mp.40010701219261431.VollemaMGSitskoornMMAppelsMCMKahnRSDoes the schizotypal personality questionnaire reflect the biological–genetic vulnerability to schizophrenia?Schizophr Res2002541394510.1016/S0920-9964(01)00350-41185397732.ValmaggiaLRLatifLKemptonMJRus-CalafellMVirtual reality in the psychological treatment for mental health problems: an systematic review of recent evidencePsychiatry Res201623618919510.1016/j.psychres.2016.01.0152679512933.Freeman D, Reeve S, Robinson A, Ehlers A, Clark D, Spanlang B, et al. Virtual reality in the assessment, understanding, and treatment of mental health disorders. Psychol Med. 2017:1–8.34.•• Freeman, D., Bradley, J., Antley, A., Bourke, E., DeWeever, N., Evans, N., … &amp; Slater, M. (2016). Virtual reality in the treatment of persecutory delusions: randomised controlled experimental study testing how to reduce delusional conviction. Br J Psychiatr, bjp-bp. The first intervention study showing that virtual reality immersion can reduce persecutory delusions in patients.35.ArseneaultLCannonMFisherHLPolanczykGMoffittTECaspiAChildhood trauma and children's emerging psychotic symptoms: a genetically sensitive longitudinal cohort studyAm J Psychiatr20111681657210.1176/appi.ajp.2010.100405672095246036.CutajarMCMullenPEOgloffJRThomasSDWellsDLSpataroJSchizophrenia and other psychotic disorders in a cohort of sexually abused childrenArch Gen Psychiatry201067111114111910.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.1472104161237.KelleherIHarleyMLynchFArseneaultLFitzpatrickCCannonMAssociations between childhood trauma, bullying and psychotic symptoms among a school-based adolescent sampleBr J Psychiatry2008193537838210.1192/bjp.bp.108.0495361897831738.SchreierAWolkeDThomasKHorwoodJHollisCGunnellDProspective study of peer victimization in childhood and psychotic symptoms in a nonclinical population at age 12 yearsArch Gen Psychiatry200966552753610.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.231941471239.SchürhoffFLaguerreAFisherHEtainBMéaryASoussyCSzökeALeboyerMSelf-reported childhood trauma correlates with schizotypal measures in schizophrenia but not bipolar pedigreesPsychol Med200939336537010.1017/S00332917080039051858874340.VareseFSmeetsFDrukkerMLieverseRLatasterTViechtbauerWReadJvan OsJBentallRPChildhood adversities increase the risk of psychosis: a meta-analysis of patient-control, prospective-and cross-sectional cohort studiesSchizophr Bull201238466167110.1093/schbul/sbs0502246148441.VelikonjaTFisherHLMasonOJohnsonSChildhood trauma and schizotypy: a systematic literature reviewPsychol Med201545594796310.1017/S00332917140020862527315142.Korver-NiebergNBerryKMeijerCJHaanLAdult attachment and psychotic phenomenology in clinical and non-clinical samples: a systematic reviewPsychol Psychother Theory Res Pract201487212715410.1111/papt.1201043.GumleyAITaylorHEFSchwannauerMMacBethAA systematic review of attachment and psychosis: measurement, construct validity and outcomesActa Psychiatr Scand2014129425727410.1111/acps.121722383464744.JohnsonJGSmailesEMCohenPBrownJBernsteinDPAssociations between four types of childhood neglect and personality disorder symptoms during adolescence and early adulthood: findings of a community-based longitudinal studyJ Personal Disord200014217118710.1521/pedi.2000.14.2.17145.CannonTDMednickSAParnasJSchulsingerFPraestholmJVestergaardADevelopmental brain abnormalities in the offspring of schizophrenic mothers: II. Structural brain characteristics of schizophrenia and schizotypal personality disorderArch Gen Psychiatry1994511295596210.1001/archpsyc.1994.03950120027006797988446.GaretyPWallerHEmsleyRJolleySKuipersEBebbingtonPDunnGFowlerDHardyAFreemanDCognitive mechanisms of change in delusions: an experimental investigation targeting reasoning to effect change in paranoiaSchizophr Bull201441240041010.1093/schbul/sbu1032505365047.MoritzSWoodwardTSJumping to conclusions in delusional and non-delusional schizophrenic patientsBr J Clin Psychol200544219320710.1348/014466505X356781600465448.PetersEGaretyPCognitive functioning in delusions: a longitudinal analysisBehav Res Ther200644448151410.1016/j.brat.2005.03.0081591354449.GaretyPAFreemanDJolleySDunnGBebbingtonPEFowlerDGKuipersEDudleyRReasoning, emotions, and delusional conviction in psychosisJ Abnorm Psychol2005114337338410.1037/0021-843X.114.3.3731611757450.FreemanDPughKGaretyPJumping to conclusions and paranoid ideation in the general populationSchizophr Res2008102125426010.1016/j.schres.2008.03.0201844289851.BirdJCWaiteFRowsellEFergussonECFreemanDCognitive, affective, and social factors maintaining paranoia in adolescents with mental health problems: a longitudinal studyPsychiatry Res2017257343910.1016/j.psychres.2017.07.0232871566652.Falcone MA, Murray RM, Wiffen BDR, O’Connor JA, Russo M, Kolliakou A, et al. Jumping to conclusions, neuropsychological functioning, and delusional beliefs in first episode psychosis. Schizophr Bull. 2014:1–8.53.BlackwoodNJHowardRJBentallRPMurrayRMCognitive neuropsychiatric models of persecutory delusionsAm J Psychiatr2001158452753910.1176/appi.ajp.158.4.5271128268554.VicensVRaduaJSalvadorRAnguera-CamósMCanales-RodríguezEJSarróSMaristanyTMcKennaPJPomarol-ClotetEStructural and functional brain changes in delusional disorderBr J Psychiatry2016208215315910.1192/bjp.bp.114.1590872638295555.Trestman, R. L., Horvath, T., Kalus, O., Peterson, A. E., Coccaro, E., Mitropoulou, V., ... &amp; Siever, L. J. (1996). Event-related potentials in schizotypal personality disorder. J Neuropsychiatr Clin Neurosci.56.VohsJLHetrickWPKieffaberPDBodkinsMBismarkAShekharAO'donnellBFVisual event-related potentials in schizotypal personality disorder and schizophreniaJ Abnorm Psychol2008117111913110.1037/0021-843X.117.1.1191826649057.FinkAWeberBKoschutnigKBenedekMReishoferGEbnerFPapousekIWeissEMCreativity and schizotypy from the neuroscience perspectiveCogn Affect Behav Neurosci201414137838710.3758/s13415-013-0210-62402279358.Folley BS, Park S. Verbal creativity and schizotypal personality in relation to prefrontal hemispheric laterality: A behavioral and near-infrared optical imaging study. Schizophrenia research. 2005;80(2), 271–282.59.DickeyCCPanychLPVoglmaierMMNiznikiewiczMATerryDPMurphyCZacksRShentonMEMcCarleyRWFacial emotion recognition and facial affect display in schizotypal personality disorderSchizophr Res2011131124224910.1016/j.schres.2011.04.0202164055760.UonoSSatoWToichiMExaggerated perception of facial expressions is increased in individuals with schizotypal traitsSci Rep2015511179510.1038/srep117952613508161.DickeyCCMcCarleyRWShentonMEThe brain in schizotypal personality disorder: a review of structural MRI and CT findingsHarvard Rev Psychiatr200210111510.1080/1067322021620162.StefanisNCTrikalinosTAAvramopoulosDSmyrnisNEvdokimidisINtzaniEEImpact of schizophrenia candidate genes on schizotypy and cognitive endophenotypes at the population levelBiol Psychiatry200762778479210.1016/j.biopsych.2006.11.0151733694663.ZavosHMFreemanDHaworthCMMcGuirePPlominRCardnoAGRonaldAConsistent etiology of severe, frequent psychotic experiences and milder, less frequent manifestations: a twin study of specific psychotic experiences in adolescenceJAMA Psychiatry20147191049105710.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.9942507579964.• Zhou, H.Y., Wong, K.K., Shi, L.J., Cui, X.L., Qian, Y., Du, Y.S., Lui, S.S.Y., Luo, X.R., Cheung, E.F.C., &amp; Chan, R.C.K. (under review). Suspicious young minds: a replication study of mistrust in 8- to 14-year-olds in 2,094 Chinese twin-pairs.65.VenablesPHRaineAPoor nutrition at age 3 and schizotypal personality at age 23: the mediating role of age 11 cognitive functioningAm J Psychiatr2012169882283010.1176/appi.ajp.2012.110811732277208566.RaineAMellingenKLiuJVenablesPMednickSAEffects of environmental enrichment at ages 3–5 years on schizotypal personality and antisocial behavior at ages 17 and 23 yearsAm J Psychiatr200316091627163510.1176/appi.ajp.160.9.16271294433867.FreemanDDunnGStartupHPughKCordwellJManderHEffects of cognitive behaviour therapy for worry on persecutory delusions in patients with psychosis (WIT): a parallel, single-blind, randomised controlled trial with a mediation analysisLancet Psychiatr20152430510.1016/S2215-0366(15)00039-568.GaretyPAWardTFreemanDFowlerDEmsleyRDunnGSlowMo, a digital therapy targeting reasoning in paranoia, versus treatment as usual in the treatment of people who fear harm from others: study protocol for a randomised controlled trialTrials201718151010.1186/s13063-017-2242-729096681
