<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC PsychiatryBMC PsychiatryBMC Psychiatry1471-244XBioMed CentralLondon44938002614927552810.1186/s12888-015-0528-4Research ArticleThe clinical and cost effectiveness of group art therapy for people with non-psychotic mental health disorders: a systematic review and cost-effectiveness analysisUttleyLesley+44 (0)114 2220782l.uttley@sheffield.ac.ukStevensonMattm.d.stevenson@sheffield.ac.ukScopeAlisona.scope@sheffield.ac.ukRawdinAndrewa.rawdin@sheffield.ac.ukSuttonAntheaa.sutton@sheffield.ac.ukSchool of Health and Related Research (ScHARR), University of Sheffield, Regent Court, 30 Regent Street, Sheffield, S1 4DA UK 77201577201520151515115120151262015© Uttley et al. 2015This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundThe majority of mental health problems are non-psychotic (e.g., depression, anxiety, and phobias). For some people, art therapy may be a more acceptable alternative form of psychological therapy than standard forms of treatment, such as talking therapies. This study was part of a health technology assessment commissioned by the National Institute for Health Research, UK and aimed to systematically appraise the clinical and cost-effective evidence for art therapy for people with non-psychotic mental health disorders.MethodsComprehensive literature searches for studies examining art therapy in populations with non-psychotic mental health disorders were performed in May 2013. A quantitative systematic review of clinical effectiveness and a systematic review of studies evaluating the cost-effectiveness of group art therapy were conducted.ResultsEleven randomised controlled trials were included (533 patients). Meta-analysis was not possible due to clinical heterogeneity and insufficient comparable data on outcome measures across studies. The control groups varied between studies but included: no treatment/wait-list, attention placebo controls and psychological therapy comparators. Art therapy was associated with significant positive changes relative to the control group in mental health symptoms in 7 of the 11 studies. A de novo model was constructed and populated with data identified from the clinical review. Scenario analyses were conducted allowing comparisons of group art therapy with wait-list control and group art therapy with group verbal therapy. Group art-therapy appeared cost-effective compared with wait-list control with high certainty although generalisability to the target population was unclear; group verbal therapy appeared more cost-effective than art therapy but there was considerable uncertainty and a sizeable probability that art therapy was more cost effective.ConclusionsFrom the limited available evidence art therapy was associated with positive effects compared with control in a number of studies in patients with different clinical profiles. The included trials were generally of poor quality and are therefore likely to be at high risk of bias. Art therapy appeared to be cost-effective versus wait-list but further studies are needed to confirm this finding in the target population. There was insufficient evidence to make an informed comparison of the cost-effectiveness of group art therapy with group verbal therapy.Trial registrationHTA project no. 12/27/16; PROSPERO registration no. CRD42013003957.KeywordsArt therapyMental health disordersPsychological therapySystematic reviewHealth technology assessmentCost-effectivenessissue-copyright-statement© tbc 2015<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Search methods</title><p>Comprehensive literature searches were used to inform the clinical and cost-effectiveness reviews. A search strategy was developed to identify reviews, randomised controlled trials (RCTs), economic evaluations and all other study types relating to art therapy. Search terms were restricted to “art therapy” or “art therap$”. Methodological search filters were applied where appropriate. No other search limitations were used and all databases were searched from inception to present. Searches were conducted from May–July 2013.</p><p>Databases searched were: MEDLINE and MEDLINE in Process &amp; Other Non-Indexed citations; EMBASE; Cochrane Library; Science Citation Index; Social Sciences Citation Index; CINAHL: Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health Literature; PsycINFO; AMED: Allied and Complementary Medicine; and ASSIA: Applied Social Sciences Index and Abstracts. All resources were searched from inception to present.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Clinical effectiveness review methods</title><p>Screening of records, study selection, and data extraction were performed by one assessor and checked by a second assessor. All studies identified for inclusion at abstract stage were obtained in full text for more detailed appraisal. Non-English studies were translated and included if relevant. Quality assessment of included studies was performed independently by two reviewers using quality assessment criteria adapted from the Cochrane risk of bias, CRD guidance, and CASP checklists to develop a modified tool to allow comprehensive and relevant quality assessment for the included trials.</p><p>The inclusion and exclusion criteria for the clinical effectiveness review are documented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for the systematic review</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Included</th><th>Excluded</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Population</td><td rowspan="2">Non-psychotic clinical samples</td><td>People with psychosis</td></tr><tr><td>Healthy samples</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Intervention</td><td rowspan="2"><sup>a</sup>Group art therapy as might be delivered in the NHS</td><td>Other “arts therapies” including drama; music; and dance</td></tr><tr><td>Play therapy</td></tr><tr><td>Comparator</td><td>Any including: interventions including an RCT containing art therapy; treatment as usual; waiting list; attention placebo; or other psychological therapy</td><td>None</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Outcomes</td><td>Primary: treatment effectiveness; response as determined by changes in mental health rating scales;</td><td rowspan="2">Outcomes focussed on interpretation of the art work itself, not the participant</td></tr><tr><td>Secondary: Related clinical or quality of life outcomes</td></tr><tr><td>Studies</td><td>Randomised controlled trials</td><td>Non-randomised controlled studies</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Whilst the full health technology assessment (Uttley et al., in press) included studies of both individual and group art therapy, only studies of group art therapy are included in this paper</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Mathematical modelling methods</title><p><italic>A de novo</italic> mathematical model was constructed. Due to the nature of the study question it was deemed that a complex model was not required, and that a simple model which could more clearly demonstrate the impact of key drivers of the cost effectiveness ratio would be sufficient. As such, an area under the curve model was developed to estimate the gain in utility with the following assumptions in the base case.<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>That the maximum treatment effect would be associated with the time at which treatment ended.</p></list-item><list-item><p>That there would be a linear increase in treatment effect, from zero at baseline to the maximum at the time at which treatment ended.</p></list-item><list-item><p>That there would be a residual effect of treatment with a linear decline in benefit until there was zero benefit at 52 weeks.</p></list-item><list-item><p>That given the short assumed duration of benefit, discounting of future costs and benefits was not necessary.</p></list-item></list></p><p>The rationale for choosing 52 weeks as the base case duration of residual benefit was based on a number of relevant references. Discussing data in Nicholson and Berman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and in Lambert and Ogles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], Cooper wrote that ‘findings from the empirical research are fairly clear: clients, on average, do not tend to improve once their therapy is over...., but equally they do not tend to deteriorate rapidly’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. More recent data provided in Sportel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], indicate that where Cognitive Bias Modification and Cognitive Behavioural Group Training provided larger decreases in an outcome measure (the Spielberger Test Anxiety Inventory) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] the effect had not entirely waned at twelve month follow-up. This may be generalisable to other forms of successful psychological therapy, and conservatively we elected to assume that all benefit had dissipated at 52 weeks post treatment, although a longer period of 104 weeks was used in sensitivity analyses.</p><p>The conceptual model used to calculate the utility gain across time is shown in graphical form in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. In this figure it is assumed that there is a gain in utility of 0.0780 at week 8. The area under the curve was then translated in quality adjusted life years (QALYs) assuming 52.18 weeks per year. The QALY considers both duration and quality of life: a person living 10 years at a utility of 0.5 would accrue 5.0 undiscounted QALYs whilst a person living 8 years with a utility of 0.8 would accrue 6.4 undiscounted QALYs.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>An illustration of the conceptual model of utility</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12888_2015_528_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e567"/></fig></p></sec></sec>AbbreviationsCRDCentre for Reviews and Dissemination–University of YorkCASPCritical Appraisal Skills ProgrammeCIConfidence intervalEQ-5DEuroQol five-dimension health instrumentGSIGlobal severity indexNHSNational Health ServiceNICENational Institute for Health and Care ExcellenceNRNot reportedPRISMAPreferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analysesPSAProbabilistic sensitivity analysisQALYQuality-adjusted life-yearQoLQuality of lifeRCTRandomised controlled trialSCL-90-RSymptoms checklist revisedSF-36Medical outcomes short form (36) health surveyUKUnited KingdomCompeting interestsThe authors declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsLU and MS drafted the manuscript. LU and AS undertook the clinical effectiveness review. AJS performed the literature searches. MS and AR carried out the economic evaluation. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.This project was funded by the UK National Institute for Health Research Health Technology Assessment (NIHR HTA no. 12.27.16) Programme and commissioned on behalf of NICE. It will be published in full in the Health Technology Assessment journal series. Visit the HTA Programme website for more details http://www.nets.nihr.ac.uk/programmes/hta.The authors would like to acknowledge Eva Kaltenthaler, John Stevens, Kim Dent-Brown, Elizabeth Taylor Buck and Chris Wood for their contributions to the full HTA report. The views and opinions expressed therein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of the HTA Programme, NICE, NIHR, NHS or the Department of Health.References1.WHO. The global burden of disease: World Health Organization, Denmark; 2004. 2008.2.Department of HealthNo health without mental health: a cross government mental health outcomes strategy for people of all ages20143.LayardRHow mental illness loses out in the NHS a report by the Centre for Economic Performance’s Mental Health Policy Group. CEP special papers2012264.ReynoldsMWNaborsLQuinlanAThe effectiveness of art therapy: does it work?Art Therapy20001732071310.1080/07421656.2000.101297065.Ruddy R, Milnes D. Art therapy for schizophrenia or schizophrenia-like illnesses. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009;1:1-30.6.SlaytonSCD’ArcherJKaplanFOutcome studies on the efficacy of art therapy: a review of findingsArt Therapy20102731081810.1080/07421656.2010.101296607.GilroyAArt therapy, research and evidence-based practice20068.NicholsonRABermanJSIs follow-up necessary in evaluating psychotherapy?Psychol Bull198393226110.1037/0033-2909.93.2.26168444739.Lambert MJ. Bergin and Garfield’s handbook of psychotherapy and behavior change. 2013;1-256.10.Cooper M. Essential research findings in counselling and psychotherapy: the facts are friendly. 2008;1-32.11.SportelBde HulluEde JongPNautaMCognitive bias modification versus CBT in reducing adolescent social anxiety: a randomized controlled trialPLoS One201385e6435510.1371/journal.pone.00643552369120312.Van der PloegHHandleiding bij de Examen/Toets attitude vragenlijst ETAV: Een nederlandstalige bewerking van de spielberger test anxiety inventory [A Dutch version of the Spielberger Test Anxiety Inventory TAI]. Swets En Zeitlinger199813.BroomeMEMaiklerVKelberSBaileyPLeaGAn intervention to increase coping and reduce health care utilization for school-age children and adolescents with sickle cell diseaseJ Natl Black Nurses Assoc20011226141190202314.ThymeKSundinECStahlbergGLindstromBEklofHWibergBThe outcome of short-term psychodynamic art therapy compared to short-term psychodynamic verbal therapy for depressed womenPsychoanal Psychother200732506410.1080/0266873070153561015.Kim SK. A randomized, controlled study of the effects of art therapy on older Korean-Americans’ healthy aging. Arts Psychother. 2013;40(1):158–164 February.16.MontiDAPetersonCKunkelEJHauckWWPequignotERhodesLA randomized, controlled trial of mindfulness-based art therapy (MBAT) for women with cancerPsycho-Oncology20061553637310.1002/pon.9881628844717.MontiDAKashKMKunkelEJBrainardGWinteringNMossASChanges in cerebral blood flow and anxiety associated with an 8-week mindfulness programme in women with breast cancerStress Health201228539740710.1002/smi.24702312955918.Lyshak-StelzerFSingerPSt. JohnPChemtobCMArt therapy for adolescents with posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms: a pilot studyArt Therapy2007244163910.1080/07421656.2007.1012947419.McCaffreyRLiehrPGregersenTNishiokaRGarden walking and art therapy for depression in older adults: a pilot studyRes Gerontol Nurs2011442374210.3928/19404921-20110201-012132329920.RustedJSheppardLWallerDA multi-centre randomized control group trial on the use of art therapy for older people with dementiaGr Analysis200645173610.1177/053331640607144721.GreenwoodHLeachCLucockMNobleRThe process of long-term art therapy: a case study combining artwork and clinical outcomePsychother Res20071755889910.1080/1050330070122755022.National Institute for Health and Care Excellence. Guide to the methods of technology appraisals. National Institute for Health and Care Excellence, London; 2013.23.DakinHReview of studies mapping from quality of life or clinical measures to EQ-5D: an online databaseHealth Qual Life Outcomes20131115110.1186/1477-7525-11-1512401087324.HattoriHHattoriCHokaoCMizushimaKMaseTControlled study on the cognitive and psychological effect of coloring and drawing in mild Alzheimer’s disease patientsGeriatr Gerontol Int2011114431710.1111/j.1447-0594.2011.00698.x2151817025.AraRBrazierJDeriving an Algorthm to convert the eight mean SF-36 Dimension scores into a mean EQ-5D preference-based score from published studies (where patient level data are not available)Value Health20081111314310.1111/j.1524-4733.2008.00352.x1848949526.RowenDBrazierJRobertsRMapping SF-36 onto the EQ-5D index: how reliable is the relationshipHealth Qual Life Outcomes200972710.1186/1477-7525-7-271933587827.DerogatisLSCL-90-R: administration, scoring and procedures manual19943MinneapolisNational Computer Systems, Inc28.CurtisLUnit costs of health and social care 20132013Canterbury, KentPersonal Social Services Research Unit29.BeebeAGelfandEWBenderBA randomized trial to test the effectiveness of art therapy for children with asthmaJ Allergy Clin Immunol20101262263610.1016/j.jaci.2010.03.0192046263230.GussakDThe effectiveness of art therapy in reducing depression in prison populationsInt J Offender Ther Comp Criminol20075144446010.1177/0306624X062941371765214831.MontiDAPetersonCMindfulness-based art therapy: results from a two-year studyPsychiatr Times2004218635
