<?xml version="1.0"?>
Transl PsychiatryTransl PsychiatryTranslational Psychiatry2158-3188Nature Publishing Group4270311tp201413010.1038/tp.2014.13025514753Original ArticleThe functional −1019C/G HTR1A polymorphism and mechanisms of fearHTR1A and fear mechanismsStraubeB1*13ReifA213RichterJ313LuekenU4WeberH3AroltV5JansenA1ZwanzgerP5DomschkeK2PauliP6KonradC15GerlachA L7LangT48FydrichT9AlpersG W10StröhleA11WittmannA11PfleidererB12WittchenH-U4HammA314DeckertJ214KircherT1141Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, Philipps-University Marburg, Marburg, Germany2Department of Psychiatry, Psychosomatics and Psychotherapy, University of Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany3Department of Biological and Clinical Psychology, University of Greifswald, Greifswald, Germany4Institute of Clinical Psychology and Psychotherapy, Technische Universität Dresden, Dresden, Germany5Department of Psychiatry, University of Münster, Münster, Germany6Department of Psychology, University of Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany7Department of Psychology, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany8University of Bremen and Christoph-Dornier Foundation for Clinical Psychology, Bremen, Germany9Department of Psychology, Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany10Department of Psychology, Clinical and Biological Psychology, School of Social Sciences, Mannheim, Germany11Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, Charité—Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany12Department of Clinical Radiology, University of Münster, Münster, Germany*Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, Philipps-University Marburg, Rudolf-Bultmann-Strasse 8, 35039 Marburg, Germany. E-mail: straubeb@med.uni-marburg.de13These authors contributed equally and should be considered as first authors.14These authors contributed equally and should be considered as last authors.122014161220141122014412e490070420142310201426102014Copyright © 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited2014Macmillan Publishers LimitedThis work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/Serotonin receptor 1A gene (HTR1A) knockout mice show pronounced defensive behaviour and increased fear conditioning to ambiguous conditioned stimuli. Such behaviour is a hallmark of pathological human anxiety, as observed in panic disorder with agoraphobia (PD/AG). Thus, variations in HTR1A might contribute to neurophysiological differences within subgroups of PD/AG patients. Here, we tested this hypothesis by combining genetic with behavioural techniques and neuroimaging. In a clinical multicentre trial, patients with PD/AG received 12 sessions of manualized cognitive-behavioural therapy (CBT) and were genotyped for HTR1A rs6295. In four subsamples of this multicentre trial, exposure behaviour (n=185), defensive reactivity measured using a behavioural avoidance test (BAT; before CBT: n=245; after CBT: n=171) and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) data during fear conditioning were acquired before and after CBT (n=39). HTR1A risk genotype (GG) carriers more often escaped during the BAT before treatment. Exploratory fMRI results suggest increased activation of the amygdala in response to threat as well as safety cues before and after treatment in GG carriers. Furthermore, GG carriers demonstrated reduced effects of CBT on differential conditioning in regions including the bilateral insulae and the anterior cingulate cortex. Finally, risk genotype carriers demonstrated reduced self-initiated exposure behaviour to aversive situations. This study demonstrates the effect of HTR1A variation on defensive behaviour, amygdala activity, CBT-induced neural plasticity and normalization of defence behaviour in PD/AG. Our results, therefore, translate evidence from animal studies to humans and suggest a central role for HTR1A in differentiating subgroups of patients with anxiety disorders.<sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>All patients with PD/AG investigated in this study participated in the Mechanism of Action in CBT study (see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>) that has been described in detail earlier.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup> Inclusion criteria were: (a) a current primary diagnosis of PD/AG; (b) a clinical interview score &gt;18 on the structured interview for the Hamilton anxiety scale (SIGH-A in anxiety and depression); (c) a score &gt;4 on the clinical global impressions scale; (d) an age of 18–65 years; and (e) the ability and availability to regularly attend treatment sessions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> Exclusion criteria were (a) comorbid DSM-IV-TR psychotic or bipolar I disorder; (b) current alcohol dependence/current abuse or dependence on benzodiazepine and other psychoactive substances; (c) current suicidal intent; (d) borderline personality disorder; (e) concurrent ongoing psychotherapeutic or psychopharmacological treatment for PD/AG or another mental disorder; (f) antidepressant or anxiolytic pharmacotherapy; and (g) physician-verified contraindications of exposure-based CBT (that is, severe cardiovascular, renal or neurological diseases).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> Additional exclusion criteria were applied to fMRI subjects: cardiac pacemaker, ferromagnetic metal implants, tattoos or permanent make-up with ferromagnetic colours.</p><p>Eight treatment centres in Germany participated in the clinical multicentre trial including BAT procedure as part of the baseline diagnostics (Aachen, Berlin-Adlershof, Berlin-Charité, Bremen, Dresden, Greifswald, Münster, Würzburg). In the study, exposure-based CBT was administered in 12 twice-weekly sessions based on a highly standardized and controlled treatment protocol.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> The treatment procedure was shown to be highly effective.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup></p><p>In total, <italic>n</italic>=369 patients were enrolled in the clinical study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> Here, we refer to four different subgroups of this clinical sample to investigate genotype effects on (1) exposure behaviour, (2) on BAT before and (3) after CBT, as well as (4) on the neural correlates of fear conditioning (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref> and ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref> for further details).</p><sec><title>Exposure sample</title><p>For the investigation of genotype effects on exposure behaviour, data of 184 patients were available (CC=45; CG=91; GG=48).</p></sec><sec><title>BAT t1 sample</title><p>In total, 364 patients performed the BAT. From 306 patients, who entered the BAT box and were not re-randomized from the waiting list group, blood samples were available in 245 patients (CC=60; CG=120; GG=65).</p></sec><sec><title>BAT t2 sample</title><p>Of the 245 patients from the BAT t1 sample, 171 were randomized to one of two active treatment conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> and also repeated BAT during post-assessment (CC=43; CG=85; GG=43).</p></sec><sec><title>fMRI sample</title><p>In total, 89 patients took part in the neuroimaging study, because only four (Aachen, Berlin, Dresden and Münster) of the eight treatment centres had fMRI technique assessable. Quality-controlled fMRI data were available before and after CBT from 42 patients. Blood samples for genotyping were obtained from 39 of these 42 patients (CC=9; CG=21; GG=9).</p><p>Clinical and demographic data of the BAT and fMRI subcohorts are comparable to the scores of the whole sample (<italic>n</italic>=369) of the clinical trial (compare <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> with Gloster <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Genotyping of rs6295 (<italic>HTR1A</italic> −1019C/G)</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from blood by using a standard de-salting procedure. A 163-bp fragment was amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The PCR reaction mix included 25 ng of genomic DNA in 2.1 μl Gold Star buffer, 25 m<sc>M</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2.5 m<sc>M</sc> of each nucleotide, 10 μ<sc>M</sc> of each forward and modifying primer and 0.5 μl of Taq polymerase. Primer sequences were 5′-GGAAGAAGACCGAGTGTGTCAT-3′ and 5′-GGCTGGACTGTTAGATGATAACG-3′. After an initial denaturation step for 5 min at 95 °C, 38 cycles of denaturating at 95 °C for 30 s, annealing at 59.5 °C for 40 s and extension at 72 °C for 50 s were performed, followed by a final extension step at 72 °C for 5 min. PCR products were digested with BseGI and visualized on a 5% agarose gel containing ethidium bromide.</p><p>The rs6295 genotype groups did not significantly differ in age, gender and clinical characteristics between the different subsamples (see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Genotypes in the total cohort, the BAT and fMRI subcohort did not deviate from Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium (<italic>P</italic>&gt;0.2).</p></sec><sec><title>Treatment intervention</title><p>For detailed information of the clinical and treatment aspects of the study, please see Gloster <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> and Straube <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref></sup> Sessions 1–3 consisted of psychoeducation and an individualized behavioural analysis of the patient's symptoms and coping behaviours. Sessions 4–5 provided the treatment rational for exposure and implemented interoceptive exposure exercises in the therapy room identically for both groups. Sessions 6–8 consisted of standardized <italic>in situ</italic> exposure exercises (bus, shopping mall and forest), which were implemented after the patient agreed to enter the situation without engaging in safety behaviours and waiting for the anxiety to take its natural course. Session 9 reviewed progress to date and addressed anticipatory anxiety. Sessions 10–11 again consisted of <italic>in situ</italic> exposures but now targeted the patients' two most significant feared situations. Session 12 repeated crucial elements of the manual and instructed patients to continue exposing themselves to feared situations. Since effects of genotype were expected specifically on exposure behaviour, data of the exposure sessions (Sessions 6–8 and 10–11), where patients where specifically motivated to do exposure homework, had been collapsed for respective analyses (see below; and Gloster <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> for an identical approach).</p></sec><sec><title>Behavioural avoidance test (BAT)</title><p>BAT procedure is described in detail elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup> Briefly, patients were instructed first to sit in front of an open test chamber (75 × 120 × 190 cm) while defensive reactivity during anticipation of the upcoming exposure was measured (for 10 min). Afterwards, patients were asked to sit in the dark and locked chamber as long as possible (maximum 10 min). Stopping exposure in the test chamber was always possible. Defensive reactivity was measured by self-reports of anxiety on a visual analogue scale, and by observable behaviour (premature escaping behaviour during exposure). Defensive reactivity during anticipation and exposure was analysed as a function of rs6295 <italic>HTR1A</italic> genotype.</p></sec><sec><title>fMRI</title><p>Parallel versions of a previously validated differential conditioning paradigm were applied during fMRI data acquisition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, details in Reinhardt <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup>) before and after CBT (see Kircher <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup> for methodological details). The fMRI brain images were acquired using a 3T Philips Achieva (Muenster and Aachen, Germany), a 3T Siemens Trio (Dresden, Germany) and a 3T General Electric Healthcare (Berlin, Germany) scanner (for acquisition parameters see Kircher <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup>). MR images were analysed using standard procedures of the software Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM5; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk">www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk</ext-link>) implemented in MATLAB 7.1 (the Mathworks, Sherborn, MA, USA).</p><p>At the single-subject level, the realignment parameters of each patient were included as regressors into the model to account for movement artefacts. The BOLD response for each event type (CS+<sub>paired</sub>, CS+<sub>unpaired</sub>, CS−, unconditioned stimulus) and each phase (familiarization phase (F): early (F1) and late (F2); acquisition phase (A): early (A1) and late (A2); extinction phase: early (E1) and late (E2)) was modelled by the canonical haemodynamic response function used by SPM5 within the framework of the general linear model to analyse brain activation differences related to the onset of the different stimuli.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup> Parameter estimates (β−) and <italic>t</italic>-statistic images were calculated for each subject.</p><p>Group analyses were performed by entering contrast images into flexible factorial analyses as implemented in SPM5, in which subjects are treated as random variables. The fMRI centre was introduced as a covariate to account for scanner differences. To investigate the influence of rs6295 on neural activity, we compared the genetic subgroups during the processing of CS+<sub>unpaired</sub> and CS− in the early acquisition phase of the fear-conditioning paradigm (where the most pronounced effects and the neural plasticity induced by CBT in PD/AG were detected, see Kircher <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref></sup>). Analyses were performed by contrasting the extreme groups of the three genetic subgroups GG (<italic>n</italic>=9), CG (21) and CC (<italic>n</italic>=9). Due to the small sample size, these analyses should be considered as preliminary. To explore general effect of genotype on the neural processing of not fully conditioned stimuli in the early acquisition phase, the genotype main effect (GG&gt;CC) independent of time point (<italic>t</italic>1/<italic>t</italic>2) and stimulus type (CS+/CS−) had been calculated. To test for genotype-specific effects on CBT-related changes, interaction analyses had been performed (GG/CC × <italic>t</italic>1/<italic>t</italic>2 × CS+/CS−).</p><p>The identical cluster threshold of at least 142 voxels at SPM significance level of <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.005 uncorrected (based on a Monte Carlo simulation for correction of multiple testing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup>), as in previous investigations of this multicentre trial has been applied.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref></sup> For the anatomical localization, functional data were referenced to probabilistic cytoarchitectonic maps<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup> and the AAL toolbox.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">49</xref></sup></p></sec></sec>We gratefully acknowledge expert technical assistance by C Gagel and I Reck. We are indebted to all the patients for participating in the MAC trial. This work is part of the German multicentre trial ‘Mechanisms of Action in CBT (MAC)'. The MAC study is funded by the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF; project no. 01GV0615) as part of the BMBF Psychotherapy Research Funding Initiative. Principal investigators (PIs) with respective areas of responsibility in the MAC study are VA (Münster: Overall MAC Program Coordination), H-UW (Dresden: PI for the Randomized Clinical Trial (RCT) and Manual Development), AH (Greifswald: PI for Psychophysiology), ALG (Münster: PI for Psychophysiology and Panic subtypes), AS (Berlin: PI for Experimental Pharmacology), TK (Marburg: PI for Functional Neuroimaging) and JD (Würzburg: PI for Genetics). Additional site directors in the RCT component of the program are GWA (Würzburg), TF and L Fehm (Berlin-Adlershof) and TL (Bremen). All principal investigators take responsibility for the integrity of the respective study data and their components. All the authors and co-authors had full access to all the study data. The following are the staff members by site: Greifswald (coordinating site for psychophysiology): Christiane Melzig, Jan Richter, Susan Richter, Matthias von Rad; Berlin-Charite (coordinating centre for experimental pharmacology): Harald Bruhn, Anja Siegmund, Meline Stoy, Andre Wittmann; Berlin-Adlershof: Irene Schulz; Münster (Overall MAC Program Coordination, Genetics and Functional Neuroimaging): Andreas Behnken, Katharina Domschke, Adrianna Ewert, Carsten Konrad, Bettina Pfleiderer, Christiana Sehlmeyer, Peter Zwanzger; Münster (coordinating site for psychophysiology and subtyping): Judith Eidecker, Swantje Koller, Fred Rist, Anna Vossbeck-Elsebusch; Marburg/ Aachen (coordinating centre for functional neuroimaging): Barbara Drüke, Sonja Eskens, Thomas Forkmann, Siegfried Gauggel, Susan Gruber, Andreas Jansen, Thilo Kellermann, Isabelle Reinhardt, Nina Vercamer-Fabri; Dresden (coordinating site for data collection, analysis, and the RCT): Franziska Einsle, Christine Fröhlich, Andrew T. Gloster, Christina Hauke, Simone Heinze, Michael Höfler, Ulrike Lueken, Peter Neudeck, Stephanie Preiß, Dorte Westphal; Würzburg Psychiatry Department (coordinating centre for genetics): Andreas Reif; Würzburg Psychology Department: Julia Dürner, Hedwig Eisenbarth, Antje B. M. Gerdes, Harald Krebs, Paul Pauli, Silvia Schad, Nina Steinhäuser; Bremen: Veronika Bamann, Sylvia Helbig-Lang, Anne Kordt, Pia Ley, Franz Petermann, Eva-Maria Schröder. Additional support was provided by the coordinating centre for clinical studies in Dresden (KKS Dresden): Xina Grählert and Marko Käppler. The study was registered with the ISRCTN: ISRCTN80046034. The RCT project was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Medical Faculty of the Technical University of Dresden (EK 164082006). The neuroimaging components were approved by the Ethics Committee of the Medical Faculty of the Rheinisch-Westfälische Hochschule University Aachen (EK 073/07). The experimental pharmacology study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the state of Berlin (EudraCT: 2006-00-4860-29). Further support was provided by Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG; German Research Foundation; Collaborative Research Centre ‘Fear, Anxiety, Anxiety Disorders' SFB-TRR-58) project C2 to KD and JD, project Z2 to JD, AR and PP, project B1 to PP and project C1 to PZ.Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on the Translational Psychiatry website (http://www.nature.com/tp)VA is a member of the advisory boards and/or gave presentations for the following companies: AstraZeneca, Janssen-Organon, Lilly, Lundbeck, Servier, Pfizer and Wyeth. He also received research grants from AstraZeneca, Lundbeck and Servier. He chaired the committee for the ‘Wyeth Research Award Depression and Anxiety'. JD received in the past 3 years honoraria by Janssen, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Wyeth, Lundbeck, AstraZeneca and Pfizer and Grant Support by Medice, Lundbeck and AstraZeneca. TK received fees for educational programs from Janssen-Cilag, Eli Lilly, Servier, Lundbeck, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Pfizer and AstraZeneca; travel support/sponsorship for congresses from Servier; speaker's honoraria from Janssen-Cilag; and research grants from Pfizer and Lundbeck. CK received fees for educational programs from Esparma GmbH/Aristo Pharma GmbH, Lilly Deutschland GmbH, Servier Deutschland GmbH and MagVenture GmbH. AR has received research support from PsyNova, and AR and KD have received research grants from AstraZeneca. KD has received honoraria for scientific talks from Pfizer, Lilly and Bristol-Myers Squibb and has been a consultant for Johnson &amp; Johnson. AS received research funding from Lundbeck, and speaker honoraria from AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Eli Lilly, Lundbeck, Pfizer, Wyeth and UCB. Educational grants were given by the Stifterverband für die Deutsche Wissenschaft, the Berlin Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, the Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds and the Eli Lilly International Foundation. H-UW has served as a general consultant (non-product related) for Pfizer, Organon, Servier and Essex Pharma and has received grant funding for his institution from Sanofi Aventis, Pfizer, Lundbeck, Novartis, Essex Pharma, Servier and Wyeth. The remaining authors declare no conflict of interest.ParksCLRobinsonPSSibilleEShenkTTothMIncreased anxiety of mice lacking the serotonin1A receptorProc Natl Acad Sci USA19989510734107399724773RambozSOostingRAmaraDAKungHFBlierPMendelsohnMSerotonin receptor 1A knockout: an animal model of anxiety-related disorderProc Natl Acad Sci USA19989514476144819826725HeislerLKChuHMBrennanTJDanaoJABajwaPParsonsLHElevated anxiety and antidepressant-like responses in serotonin 5-HT1A receptor mutant miceProc Natl Acad Sci USA19989515049150549844013GrossCSantarelliLBrunnerDZhuangXHenRAltered fear circuits in 5-HT(1A) receptor KO miceBiol Psychiatry2000481157116311137057KlemenhagenKCGordonJADavidDJHenRGrossCTIncreased fear response to contextual cues in mice lacking the 5-HT1A receptorNeuropsychopharmacology20063110111115920501TsetsenisTMaXHLoILBeckSGGrossCSuppression of conditioning to ambiguous cues by pharmacogenetic inhibition of the dentate gyrusNat Neurosci20071089690217558402LissekSRabinSHellerRELukenbaughDGeraciMPineDSOvergeneralization of conditioned fear as a pathogenic marker of panic disorderAm J Psychiatry2010167475519917595LuekenUStraubeBKonradCWittchenHUStröhleAWittmannANeural substrates of treatment response to cognitive-behavioral therapy in panic disorder with agoraphobiaAm J Psychiatry20131701345135523982225LuekenUStraubeBReinhardtIMaslowskiNIWittchenHUStröhleAAltered top-down and bottom-up processing of fear conditioning in panic disorder with agoraphobiaPsychol Med20144438139423611156AkimovaELanzenbergerRKasperSThe serotonin-1A receptor in anxiety disordersBiol Psychiatry20096662763519423077RotheCGutknechtLFreitagCTauberRMossnerRFrankePAssociation of a functional 1019C&gt;G 5-HT1A receptor gene polymorphism with panic disorder with agoraphobiaInt J Neuropsychopharmacol2004718919214984628Le FrancoisBCzesakMSteublDAlbertPRTranscriptional regulation at a HTR1A polymorphism associated with mental illnessNeuropharmacology20085597798518639564DomschkeKBraunMOhrmannPSuslowTKugelHBauerJAssociation of the functional −1019C/G 5-HT1A polymorphism with prefrontal cortex and amygdala activation measured with 3 T fMRI in panic disorderInt J Neuropsychopharmacol2006934935516316476HuangYYBattistuzziCOquendoMAHarkavy-FriedmanJGreenhillLZalsmanGHuman 5-HT1A receptor C(−1019)G polymorphism and psychopathologyInt J Neuropsychopharmacol2004744145115469667LemondeSTureckiGBakishDDuLHrdinaPDBownCDImpaired repression at a 5-hydroxytryptamine 1A receptor gene polymorphism associated with major depression and suicideJ Neurosci2003238788879914507979GrossCZhuangXStarkKRambozSOostingRKirbyLSerotonin1A receptor acts during development to establish normal anxiety-like behaviour in the adultNature200241639640011919622RichterJHammAOPané-FarréCAGerlachALGlosterATWittchenHUDynamics of defensive reactivity in patients with panic disorder and agoraphobia: implications for the etiology of panic disorderBiol Psychiatry20127251252022621998SchmitzAKirschPReuterMAlexanderNKozyraEKuepperYThe 5-HT1A C(−1019)G polymorphism, personality and electrodermal reactivity in a reward/punishment paradigmInt J Neuropsychopharmacol20091238339218796187FakraEHydeLWGorkaAFisherPMMunozKEKimakMEffects of HTR1A C(−1019)G on amygdala reactivity and trait anxietyArch Gen Psychiatry200966334019124686LangPJBradleyMMEmotion and the motivational brainBiol Psychol20108443745019879918BoutonMEMinekaSBarlowDHA modern learning theory perspective on the etiology of panic disorderPsychol Review2001108432RachmanSThe conditioning theory of fear-acquisition: a critical examinationBehav Res Ther197715375387612338LissekSPowersASMcClureEBPhelpsEAWoldehawariatGGrillonCClassical fear conditioning in the anxiety disorders: a meta-analysisBehav Res Ther2005431391142415885654DamsaCKoselMMoussallyJCurrent status of brain imaging in anxiety disordersCurr Opin Psychiatry2009229611019122541de CarvalhoMRDiasGPCosciFde-Melo-NetoVLBevilaquaMCGardinoPFCurrent findings of fMRI in panic disorder: contributions for the fear neurocircuitry and CBT effectsExpert Rev Neurother20101029130320136384GormanJMKentJMSullivanGMCoplanJDNeuroanatomical hypothesis of panic disorder, revisedAm J Psychiatry200015749350510739407KircherTAroltVJansenAPykaMReinhardtIKellermannTEffect of cognitive-behavioral therapy on neural correlates of fear conditioning in panic disorderBiol Psychiatry2013739310122921454BuchelCDolanRJArmonyJLFristonKJAmygdala-hippocampal involvement in human aversive trace conditioning revealed through event-related functional magnetic resonance imagingJ Neurosci199919108691087610594068SehlmeyerCSchoningSZwitserloodPPfleidererBKircherTAroltVHuman fear conditioning and extinction in neuroimaging: a systematic reviewPLoS One20094e586519517024ReinhardtIJansenAKellermannTSchuppenAKohnNGerlachALNeural correlates of aversive conditioning: development of a functional imaging paradigm for the investigation of anxiety disordersEur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci201026044345320148332NashJRSargentPARabinerEAHoodSDArgyropoulosSVPotokarJPSerotonin 5-HT1A receptor binding in people with panic disorder: positron emission tomography studyBr J Psychiatry200819322923418757983NeumeisterABainENugentACCarsonREBonneOLuckenbaughDAReduced serotonin type 1A receptor binding in panic disorderJ Neurosci20042458959114736842McHughRKSmitsJAOttoMWEmpirically supported treatments for panic disorderPsychiatr Clin North Am20093259361019716992Sanchez-MecaJRosa-AlcazarAIMarin-MartinezFGomez-ConesaAPsychological treatment of panic disorder with or without agoraphobia: a meta-analysisClin Psychol Rev201030375019775792GlosterATWittchenHUEinsleFLangTHelbig-LangSFydrichTPsychological treatment for panic disorder with agoraphobia: a randomized controlled trial to examine the role of therapist-guided exposure in situ in CBTJ Consult Clin Psychol20117940642021534651PraskoJHoracekJZaleskyRKopecekMNovakTPaskovaBThe change of regional brain metabolism (18FDG PET) in panic disorder during the treatment with cognitive behavioral therapy or antidepressantsNeuro Endocrinol Lett20042534034815580167SakaiYKumanoHNishikawaMSakanoYKaiyaHImabayashiEChanges in cerebral glucose utilization in patients with panic disorder treated with cognitive-behavioral therapyNeuroimage20063321822616889985KumariVPetersERFannonDAntonovaEPremkumarPAnilkumarAPDorsolateral prefrontal cortex activity predicts responsiveness to cognitive-behavioral therapy in schizophreniaBiol Psychiatry20096659460219560121FuCHWilliamsSCCleareAJScottJMitterschiffthalerMTWalshNDNeural responses to sad facial expressions in major depression following cognitive behavioral therapyBiol Psychiatry20086450551218550030ReifARichterJStraubeBHöflerMLuekenUGlosterATMAOA and mechanisms of panic disorder revisited: from bench to molecular psychotherapyMol Psychiatry20141912212823319006LonsdorfTBKalischRA review on experimental and clinical genetic associations studies on fear conditioning, extinction and cognitive-behavioral treatmentTransl Psychiatry20111e4122832657LesterKJEleyTCTherapygenetics: using genetic markers to predict response to psychological treatment for mood and anxiety disordersBiol Mood Anxiety Disord20133423388219YangYKircherTStraubeBThe neural correlates of cognitive behavioral therapy: Recent progress in the investigation of patients with panic disorderBehav Res Ther201462889625124776LuekenUStraubeBWittchenHUKonradCStröhleAWittmannATherapygenetics: anterior cingulate cortex-amygdala coupling is associated with 5-HTTLPR and treatment response in panic disorder with agoraphobiaJ Neural Transm2014GlosterATWittchenHUEinsleFHoflerMLangTHelbig-LangSMechanism of action in CBT (MAC): methods of a multi-center randomized controlled trial in 369 patients with panic disorder and agoraphobiaEur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci2009259155166StraubeBLuekenUJansenAKonradCGlosterATGerlachALNeural correlates of procedural variants in cognitive-behavioral therapy: a randomized, controlled multicenter FMRI studyPsychother Psychosom20148322223324970601SlotnickSDMooLRSegalJBHartJJrDistinct prefrontal cortex activity associated with item memory and source memory for visual shapesBrain Res Cogn Brain Res200317758212763194EickhoffSBStephanKEMohlbergHGrefkesCFinkGRAmuntsKA new SPM toolbox for combining probabilistic cytoarchitectonic maps and functional imaging dataNeuroimage2005251325133515850749Tzourio-MazoyerNLandeauBPapathanassiouDCrivelloFEtardODelcroixNAutomated anatomical labeling of activations in SPM using a macroscopic anatomical parcellation of the MNI MRI single-subject brainNeuroimage20021527328911771995StraubeBLuekenUJansenAKonradCGlosterATGerlachALNeural correlates of procedural variants in cognitive behavioral therapy: a randomized, controlled multicentre fMRI studyPsychother Psychosom20148322223324970601TimberlakeWBehavior systems and reinforcement: an integrative approachJ Exp Anal Behav1993601051288354963McNaughtonNCorrPJA two-dimensional neuropsychology of defense: fear/anxiety and defensive distanceNeurosci Biobehav Rev20042828530515225972Del-BenCMGraeffFGPanic disorder: is the PAG involvedNeural Plast2009200910813519283082MobbsDMarchantJLHassabisDSeymourBTanGGrayMFrom threat to fear: the neural organization of defensive fear systems in humansJ Neurosci200929122361224319793982LuekenUHilbertKStolyarVMaslowskiNIWittchenH-UNeural substrates of defensive reactivity in two subtypes of specific phobiaSoc Cogn Affect Neurosci201491668167524174207GraeffFGZangrossiHJrThe dual role of serotonin in defense and the mode of action of antidepressants on generalized anxiety and panic disordersCent Nerv Syst Agents Med Chem20101020721720528764CraigADHow do you feel--now? The anterior insula and human awarenessNat Rev Neurosci200910597019096369PaulusMPSteinMBAn insular view of anxietyBiol Psychiatry20066038338716780813AmuntsKKedoOKindlerMPieperhoffPMohlbergHShahNJCytoarchitectonic mapping of the human amygdala, hippocampal region and entorhinal cortex: intersubject variability and probability mapsAnat Embryol (Berl)200521034335216208455Figure 1Exposure behaviour. Every CBT session patients were asked how long they exposed their self to an anxiety-related situation. HTR1A CC genotype (light grey; n=45) in contrast to GG (dark grey; n=48) genotype carriers reported longer exposure times, especially during later sessions of CBT (session 10–11). The significant difference (P&gt;0.05) between bars is illustrated by a black line. Thus, the comparable clinical outcome between groups might be a result of different exposure behaviour as a specific mechanism of CBT. CBT, cognitive-behavioural therapy.Figure 2BAT baseline assessment. Rate of escaping behaviour during exposure period ((a) GG=32% (n=21 of 65); CG=23% (n=27 of 120); CC=15% (n=9 of 60)) and (b) means and s.e. of reported anxiety during anticipation and exposure period as a function of rs6295 [C(−1019)G] genotype and defensive behaviour in 245 PD/AG patients during baseline assessment before therapy. BAT, behavioural avoidance test; PD/AG, panic disorder/agoraphobia.Figure 3BAT baseline to post-assessment. Means and s.e. of reported anxiety during anticipation period (a) and exposure period (b) and of tolerated duration of exposure during baseline and post-assessment (c) in 171 PD/AG patients randomized to one of two active treatment groups. BAT, behavioural avoidance test; PD/AG, panic disorder/agoraphobia.Figure 4Main effects and interactions of rs6295 (−1019C/G HTR1A) during early fear acquisition in patients with PD/AG. (a) Main effect of genotype (GG&gt;CC) for the processing of CS+unpaired and CS− during early acquisition phase of the conditioning paradigm at pre- (t1) and post-treatment (t2). Risk type carriers (GG) generally demonstrated more activity in the illustrated regions independent of time point or stimulus type. Bar graphs illustrate the contrast estimates for the activity in the left amygdala (collapsed across CS+unpaired and CS− at t1 and t2; the cluster was restricted to the amygdala using a ROI defined by the anatomy toolbox of SPM.48, 59 Cluster extension: 272 voxels). Contrast estimates for all other activation clusters demonstrate a similar pattern of increased activity in the GG group. (b) Interaction of genotype, the processing of CS+unpaired vs CS− during early acquisition phase and pre- (t1) vs post-treatment effects (t2). Bar graphs illustrate the contrast estimates for the activity in the left insula (whole cluster: 330 voxels). Contrast estimates for all other activation clusters demonstrate similar patterns. Risk type carriers demonstrated relatively stable activity in the illustrated regions independent of time point or stimulus type. By contrast, patients with the protective genotype (CC) showed a reduced activation for the CS+unpaired after treatment and an opposite effect for the CS−. For coordinates and statistics, see Table 2. CS, conditioned stimulus; PD/AG, panic disorder/agoraphobia; ROI, region of interest; SPM, statistical parametric mapping.Table 1Demographic and clinical characteristics of the fMRI and BAT samples according to rs6295 (−1019C/G HTR1A) genotype GenotypeDifferences (CC vs GG) CCCGGG Genetic-BAT-sample (N=245) N6012065χ2/FP Female (n (%))42 (70.21)82 (68.33)54 (83.08)2.99a0.08 Age (years)36.38 (10.88)35.58 (11.50)35.46 (10.23)0.240.63 Clinical characteristics at baseline  SIGH-A total24.53 (5.04)23.71 (5.23)24.46 (5.55)0.010.94  PAS total26.96 (9.64)26.14 (9.96)28.23 (9.33)0.570.45  CGI5.17 (0.74)5.18 (0.72)5.29 (0.61)1.090.30  ASI total31.15 (9.96)30.51 (11.60)32.28 (12.61)0.310.58  BDI II total16.19 (8.82)16.56 (8.24)15.87 (9.02)0.040.84  MI72.07 (0.92)1.93 (0.99)1.92 (0.99)0.690.41 GenotypeDifferences (CC/CG vs GG) CCCGGG Genetic-BAT-treatment-sample (N=171) N438543χ2/FP Female (n (%))29 (67.44)57 (67.06)34 (79.07)2.17a0.34 Age (years)36.28 (11.31)36.60 (12.09)33.28 (9.40)1.310.27 Clinical characteristics at baseline  SIGH-A total25.09 (5.37)23.62 (5.07)25.19 (5.76)1.740.18  PAS total26.39 (9.18)25.78 (9.85)29.33 (9.37)2.040.13  CGI5.26 (0.76)5.16 (0.72)5.28 (0.63)0.460.63  ASI total32.81 (9.95)30.72 (11.35)33.12 (12.62)0.840.43  BDI II total16.67 (9.00)16.34 (8.56)15.51 (9.14)0.210.81  MI71.97 (0.89)1.83 (0.88)1.87 (0.89)0.350.70 Clinical characteristics at post-treatment  SIGH-A total13.65 (7.89)11.78 (7.57)12.60 (6.90)0.890.41  PAS total13.68 (8.93)14.21 (9.52)14.18 (8.14)0.050.95  CGI3.42 (0.85)3.46 (1.11)3.40 (1.00)0.060.94  ASI total17.23 (10.36)15.86 (10.42)16.47 (10.04)0.260.77  BDI II total8.49 (8.36)8.62 (7.99)8.44 (8.26)0.010.99  MI71.53 (0.68)1.29 (0.49)1.47 (0.68)2.430.09 GenotypeDifferences (CC vs GG) CCCGGG Genetic-fMRI-treatment-sample (N=39) N9219FP Female (n (%))7 (77.78)14 (66.67)5 (55.56)1.00a0.62 Age (years)30.11 (11.47)37.67 (10.01)36.11 (7.57)1.760.20 Clinical characteristics at baseline  SIGH-A total22.89 (4.68)23.62 (5.34)26.22 (5.93)1.750.20  PAS total22.99 (6.72)24.19 (9.33)31.90 (7.80)6.740.02  CGI5.00 (0.71)5.38 (0.59)5.67 (0.50)5.330.04  ASI total30.44 (6.50)29.14 (9.08)36.00 (11.41)1.610.22  BDI II total14.00 (7.63)16.05 (7.40)18.67 (11.51)1.030.33  MI71.84 (0.71)1.84 (0.93)1.65 (1.00)0.220.65 Clinical characteristics at post-treatment  SIGH-A total9.78 (3.99)12.38 (6.66)13.44 (9.38)1.160.29  PAS total9.15 (5.28)13.57 (8.96)18.54 (8.79)7.540.01  CGI3.22 (0.97)3.62 (1.24)3.78 (0.67)2.000.18  ASI total13.00 (7.81)15.05 (7.41)19.11 (11.94)1.650.22  BDI II total4.78 (6.40)9.67 (6.16)9.89 (11.17)1.420.25  MI71.45 (0.71)1.24 (0.38)1.20 (0.41)0.820.38Abbreviations: ASI, Anxiety Sensitivity Index; BDI II, Beck Depression Inventory II; CGI, Clinical Global Impressions Scale; PAS, Panic and Agoraphobia Scale; MI7, 7-day version of the Movement Inventory (accompanied); SIGH-A, Hamilton Anxiety Scale.aPearson's Chi-square.Means (s.d.) except where noted. Due to missing values, MI7 scores were available in the BAT total sample only in 229 patients (CC: 57, CG: 112, GG: 60) and in the BAT treatment group sample only in 160 patients (CC: 41, CG: 80, GG: 39).Table 2fMRI results (coordinates and statistics)Contrast/regionCluster extensions/submaximaxyzt-valueP uncorrectedCluster sizeMain effect: GG&gt;CC Right Amy/HCAmy (SF, 69.7% CM, 80.3%), HC (CA, 8.5%)18−6−164.05&lt;0.001837 Right putamen30−8−63.54&lt;0.001  Right insula32−18203.51&lt;0.001  Left SPL −18−64544.01&lt;0.001865 Left postcentral gyrus−18−40723.69&lt;0.001  Right postcentral gyrusRight postcentral gyrus32−38523.80&lt;0.001802 Right precentral gyrus28−26683.53&lt;0.001  Right calcarine gyrus 16−58123.44&lt;0.001695 Right precuneus18−54163.260.001  Right thalamus 8−14243.80&lt;0.001460 Right SPL 24−66523.200.001303 Right cuneus18−76383.170.001  Left HC/AmyAmy (SF, 31.5%), HC (CA, 7.4% FD, 13.3%)−14−12−143.81&lt;0.001279 Left HC−28−20−123.300.001  Left SMABA 6−610703.56&lt;0.001223 Right SMA20662.940.002  Thalamus −20−1483.170.001202 Left insula−34−2043.060.001  Left cerebellum −12−68−163.74&lt;0.001143        Interaction: genotype (CC&gt;GG) × time (t1&gt;t2) × stimulus (CS+unpaired&gt;CS−) Left precentral gyrus −38−12584.37&lt;0.0014471 Right SMA86604.36&lt;0.001  Left precentral gyrus−28−18724.18&lt;0.001  Right middle occipital gyrus 30−74304.34&lt;0.0012360 Right postcentral gyrus34−32683.94&lt;0.001  Right precentral gyrus30−28743.94&lt;0.001  Right temporal pole 5418−163.69&lt;0.001455 Right temporal pole6014−43.170.001  Right insula4618−42.990.002  Left insula −468−43.47&lt;0.001330 Left temporal pole−5410−103.220.001  Left IFG (pars opercularis)−40882.930.002  Right MFG 484863.71&lt;0.001149 Right MFG405683.120.001  Left ACC −1034263.180.001144 Left superior medial gyrus−232342.980.002  Left ACC−642182.860.002  Left STG −52−18103.100.001142Abbreviations: ACC, anterior cingulate gyrus; Amy, amygdala; CA, cornu amonis; CM, centromedial group; FD, fascicular dentata; HC, hippocampus; IFG, inferior frontal gyrus; MFG, middle frontal gyrus; SF, superficial group; SPL, superior parietal lobe; STG, superior temporal gyrus.Significance level, t-values, uncorrected P-value and the size of the respective cluster (voxels) at P&lt;0.05, corrected (MC), were mentioned. Coordinates are listed in MNI atlas space. Contrasts are named in italic letters. Cluster extensions denominate activated regions for larger voxel clusters encompassing different brain areas and should be considered approximate. Anatomical regions have been defined by the anatomy toolbox of statistical parametric mapping.48, 59
