<?xml version="1.0"?>
Int J YogaIJYInternational Journal of Yoga0973-61310973-6131Medknow PublicationsIndia3144612IJY-01-6010.4103/0973-6131.41033Original ArticlePlanning ability improves in a yogic education system compared to a modernRanganRNagendraH RBhatG RamachandraDepartment of Yoga Research, Swami Vivekananda Yoga Anusandhana Samsthana, Bangalore, IndiaCorrespondence to: R Rangan, 167, North Chithra Street, Srirangam, Trichy – 620 006, Tamil Nadu, India. E-mail: valmiki1977@yahoo.comJul-Dec2008126065© International Journal of Yoga2008This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Background:Planning skills play a key role in higher developmental processes. The Tower of London test not only measures planning skills, but also the ability to execute plans. Yoga practices aim to bring about higher development. Can a Yoga-based education system be shown to meet this challenge?Aim:This study was aimed at comparing a Modern Education System (MES) with the ancient Yoga-based system of education, the Gurukula Education System (GES), in developing planning skills.Materials and Methods:Forty-nine boys with ages ranging from 11 to 13 years were selected from each of two residential schools, one MES and the other GES, providing similar ambience and daily routines. The boys were matched for age and socio-economic status. The GES educational program is based around integrated yoga modules while the MES provides a conventional modern education program. Planning and executive abilities were assessed using the Tower of London test at the start and the end of an academic year.Results:Within groups, the pre-post test differences were significant for both groups. However, the between-groups results showed improvement in the GES group compared to the MES group at a P &lt; 0.001 significance level.Conclusions:The study suggests that whereas both MES and GES Yoga-based education improve planning and execution skills in school boys, GES is more effective of the two systems.Gurukula education systemplanning abilityTower of London testVedic chantingYoga<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Subjects</title><p>Two residential schools, one MES and the other GES providing similar ambience and daily routines, were chosen. Both the residential schools had similar natural surroundings with an atmosphere congenial for learning. Out of the 110 students in the Yoga-based boys' Gurukula (GES) and 500 students studying in the MES, a group of 49 healthy boys between 11 and 13 years of age from each school, were one-to-one matched for age, family circumstances and socio-economic background.</p><p>The boys' health status was assessed by a doctor based on their personal history and a general clinical examination. Those having congenital defects or taking medication known to affect planning or cognitive abilities were excluded from the study. The students in the GES school were all freshers and had received a modern education similar to the MES school until that time, when being interested in GES, they had chosen the Gurukula school. An independent samples‘t’-test on the baseline data showed no significant differences (P &gt; 0.05) between the two groups for any of the demographic parameters. The demographic data for the two groups are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T0001" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic data of boys studying in MES and GES schools</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Details of students</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RS</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mean±sd)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mean±sd)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mean±sd)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mean±sd)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mean±sd)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mean±sd)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mean±sd)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6448.98 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.16 ±</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GES</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1969.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6704.08 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 ±</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.31 ±</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MES</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2174.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>GES: Gurukula education system, MES: Modern education system</p></fn><fn><p>A-Education of father, B-Education of mother, (Education up to SSLC–1, Graduation–2, Post graduation–3, Professionals–4) C: Occupation of father, D: Occupation of mother (Agriculture-1, Business-2, Academician-3, Others-4) E: social setup (Rural-1 Urban-2)</p></fn><fn><p>The results show no significant differences between GES and MES in all the demographic parameters (Independent samples † test P &gt; 0.05). Differences between the GES and MES groups for levels of education of father and mother, occupation of father and mother and social setup were assessed using X<sup>2</sup> test and were found to be not significant (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Assessments</title><p>Shallice's Tower of London test was used to assess planning abilities and execution skills.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT9">9</xref>] The Tower of London test requires the subject to move an array of colored discs mounted on three vertical rods, to match a particular goal arrangement given in a picture. Each subject has to complete four tasks at increasing levels of complexity; the first level requires two moves to reach the goal, the second three moves, the next four and the fourth level, five moves. Subjects are assessed on planning time, execution time, mean total time, and the number of moves. Both groups were assessed before and after the academic year. All assessments were made before lunch. Time and day of assessments were the same for matched pairs. Test instructions were given in English in both schools.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Significance of planning time</title><p>The measure of planning time assesses planning skill. The essence of planning is to see how to attain a goal through a series of intermediate steps. The subject plans in advance the complete sequence of moves required to solve the problem. In order to do so, the subject considers the consequences of various courses of action.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT10">10</xref>] Goal setting involves not only identifying the final goal, but also any necessary intermediate goals. Thus, assessment of planning time evaluates both these faculties: setting the goal and intermediate steps.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Significance of execution time</title><p>Measuring execution time not only assesses motor skill but also the planning ability. This is because new decisions can occur during execution. Planning ability not only sets goals, but also monitors performance to reach a goal and make corrections to the chosen course, in order to ensure that the goal is attained.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT10">10</xref>] In carrying out a planned strategy, frontal association areas of the brain cortex are used to execute complex functions such as delayed response motor tasks and changing strategies, if and when necessary.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT11">11</xref>] Thus, assessing execution time can evaluate motor skills and planning ability related to frontal association areas.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Significance of number of moves</title><p>Assessing the number of moves evaluates perfection of planning. If planning has not been perfect, the number of moves increases. This is also a measure of brain function. Imaging studies have found that more efficient planning involving fewer moves is associated with increased activation of the left prefrontal cortex.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Masking</title><p>One-to-one matching of students was done under the guidance of a statistician. Demographic data were collected by trained persons not involved in the design of the study. The Tower of London test assessments were carried out under the guidance of a psychologist, by trained persons who had not been involved in the selection process, and who did not know the design of the study. No teacher at either school was involved in making the assessments. There were no interactions between the GES and MES schools as they were in different locations more than 100 kilometers apart. Furthermore, no one at either school knew the identity of the other school.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Intervention</title><p>The GES School used an educational program which integrated yoga practices, while the MES provided a conventional modern education program. The GES program included yogic postures (asanas), voluntary regulated breathing (pranayama), meditation (dhyana), recitation of mantras (japa), yogic prayers, worship (puja) and Yogic games (team games played on Yogic principles). In contrast, the MES program included physical exercises, mathematical puzzles, music, prayer and normal sports. The daily routines of the two schools are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T0002">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T0002" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Daily routine in the two residential schools</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">GES</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MES</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schedule</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schedule</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:00 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wake up</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:00 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wake up</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:30–5:45 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation and Pranayama</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:00–5:50 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ablutions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:45–6:15 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yogasanas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:00–6:15 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prayer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:15–6:45 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleaning</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:15–6:45 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical exercises</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:45–7:30 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ablutions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:00–7:55 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:40–8:00 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puja</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:30–9:15 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breakfast</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00–9:15 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breakfast/cleaning</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:30–10:30 AM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vedic chanting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:30 AM–12.00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sessions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:30 AM–12:45 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sessions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00–1:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Music</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:00–2:30 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lunch</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:00–2:20 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lunch/rest</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2:45–4:45 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sessions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2:30–4:30 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sessions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:45–5:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snacks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:45–5:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snacks</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:00–6:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tuning to nature</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:00–6:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tuning to nature</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:00–6:45 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yogic games</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:15–6:45 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Games</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:45–7:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation and pranayama</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:45–7:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prayer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:00–8:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-study</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00–8.30 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00–9.00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinner</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:30–9:15 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinner</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:00–10.00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-work</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:15–10:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-work</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lights off</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:00 PM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lights off</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>GES: Gurukula Education System, MES: Modern education system.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Data analysis</title><p>The pre- data of the two groups were compared using an Independent Samples ‘t’ test. The Kolmogorov test of normality showed that the pre- data were not normally distributed, as would be expected, because the Tower of London test has distinct minima but no upper limits. Hence, nonparametric tests were used in the analysis. Within groups, the pre-post data were analyzed using the Wilcoxon Signed Ranks Test, while between groups the pre-post data were analyzed using the Mann-Whitney U Test. SPSS 10.0 was used for analysis.</p></sec></sec>REFERENCES1DuttaMNThe dharam shasthra: Hindu religious codes1987New DelhiCosmo Publications2TellesSHanumanthaiahBNagarathnaRNagendraHRImprovement in static motor performance following yogic training of school childrenPercept Mot Skills1993761264683370753NaveenKVNagendraHRNagaratnaRTellesSBreathing through a particular nostril improves spatial memory scores without lateralized effectsPsychol Rep1997815556193541114ManjunathNKTellesSImproved performance in the tower of London test following YogaIndian J Physiol Pharmacol2001453514118815755KadambiniAEffect of Yoga on performance in a planning task with the tower of London test, Masters's Dissertation2005BangaloreSVYASA University6LezakMDNeuropsychological assessment19953rd edNew YorkOxford University Press7RaoLSSubbakrishnaDKGopukumarKNimhans neuropsychology battery-2004 manual2004BangaloreThe national institute of mental health and neurosciences788StussDTBensonDFNeurophysiological studies of frontal lobesPsychol Bull19849532865444329ShalliceTSpecific impairments of planningPhil Trans R Soc Lon19821319920910BakerSCRogersRDOwenAMFrithCDDolanRJFrackowiakRSNeural systems engaged by planning: A PET study of Tower of London taskNeuropsychologia19963451526873656511FusterJMThe prefrontal cortex anatomy, physiology and neurophysiology of the frontal lobe19892nd edNew YorkRaven Press12Orme-JohnsonDWGranieriBOrme-JohnsonDWFarrowJThe effects of the age of enlightenment Governor Training Courses on field independence, creativity, intelligence and behavioral flexibilityScientific Research on the Transcendental Meditation Program Collected Papers1977Vol. I2nd edSeelisbergMERU Press103713813LazarSWBushGGollubRLFricchioneGLKhalsaGBensonHFunctional brain mapping of the relaxation response and meditationNeuroreport200011158151084138014KemberPThe Transcendental Meditation technique and academic performance: A short report on controlled longitudinal pilot studyBr J Educ Psychol198555164615HerzogHLeleVRKuwertTLangenKJKopsERFelnendegenLEChanged pattern of regional glucose metabolism during yoga meditative relaxationNeuropsychobiology1990231827213028716MorrisRGAhmedSSyedGMTooneBKNeural correlates of planning ability: frontal lobe activation during the Tower of London testNeuropsychologia199331136778812743317OwenAMBownesJJShakanBJPoltreyCARobbinsTWPlanning and spatial working memory following frontal lobe lesions in manNeuropsychologia199028102134226705418RoweJBOwernAMJohnsrudeISPassinghamREImaging the mental components of a planning taskNeuropsychologia200139315271116360919MaddenDJWhitingWLHuettelSAWhiteLEMacFallJRProvenzaleJMDiffusion tensor imaging of adult age differences in cerebral white matter: Relation to response timeNeuroimage2004311748115006684
