<?xml version="1.0"?>
BMC PsychiatryBMC PsychiatryBMC Psychiatry1471-244XBioMed CentralLondon44890432613872651510.1186/s12888-015-0515-9Study ProtocolInvestigating neural mechanisms of change of cognitive behavioural therapy for chronic fatigue syndrome: a randomized controlled trialvan Der SchaafMarieke Emarieke.vanderschaaf@donders.ru.nl123SchmitsIris Ciris.schmits@radboudumc.nl1RoerinkMeganMegan.Roerink@radboudumc.nl4GeurtsDirk EMdirk.e.m.geurts@gmail.com5ToniIvanivan.toni@donders.ru.nl2RoelofsKarink.roelofs@donders.ru.nl6De LangeFloris Pfloris.delange@donders.ru.nl2NaterUrs Mnater@uni-marburg.de7van der MeerJos WMJos.vanderMeer@radboudumc.nl4KnoopHanshans.knoop@radboudumc.nl11Radboud University Medical Center, Expert Centre for Chronic Fatigue, Nijmegen, The Netherlands 2Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition, and Behaviour, Centre for Neuroimaging, Radboud University Nijmegen, Nijmegen, The Netherlands 3Donders Institute, Centre for neuroimaging, Kapittelweg 29, P.O. Box 9101, NL-6500 HB Nijmegen, The Netherlands 4Department of Internal Medicine, Radboud University Medical Center, Nijmegen, The Netherlands 5Department of Psychiatry, Radboud University Medical Centre, Nijmegen, The Netherlands 6Behavioral Science Institute (BSI), Radboud University Nijmegen, Nijmegen, The Netherlands 7Department of Psychology, University of Marburg, Marburg, Germany 3720153720152015151441742015262015© van der Schaaf et al. 2015This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.BackgroundChronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) is characterized by profound and disabling fatigue with no known somatic explanation. Cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) has proven to be a successful intervention leading to a reduction in fatigue and disability. Based on previous neuroimaging findings, it has been suggested that central neural mechanisms may underlie CFS symptoms and play a role in the change brought on by CBT. In this randomized controlled trial we aim to further investigate the neural mechanisms that underlie fatigue in CFS and their change by CBT.Methods/DesignWe will conduct a randomized controlled trial in which we collect anatomical and functional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) measures from female CFS patients before and after CBT (N = 60) or waiting list (N = 30) and compare these with measures from age and education matched healthy controls (N = 30). By including a large treatment group we will also be able to compare patients that benefit from CBT with those that do not. In addition, to further investigate the role of endocrine and immune biomarkers in CFS, we will determine cortisol and cytokine concentrations in blood, hair and/or saliva.DiscussionThis project creates an unique opportunity to enhance our understanding of CFS symptoms and its change by CBT in terms of neuroanatomical, neurofunctional, endocrinological and immunological mechanisms and can help to further improve future treatments strategies.Trial registrationDutch Trial Register #15852. Registered 9 December 2013 (http://www.trialregister.nl/trialreg/admin/rctview.asp?TC=4311)KeywordsChronic fatigue syndromeCognitive behavioral therapyMRIissue-copyright-statement© The Author(s) 2015<sec xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Sec6" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods/design</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Study design</title><p>A RCT will be conducted to investigate neural correlates of change brought on by CBT in patients diagnosed with CFS. CFS patients will be randomly assigned to either the intervention group (N = 60), which will immediately start with CBT, or the waiting group (N = 30), which will start with CBT after a 6 months waiting period. In order to compare CFS patients that recover from CBT with those that do not we will use a 2:1 allocation ratio for CBT and waiting group respectively. MRI measurements, behavioral measures, questionnaires and biomarker sampling will be gathered at baseline and at a second session after approximately 6 months in both groups. Results will be compared to 30 age, gender and education matched healthy controls, which will also be tested twice, separated by a 6 months period (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Trial design. CBT = Cognitive behavioural therapy</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12888_2015_515_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e653"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Ethical aspects</title><p>The study is approved by the Medical research ethics committee and Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (registration number NL43606.091.13). This study will be conducted according to the principles of the declaration of Helsinki. CFS patients will be recruited from the Expert Centre for Chronic Fatigue (ECCF). Participants will be informed about the study and written informed consents will be obtained before the first testing day and randomization.</p><p>Participants can withdraw from the study at any time, and for any reason, without consequences. The investigator can decide to withdraw a participant from the study in case of late disclosure of exclusion criteria (e.g. psychiatric co-morbidity) or a change in meeting in- and exclusion criteria (e.g. when participant decides to start psychotropic medication after inclusion). CFS patients who (are) withdraw(n) from the study will continue to receive treatment at the ECCF. Patients that withdraw before randomization or did not start face-to-face CBT when assigned to the CBT condition and participants that are withdrawn by the investigator will be replaced when time allows. Patients that received CBT for CFS outside the ECCF during their waiting list period will be excluded from analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Study population and recruitment procedure</title><p>A total of 90 female CFS patients and 30 age and education matched female healthy controls will be recruited from the ECCF of the radboudUMC in Nijmegen, the Netherlands. Only female patients are included for homogeneity. Patients that are referred to the ECCF of the Radboudumc, are diagnosed with CFS according to the US Centers for Disease Control and prevention (CDC) consensus-criteria ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]; Reeves et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]), and scoring 40 or higher on the subscale fatigue severity of the Checklist Individual Strength (CIS) and have a total score of 700 or higher on the Sickness Impact Profile 8 (SIP8) will be informed about the study by their treating psychologist during their first intake session at the ECCF. If the patients agree, they will receive an information folder. The investigator will call the patients after a one week reflection period to answer any further questions and to ask for participation. If willing to participate, and meeting all in- and exclusion criteria (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), patients will be invited for the first testing day at the Donders institute for brain cognition and behavior. Age and education matched female healthy controls will be recruited though advertisements and through flyers in the patients folder. Interested healthy controls will receive an information folder and the recruitment procedure will follow the same steps as described above. Written informed consent will be given at the first session day. Randomization of patients will take place after the first session day. The Mini-international Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I) will be used to rule out any current psychiatric disorders.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2">Inclusion criteria</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1.</td><td>Female</td></tr><tr><td>2.</td><td>Age between 18 and 55 years</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">
<underline>Additional inclusion criteria for CFS patients</underline>
</td></tr><tr><td>1.</td><td>CFS diagnosis according to the CDC-criteria ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]; Reeves et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]);</td></tr><tr><td>2.</td><td>Fatigue severity subscale (CIS) score ≥40</td></tr><tr><td>3.</td><td>Severely disabled, defined by scoring ≥ 700 on the Sickness Impact Profile (SIP)</td></tr><tr><td>4.</td><td>Eligible for treatment with CBT</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">
<underline>Additional inclusion criteria for healthy controls</underline>
</td></tr><tr><td>5.</td><td>Fatigue severity subscale (CIS) score ≤ 35</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Exclusion criteria</td></tr><tr><td>1.</td><td>Current use of psychotropic medication (e.g. antidepressants)</td></tr><tr><td>2.</td><td>Contra-indication for MR-examinations (e.g. claustrophobia)</td></tr><tr><td>3.</td><td>Abnormal hearing or (uncorrected) vision</td></tr><tr><td>4.</td><td>Insufficient command of the Dutch language to fill out questionnaires, understand task instructions or perform the neuropsychological tests</td></tr><tr><td>5.</td><td>Restricted function of the right hand that confounds handgrip performance for the fMRI tasks</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">
<underline>Additional exclusion criteria for healthy controls</underline>
</td></tr><tr><td>6.</td><td>Current psychological or psychiatric disorder<sup>a,b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>7.</td><td>(History of) alcohol or substance abuse<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>8.</td><td>Severe obesity (BMI ≥ 40)<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>9.</td><td>Chronic disease or pain condition (e.g. rheumatoid arthritis)</td></tr><tr><td>10.</td><td>Current acute pain condition</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>these criteria are part of the CDC criteria for CFS</p><p><sup>b</sup>as revealed by the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I.)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Intervention</title><p>CBT for CFS (Heins et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]; Wiborg et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]) aims at recovery, meaning that the CFS patient is no longer severely fatigued and disabled by the fatigue, by changing cognitions and behaviors assumed to perpetuate the symptoms. Previous trials have repeatedly demonstrated that CBT for CFS leads to a significant reduction of fatigue and disability ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]; Prins et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]; White et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]; White et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]; Wiborg et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]) and to recovery in a subset of patients (Knoop et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]; White et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]). CBT treatment will be given by trained cognitive behavioral therapists at the ECCF of the radboudUMC in Nijmegen, the Netherlands. Treatment consists of 12–14 individual sessions with a trained cognitive behavioral therapist within a period of approximately 6 months. The treatment starts with explanation of the cognitive behavioral model of CFS and goal setting. Patients formulate their goals in concrete activities they will do when they are no longer bothered by fatigue, e.g. resumption of work or study. Then, patients will learn to regulate their sleep-wake cycle by maintaining fixed bedtimes and no longer sleep or lie down during the day. Once the sleep-wake cycle is regulated, patients will start with a graded activity program consisting of a graded increase in walking of cycling activities. Based on their physical activity patterns, relative active patients will first learn to better divide activities across the day before starting with the graded activity program and low active patients will start directly with the graded activity program. Dysfunctional fatigue-related cognitions, e.g. catastrophising in response to fatigue, low self-efficacy and increased focus on symptoms are challenged continuously throughout the intervention. When activity levels are increased and patients attain the belief that they have potential to be more active, they start with realization of their prior set goals. The last part of the intervention aims at reappraisal of fatigue as a normal sensation and prevention of relapse.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Outcome measures</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Primary clinical outcome measures</title><p>Fatigue severity will be measured using the subscale fatigue severity of the CIS consisting of 8 items scored on a 7-point Likert Scale with a total score ranging between 8–56 (Vercoulen et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]). Higher scores indicate higher levels of fatigue. This questionnaire has been validated extensively in patients with CFS ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]; Vercoulen et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]; Vercoulen et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]). Following previous reports (Prins et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]; Wiborg et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]) we will use cut-off score of ≥ 40 for inclusion of severely fatigued CFS patients.</p><p>Successful treatment is defined by a clinically significant improvement on the CIS sub-scale fatigue severity, i.e. scoring lower than 35 and a reliable change index of &gt;1.96 on the CIS subscale fatigue (Knoop et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]). The cut-off score of 35 has frequently been used as a criterion to indicate clinically relevant fatigue in clinical studies (Knoop et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]; Wiborg et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]).</p><p>Functional impairment will be measured in CFS patients using the Sickness Impact Profile 8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. The SIP8 contains 85 statements about health-related dysfunction in 8 areas domains (home management, ambulation, mobility, intellect, social interactions, sleep/rest behaviour, recreation and work). In completing the SIP, the patient is asked to check only those statements that she is sure describe her on a given day and are related to her health. The eight subscales are added to provide one weighted score of disability (SIP8 total, range 0–5799) (Knoop et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]; Prins et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]; Wiborg et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]). Higher scores indicate higher levels of experienced disabilities. Functional impairment will be defined as a SIP score higher than 700.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Secondary clinical measures</title><p>Fatigue related cognitions and behaviours, physical and social functioning are assessed using questionnaires as part of the clinical routine of the ECCF. A selection of these questionnaires will also be assed in the healthy control group and include the RAND-36 (Stewart et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]; Ware and Sherbourne, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]), the Beck depression Inventory (BDI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>], the Symptom Checklist 90 (SCL-90) (Arrindell and Ettema, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]), the Fatigue Quality List (KWAMOE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>], the self efficacy scale fatigue (SES) (Prins et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]; Vercoulen et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]; Wiborg et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]) and the Adjusted Physical Activities Rating Scale (PARS) (Vercoulen et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]). In addition, the attention Control Scale questionnaire (ACS)(Derryberry and Reed, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]) will be assessed in all subjects. During each test day, state changes in fatigue and mood will be assessed using the profile of moods (POMS) questionnaires (McNair et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]) at 3 time points in both patients and healthy controls.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Physical activity</title><p>Previous work in both humans[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>] and animals (Praag, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]) suggest a possible link between physical exercise and neurogenesis. Accordingly, given that graded increase of physical activity levels is an important part of the CBT program, we will also assess physical activity levels. As in the previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], physical activity levels will be assessed in all participants, over a period of two weeks preceding both test sessions using an actometer. The actometer is a motion-sensitive device, worn at the ankle, which can register and quantify human physical activity (Werf et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Neuropsychological testing</title><p>To be able to replicate previous reported correlations between grey matter volume changes and neuropsychological performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] we will assess two tasks of cognitive speed: the digit symbol substitution test of the Dutch Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (Stinnissen J et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]) and a choice reaction time task ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]; Vercoulen et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]). Additionally, working memory capacity will be assessed with the digit span of the Dutch Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (Groth-Marnat, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]; Stinnissen J et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]) and intelligence/education level will be determined with the Dutch adult reading test (Schmand et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Structural neuroimaging measures</title><p>To investigate changes in brain anatomy and metabolism, several MR-measurements will be obtained on a 3-Tesla SIEMENS MAGNETON skyra MRI scanner. To investigate global and regional grey and white matter changes high resolution anatomical images will be obtained using a T1 weighted magnetization-prepared rapid gradient-echo (MP-RAGE) sequence (TR\TE: 2300\3.03 ms, flip angle = 8°, 192 sagittal slices, FoV: 256 × 256 mm, voxelsize: 1 mm<sup>3</sup>, slice thickness: 1.00 mm). To investigate the microstructural properties of white matter pathways in the brain, diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) scans will be assessed (TR = 8200 ms, TE = 89.0 ms, voxel size: 2.2 × 2.2 × 2.2 mm, FOV 220 mm, 64 slices, slice thickness: 2.2 mm). Brain metabolite changes will be assessed using single voxel proton magnetic resonance spectroscopic (MRS) imaging (TR = 1500 ms, TE = 30 ms, and 64 averages). MRS spectra will be obtained from two voxels (10 × 20 × 30 mm): One voxel placed in the left middle frontal gyrus, corresponding to the previous reported region of CBT-associated grey matter changes in CFS patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and one voxel placed in the left calcarine gyrus (i.e.primary visual cortex) to assess regional specificity of the changes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Functional MRI</title><p>To explore task-dependent functional MRI will be assessed using a multi echo, T2*-weighted, gradient-echo planar imaging (EPI) sequence (TR = 2190 ms, TE = 9.0/19.28/29.56/39.84 ms, flip angle = 90°, 36 axial slices aligned with AC-PC plane, slice-matrix size = 64 × 64, slice thickness = 3.0 mm, slice gap = 0.3 mm, FOV = 212*212 mm). Two different tasks will be employed.</p><p>With the first task, we will assess alterations in brain activation patterns in anticipation of effortful physical exertions and in response to task-feedback about these exertions. Participants are instructed to prepare and then squeeze quickly in a hand grip up to a certain level indicated by a cue. Cues will indicate to squeeze 30, 50 or 70 % of their maximal voluntary contraction (MVC). MVC will be calibrated before and after the task to assess (change in) physical ability. Subjective experience of fatigue and effort will be assessed before and after the task. Visual feedback is provided after the squeeze and will indicate whether the squeeze was “correct”, “too little” or “too much”. Neural outcome measure is the Blood Oxygen Level Dependent (BOLD) contrast during task performance. Behavioral output is the squeezed force. We will assess the hypothesis that, compared with healthy controls, CFS patients will show alterations in neural response to “too much” and “too little” and that these alterations will vary as a function of effort level. We expect that these alterations will normalize after successful treatment. In addition, neural responses during effort anticipation will be explored.</p><p>With the second task, we will assess alterations in neural activation patterns during effort avoidance learning using an adapted version of the salience attribution task (Roiser et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]; Roiser et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]). In this task participants learn to reduce the effort level of handgrip contractions by responding sufficiently quickly to a target presented after a cue. The cues have two dimensions (shape and color) that provide information about the probability of the occurrence of the effortful handgrip contractions. One dimension is predictive for the outcome, signaling the occurrence of the effortful handgrip contractions with 80 % and 20 % certainty. The other dimension is non-predictive for the outcome, signaling the occurrence of the effortful handgrip contractions with 50 % certainty for both cues. When effortful outcomes occur, the required effort level of the handgrip contraction is reduced as a function of reaction time to the target. Thus, the faster the subject responds to the target, the lower the effort level. Neural outcome measure is the Blood Oxygen Level Dependent (BOLD) contrast during task performance. Explicit and implicit avoidance learning will be assessed using cue ratings assessed after the task, and response reaction times, respectively. Adaptive avoidance learning is defined by higher neural responses, faster reaction times and higher explicit ratings for high relative to low predictive cues. Non-adaptive avoidance learning is defined by larger differential neural responses, reaction times and explicit ratings for the two non-predictive cue dimensions. We will assess whether CFS patients will show increased adaptive and/or non-adaptive avoidance learning compared to healthy controls and whether this normalizes after CBT.</p><p>Task independent-neuroimaging will be used to explore alterations in neural networks during rest that may underlie CFS symptoms and CBT effects. A 5 minute resting state scan will be obtained to explore task-independent functional connectivity patterns using a multi echo T2*-weighted, gradient-echo planar imaging (EPI) sequence (TR = 2000 ms, TE = 9.0 ms, flip angle = 90°, voxel size = 3.3 × 3.3 × 3.3 mm, slice thickness: 3.0 mm). During the scan, the room will be completely dark and subjects are asked to lie still with their eyes open to avoid falling asleep.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Behavioral task</title><p>We will use a behavioral version of the moving dot paradigm ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]; Rahnev et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]) to investigate the influence of expectancy cues on perceptual decisions. Subjects are presented with motion of white dots and are requested to indicate the direction of movement with a button press (i.e. left or right). Moving dots are presented using three coherence levels, determined by subjects’ accuracy level during a preceding training session. Prior to each stimulus subjects are presented with the words “LEFT” or “RIGHT” indicating the direction of motion with 75 % accuracy or with the non-informative word “NEUTRAL”. After each trial feedback is given by changing the colour of the fixation point to green (correct) or red (incorrect). Behavioural outcome measures are the direction of the movement indicated by the participant and reaction times. As described by ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]; Rahnev et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]), subjects’ hit rates will be used to calculate individual stimulus discrimination sensitivity (d’) and bias towards the cued direction (c). Following Edwards model (see introduction) we will test the hypothesis that CFS patients show a larger bias towards the cued direction compared to healthy controls and whether this changes following CBT.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Citokines and cortisol</title><p>Circulating cytokine concentrations will be determined in blood-plasma using a commercial multiplex assay. Using pax-gene tubes, cytokine mRNA concentrations will be measured. The latter will give more insight into upstream regulation of local cytokine production. Cortisol concentrations will be determined from saliva and hair. We will measure both daily variations of cortisol levels (i.e. cortisol awakening response) in saliva as well as baseline cortisol levels of the past month in hair. Blood and hair samples will be assessed on each test day. Saliva will be collected at home during two consecutive weekdays within two weeks prior to or after each test day. Saliva samples will be taken at 4 different time points during a day: directly after waking, 30 minutes after waking, around 11.00 a.m. or at least 1 hour after the second sampling and around 08.00 p.m. Cytokine and cortisol concentrations will be compared between CFS and HC and before and after CBT or waiting list.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Session procedure</title><p>Participants will be invited to the Donders institute for brain cognition and behavior on two session days separated by approximately 6 months. Each session will include the following procedures: (1) hair and blood sampling. (2) practice of fMRI tasks, including the calibration of MVC for the two fMRI tasks. The practice session is done in a dummy scanner to ensure same body position during handgrip-calibration, practice and fMRI-scanning. (3) MRI scanning, including six scans and a 15 minute break: structural MRI, fMRI during task1, MRS, break, fMRI during task2, DTI and resting state. (4) Behavioral and neuropsychological testing. The order is kept the same across subjects and sessions. An overview of a session day is given in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Written informed consent is given on the first session day. Trait measures such as the adult reading test are only assessed on the first test day. POMS measurements are assessed before sampling, during the break and after behavioral testing. The total duration of each session will be about 5 hours. For CFS patients, questionnaires are assessed as part of the clinical routine of the ECCF prior to the session days. For healthy controls, questionnaires are assessed at home through an internet link, sent to the subjects by email.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Flowchart of fMRI session day. MVC = Maximal voluntaty contraction, MRI = Magnetic resonance imaging, fMRI = functional MRI</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12888_2015_515_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e1098"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Analysis</title><p>The aim of this project is to explore the neural mechanisms of change underlying (successful) CBT for CFS. Accordingly, we will include all patients that completed both sessions for analysis of CBT effects. Statistical analysis will be done to 1) compare outcome measures between CFS patients and healthy controls at baseline, 2) compare changes between baseline and second assessment between patients that had CBT and waiting list and 3) compare changes between baseline and second assessment between CFS patients within the CBT condition that show clinical significant improvement (see above) and those that do not. Following previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], relationship between neural outcome measures and clinical outcome measures, physical activity levels and neuropsychological functioning will be assessed. Multiple mediation analyses will be conducted to explore whether neural outcome measures mediate therapy effects on clinical outcome measures (Preacher and Hayes, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Sample size</title><p>Power calculation is based on current standards in neuroimaging. For (f)MRI, the recommended number of subjects for between-group designs is 20 (Thirion et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]). In addition, from previous studies we know that groups of 20 subjects per condition are sufficient to detect significant differences in (neuro) physiological parameters measured with fMRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Similarly, a group of 22 subjects were sufficient to detect significant treatment effects measured with MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Based on previous work at the ECCF (Knoop et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]) it is assumed that approximately 50 % of the CFS patients in the CBT condition will show significant improvement (for definition: see above). Accordingly, to be able to compare successfully treated patients with non-successfully treated patients we will include twice as many patients in the CBT condition as in the waiting list condition. Assuming that 10 % of the measurements (from baseline as well as 2nd assessment) will yield technically insufficient data, 17 % of the patients will drop out from the study and a ratio of 2:1 (CBT: waiting list), we will include 30 healthy controls, 30 patients in the waiting list condition and 60 patients in the CBT condition (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Based on previous clinical work (Knoop et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]; Wiborg et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]), we expect a mean decline of–15.2 (±15.8) for patients in the CBT condition and–5.2 (±7.2) for patients in the waiting list condition. Accordingly, assuming an alfa of 0.05 and a power of 0.95 this will also yield enough power to replicate previous reported treatment effects on the primary clinical outcome measures. Note that technical failure of MRI measurements will not affect the collection of clinical measures.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Flowchart of inclusion. CFS = Chronic fatigue syndrome, CBT = Cognitive behavioural therapy</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12888_2015_515_Fig3_HTML" id="d30e1151"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Randomization</title><p>CFS patients will be randomized to either the CBT condition (66 %) or waiting list condition (33 %). Randomization will take place per patient after the first session day in the presence of the therapist and patient, either during the second diagnostic appointment with the therapist or during a phone call with the therapist. Randomization will be done by supporting staff of the ECCF who are not directly involved in the study. Concealed allocation will be guaranteed by using a central web-based randomization program, developed by an independent statistical advisor. Patients randomized to the intervention group will start treatment directly and will be treated with CBT for CFS (see above). Patients randomized to the control group will start with CBT for CFS 6 months later, after the second assessment. The researchers that will collect and analyze the data are not blind to the allocation, because knowledge of treatment progress is necessary for the planning of the second test day.</p></sec></sec>Competing interestsThe author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.Authors’ contributionsMS, IT, KR, FL, JM and HK participated in the design of the study; IT, KR, FL and HK will help with MRI and behavioral data analysis and drafting of potential manuscripts; MS and IS coordinate the study, collect the data, perform MRI and behavioral data analysis and drafted the manuscript; HK and IT help coordinate the study and helped drafting the manuscript; DG acts as medical responsible person and will help drafting potential manuscripts, JM, UN and MR will analyze blood, saliva and hair samples and draft potential manuscripts; JM and HK obtained the grant, IT and HK supervise the study. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.Authors’ informationM.E. van der Schaaf, PhD, Post-doctoral researcher, affiliations: Radboud University Nijmegen, Donders institute for Brain cognition and behaviour and Radboud UMC Nijmegen, Expert Centre for Chronic FatigueI.C. Schmits, MSc, Research Assistant, affiliation: Radboud UMC Nijmegen, Expert Centre for Chronic FatigueM. Roerink, MD, affliation: RadboudUMC, Nijmegen, Department of Internal MedicineD.E.M. Geurts, MD, affiliations: Radboud University Nijmegen, Donders institute for Brain cognition and behaviour and Radboud UMC Nijmegen, Department of psychiatryProf. Toni, Principle investigator Donders Institute, affiliations: Radboud University Nijmegen, Donders institute for Brain cognition and behaviourProf. K. Roelofs, Principle investigator Donders Institute, affiliations: Radboud University Nijmegen, Donders institute for Brain cognition and behaviourF.P. De Lange, Junior Principle investigator Donders Institute, affiliation: Radboud University Nijmegen, Donders institute for Brain cognition and behaviourProf. U.M. Nater, affiliation: University of Marburg, Department of Psychology, GermanyProf. J.W.M. van der Meer, affiliation: RadboudUMC, Nijmegen, Department of Internal MedicineH. Knoop, PhD, Head of Expert Centre for Chronic Fatigue, affiliation: Radboud UMC Nijmegen, Expert Centre for Chronic FatigueReferences1.FukudaKStrausSEHickieISharpeMCDobbinsJGKomaroffAThe chronic fatigue syndrome: a comprehensive approach to its definition and study. International chronic fatigue syndrome study groupAnn Intern Med19941211295395910.7326/0003-4819-121-12-199412150-0000979787222.ReevesWCLloydAVernonSDIdentification of ambiguities in the 1994 chronic fatigue syndrome research case definition and recommendations for resolutionBMC Health Serv Res2003312510.1186/1472-6963-3-25147022023.PrinsJvan der MeerJBleijenbergGChronic fatigue syndromeLancet2006367950734635510.1016/S0140-6736(06)68073-2164430434.CastellBKazantzisNMoss-MorrisRCognitive behavioral therapy and graded exercise for chronic fatigue syndrome: a meta-analysisClin Psychol Sci Pract20111831132410.1111/j.1468-2850.2011.01262.x5.KnoopHBleijenbergGGielissenMFvan der MeerJWWhitePDIs a full recovery possible after cognitive behavioural therapy for chronic fatigue syndrome?Psychother Psychosom200776317117610.1159/000099844174264166.WhitePGoldsmithKJohnsonAChalderTSharpeMGroup PTMRecovery from chronic fatigue syndrome after treatments given in the PACE trialPsychol Med2013431022273510.1017/S0033291713000020233636407.Chalder T, Goldsmith KA, White PD, Sharpe M, Pickles AR (2015). Rehabilitative therapies for chronic fatigue syndrome: a secondary mediation analysis of the PACE trial. The Lancet Psychiatry.8.KnoopHPrinsJMoss-MorrisRBleijenbergGThe central role of cognitive processes in the perpetuation of chronic fatigue syndromeJ Psychosom Res201068548949410.1016/j.jpsychores.2010.01.022204035099.WiborgJKnoopHFrankLBleijenbergGTowards an evidence-based treatment model for cognitive behavioral interventions focusing on chronic fatigue syndromeJ Psychosom Res201272539940410.1016/j.jpsychores.2012.01.0182246928410.WiborgJKnoopHPrinsJBleijenbergGDoes a decrease in avoidance behavior and focusing on fatigue mediate the effect of cognitive behavior therapy for chronic fatigue syndrome?J Psychosom Res201170430631010.1016/j.jpsychores.2010.12.0112141444911.WiborgJFKnoopHStulemeijerMPrinsJBBleijenbergGHow does cognitive behaviour therapy reduce fatigue in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome? The role of physical activityPsychol Med20104081281128710.1017/S00332917099922122004770712.BrowningMFletcherPSharpeMCan neuroimaging help us to understand and classify somatoform disorders? A systematic and critical reviewPsychosom Med201173217318410.1097/PSY.0b013e31820824f62121709513.De LangeFKalkmanJBleijenbergGHagoortPvan der MeerJToniIGray matter volume reduction in the chronic fatigue syndromeNeuroimage200526377778110.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.02.0371595548714.De LangeFKoersAKalkmanJBleijenbergGHagoortPvan der MeerJIncrease in prefrontal cortical volume following cognitive behavioural therapy in patients with chronic fatigue syndromeBrain : a journal of neurology2008131Pt 82172218010.1093/brain/awn1401858715015.OkadaTTanakaMKuratsuneHWatanabeYSadatoNMechanisms underlying fatigue: a voxel-based morphometric study of chronic fatigue syndromeBMC Neurol2004411410.1186/1471-2377-4-141546181716.ZeinehMMKangJAtlasSWRamanMMReissALNorrisJLRight arcuate fasciculus abnormality in chronic fatigue syndromeRadiology201427425172610.1148/radiol.141410792535305417.CaserasXMataix-ColsDGiampietroVRimesKBrammerMZelayaFProbing the working memory system in chronic fatigue syndrome: a functional magnetic resonance imaging study using the n-back taskPsychosom Med200668694795510.1097/01.psy.0000242770.50979.5f1707970318.CaserasXMataix-ColsDRimesKGiampietroVBrammerMZelayaFThe neural correlates of fatigue: an exploratory imaginal fatigue provocation study in chronic fatigue syndromePsychol Med200838794195110.1017/S00332917080034501844796319.CookDO’ConnorPLangeGSteffenerJFunctional neuroimaging correlates of mental fatigue induced by cognition among chronic fatigue syndrome patients and controlsNeuroImage200736110812210.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.02.0331740897320.De LangeFKalkmanJBleijenbergGHagoortPvan der WerfSvan der MeerJNeural correlates of the chronic fatigue syndrome–an fMRI studyBrain : a journal of neurology2004127Pt 91948195710.1093/brain/awh2251524043521.LangeGSteffenerJCookDBlyBChristodoulouCLiuWCObjective evidence of cognitive complaints in chronic fatigue syndrome: a BOLD fMRI study of verbal working memoryNeuroImage200526251352410.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.02.0111590730822.NakatomiYMizunoKIshiiAWadaYTanakaMTazawaSNeuroinflammation in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis: an 11C-(R)-PK11195 PET studyJ Nucl Med201455694595010.2967/jnumed.113.1310452466508823.StraumanTJGoetzELDetloffAMMacDuffieKEZaunmüllerLLutzWSelf-regulation and mechanisms of action in psychotherapy: a theory-based translational perspectiveJ Pers201381654255310.1111/jopy.120122307238324.BeauregardMFunctional neuroimaging studies of the effects of psychotherapyDialogues Clin Neurosci201416175812473397225.EtkinAPittengerCPolanHJKandelERToward a neurobiology of psychotherapy: basic science and clinical applicationsJ Neuropsychiatry Clinical Neurosciences200517214515810.1176/jnp.17.2.14526.MoffettJRRossBArunPMadhavaraoCNNamboodiriAMN-Acetylaspartate in the CNS: from neurodiagnostics to neurobiologyProg Neurobiol20078128913110.1016/j.pneurobio.2006.12.0031727597827.ChangLMunsakaSMKraft-TerrySErnstTMagnetic resonance spectroscopy to assess neuroinflammation and neuropathic painJ Neuroimmune Pharmacology20138357659310.1007/s11481-013-9460-x28.BrooksJCRobertsNWhitehouseGMajeedTProton magnetic resonance spectroscopy and morphometry of the hippocampus in chronic fatigue syndromeBr J Radiol2000738751206120810.1259/bjr.73.875.111447991114479929.PuriBKCounsellSJZamanRMainJCollinsAGHajnalJVRelative increase in choline in the occipital cortex in chronic fatigue syndromeActa Psychiatr Scand2002106322422610.1034/j.1600-0447.2002.01300.x1219786130.TomodaAMiikeTYamadaEHondaHMoroiTOgawaMChronic fatigue syndrome in childhoodBrain Dev2000221606410.1016/S0387-7604(99)00111-41076183731.ChaudhuriABehanPOIn vivo magnetic resonance spectroscopy in chronic fatigue syndromeProstaglandins Leukot Essent Fat Acids200471318118310.1016/j.plefa.2004.03.00932.HarrisREClauwDJImaging central neurochemical alterations in chronic pain with proton magnetic resonance spectroscopyNeurosci Lett2012520219219610.1016/j.neulet.2012.03.0422244584533.NiddamDMTsaiSYLuCLKoCWReduced hippocampal glutamate–glutamine levels in irritable bowel syndrome: preliminary findings using magnetic resonance spectroscopyAm J Gastroenterol2011106815031110.1038/ajg.2011.1202150299934.HarrisRESundgrenPCPangYHsuMPetrouMKimS-HHDynamic levels of glutamate within the insula are associated with improvements in multiple pain domains in fibromyalgiaArthritis Rheum200858390390710.1002/art.232231831181435.PetrouMHarrisREFoersterBRProton MR spectroscopy in the evaluation of cerebral metabolism in patients with fibromyalgia: comparison with healthy controls and correlation with symptom severityAJNR Am J Neuroradiol2008295913810.3174/ajnr.A09591833972336.FayedNAndresERojasGMorenoSSerrano-BlancoARocaMBrain dysfunction in fibromyalgia and somatization disorder using proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy: a controlled studyActa Psychiatr Scand2012126211512510.1111/j.1600-0447.2011.01820.x2221132237.AbdallahCGNiciuMJFentonLRFasulaMKJiangLBlackADecreased occipital cortical glutamate levels in response to successful cognitive-behavioral therapy and pharmacotherapy for major depressive disorderPsychother Psychosom201483529830710.1159/0003610782511672638.O’NeillJGorbisEFeusnerJDYipJCChangSMaidmentKMEffects of intensive cognitive-behavioral therapy on cingulate neurochemistry in obsessive-compulsive disorderJ Psychiatr Res201347449450410.1016/j.jpsychires.2012.11.0102329056039.ZurowskiBKordonAWeber-FahrWVoderholzerUKuelzAKFreyerTRelevance of orbitofrontal neurochemistry for the outcome of cognitive-behavioural therapy in patients with obsessive-compulsive disorderEur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci2012262761762410.1007/s00406-012-0304-02242715140.BeaulieuCThe basis of anisotropic water diffusion in the nervous system-a technical reviewNMR Biomed2002157–843545510.1002/nbm.7821248909441.EdwardsMAdamsRBrownHPareésIFristonKA Bayesian account of ‘hysteria’Brain : a journal of neurology2012135Pt 113495351210.1093/brain/aws1292264183842.VercoulenJSwaninkCGalamaJFennisJJongenPHommesOThe persistence of fatigue in chronic fatigue syndrome and multiple sclerosis: development of a modelJ Psychosom Res199845650751710.1016/S0022-3999(98)00023-3985985343.NijsJAelbrechtSMeeusMVan OosterwijckJZinzenEClarysPTired of being inactive: a systematic literature review of physical activity, physiological exercise capacity and muscle strength in patients with chronic fatigue syndromeDisabil Rehabil20113317–181493150010.3109/09638288.2010.5415432116661344.WerfSPPrinsJBVercoulenJMeerJWMBleijenbergGIdentifying physical activity patterns in chronic fatigue syndrome using actigraphic assessmentJ Psychosom Res200049537337910.1016/S0022-3999(00)00197-51116406345.FryAMartinMFatigue in the chronic fatigue syndrome: a cognitive phenomenon?J Psychosom Res199641541542610.1016/S0022-3999(96)00190-0903270646.RileyMO’BrienCMcCluskeyDBellNNichollsDAerobic work capacity in patients with chronic fatigue syndromeBMJ (Clinical research ed)1990301675895395610.1136/bmj.301.6758.95347.SchillingsMKalkmanJvan der WerfSVan EngelenBBleijenbergGZwartsMDiminished central activation during maximal voluntary contraction in chronic fatigue syndromeClin Neurophysiol2004115112518252410.1016/j.clinph.2004.06.0071546544148.HeinsMKnoopHNijsJFeskensRMeeusMMoorkensGInfluence of Symptom Expectancies on Stair-Climbing Performance in Chronic Fatigue Syndrome: Effect of Study ContextInt J Behav Med201220213810.1007/s12529-012-9253-22286510049.NijsJMeeusMHeinsMKnoopHMoorkensGBleijenbergGKinesiophobia, catastrophizing and anticipated symptoms before stair climbing in chronic fatigue syndrome: an experimental studyDisabil Rehabil201234151299130510.3109/09638288.2011.6416612232451050.DealeAChalderTWesselySIllness beliefs and treatment outcome in chronic fatigue syndromeJ Psychosom Res1998451778310.1016/S0022-3999(98)00021-X972085751.NijsJRousselNVan OosterwijckJDe KooningMIckmansKStruyfFFear of movement and avoidance behaviour toward physical activity in chronic-fatigue syndrome and fibromyalgia: state of the art and implications for clinical practiceClin Rheumatol20133281121112910.1007/s10067-013-2277-42363999052.Roiser JP, Howes OD, Chaddock CA, Joyce EM, McGuire P. Neural and behavioral correlates of aberrant salience in individuals at risk for psychosis. Schizophr Bull. 2012.53.RoiserJPStephanKEDen OudenHEFristonKJJoyceEMAdaptive and aberrant reward prediction signals in the human brainNeuroImage201050265766410.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.11.0751996909054.RahnevDLauHDe LangeFPPrior expectation modulates the interaction between sensory and prefrontal regions in the human brainJ Neurosci20113129107411074810.1523/JNEUROSCI.1478-11.20112177561755.DantzerRHeijnenCKavelaarsALayeSCapuronLThe neuroimmune basis of fatigueTrends Neurosci2014371394610.1016/j.tins.2013.10.0032423906356.KelleyKWBluthéR-MMDantzerRZhouJ-HHShenW-HHJohnsonRWCytokine-induced sickness behaviorBrain Behav Immun2003171857.LyallMPeakmanMWesselySA systematic review and critical evaluation of the immunology of chronic fatigue syndromeJ Psychosom Res2003552799010.1016/S0022-3999(02)00515-91293250558.PowellDJLiossiCMoss-MorrisRSchlotzWUnstimulated cortisol secretory activity in everyday life and its relationship with fatigue and chronic fatigue syndrome: a systematic review and subset meta-analysisPsychoneuroendocrinology201338112405242210.1016/j.psyneuen.2013.07.0042391691159.SilvermanMNHeimCMNaterUMMarquesAHSternbergEMNeuroendocrine and immune contributors to fatiguePM &amp; R : the journal of injury, function, and rehabilitation20102533834610.1016/j.pmrj.2010.04.00860.TakLMCleareAJOrmelJManoharanAKokICWesselySMeta-analysis and meta-regression of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis activity in functional somatic disordersBiol Psychol201187218319410.1016/j.biopsycho.2011.02.0022131579661.NaterUMMaloneyEBonevaRSGurbaxaniBMLinJ-MMJonesJFAttenuated morning salivary cortisol concentrations in a population-based study of persons with chronic fatigue syndrome and well controlsJ Clin Endocrinol Metabol200893370370910.1210/jc.2007-174762.NaterUMYoungbloodLSJonesJFUngerERMillerAHReevesWCAlterations in diurnal salivary cortisol rhythm in a population-based sample of cases with chronic fatigue syndromePsychosom Med200870329830510.1097/PSY.0b013e31816510251837887563.NijhofSLRuttenJMTMUiterwaalCSBleijenbergGKimpenJLLPutteEMThe role of hypocortisolism in chronic fatigue syndromePsychoneuroendocrinology20144219920610.1016/j.psyneuen.2014.01.0172463651664.RimesKAPapadopoulosASCleareAJChalderTCortisol output in adolescents with chronic fatigue syndrome: Pilot study on the comparison with healthy adolescents and change after cognitive behavioural guided self-help treatmentJ Psychosom Res201477540941410.1016/j.jpsychores.2014.08.0182526086165.RobertsADPapadopoulosASWesselySChalderTCleareAJSalivary cortisol output before and after cognitive behavioural therapy for chronic fatigue syndromeJ Affect Disord20091151–228028610.1016/j.jad.2008.09.0131893797866.FukudaKStrausSHickieISharpeMDobbinsJKomaroffAThe chronic fatigue syndrome: a comprehensive approach to its definition and study. International Chronic Fatigue Syndrome Study GroupAnn Intern Med19941211295395910.7326/0003-4819-121-12-199412150-00009797872267.HeinsMJKnoopHBurkWJBleijenbergGThe process of cognitive behaviour therapy for chronic fatigue syndrome: which changes in perpetuating cognitions and behaviour are related to a reduction in fatigue?J Psychosom Res201375323524110.1016/j.jpsychores.2013.06.0342397241268.BronwynDCNikolaosKRonaEM-MCognitive Behavioral Therapy and Graded Exercise for Chronic Fatigue Syndrome: A Meta-AnalysisClin Psychol Sci Pract20111831132410.1111/j.1468-2850.2011.01262.x69.PrinsJBleijenbergGBazelmansEElvingLDe BooTSeverensJCognitive behaviour therapy for chronic fatigue syndrome: a multicentre randomised controlled trialLancet2001357925984184710.1016/S0140-6736(00)04198-21126595370.WhitePGoldsmithKJohnsonAPottsLWalwynRDeCesareJComparison of adaptive pacing therapy, cognitive behaviour therapy, graded exercise therapy, and specialist medical care for chronic fatigue syndrome (PACE): a randomised trialLancet2011377976882383610.1016/S0140-6736(11)60096-22133406171.VercoulenJSwaninkCFennisJGalamaJvan der MeerJBleijenbergGDimensional assessment of chronic fatigue syndromeJ Psychosom Res199438538339210.1016/0022-3999(94)90099-X796592772.BeurskensABültmannUKantIJFatigue among working people: validity of a questionnaire measureOccup Environ Med2000575353710.1136/oem.57.5.3531076930273.DittnerAJWesselySCBrownRGThe assessment of fatigue: a practical guide for clinicians and researchersJ Psychosom Res200456215717010.1016/S0022-3999(03)00371-41501657374.KnoopHvan der MeerJWBleijenbergGGuided self-instructions for people with chronic fatigue syndrome: randomised controlled trialBr J Psychiatr2008193434034110.1192/bjp.bp.108.05129275.WiborgJFWensingMTummersMKnoopHBleijenbergGImplementing evidence-based practice for patients with chronic fatigue syndromeClin Psychol Psychother201421210811410.1002/cpp.18272322995676.BergnerMBobbittRACarterWBGilsonBSThe Sickness Impact Profile: development and final revision of a health status measureMed Care198119878780510.1097/00005650-198108000-00001727841677.StewartAHaysRWareJThe MOS short-form general health survey. Reliability and validity in a patient populationMed Care198826772473510.1097/00005650-198807000-00007339303278.WareJESherbourneCDThe MOS 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36): I. Conceptual framework and item selectionMed Care199230647348310.1097/00005650-199206000-00002159391479.BeckATWardCHMendelsonMMockJErbaughJAn inventory for measuring depressionArch Gen Psychiatry1961456157110.1001/archpsyc.1961.017101200310041368836980.Arrindell WAM, Ettema H. Dimensionele structuur, betrouwbaarheid en validiteit van de Nederlandse bewerking van de Symptom Checklist (SCL-90). Tijdschrift voor de Psychologie en haar. 1981.81.GielissenMKnoopHServaesPKalkmanJHuibersMVerhagenSDifferences in the experience of fatigue in patients and healthy controls: patients’ descriptionsHealth Qual Life Outcome200753610.1186/1477-7525-5-3682.VercoulenJBazelmansESwaninkCMAPhysical activity in chronic fatigue syndrome: assessment and its role in fatigueJ Psychiatr Res19973166617310.1016/S0022-3956(97)00039-3944757183.Derryberry D, Reed MA. Anxiety-related attentional biases and their regulation by attentional control. J Abnorm Psychol. 2002.84.McNair D, Lorr M, Droppleman L. Profile of mood states (POMS). Profile of mood states (POMS). 1989.85.EricksonKILeckieRLWeinsteinAMPhysical activity, fitness, and gray matter volumeNeurobiol Aging2014352S20810.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2014.03.0342495299386.Praag VH. Neurogenesis and exercise: past and future directions. Neruomol Med. 2008.87.StinnissenJWillems PJLCHandleiding bij de Nederlandse bewerking van de WAISS1970Swets and Zeitlinger: AmsterdamManual of the Dutch edition of the WAIS88.Groth-MarnatGGroth-MarnatGThe Wechsler Intelligence ScalesHandbook of psychological assessment1997Hoboken, New JerseyWiley &amp; Sons17517689.SchmandBBakkerDSaanRLoumanJThe Dutch Reading Test for Adults: a measure of premorbid intelligence levelTijdschr Gerontol Geriatr19912211519187706890.De LangeFPRahnevDADonnerTHLauHPrestimulus oscillatory activity over motor cortex reflects perceptual expectationsJ Neurosci20133341400141010.1523/JNEUROSCI.1094-12.20132334521691.PreacherKJHayesAFAsymptotic and resampling strategies for assessing and comparing indirect effects in multiple mediator modelsBehav Res Methods200840387989110.3758/BRM.40.3.8791869768492.ThirionBPinelPMeriauxSRocheADehaeneSPolineJAnalysis of a large fMRI cohort: Statistical and methodological issues for group analysesNeuroImage200735110512010.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.11.0541723961993.SeminowiczDAShpanerMKeaserMLCognitive-Behavioral Therapy Increases Prefrontal Cortex Gray Matter in Patients With Chronic PainJ Pain2013141215738410.1016/j.jpain.2013.07.02024135432
