<?xml version="1.0"?>
Front PsychiatryFront PsychiatryFront. PsychiatryFrontiers in Psychiatry1664-0640Frontiers Media S.A.502884010.3389/fpsyt.2016.00154PsychiatryOriginal ResearchA Pilot Study of Mindfulness-Based Exposure Therapy in OEF/OIF Combat Veterans with PTSD: Altered Medial Frontal Cortex and Amygdala Responses in Social–Emotional ProcessingKingAnthony P.12*BlockStefanie R.3SripadaRebecca K.24RauchSheila A. M.56PorterKatherine E.1FavoriteTodd K.127GiardinoNicholas2LiberzonIsrael121Mental Health Service, VA Ann Arbor Health System, Ann Arbor, MI, USA2Department of Psychiatry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA3Department of Psychology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA4VA Center for Clinical Management Research, Ann Arbor, MI, USA5Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA6Mental Health Service, Atlanta VA Medical Center, Atlanta, GA, USA7Mary A. Rackham Institute (MARI), University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USAEdited by: Brian Edward Engdahl, University of Minnesota, USAReviewed by: Steven J. A. Van Der Werff, Leiden University, Netherlands; Annette Beatrix Bruehl, University of Zurich, Switzerland*Correspondence: Anthony P. King, samadhi@med.umich.eduSpecialty section: This article was submitted to Neuroimaging and Stimulation, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychiatry20920162016715417220162582016Copyright © 2016 King, Block, Sripada, Rauch, Porter, Favorite, Giardino and Liberzon.2016King, Block, Sripada, Rauch, Porter, Favorite, Giardino and LiberzonThis is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.Combat-related posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is common among returning veterans, and is a serious and debilitating disorder. While highly effective treatments involving trauma exposure exist, difficulties with engagement and early drop may lead to sub-optimal outcomes. Mindfulness training may provide a method for increasing emotional regulation skills that may improve engagement in trauma-focused therapy. Here, we examine potential neural correlates of mindfulness training and in vivo exposure (non-trauma focused) using a novel group therapy [mindfulness-based exposure therapy (MBET)] in Afghanistan (OEF) or Iraq (OIF) combat veterans with PTSD. OEF/OIF combat veterans with PTSD (N = 23) were treated with MBET (N = 14) or a comparison group therapy [Present-centered group therapy (PCGT), N = 9]. PTSD symptoms were assessed at pre- and post-therapy with Clinician Administered PTSD scale. Functional neuroimaging (3-T fMRI) before and after therapy examined responses to emotional faces (angry, fearful, and neutral faces). Patients treated with MBET had reduced PTSD symptoms (effect size d = 0.92) but effect was not significantly different from PCGT (d = 0.43). Improvement in PTSD symptoms from pre- to post-treatment in both treatment groups was correlated with increased activity in rostral anterior cingulate cortex, dorsal medial prefrontal cortex (mPFC), and left amygdala. The MBET group showed greater increases in amygdala and fusiform gyrus responses to Angry faces, as well as increased response in left mPFC to Fearful faces. These preliminary findings provide intriguing evidence that MBET group therapy for PTSD may lead to changes in neural processing of social–emotional threat related to symptom reduction.PTSDmindfulnessfMRI BOLDamygdalaexposure therapydorsal anterior cingulate cortexU.S. Department of Defense10.13039/100000005W81XWH-08-2-0208<sec xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2-1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S2-1-1"><title>Participants</title><p>The study was approved by the Institutional Review Boards at the University of Michigan Medical School and the Ann Arbor VA. Written informed consent was obtained after a complete description of the study was provided to the participants. We recruited male OEF/OIF combat veterans with PTSD (<italic>N</italic> = 23) seeking treatment for PTSD at the VA Ann Arbor Health System (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). All individuals met DSM-IV criteria for current (past month) PTSD, as assessed by the Clinician Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS) (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Participants were also assessed for comorbid disorders using the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI) (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Participants with psychosis, personality disorders, or suicidal risk were excluded. Psychiatric medications were allowed, but no changes in medications were allowed from 4 weeks before the intake scan until the end of the interventions and post-intervention scan. No differences in presence of medications were observed between the treatment group (medications included SSRI: citalopram, fluoxetine, sertraline, venlafaxine; Sleep: trazadone, zolpidem; Pain: codeine, morphine, tramadol; Benzodiazepine: clonazepam, lorazepam; Other: aripiprazole, buproprion, prazocin, sumatriptan, topiramate).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Demographics</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBET (<italic>N</italic> = 14)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCGT (<italic>N</italic> = 9)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t/</italic>χ<sup>2</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, M (SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.43 (7.54)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.67 (10.14)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.207</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.838</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race, <italic>N</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> European American</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (93%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (89%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> African American</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education, <italic>N</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.431</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.489</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Some grad school or graduate degree</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Some college or college degree</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High school grad</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAPS, M (SD)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.29 (18.32)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.11 (15.34)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.213</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities, <italic>N</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mood disorder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (93%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (67%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.616</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anxiety disorder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (21%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Substance use disorder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (21%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.218</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatric medications</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (14%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.168</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.280</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SSRI</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (29%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.809</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (14%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.240</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.624</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Benzodiazepine</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (21%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pain</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (21%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (36%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.028</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.311</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S2-1-2"><title>Procedure</title><p>Participants underwent a functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) scan within 2 weeks of the initial screening visit. Patients were randomized into one of two 16-week group therapy groups for PTSD: MBET or PCGT, each with two to six patients per group. However, randomization was only partial because the PCGT arm was discontinued during the trial due to higher drop-out rate and recruitment difficulties. Within 2 weeks after the end of the interventions, participants underwent a second diagnostic interview and fMRI scan.</p></sec><sec id="S2-1-3"><title>Therapists and Raters</title><p>Therapists were doctoral and masters-level psychologists at a VA PTSD clinic who had training in MBCT and in PCT. Trained, experienced clinical raters administered diagnostic clinical interviews (CAPS and MINI) and were blind to treatment condition.</p><sec id="S2-1-3-1"><title>Mindfulness-Based Exposure Therapy</title><p>This 16-week non-trauma-focused intervention was developed by the authors at the VA Ann Arbor, incorporating mindfulness training from MBCT, PTSD psycho-education and <italic>in vivo</italic> exposure from prolonged exposure therapy, and self-compassion exercises as we have recently described (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). <italic>In vivo</italic> exposures were conducted only to avoided (and objectively safe) situations or activities. It was explicitly stated that no imaginal exposure or processing of trauma memories would be done in this group. The intervention consists of four “modules”: (a) PTSD psycho-education and relaxation, (b) mindfulness of body and breath exercises and <italic>in vivo</italic> exposure, (c) mindfulness of emotion and <italic>in vivo</italic> exposure, and (d) self-compassion training. The group sessions were 2 h each and participants completed daily homework in between sessions, involving formal and informal mindfulness practice and <italic>in vivo</italic> exposure, but no trauma exposure or processing.</p></sec><sec id="S2-1-3-2"><title>Present-Centered Group Therapy</title><p>This therapy was initially developed by Schnurr et al. (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) to represent all of the elements of effective PTSD treatment that are not specifically trauma-focused. PCGT is a group intervention derived from and with the same content as an individual therapy (PCT) that has considerable efficacy for improvement in PTSD symptoms in military veterans (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). PCGT controls for non-specific therapeutic factors such as group bonding and therapist support, as well as contact with therapists with specialized knowledge about PTSD. It focuses on identifying and discussing current life stressors that contribute to PTSD, group problem solving, psycho-education, and promotion of wellness and physical health. Similar to the MBET group, the intervention contains daily homework assignments, involving monitoring diaries of stressful situations and when PTSD symptoms cause impairment in social and occupational functioning, and also meets for 2 h a week for 16 weeks. It does not contain instructions on mindfulness, exposure, or cognitive restructuring.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S2-1-4"><title>MRI Scanning</title><p>At week 0–1 (prior to starting group therapy) and at weeks 17–18 (after group termination), participants underwent both structural and functional MRI scanning. The functional MRI session included the emotional faces task reported here, a resting-state scan and a separate emotion regulation task in which aversive general social–emotional scenes [from the international affective picture set (“IAPS”)] were viewed (results reported separately). This paper reports results obtained from an emotional faces processing task. To control for potential order effects (“bleed over”), the order of tasks were counter balanced in a pseudo-randomized manner. It should be noted that no “trauma-related” tasks (e.g., trauma script-driven imagery, Iraq, Afghanistan, or combat-related imagery tasks, etc.) were performed in this study. fMRI data are available from <italic>N</italic> = 23 PTSD patients reported here, out of a total of <italic>N</italic> = 38 who started one of the two group therapies. Patients in the initial therapy groups in the study were not scanned.</p></sec><sec id="S2-1-5"><title>fMRI Data Acquisition and Analyses</title><p>All scanning was performed using a Philips 3-Tesla MRI scanner (Phillips Medical Systems, Andover, MA, USA) in the fMRI laboratory at the Ann Arbor VA. A total of 240 T2*-weighted echo planar gradient-recall echo volumes were acquired during rest (echo time = 30 ms, repetition time = 2000 ms, 64 × 64 matrix, flip angle = 90°, field of view = 22 cm, 42 contiguous 3 mm axial slices per volume). Five additional volumes were discarded at the beginning of each run to allow for equilibration of the MRI signal. A high-resolution T1-weighted structural image (3D turbo-fast-field-echo, 1 mm isotropic voxel, 256<sup>2</sup> matrix, 180 slices, repetition time = 9.8 ms, echo time = 4.6 ms, flip angle = 8°) was also obtained to provide for more precise anatomical localization. fMRI data were analyzed using the statistical parametric mapping software package, SPM8 (Wellcome Department of Cognitive Neurology, London, UK). Functional slices within each volume were sinc-interpolated, weighted in time, slice-by-slice, to correct for the sequence of slice acquisition. The functional volumes were realigned to correct for head motion and structural images coregistered to the mean of functional images. The structural images were spatially normalized to a standard Montreal Neurological Institute (MNI) template using the voxel-based morphometry toolbox (VBM8; <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dbm.neuro.uni-jena.de/vbm">http://dbm.neuro.uni-jena.de/vbm</uri>) and DARTEL high dimensional warping (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Estimated deformation fields from warping were applied to normalize images to MNI space, and smoothed using an 8-mm FWHM Gaussian kernel. Functional data are detrended to account for scanner drift.</p></sec><sec id="S2-1-6"><title>Experimental Paradigm</title><p>This paper reports results from a variant of an emotional faces matching task (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). This task has previously been shown to reliably and robustly engage the amygdala and has been widely used to assess amygdala’s reactivity to social cues, and we have previously reported this task (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Participants viewed a trio of faces on the screen and were instructed to choose one of the two faces on the bottom that expressed the same emotion as the target face on top. The face photographs were selected from a validated stimulus set (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). The identities of the three faces were different and overall an equal number of male and female faces were presented. We studied target and congruent probe faces displaying one of three expressions (angry, fearful, or neutral); and the other (incongruent) probe faces always displayed a neutral face (during emotional target blocks) or a pseudo random emotional face (during neutral target blocks). Equal numbers of angry and fearful faces were randomly presented across trials. Blocks of face-matching tasks were interspersed with blocks of a baseline task of matching geometric shapes (circles, rectangles, and triangles) with similar instructions as above to maintain attention and provide a non-emotion processing contrast. Three blocks of each emotional face were presented, interspersed with blocks of shapes; each block was presented for 20 s.</p></sec><sec id="S2-1-7"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using the statistical parametric mapping software package, SPM8 (Welcome Department of Cognitive Neurology, London, UK). Functional volumes were slice time corrected to account for temporal differences in slice acquisition time, realigned to the 10th volume to correct for head motion, segmented into gray matter, white matter, and CSF using the voxel-based morphometry toolbox (VBM8) and spatially normalized to a standard template based on the MNI reference brain using DARTEL high dimensional warping, and spatially smoothed using a 6-mm FWHM Gaussian kernel. Single-subject analysis was performed using standard GLM analysis in SPM8. Models consisted of regressors for task conditions (angry, fearful, and neutral blocks) as well as nuisance regressors consisting of the motion correction parameters from the realignment preprocessing step. Contrasts of responses of each facial expression to shapes were generated for each subject, and then entered into a second-level general linear model treating subject as a random effect (random effects analysis). We utilized the analysis strategy used by multiple previous studies (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>–<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) to explore the potential specific signature effects of each of the threat faces (fearful and angry) as well as neutral faces separately contrasted to the shapes condition (angry &gt; shapes, fearful &gt; shapes, neutral &gt; shapes). Our approach to model each facial expression (contrasted with shapes) allows us to examine effects of treatment on each face type, and is less potentially ambiguous than using a contrast of emotional faces &gt; neutral faces. Previous work has reported that “neutral” faces have robust amygdala responses (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>–<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) and amygdala responses to neutral expression faces appears to be moderate by both psychopathology (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>) and facial “trait” characteristics (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>); and, thus, potential effects of symptoms and other moderators on both emotional and neutral faces could create ambiguity in interpreting emotional &gt; neutral contrasts. Angry and fearful faces were also analyzed separately because of reports of different processing of angry and fearful threat cues (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>), and because we are interested changes in neural responses to emotional faces over time (pre- to post-therapy). This approach represented a within-subjects, longitudinal repeated measures (pre- to post-therapy) design, in which each participant’s post-therapy scan to each face expression type (angry, fearful, and neutral) was compared to their own baseline (pre-therapy) scan of the same contrast.</p><p>In our primary analyses, we aimed to identify brain regions in which responses to emotional faces changed from pre- to post-psychotherapy in association with improvement in PTSD symptoms. We first constructed within-subjects T-maps of the Post &gt; Pre-therapy contrasts of emotional faces &gt; shapes to identify therapy-associated changes in brain responses. We then used a regressor of change in total CAPS scores (“deltaCAPS” regressor) in between-subjects regression analyses to identify brain activation changes that correlated with symptom change. <italic>A priori</italic> defined regions of interests (ROI) amygdala and mPFC/anterior cingulate were examined for differences in emotional activations, based on the published literature in PTSD neuroimaging (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). For our primary ROI analyses, small volume correction (SVC) with family-wide error (FWE) corrected <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 was used. SVC masks were created using anatomical AAL atlas for bilateral amygdala, and mPFC. To explore direction of the changes contributing to the observed effects, signal changes were extracted from ROIs. Clusters of activation observed outside of <italic>a priori</italic> regions were reported as significant if they met whole-brain FWE corrected <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p><p>To identify potential differential effects of the two psychotherapies (MBET and PCGT), we conducted exploratory analyses utilizing flexible repeated-measures ANOVA (RM-ANOVA) in spm8. In this intervention outcome study, we were specifically interested in group × time interactions characterized by group differences at post-intervention due to the experimental group increasing (or decreasing) over time, but no difference at pre-intervention, and in which the control group does not change over time (known as “spreading” interactions, as opposed to “cross-over” interactions that could reflect pre-existing differences in groups at intake). To test for spreading interactions, we utilized the conjunction analysis of Friston and colleagues (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>) within flexible ANOVA F test maps to test the likelihood of voxels having a consistent main effect of time, group, and group × time interaction effect (each of which should exist in a consistent direction at a minimum threshold in a true spreading interaction, although each may not be individually significant) with search area restricted to areas where direction of all three effects agreed. The conjunction was performed on the F test maps for the three effects, with the search area being restricted to areas where the direction of all three effects agreed, <italic>p</italic>-values were adjusted for the <italic>a priori</italic> conditions of interest (i.e., all three signs consistent), and thresholded at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.005.</p><p>To identify potential psychotherapy-associated changes in patterns of effective connectivity of brain regions associated with PTSD symptom improvement, we conducted exploratory analyses utilizing psychophysiological interaction (PPI) analysis. We performed PPI analyses of connectivity during processing of threat (angry faces) compared to baseline connectivity (during the shapes condition) in brain regions, associated with PTSD symptom changes. Regions with changes in activity that correlated with PTSD symptom improvement were used as “seed regions.” Seeds were 5-mm radius spheres centered around voxels showing peak correlation of post &gt; pre-therapy T-maps with a delta CAPS regressor. De-convolved time series for each seed from each participant were multiplied by a block vector representing the contrast of interest (angry faces vs. shapes), and individual models contained regressors for the seed time series, the original conditions, and the interaction terms, and regressors were convolved with the canonical HRF (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Resulting contrast maps were entered into second-level random effects analyses (pre- vs. post-therapy paired <italic>t</italic>-tests) and thresholded at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.005.</p></sec></sec></sec>ResultsParticipantsThe two PTSD therapy groups did not significantly differ by PTSD symptom severity (CAPS scores), number of Axis I comorbidities, age, race, or medication use at intake (see Table 1).Effects of MBET and PCGT Group Therapy on PTSD SymptomsThe participants in this fMRI study (N = 23) were a subset of a larger controlled trial comparing MBET and PCGT (N = 38). The overall outcomes in the entire sample, as well as details of study design, compliance and retention, and detailed description of the interventions, are reported separately (King et al., unpublished data). Individual pre- and post-therapy total CAPS scores for patients in this sub-sample recruited for pre-post fMRI experiment and treated with each therapy are shown in Figure 1. MBET showed a significant reduction in total CAPS score [pre vs. post MBET t(13) = 3.29, p = 0.006, average 16 point decrease in total CAPS, effect size d = 0.92, effect size as per Ref. (67) Eq. 8]. PCGT was associated with a smaller decrease [pre vs. post PCGT t(8) = 1.81, p = 0.10, average 7.0 point decrease in total CAPS, d = 0.43]. In between condition analyses, RM-ANOVA condition × time interaction were not significant for pre–post analyses [F(1,20) = 1.62, p = 0.22] in total CAPS scores. The between condition post-therapy CAPS score effect was d = 0.41. Patients in the MBET group attended more group therapy sessions than patients treated with PCGT [average of 13.5 vs. 8.5 sessions, respectively, t(19) = 5.39, p &lt; 0.001].Figure 1Changes in PTSD symptoms in response to group therapy in the patients with fMRI scans in this study. Shown are PTSD symptoms (total CAPS scores) before and after a 16-week group therapy with (A) mindfulness-based exposure therapy (MBET, N = 13 pre–post) and (B) present-centered group therapy (PCGT, N = 8 pre-post). Patients who experienced a clinically significant improvement in PTSD (change in CAPS &gt;10 points from pre–post treatment) are shown in solid lines, patients who did not have clinically significant improvement shown in dashed lines.Changes in Brain Responses to Emotional Faces Pre- to Post-Therapy that Correlate with Improvement in PTSD SymptomsImaging data from two participants (one in MBET, one in PCGT condition) were excluded from the following analyses due to technical problems with data acquisition that made the data unusable. As could be expected, the emotional faces (fearful, angry, and neutral) evoked robust activations of visual cortex, dorsal medial frontal gyrus/SMA, bilateral inferior frontal gyrus, and bilateral amygdala, and de-activations of “task-negative” regions posterior cingulate and ventral medial PFC (data not shown). To test for potential order or “spill-over” effects of tasks (which were counter balanced), we examined amygdala responses in patients who had IAPS pictures or faces tasks completed first. No differences in amygdala reactions to neutral, angry, or fearful faces were observed. To identify brain changes associated with improvement in PTSD symptoms, we first searched for clusters of brain activations whose change from pre- to post-therapy was correlated with improvement in total PTSD symptoms (using a delta CAPS regressor). To maximize our power in this pilot study, we first conducted regression analyses in the total sample of PTSD patients (i.e., treated with either MBET or PCGT, N = 21) to identify brain regions associated with improvement in PTSD symptoms associated with either therapy. Significant clusters of correlation with PTSD symptom changes are shown in Table 2 (hypothesized regions reported as significant after SVC FWE corrected p-value &lt;0.05, clusters outside of a priori regions reported as significant if they met whole-brain FWE corrected p &lt; 0.05). Positive correlations of increased brain responses to angry faces with PTSD symptom improvement from pre- to post-therapy were identified in two regions in medial frontal cortex: a cluster spanning mPFC (BA10) and rostral ACC (BA32, Figure 2A), and a more dorsal region of medial frontal cortex spanning BA9 and BA10 (Figure 2A), and left peri-amygdala area (Figure 2B). To visualize the distribution of improvement in PTSD vs. change in activations in ROIs, scatter plots are shown in Figure 2C. dmPFC BA9, Figure 2D, rmPFC BA10/BA32, and Figure 2E, left peri-amygdala from pre- to post-therapy. All images represented in neurological convention, i.e., left side of the image corresponds to the left side of the brain. Colors of clusters represent “heat map” of Z-scores, see scale to right of images. No significant clusters of negative correlation were seen with the same contrast (i.e., brain responses that decreased from pre- to post-therapy correlated with PTSD symptom improvement). No significant positive or negative correlations of delta CAPS regressor with pre- to post-therapy changes in brain responses to fearful or neutral faces were detected.Table 2Changes in brain responses to emotional faces from pre- to post-therapy that correlate with improvement in PTSD symptoms (change in total CAPS score).PeakClusterRegionxyzZ-scoreSVC pFWEkESVC pFWEAngry &gt; shapePost &gt; preMedial frontal gyrus (BA10)/rostral ACC (BA 32)−125044.180.011420.014Medial frontal gyrus (BA9)−947373.560.078220.039(BA10)−1244223.470.100Left Amygdala/peri-amygdala−15−1−174.800.006150.019Fearful &gt; shapePost &gt; preNo significant clustersNeutral &gt; shapePost &gt; preNo significant clustersItalics: peak of a subcluster.Figure 2Correlations of changes in brain responses to angry faces to improvement in PTSD symptoms pre- to post-group therapy. Post-therapy &gt; pre-therapy Z-maps of brain activations to angry faces were regressed with improvement in PTSD symptoms (change in CAPS scores) in whole-brain voxel-wise analyses (visualized at p &lt; 0.001, uncorrected). (A) Saggital section (x = −12) showing dorsal medial PFC BA9 peak (−12, 44, 22) and medial PFC BA10/BA32 peak (−12, 50, 4) correlation clusters. (B) Coronal section (y = −1) showing left amygdala/peri-amygdala correlation cluster [peak (−15, −1, −17)]. (C–E) Scatter plots are shown to visualize distribution of improvement in PTSD vs. change in activations (betas from ROI, arbitrary units) in (C) dmPFC BA9, (D) rmPFC BA10/BA32, and (E) left peri-amygdala from pre- to post-therapy. Filled circles are beta values from PTSD patients treated with MBET, open circles patients treated with PCGT. (Colors of clusters represent “heat map” of Z-scores, see scale to right of images. All images represented in neurological convention, i.e., left side of the image corresponds to the left side of the brain).Differential Changes in Responses to Emotional Faces Pre- to Post-Therapy with MBET vs. PCGTTo identify potential differential effects of therapies (MBET vs. PCGT) in evoking changes in brain responses to emotional faces related to changes in PTSD symptoms (e.g., changes in amygdala and medial frontal cortex responses), we used a whole-brain RM-ANOVA approach test group (MBET vs. PCGT) by time (pre- vs. post-therapy) interaction effects, utilizing a “spreading interaction” contrast (as described in Methods). Differential changes in brain activations to angry, fearful, and neutral faces are listed in Table 3 (group × time spreading interaction term). Treatment-specific changes in response to angry faces were observed in left amygdala, characterized by increased left amygdala responses in patients treated with MBET, but not in patients treated with PCGT (Figure 3A). Treatment-specific changes were also seen in right fusiform gyrus (Figure 3B) and left parahippocampal gyrus, as well as left precuneus, and posterior cingulate (Table 3). In responses to fearful faces, an increase in activity in an area of medial frontal cortex/BA10 was seen in MBET but not in PCGT (Table 3, Figure 3C.). In responses to neutral faces, a similar increase in response to in fusiform gyrus was seen in the MBET group only (Table 3).Table 3Differential changes in responses to emotional faces pre- to post-therapy with MBET vs. PCGT (RM-ANOVA spreading interaction term p &lt; 0.005).RegionxyzFkAngry facesClusters within search areaL amygdala−152−1710.6516R parahippocampus21−10−2021.4325Other clustersR fusiform/lingual gyrus27−67−820.8036R precuneus21−645518.1120218−584815.75Posterior cingulate0−464010.7615Fearful facesClusters within search areaL medial frontal gyrus (BA10)−12621317.1916Other clustersNoneNeutral facesClusters within search areaNoneOther clustersR fusiform/lingual gyrus24−76−820.807130−68−811.90L lingual gyrus−33−781612.2773L fusiform/lingual gyrus−18−70−1111.2830L caudate body−18−1−1311.1236Italics: peak of a subcluster.Figure 3Differential effects of MBET vs. PCGT on changes in responses to emotional faces from pre- to post-therapy (RM-ANOVA, group × time “spreading interaction”). (A) Group × time interactions in left amygdala (−15, 2, −17) in the viewing Angry Faces condition. (B) Group × time interactions in right lingual gyrus/fusiform gyrus (27, −67, −8) viewing Angry Faces. (C) Group × time interactions in left medial frontal gyrus (−12, 62, 13) viewing Fearful Faces.Changes in Pre- to Post-Therapy Effective Connectivity Viewing Angry Faces in Brain Regions Associated with PTSD Symptom ImprovementPsychophysiological interaction analyses were used to identify potential changes from pre- to post-therapy in effective connectivity with the brain regions that were associated with PTSD improvement. Time series of activity of the left amygdala (−15, −1, −17) and left mPFC (−12, 50, 4) peaks of correlation with symptom improvement were used as seeds in PPI comparing viewing angry faces to baseline (viewing shapes). Table 4 shows results of changes in effective connectivity, from pre- to post-therapy Clusters of increases in effective connectivity to the left amygdala seed while viewing angry faces were seen in medial frontal gyrus (BA6)/dorsal ACC (BA 32, Figure 4A), lingual gyrus (Figure 4B), and left precentral gyrus following psychotherapy. Increased amygdala connectivity in these regions was not correlated with improvement in PTSD symptoms. No significant clusters were observed with the left mPFC seed.Table 4Changes from pre- to post-therapy in effective connectivity viewing angry faces in brain regions associated with PTSD symptom improvement (p &lt; 0.001 uncorrected).Seed/regionxyzZ-scoreKL amygdala seed (−15, −1, −17)L lingual/fusiform gyrus−15−76−23.9836−6−94−53.98L precentral gyrus−39−7523.5525Medial frontal gyrus (BA6)/cingulate gyrus (BA32)98523.3220L mPFC seed (−12, 50, 4)No significant clustersItalics: peak of a subcluster.Figure 4Increased left amygdala connectivity viewing angry faces following group psychotherapy. (A) Increased left amygdala connectivity with SMA/dorsal ACC. (B) Increased left amygdala connectivity with lingual gyrus.Author ContributionsAK designed the study, obtained funding, performed study, analyzed and interpreted data, and wrote the initial draft of paper. fMRI data collection and analyses were performed by SB and RS. Clinical psychotherapy was performed by AK, KP, SR, and NG. AK, IL, SR, and NG were involved in study design and obtaining funding. IL, SB, RS, SR, NG, KP, and AK were involved in drafting the final manuscript.Conflict of Interest StatementThe authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.FundingWe are grateful for support from U.S. Department of Defense W81XWH-08-2-0208 to AK and IL, and to the Mind and Life Institute for Varela Awards to AK.References1FultonJJCalhounPSWagnerHRSchryARHairLPFeelingN
The prevalence of posttraumatic stress disorder in operation enduring freedom/operation Iraqi freedom (OEF/OIF) veterans: a meta-analysis. J Anxiety Disord (2015) 31:98–107.10.1016/j.janxdis.2015.02.003257683992BradleyRGreeneJRussEDutraLWestenD. A multidimensional meta-analysis of psychotherapy for PTSD. Am J Psychiatry (2005) 162:214–27.10.1176/appi.ajp.162.2.214156775823SteenkampMMLitzBTHogeCWMarmarCR. Psychotherapy for military-related PTSD: a review of randomized clinical trials. JAMA (2015) 314:489–500.10.1001/jama.2015.8370262416004Kehle-ForbesSMMeisLASpoontMRPolusnyMA. Treatment initiation and dropout from prolonged exposure and cognitive processing therapy in a VA outpatient clinic. Psychol Trauma (2016) 8(1):107–14.10.1037/tra0000065261211755SripadaRKBohnertKMGanoczyDBlowFCValensteinMPfeifferPN
Initial group versus individual therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder and subsequent follow-up treatment adequacy. Psychol Serv (2016).10.1037/ser00000776SchnurrPPFriedmanMJEngelCCFoaEBSheaMTChowBK
Cognitive behavioral therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder in women: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA (2007) 297:820–30.10.1001/jama.297.8.820173275247SchnurrPPFriedmanMJFoyDWSheaMTHsiehFYLavoriPW
Randomized trial of trauma-focused group therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder: results from a department of veterans affairs cooperative study. Arch Gen Psychiatry (2003) 60:481–9.10.1001/archpsyc.60.5.481127428698CastilloDTLacefieldKC’De BacaJBlankenshipAQuallsC. Effectiveness of group-delivered cognitive therapy and treatment length in women veterans with PTSD. Behav Sci (2014) 4:31–41.10.3390/bs4010031253792669SloanDMFeinsteinBAGallagherMWBeckJGKeaneTM
Efficacy of group treatment for posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms: a meta-analysis. Psychol Trauma (2013) 5:176–83.10.1037/a002629110HolzelBKLazarSWGardTSchuman-OlivierZVagoDROttU. How does mindfulness meditation work? Proposing mechanisms of action from a conceptual and neural perspective. Perspect Psychol Sci (2011) 6:537–59.10.1177/17456916114196712616837611VagoDRSilbersweigDA. Self-awareness, self-regulation, and self-transcendence (S-ART): a framework for understanding the neurobiological mechanisms of mindfulness. Front Hum Neurosci (2012) 6:296.10.3389/fnhum.2012.002962311277012SegalZVBielingPYoungTMacQueenGCookeRMartinL
Antidepressant monotherapy vs sequential pharmacotherapy and mindfulness-based cognitive therapy, or placebo, for relapse prophylaxis in recurrent depression. Arch Gen Psychiatry (2010) 67:1256–64.10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.1682113532513EisendrathSJGillungEDelucchiKMathalonDHYangTTSatreDD
A preliminary study: efficacy of mindfulness-based cognitive therapy versus sertraline as first-line treatments for major depressive disorder. Mindfulness (N Y) (2015) 6:475–82.10.1007/s12671-014-0280-82608585314EisendrathSJGillungEPDelucchiKLChartierMMathalonDHSullivanJC
Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) versus the health-enhancement program (HEP) for adults with treatment-resistant depression: a randomized control trial study protocol. BMC Complement Altern Med (2014) 14:95.10.1186/1472-6882-14-952461282515HogeEABuiEMarquesLMetcalfCAMorrisLKRobinaughDJ
Randomized controlled trial of mindfulness meditation for generalized anxiety disorder: effects on anxiety and stress reactivity. J Clin Psychiatry (2013) 74:786–92.10.4088/JCP.12m080832354116316KimbroughEMagyariTLangenbergPChesneyMBermanB. Mindfulness intervention for child abuse survivors. J Clin Psychol (2010) 66:17–33.10.1002/jclp.206241999842517EarleyMDChesneyMAFryeJGreenePABermanBKimbroughE. Mindfulness intervention for child abuse survivors: a 2.5-year follow-up. J Clin Psychol (2014) 70:933–41.10.1002/jclp.221022484494418KearneyDJMcDermottKMalteCMartinezMSimpsonTL. Association of participation in a mindfulness program with measures of PTSD, depression and quality of life in a veteran sample. J Clin Psychol (2012) 68:101–16.10.1002/jclp.208532212518719KearneyDJMcDermottKMalteCMartinezMSimpsonTL. Effects of participation in a mindfulness program for veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder: a randomized controlled pilot study. J Clin Psychol (2013) 69:14–27.10.1002/jclp.219112293049120KingAPEricksonTMGiardinoNDFavoriteTRauchSARobinsonE
A pilot study of group mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) for combat veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD). Depress Anxiety (2013) 30:638–45.10.1002/da.221042359609221PolusnyMAErbesCRThurasPMoranALambertyGJCollinsRC
Mindfulness-based stress reduction for posttraumatic stress disorder among veterans: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA (2015) 314:456–65.10.1001/jama.2015.83612624159722HayesJPHayesSMMikedisAM. Quantitative meta-analysis of neural activity in posttraumatic stress disorder. Biol Mood Anxiety Disord (2012) 2:9.10.1186/2045-5380-2-92273812523EtkinAWagerTD. Functional neuroimaging of anxiety: a meta-analysis of emotional processing in PTSD, social anxiety disorder, and specific phobia. Am J Psychiatry (2007) 164:1476–88.10.1176/appi.ajp.2007.070305041789833624PatelRSprengRNShinLMGirardTA. Neurocircuitry models of posttraumatic stress disorder and beyond: a meta-analysis of functional neuroimaging studies. Neurosci Biobehav Rev (2012) 36:2130–42.10.1016/j.neubiorev.2012.06.0032276614125StarkEAParsonsCEVan HarteveltTJCharquero-BallesterMMcMannersHEhlersA
Post-traumatic stress influences the brain even in the absence of symptoms: a systematic, quantitative meta-analysis of neuroimaging studies. Neurosci Biobehav Rev (2015) 56:207–21.10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.07.0072619210426BryantRAFelminghamKKempADasPHughesGPedutoA
Amygdala and ventral anterior cingulate activation predicts treatment response to cognitive behaviour therapy for post-traumatic stress disorder. Psychol Med (2008) 38:555–61.10.1017/S00332917070022311800549627CislerJMSigelBAKramerTLSmithermanSVanderzeeKPembertonJ
Amygdala response predicts trajectory of symptom reduction during trauma-focused cognitive-behavioral therapy among adolescent girls with PTSD. J Psychiatr Res (2015) 71:33–40.10.1016/j.jpsychires.2015.09.0112652286928FalconerEAllenAFelminghamKLWilliamsLMBryantRA. Inhibitory neural activity predicts response to cognitive-behavioral therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder. J Clin Psychiatry (2013) 74:895–901.10.4088/JCP.12m080202410776329AupperleRLAllardCBSimmonsANFlaganTThorpSRNormanSB
Neural responses during emotional processing before and after cognitive trauma therapy for battered women. Psychiatry Res (2013) 214:48–55.10.1016/j.pscychresns.2013.05.0012391653730SimmonsANNormanSBSpadoniADStrigoIA. Neurosubstrates of remission following prolonged exposure therapy in veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder. Psychother Psychosom (2013) 82:382–9.10.1159/0003488672406148431ThomaesKDorrepaalEDraijerNde RuiterMBElzingaBMvan BalkomAJ
Treatment effects on insular and anterior cingulate cortex activation during classic and emotional stroop interference in child abuse-related complex post-traumatic stress disorder. Psychol Med (2012) 42:2337–49.10.1017/S00332917120004992243659532van RooijSJGeuzeEKennisMRademakerARVinkM. Neural correlates of inhibition and contextual cue processing related to treatment response in PTSD. Neuropsychopharmacology (2015) 40:667–75.10.1038/npp.2014.2202515470733BrewerJAWorhunskyPDGrayJRTangYYWeberJKoberH. Meditation experience is associated with differences in default mode network activity and connectivity. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (2011) 108:20254–9.10.1073/pnas.11120291082211419334HasenkampWBarsalouLW. Effects of meditation experience on functional connectivity of distributed brain networks. Front Hum Neurosci (2012) 6:38.10.3389/fnhum.2012.000382240353635GarrisonKAZeffiroTAScheinostDConstableRTBrewerJA. Meditation leads to reduced default mode network activity beyond an active task. Cogn Affect Behav Neurosci (2015) 15:712–20.10.3758/s13415-015-0358-32590423836FroeligerBGarlandELKozinkRVModlinLAChenNKMcClernonFJ
Meditation-state functional connectivity (msFC): strengthening of the dorsal attention network and beyond. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med (2012) 2012:680407.10.1155/2012/6804072253628937KilpatrickLASuyenobuBYSmithSRBuellerJAGoodmanTCreswellJD
Impact of mindfulness-based stress reduction training on intrinsic brain connectivity. Neuroimage (2011) 56:290–8.10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.02.0342133444238HaaseLMayACFalahpourMIsakovicSSimmonsANHickmanSD
A pilot study investigating changes in neural processing after mindfulness training in elite athletes. Front Behav Neurosci (2015) 9:22910.3389/fnbeh.2015.002292637952139RolandLTLenzeEJHardinFMKallogjeriDNicklausJWinelandAM
Effects of mindfulness based stress reduction therapy on subjective bother and neural connectivity in chronic tinnitus. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg (2015) 152:919–26.10.1177/01945998155715562571535040WellsREYehGYKerrCEWolkinJDavisRBTanY
Meditation’s impact on default mode network and hippocampus in mild cognitive impairment: a pilot study. Neurosci Lett (2013) 556:15–9.10.1016/j.neulet.2013.10.0012412043041TarenAAGianarosPJGrecoCMLindsayEKFairgrieveABrownKW
Mindfulness meditation training alters stress-related amygdala resting state functional connectivity: a randomized controlled trial. Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci (2015) 10(12):1758–68.10.1093/scan/nsv0662604817642FarbNASegalZVAndersonAK. Mindfulness meditation training alters cortical representations of interoceptive attention. Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci (2013) 8:15–26.10.1093/scan/nss0662268921643FarbNASegalZVMaybergHBeanJMcKeonDFatimaZ
Attending to the present: mindfulness meditation reveals distinct neural modes of self-reference. Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci (2007) 2:313–22.10.1093/scan/nsm0301898513744GoldinPZivMJazaieriHGrossJJ. Randomized controlled trial of mindfulness-based stress reduction versus aerobic exercise: effects on the self-referential brain network in social anxiety disorder. Front Hum Neurosci (2012) 6:295.10.3389/fnhum.2012.002952313341145GoldinPZivMJazaieriHHahnKGrossJJ. MBSR vs aerobic exercise in social anxiety: fMRI of emotion regulation of negative self-beliefs. Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci (2013) 8:65–72.10.1093/scan/nss0542258625246HolzelBKHogeEAGreveDNGardTCreswellJDBrownKW
Neural mechanisms of symptom improvements in generalized anxiety disorder following mindfulness training. Neuroimage Clin (2013) 2:448–58.10.1016/j.nicl.2013.03.0112417979947ResickPAWachenJSMintzJYoung-McCaughanSRoacheJDBorahAM
A randomized clinical trial of group cognitive processing therapy compared with group present-centered therapy for PTSD among active duty military personnel. J Consult Clin Psychol (2015) 83:1058–68.10.1037/ccp00000162593901848KingAPFavoriteTK
Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) for combat-related posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in mindfulness-based cognitive therapy. In: EisendrathSJ, editor. Innovative Applications. Berlin, Germany: Springer (2016). p. 163–89.49KingAPBlockSRSripadaRKRauchSGiardinoNFavoriteT
Altered default mode network (Dmn) resting state functional connectivity following a mindfulness-based exposure therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder (Ptsd) in combat Veterans of Afghanistan and Iraq. Depress Anxiety (2016) 33:289–99.10.1002/da.224812703841050FrostNDLaskaKMWampoldBE. The evidence for present-centered therapy as a treatment for posttraumatic stress disorder. J Trauma Stress (2014) 27:1–8.10.1002/jts.218812451553451AshburnerJ
A fast diffeomorphic image registration algorithm. Neuroimage (2007) 38:95–113.10.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.07.0071776143852HaririARMattayVSTessitoreAFeraFWeinbergerDR. Neocortical modulation of the amygdala response to fearful stimuli. Biol Psychiatry (2003) 53:494–501.10.1016/S0006-3223(02)01786-91264435453HaririARTessitoreAMattayVSFeraFWeinbergerDR. The amygdala response to emotional stimuli: a comparison of faces and scenes. Neuroimage (2002) 17:317–23.10.1006/nimg.2002.11791248208654JavanbakhtAKingAPEvansGWSwainJEAngstadtMPhanKL
Childhood poverty predicts adult amygdala and frontal activity and connectivity in response to emotional faces. Front Behav Neurosci (2015) 9:154.10.3389/fnbeh.2015.001542612471255EvansGWSwainJEKingAPWangXJavanbakhtAHoSS
Childhood cumulative risk exposure and adult amygdala volume and function. J Neurosci Res (2016) 94(6):535–43.10.1002/jnr.236812646987256GurRCSchroederLTurnerTMcGrathCChanRMTuretskyBI
Brain activation during facial emotion processing. Neuroimage (2002) 16(3):651–62.10.1006/nimg.2002.10971216925057Salgado-PinedaPFakraEDelaveauPHaririARBlinO. Differential patterns of initial and sustained responses in amygdala and cortical regions to emotional stimuli in schizophrenia patients and healthy participants. J Psychiatry Neurosci (2010) 35:41–8.10.1503/jpn.0900172004024558BlasiGHaririARAlceGTaurisanoPSambataroFDasS
Preferential amygdala reactivity to the negative assessment of neutral faces. Biol Psychiatry (2009) 66:847–53.10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.06.0171970964459CooneyREAtlasLYJoormannJEugeneFGotlibIH. Amygdala activation in the processing of neutral faces in social anxiety disorder: is neutral really neutral?
Psychiatry Res (2006) 148:55–9.10.1016/j.pscychresns.2006.05.0031703011760SaidCPSebeNTodorovA. Structural resemblance to emotional expressions predicts evaluation of emotionally neutral faces. Emotion (2009) 9:260–4.10.1037/a00146811934853761TodorovAEngellAD. The role of the amygdala in implicit evaluation of emotionally neutral faces. Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci (2008) 3:303–12.10.1093/scan/nsn0331901508262WhalenPJShinLMMcInerneySCFischerHWrightCIRauchSL. A functional MRI study of human amygdala responses to facial expressions of fear versus anger. Emotion (2001) 1:70–83.10.1037/1528-3542.1.1.701289481263SimmonsANMatthewsSC. Neural circuitry of PTSD with or without mild traumatic brain injury: a meta-analysis. Neuropharmacology (2012) 62:598–606.10.1016/j.neuropharm.2011.03.0162142098664FristonKJHolmesAPPriceCJBuchelCWorsleyKJ. Multisubject fMRI studies and conjunction analyses. Neuroimage (1999) 10:385–96.10.1006/nimg.1999.04841049389765FristonKJPennyWDGlaserDE. Conjunction revisited. Neuroimage (2005) 25:661–7.10.1016/j.neuroimage.2005.01.0131580896766McLarenDGRiesMLXuGJohnsonSC. A generalized form of context-dependent psychophysiological interactions (gPPI): a comparison to standard approaches. Neuroimage (2012) 61:1277–86.10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.03.0682248441167MorrisSBDeShonRP. Combining effect size estimates in meta-analysis with repeated measures and independent-groups designs. Psychol Methods (2002) 7:105–25.10.1037/1082-989X.7.1.1051192888668SmithERPorterKEMessinaMGBeyerJADefeverMEFoaEB
Prolonged exposure for PTSD in a Veteran group: a pilot effectiveness study. J Anxiety Disord (2015) 30:23–7.10.1016/j.janxdis.2014.12.0082559437069KimMJLoucksRAPalmerALBrownACSolomonKMMarchanteAN
The structural and functional connectivity of the amygdala: from normal emotion to pathological anxiety. Behav Brain Res (2011) 223:403–10.10.1016/j.bbr.2011.04.0252153607770DuvalERJavanbakhtALiberzonI. Neural circuits in anxiety and stress disorders: a focused review. Ther Clin Risk Manag (2015) 11:115–26.10.2147/TCRM.S485282567090171LiberzonISripadaCS. The functional neuroanatomy of PTSD: a critical review. Prog Brain Res (2008) 167:151–69.10.1016/S0079-6123(07)67011-31803701372MarenSPhanKLLiberzonI. The contextual brain: implications for fear conditioning, extinction and psychopathology. Nat Rev Neurosci (2013) 14:417–28.10.1038/nrn34922363587073ShinLMLiberzonI. The neurocircuitry of fear, stress, and anxiety disorders. Neuropsychopharmacology (2010) 35:169–91.10.1038/npp.2009.831962599774RauchSLWhalenPJShinLMMcInerneySCMacklinMLLaskoNB
Exaggerated amygdala response to masked facial stimuli in posttraumatic stress disorder: a functional MRI study. Biol Psychiatry (2000) 47:769–76.10.1016/S0006-3223(00)00828-31081203575ArmonyJLCorboVClementMHBrunetA. Amygdala response in patients with acute PTSD to masked and unmasked emotional facial expressions. Am J Psychiatry (2005) 162:1961–3.10.1176/appi.ajp.162.10.19611619984576ShinLMWrightCICannistraroPAWedigMMMcMullinKMartisB
A functional magnetic resonance imaging study of amygdala and medial prefrontal cortex responses to overtly presented fearful faces in posttraumatic stress disorder. Arch Gen Psychiatry (2005) 62:273–81.10.1001/archpsyc.62.3.2731575324077BremnerJDNarayanMStaibLHSouthwickSMMcGlashanTCharneyDS. Neural correlates of memories of childhood sexual abuse in women with and without posttraumatic stress disorder. Am J Psychiatry (1999) 156:1787–95.1055374478BrittonJCPhanKLTaylorSFFigLMLiberzonI. Corticolimbic blood flow in posttraumatic stress disorder during script-driven imagery. Biol Psychiatry (2005) 57:832–40.10.1016/j.biopsych.2004.12.0251582070379LaniusRAWilliamsonPCBoksmanKDensmoreMGuptaMNeufeldRW
Brain activation during script-driven imagery induced dissociative responses in PTSD: a functional magnetic resonance imaging investigation. Biol Psychiatry (2002) 52:305–11.10.1016/S0006-3223(02)01367-71220863780PhanKLBrittonJCTaylorSFFigLMLiberzonI. Corticolimbic blood flow during nontraumatic emotional processing in posttraumatic stress disorder. Arch Gen Psychiatry (2006) 63:184–92.10.1001/archpsyc.63.2.1841646186281MacNamaraAPostDKennedyAERabinakCAPhanKL. Electrocortical processing of social signals of threat in combat-related post-traumatic stress disorder. Biol Psychol (2013) 94:441–9.10.1016/j.biopsycho.2013.08.0092402576082FoaEBHearst-lkedaD
Emotional dissociation in response to trauma: an information processing approach. In: MichelsonLKRayWJ, editors. Handbook of Dissociation: Theoretical, Empirical, and Research Perspectives. New York: Plenum (1996). p. 207–26.
